<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_software_annotation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title><rs type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs> Design and Survival Strategies:
                    Observations from the Post-Launch Trenches</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Ilovan</surname>
                        <forename>Mihaela</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory, University of Alberta,
                        Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>ilovan@ualberta.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Brown</surname>
                        <forename>Susan</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>School of English and Theatre Studies, University of Guelph,
                        Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>sbrown@uoguelph.ca</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019-04-27T20:08:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Name, Institution</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Street</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>City</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Country</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Name</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>editing; tool development; user uptake; sustainability</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>literary studies</term>
                    <term>scholarly editing</term>
                    <term>english studies</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                    <term>sustainability and preservation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p style="text-align:left; ">The <rs type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs> XML/RDF editor is
                the centerpiece of the Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory (CWRC) platform for
                the production, hosting, and dissemination of digital humanities scholarship. In
                development since 2011 and launched with the platform in 2016, the browser-based
                editor has reached maturity and stability. Well prior to this, the team had begun
                strategizing towards sustainability. We outline this strategy while highlighting
                features of the editor.</p>
            <p style="text-align:left; ">Compared to some outcomes of digital dumanities tool
                building – such as gaining new insights into one’s own research – the effort of
                turning a tool into a sustainable, generalized service is less glamorous, more
                laborious, and less acknowledged. Tool-building is considered part and parcel of the
                scholarly work of DH (Schreibman and Hanlon, 2010) and is beginning to be recognized
                by academic reward systems. Yet scant support and rewards accrue once software is up
                and running. This situation has changed little over the years, despite increasing
                concern regarding digital infrastructure sustainability generally (Eghbal, 2016;
                Maron and Pickle, 2014) and attention to “care and repair” within DH (Nowviskie,
                2015; Sayers). Like all software, DH tools require maintenance, enhancement and
                updates, which is to say, continued funding and expertise. </p>
            <p style="text-align:left; ">Pursuing uptake seems like a natural approach to the
                sustainability dilemma, since:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
                <item>it is easier to demonstrate the success of a tool and to justify further
                    resource allocation in light of increases in use; and</item>
                <item>adopters of a tool are invested in its survival and might put resources
                    towards sustainability.</item>
            </list>
            <p style="text-align:left; ">However, uptake is no guarantee of sustainability. As
                observed by Cameron Neylon, many scholarly infrastructures are public goods, and
                “Finding sustainability models to support them is a challenge due to free-loading,
                where someone who does not contribute to the support of an infrastructure
                nonetheless gains the benefit of it” (2017: 3). Nevertheless, unused tools are
                poorly positioned to request continued funding or support. </p>
            <p style="text-align:left; ">The uptake or adoption of existing DH software by new users
                is far from guaranteed, even if it fulfills a need that it is well-documented in the
                research community where it originates. Fred Gibbs and Trevor Owens crystallize the
                ways in which tool uptake is hindered by multiple factors (2012). Significant
                problems include: </p>
            <list type="unordered">
                <item>
                    <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">managing expectations, </hi>while also
                    scaling up functionality from local to more general needs (Koeser and Hicks,
                    2018); </item>
                <item>limited <hi rend="bold">learning resources</hi> (examples, user
                    documentation); </item>
                <item>unintuitive or complex <hi rend="bold">user interfaces</hi> that discourage
                    novice users; </item>
                <item>lack of support for <hi rend="bold">standards and interoperability</hi>. </item>
                <item>community building</item>
            </list>
            <p style="text-align:left; ">Together with more mundane but important activities like
                code maintenance, stable hosting, and systems administration, these factors create
                challenges that can prove fatal to promising technologies. Some are proclaimed at
                digital humanities conferences but seldom heard from again, while others like Paper
                Machines (Guldi and Johnson-Roberson, 2012) show immense promise but do not develop
                into fully robust tools. Even mature tools with uptake from a wide range of users,
                such as <rs type="software">Gephi</rs>, live quite precarious lives (Jacomy, 2018).
                In short, the challenges of sustaining tools are manifold. We use the above points
                as a rubric for reflecting on <rs type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs>’s engagement with
                the challenges of uptake. </p>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Scaling features and expectations </head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">The modular <rs type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs> exists
                    in several types of installation to suit users from novices to technical
                    experts: </p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item><rs type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs>: available to researchers within the
                        CWRC platform, where it is integrated with an Islandora repository, </item>
                    <item>Git-Writer ( <ref target="https://cwrc-writer.cwrc.ca"
                            >cwrc-writer.cwrc.ca</ref>): uses <rs type="software">GitHub</rs>’s file
                        storage, versioning, and authentication to allow anyone to edit <rs
                            type="software">GitHub</rs>-hosted XML documents (Fig. 1). </item>
                    <item>Installations by third parties in other software stacks. <lb/>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="10.93355cm" height="12.138052777777778cm"
                        url="Pictures/a98e3a1580b062d637f8b16ff8004cd5.png" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Fig. 1. Git-Writer document loading interface</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">To support a wide variety of users, <rs type="software"
                        >CWRC-Writer</rs> provides these core features:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>an interface that renders XML in a human-readable layout using CSS (Fig.
                        2);</item>
                    <item>XML tagging, with or without tags showing, with validation and error
                        identification;</item>
                    <item>raw/source XML editing for experts;</item>
                    <item>entities tagging in XML and/or Web Annotation RDF with built-in authority
                        lookups.</item>
                </list>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Members of the DH community, as well as literary and
                    cultural studies scholars using XML for their texts, were involved from the
                    beginning in the design of the tool. The user group comprises both power-users –
                    researchers with decades of experience in markup – and novice or occasional
                    users with little familiarity with DH. <rs type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs> was
                    designed from the outset as a light-weight editor to allow novices to tag XML
                    documents and link them to named entity authorities, such as the Virtual
                    International Authority File, in a manner that would avoid the steep learning
                    curve associated with other, more complex editing tools (Brown, 2015). </p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">This lightweight usage is our main use case. <rs
                        type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs> does not aim to replace a full-featured XML
                    editor for heavy-duty markup or transformations. The complexity of managing XML
                    through an HTML front-end mean that major restructuring, for instance, is very
                    tricky. To ensure that available affordances are aligned with the needs of the
                    users, <rs type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs> offers three different editing
                    modes: </p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>A default combined XML &amp; RDF mode creates both XML tags and Web
                        Annotations identifying entities in the same span of text; <hi rend="background(white)" xml:space="preserve">external named entity identifiers are mapped onto the equivalent tags within supported XML schemas - which include established </hi>
                        <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/guidelines/customization/">
                            <hi rend="background(white)">TEI customizations</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi rend="background(white)" xml:space="preserve"> and other schemas employed by CWRC-supported projects. </hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>RDF-only mode for Web Annotations that leave the body of the XML file
                        untouched.</item>
                    <item>XML-only mode for tagging without adding any Web Annotations. </item>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1002" width="16.51cm" height="10.230555555555556cm"
                        url="Pictures/a819e204eb3531e4306d6d6a468dbb56.png" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Fig. 2. <rs type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs> document
                    showing application of CSS</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">In conjunction with particular user communities, we are
                    extending <rs type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs> functionality based on a
                    document’s schema declaration; for example, for EpiDoc files, a popup editor for
                    translations will allow users to create or tag a translation while viewing it
                    side-by-side with the original. To support transcription, side-by-side display
                    of the XML and images allows transcribers to view the scanned manuscript within
                    the tool (Fig. 3).</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1003" width="16.51cm" height="10.265833333333333cm"
                        url="Pictures/eccd006f77699c21180fa47810e731a5.png" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">
                    <hi rend="background(white)">Fig. 3. Editing interface (XML &amp; RDF mode) with
                        side-by-side display of manuscript scan</hi>
                    <lb/>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Learning resources</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">We mitigate the challenge of a new interface by
                    providing extensive, searchable <ref
                        target="https://cwrc.ca/CWRC-Writer_Documentation/">
                        <hi rend="underline color(1155CC)">user documentation</hi>
                    </ref> (produced with the DITA documentation standard) and <ref
                        target="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCh53vP26J4FX_GeWOhnm6qw">
                        <hi rend="underline color(1155CC)">tutorial videos</hi>
                    </ref>, as well as virtual office hours for real-time support. Learning to apply
                    markup is a major challenge for the uninitiated, so there are sandbox templates
                    for fooling around. Projects can create customized document templates that can
                    be used to kickstart content creation and editing. These can provide highly
                    detailed instructions, in order to promote consistency and best practices. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>A user-friendly interface </head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">From 2012 on, <rs type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs> has
                    undergone successive rounds of user testing, which have informed feature
                    development and UX improvements. Two extensive rounds of survey-based
                    user-testing were conducted before 2016, followed by numerous informal
                    consultations and feedback from users and workshop participants. <rs
                        type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs> code is available in <rs type="software"
                        >GitHub</rs> and a ticketing template allows adopters to submit both feature
                    requests and bug reports. Formal announcement of the <rs type="software"
                        >GitHub</rs> version in 2019 will be followed by another round of systematic
                    user testing. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Standards and interoperability </head>
                <p style="text-align:left; "><rs type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs> editor adheres to
                    the standards for both markup and Web Annotation. An integrated XML validator
                    allows users to validate against the declared schema as they work on the
                    document. TEI is supported in all version of the editor. RDF annotations adhere
                    to the Web Annotation Data model, a W3C Recommendation that is being widely
                    adopted within DH and in the scholarly publishing community as a standard for
                    annotation data.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Promoting a community of users </head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">In addition to passive adopters, who employ <rs
                        type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs> as made available through CWRC or <rs
                        type="software">GitHub</rs>, we have projects joining CWRC primarily thanks
                    to its integration of the editor with other tools. There is growing interest
                    from members of the DH community considering it for use in TEI editing projects,
                    as components of library-based DH tool suites, or for teaching XML. The Center
                    of Digital Humanities Research at Texas A&amp;M has produced a containerized
                    version and has installed it on top of Fedora 4 as part of a larger toolkit.
                    Bucknell University is installing a version of the Git-Writer to support diverse
                    local DH projects, and other institutional installations are planned. External
                    partners were consulted for the development of Git-Writer, and the code is
                    configurable, modular, and well documented in order to permit installation in a
                    range of software environments. Users currently cohere around specific projects.
                    We hope a broader <rs type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs> community will develop as
                    numbers grow, and be joined by a community of developers familiar with and
                    willing to contribute to upkeep. However, the experience of other projects
                    indicates that this is a major challenge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Future developments</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; "><rs type="software">CWRC-Writer</rs> has for several
                    years now, since its launch within CWRC, been thinking hard about how to promote
                    uptake and long-term sustainability. Our development roadmap is constructed
                    around current and oncoming user needs. We will continue to adapt our strategy
                    in response to insights gained from further user testing and feedback from the
                    community following the launch of the Git-Writer to the DH community.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Brown, S.</hi> (2015). Remediating the Editor. <hi
                            rend="italic">Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</hi>, <hi rend="bold"
                            >40</hi>(1): 78–94 doi:10.1179/0308018814Z.000000000106. </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Eghbal, N.</hi> (2016). <hi rend="italic">Roads and Bridges:
                            The Unseen Labor Behind Our Digital Infrastructure</hi>. Ford Foundation
                        https://fordfoundcontent.blob.core.windows.net/media/2976/roads-and-bridges-the-unseen-labor-behind-our-digital-infrastructure.pdf. </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Gibbs, F. and Owens, T.</hi> (2012). Building Better Digital
                        Humanities Tools: Toward broader audiences and user-centered designs. <hi
                            rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi>, <hi rend="bold"
                            >006</hi>(2). </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Guldi, J. and Johnson-Roberson, C.</hi> (2012). <hi
                            rend="italic">Paper Machines</hi>. http://papermachines.org/. </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Jacomy, M.</hi> (2018). Is <rs type="software">Gephi</rs>
                        obsolete? Situation and perspectives. <hi rend="italic"><rs type="software"
                                >Gephi</rs> Blog</hi>
                        https://gephi.wordpress.com/2018/11/01/is-gephi-obsolete-situation-and-perspectives/
                        (accessed 27 November 2018). </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Koeser, R. S. and Hicks, Benamin</hi> (2018). Bridging
                        Digital Humanities Internal and Open Source Software Projects through
                        Reusable Building Blocks. Mexico City, Mexico
                        https://dh2018.adho.org/en/bridging-digital-humanities-internal-and-open-source-software-projects-through-reusable-building-blocks/
                        (accessed 27 November 2018). </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Maron, N. L. and Pickle, S.</hi> (2014). <hi rend="italic"
                            >Sustaining the Digital Humanities Host Institution Support beyond the
                            Start-Up Phase</hi>. ITHAKA. </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Neylon, C.</hi> (2017). Sustaining Scholarly Infrastructures
                        through Collective Action: The Lessons that Olson can Teach us. <hi
                            rend="italic">KULA: Knowledge Creation, Dissemination, and Preservation
                            Studies</hi>, <hi rend="bold">1</hi>(1): 3 doi:10.5334/kula.7. </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Nowviskie, B.</hi> (2015). On capacity and care <hi
                            rend="italic">Bethany Nowviskie</hi>
                        http://nowviskie.org/2015/on-capacity-and-care/ (accessed 27 November 2018). </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Sayers, J.</hi> From Make or Break to Care and Repair <hi
                            rend="italic">MLab in the Humanities.</hi> http://maker.uvic.ca/inke16/
                        (accessed 27 November 2018). </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; "> (2015). Remediating the Editor. <hi
                            rend="italic">Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</hi>
                        <hi rend="bold">40</hi>, (1): 78–94 doi:10.1179/0308018814Z.000000000106. </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Eghbal, N.</hi> (2016). <hi rend="italic">Roads and Bridges:
                            The Unseen Labor Behind Our Digital Infrastructure</hi>. Ford Foundation
                        https://fordfoundcontent.blob.core.windows.net/media/2976/roads-and-bridges-the-unseen-labor-behind-our-digital-infrastructure.pdf. </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Gibbs, F. and Owens, T.</hi> (2012). Building Better Digital
                        Humanities Tools: Toward broader audiences and user-centered designs. <hi
                            rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi>, <hi rend="bold"
                            >006</hi>(2). </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Guldi, J. and Johnson-Roberson, C.</hi> (2012). <hi
                            rend="italic">Paper Machines</hi>. http://papermachines.org/. </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Jacomy, M.</hi> (2018). Is <rs type="software">Gephi</rs>
                        obsolete? Situation and perspectives. <hi rend="italic"><rs type="software"
                                >Gephi</rs> Blog</hi>
                        https://gephi.wordpress.com/2018/11/01/is-gephi-obsolete-situation-and-perspectives/
                        (accessed 27 November 2018). </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Koeser, R. S. and Hicks, Benamin</hi> (2018). Bridging
                        Digital Humanities Internal and Open Source Software Projects through
                        Reusable Building Blocks. Mexico City, Mexico
                        https://dh2018.adho.org/en/bridging-digital-humanities-internal-and-open-source-software-projects-through-reusable-building-blocks/
                        (accessed 27 November 2018). </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Maron, N. L. and Pickle, S.</hi> (2014). <hi rend="italic"
                            >Sustaining the Digital Humanities Host Institution Support beyond the
                            Start-Up Phase</hi>. ITHAKA. </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Neylon, C.</hi> (2017). Sustaining Scholarly Infrastructures
                        through Collective Action: The Lessons that Olson can Teach us. <hi
                            rend="italic">KULA: Knowledge Creation, Dissemination, and Preservation
                            Studies</hi>, <hi rend="bold">1</hi>(1): 3 doi:10.5334/kula.7. </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Nowviskie, B.</hi> (2015). On capacity and care <hi
                            rend="italic">Bethany Nowviskie</hi>
                        http://nowviskie.org/2015/on-capacity-and-care/ (accessed 27 November 2018). </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Sayers, J.</hi> From Make or Break to Care and Repair <hi
                            rend="italic">MLab in the Humanities.</hi> http://maker.uvic.ca/inke16/
                        (accessed 27 November 2018). </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Schreibman, S. and Hanlon, A. M.</hi> (2010). Determining
                        Value for Digital Humanities Tools: Report on a Survey of Tool Developers.
                            <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi>, <hi rend="bold"
                            >004</hi>(2). </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
