<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_software_annotation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Subjectifying Library Users to the Macroscope Using Automatic Classification
                    Matching</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Gooding</surname>
                        <forename>Paul Matthew</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Glasgow, United Kingdom</affiliation>
                    <email>paul.gooding@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Terras</surname>
                        <forename>Melissa</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Edinburgh, United Kingdom</affiliation>
                    <email>m.terras@ed.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Berube</surname>
                        <forename>Linda</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of East Anglia, United Kingdom</affiliation>
                    <email>l.berube@uea.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bennett</surname>
                        <forename>Mike</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Edinburgh, United Kingdom</affiliation>
                    <email>mike.bennett@ed.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Hadden</surname>
                        <forename>Richard</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Edinburgh, United Kingdom</affiliation>
                    <email>richard.hadden@ed.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019-04-01T15:52:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Name, Institution</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Street</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>City</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Country</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Name</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Classification</term>
                    <term>Library Datasets</term>
                    <term>User Studies</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>digital archives and digital libraries</term>
                    <term>metadata</term>
                    <term>GLAM: galleries</term>
                    <term>libraries</term>
                    <term>archives</term>
                    <term>museums</term>
                    <term>interdisciplinary &amp; community collaboration</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                    <term>library &amp; information science</term>
                    <term>digital humanities (history</term>
                    <term>theory and methodology)</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Libraries are sources of large-scale data: both in terms of their collections and
                    the information they collate on their spaces, users, and systems. These data
                    provide opportunities to explore technical, methodological, and ethical
                    questions from the valuable interdisciplinary perspective of Data Science and
                    the Digital Humanities. In light of this, we will explore our analysis of
                    library datasets using <hi rend="italic">Subjectify</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> The code and documentation for
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Subjectify </hi>is available on
                            Github at <ref target="https://github.com/mbennett-uoe/librarytools"
                                >https://github.com/mbennett-uoe/librarytools</ref>. </p>
                    </note>, an automatic classification matching tool developed to assist analysis
                    of UK Non-Print Legal Deposit (NPLD) collections. NPLD regulations were
                    introduced to the UK in 2013 to support legal deposit libraries to collect
                    electronic publications (2013). Access restrictions mean that readers may only
                    use these materials on fixed terminals within the physical walls of the six
                    legal deposit libraries (see British Library, 2014 for details). The resultant
                    web logs are therefore unambiguous sources of NPLD collection usage within UK
                    legal deposit libraries. </p>
                <p> Our study is part of an established tradition of user studies in the digital
                    humanities. To date, these have focused on user behaviour with digital resources
                    (Warwick et al., 2008; Ross and Terras, 2011; Sinn and Soares, 2014). Web log
                    analysis has been used successfully in this context for over twenty years
                    (Almind and Ingwersen, 1997; Nicholas et al., 2005; Gooding, 2016). These
                    studies adopt methodological approaches and topics of study that contribute
                    directly to our understanding of information sources in the digital humanities.
                    However, there have been fewer studies that address critical humanistic
                    perspectives to inform approaches to the data itself. This paper addresses that
                    gap by describing our research into the users of NPLD materials in the United
                    Kingdom, and the implications of automatic classification matching for library
                    dataset analysis. It will address the following questions: what insights into
                    users of digital library collections can be derived from automatic
                    classification matching? What limitations are introduced by the use of existing
                    classification schemes? And, in light of ongoing debates on responsible data
                    curation in DH (Weingart, 2014; Brown et al., 2016), how might DH and LIS
                    scholars collaborate to inform ethical analysis of large-scale library datasets?
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Methodology</head>
                <p>Our analysis follows Bates’ observation that scholarly communication practices
                    function differently across domains, and that “these many differences
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">do </hi>make a difference” (1998: 1200)
                    to information access and use: as such, we should be able to identify
                    differences in behaviour by studying the subjects requested by users. To this
                    end we were provided with two datasets comprising title-level NPLD access logs
                    from the reading rooms of the six UK legal deposit libraries <note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> The six libraries are the British Library, National
                            Library of Scotland, National Library of Wales, Bodleian Libraries,
                            Cambridge University Library, and Trinity College Dublin Library.</p>
                    </note>. The anonymous logs contained only bibliographic records of NPLD
                    materials accessed by users, excluding both identifiable information about users
                    and interactions with discovery systems and other materials. The first dataset
                    comprised metadata for all eBook requests (total 91,809) from 31 <hi
                        rend="superscript">st</hi> July 2015 to 31 <hi rend="superscript">st</hi>
                    March 2017. The second dataset comprised metadata for all eJournal article
                    requests (total 36,506) over the same period. Each dataset contained the
                    following metadata: date and time of access request; originating legal deposit
                    library; title of book or article; journal title (where applicable); publisher;
                    and ISBN or ISSN. Each dataset was provided as a CSV file, then cleaned by the
                    research team in OpenRefine to address metadata errors. </p>
                <p> Although our dataset contained no identifiable information about users, it may
                    still be possible to infer information about users from the works they consult.
                    We therefore decided to abstract our data and undertake a macroanalysis of user
                    behaviour. To achieve this, we created a small <rs type="software"
                    >Python</rs>-based tool called <hi rend="italic">Subjectify</hi>. This tool uses
                    the OCLC Classify2 API service <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <ref target="http://classify.oclc.org/classify2/api_docs/index.html"
                                >http://classify.oclc.org/classify2/api_docs/index.html</ref>
                        </p>
                    </note> to automatically obtain Dewey Decimal (DDC) and Library of Congress
                    (LCC) classmarks from CSV files using key data fields such as title, author, and
                    ISBN. It additionally provides for different options to locate relevant fields
                    to allow input from different data sources.
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Subjectify </hi>found a matching
                    classmark for 76.42% for eBooks, and 55.53% for eJournals. This was partly due
                    to missing key data fields in records for eJournals, and partly because many
                    records did not have a corresponding classmark: time-consuming manual
                    classification samples via OCLC Classify2 achieved only slightly higher accuracy
                    rates. We discarded unclassified records used the remaining records to represent
                    patterns of usage by DDC subject. Due to the large number of repeat requests due
                    to system timeouts, we split the remaining records into unique titles (each
                    title counted once regardless of number of requests), and total results
                    (including repeat requests). Our results show that findings were not unduly
                    influenced by repeat requests. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Findings</head>
                <p>The following charts show the most commonly accessed subject, by DDC, for titles
                    viewed by users of eBook and eJournal materials. We found that usage by DDC
                    differs distinctly from the spread of classmarks across, for instance, the BL’s
                    entire collections <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> The sub-subroutine blog has produced a fascinating
                            visualisation of the BL’s collections, which is worthy of comparison
                            (sub-subroutine, 2015). </p>
                    </note>: </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="12.726458333333333cm" height="7.070255555555556cm"
                        url="Pictures/f8725612077c7049f871fbf5d92c9ff1.jpg" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1002" width="12.964583333333334cm" height="8.951736111111112cm"
                        url="Pictures/bbdcb2df147ebb5f5c876c4a58000e4b.jpg" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Social Sciences texts were notably among the most commonly accessed titles for
                    both formats. The most common subject for eJournals was Technology, whereas for
                    eBooks both Social Sciences and Literature subjects were more frequently
                    accessed. Our findings reflect differing information behaviour across domains:
                    books, for instance, remain a vital source for the Arts and Humanities (Stone,
                    1982; Palmer and Cragin, 2008) whereas technology and science subjects rely on
                    journals (Talja and Maula, 2003), which tend to provide faster publication of
                    new research. Indeed, Stone’s flagship early study noted that “retrospective
                    coverage may be more important to the humanists than having access to current
                    material” (1982: 296). The Social Sciences, on the other hand, are shown by our
                    findings to be more hybrid in their reading patterns. </p>
                <p> Analysing individual subject categories can derive a better sense of the
                    difference between institutions. The following charts show usage of books in the
                    DDC600-699 classmark (Technology), for the Bodleian Libraries, British Library
                    and Cambridge University Library.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1003" width="13.440833333333334cm" height="8.05235cm"
                        url="Pictures/171c543d7377ca8eec9cb3fd9555dc7d.jpg" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1004" width="13.707180555555556cm" height="8.149166666666666cm"
                        url="Pictures/5d8cb4425a137eb2886c532f607eb2c8.jpg" rend="inline"/>
                    <graphic n="1005" width="13.520208333333333cm" height="9.50826111111111cm"
                        url="Pictures/f4c6a5d676019fdb175f9b38fa5d7a7e.jpg" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The British Library receives proportionally fewer requests for NPLD medical and
                    health materials. Our interviews with staff at the Bodleian and Cambridge
                    University libraries showed that local medical school staff were a key user
                    group, so we can trace a direct correlation between the user communities of
                    these libraries, and the subjects of the NPLD material used. </p>
                <p> Finally, the following table demonstrates usage of 800-899 (Literature) sources
                    to underline a key problem with DDC for automatic classification:</p>
                <p>Library classification is a subjective process undertaken by humans within the
                    biased frameworks provided by existing classification schemes (Mai, 2010). Here,
                    for instance, DDC provides distinct categories for English, American, and
                    classical European schools of literature, while lumping the rest of the world
                    under “other literatures” (800-899). This bias emerges from the nineteenth
                    century North American perspective embedded within DDC (Kua, 2008). By relying
                    on automatic matching, we inevitably embed problematic perspectives into our
                    data: while our case study uses UK legal deposit collections, which comprise
                    works represented strongly by DDC, the applicability of this method for library
                    datasets in other parts of the world is questionable. Each time we zoom in with
                    the macroscope, the bias of our chosen classification scheme becomes
                    increasingly evident in the resultant data structures – yet in order to report
                    on literature from without the established canon, we have to do precisely this.
                    The use of established classification schemes is therefore both a methodological
                    and epistemological problem, and future work will be needed to refine our
                    approach. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Our results demonstrate that
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Subjectify </hi>was successful in
                    allowing us to analyse user behaviour at scale. It contributes to macroscopic
                    analysis of library data in two ways: first, it allows us to report on
                    bibliographic library users while maintaining privacy through data abstraction;
                    and second, this abstraction allows us to identify patterns of user behaviour
                    with NPLD materials. We believe this approach would work for subject-based
                    analysis of similar collections of bibliographic data, and that it does so in a
                    way that closely reflects how collections are represented in libraries. However,
                    we are also aware that automated classification introduces the biases of those
                    classification schemes into our own data (Adler, 2017). This is an unfortunate
                    side effect of the growing scale of library data. Weingart (2014) notes that the
                    role of the humanities is to tie the very distant to the very close, in order to
                    become ethical stewards of our data. It is therefore essential, when viewing
                    library datasets from a humanistic perspective, to consider the ethics of data
                    representation in our own work. Our priority for future work is to consider how
                    a fruitful conversation between DH and Information Science might develop more
                    nuanced approaches to representing (in the sense meant by Unsworth, 2000) of
                    library data. This should include further consideration of the consequences of
                    how bias in library classification schemes affects microanalytic approaches to
                    bibliographic datasets. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography"> (2017). <hi rend="bold">Adler, M.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Cruising the Library: Perversities in the Organization of
                            Knowledge</hi>. New York: Fordham University Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Almind, T. C. and Ingwersen, P.</hi> (1997). Infometric
                        Analyses on the World Wide Web: Methodological Approaches to ‘Webometrics’.
                            <hi rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</hi>, <hi rend="bold"
                        >53</hi>(4). </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Bates, M.</hi> (1998). Indexing and access for digital
                        libraries and the Internet: human, database, and domain factors. <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal of the American Society for Information
                            Science</hi>, <hi rend="bold">49</hi>(13)
                        doi:10.1002/(SICI)1097-4571(1998110)49:13&lt;1185::AID-ASI6&gt;3.3.CO;2-M
                        (accessed 23 March 2011). </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">British Library</hi> (2014). Legal Deposit <hi rend="italic"
                            >British Library - About Us</hi> http://www.bl.uk/aboutus/legaldeposit/. </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Brown, S., Clement, T., Mandell, L., Verhoeven, D. and
                            Wernimont, J.</hi> (2016). Creating Feminist Infrastructures in the
                        Digital Humanities. Krakow http://dh2016.adho.org/abstracts/233 (accessed 10
                        March 2017). </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Gooding, P.</hi> (2016). Exploring the information behaviour
                        of users of Welsh Newspapers Online through web log analysis. <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</hi>, <hi rend="bold">72</hi>(2):
                        232–46. </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Kua, E.</hi> (2008). Non-Western Languages and Literatures
                        in the Dewey Decimal Classification Scheme. <hi rend="italic">Libri</hi>,
                            <hi rend="bold">54</hi>(4): 256–265 doi:10.1515/LIBR.2004.256. </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Mai, J.</hi> (2010). Classification in a social world: bias
                        and trust. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</hi>, <hi rend="bold"
                            >66</hi>(5): 627–42 doi:10.1108/00220411011066763. </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Nicholas, D., Jamali, H. R. and Huntington, P.</hi> (2005).
                        The use and users of scholarly e-journals: a review of log analysis studies.
                            <hi rend="italic">Aslib Proceedings</hi>, <hi rend="bold">57</hi>(6):
                        554–71. </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Palmer, C. L. and Cragin, M. H.</hi> (2008). Scholarship and
                        disciplinary practices. <hi rend="italic">Annual Review of Information
                            Science and Technology</hi>, <hi rend="bold">42</hi>(1): 163–212
                        doi:10.1002/aris.2008.1440420112. </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Ross, C. and Terras, M.</hi> (2011). Scholarly
                        Information-Seeking Behaviour in the British Museum Online Collection.
                        Philadelphia, PA
                        http://www.museumsandtheweb.com/mw2011/papers/scholarly_information_seeking_behaviour_in_the
                        (accessed 10 October 2012). </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Sinn, D. and Soares, N.</hi> (2014). Historian’s Use of
                        Digital Archival Collections: The Web, Historical Scholarship, and Archival
                        Research. <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Association for Information
                            Science and Technology</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Online First</hi>
                        http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/asi.23091/abstract (accessed 26
                        June 2014). </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Stone, S.</hi> (1982). Humanities Scholars: Information
                        Needs and Uses. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</hi>, <hi
                            rend="bold">38</hi>(4): 292–313. </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">sub-subroutine</hi> (2015). Visualising the distribution of
                        human knowledge in the Dewey Decimal System <hi rend="italic"
                            >Sub-Subroutine</hi>
                        http://www.subsubroutine.com/sub-subroutine/2014/12/29/dewey-decimal-system-and-books-filed-therein
                        (accessed 11 November 2018). </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Talja, S. and Maula, H.</hi> (2003). Reasons for the use and
                        non <hi style="font-family:Cambria Math">‐</hi>use of electronic journals
                        and databases: A domain analytic study in four scholarly disciplines. <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</hi>, <hi rend="bold">59</hi>(6):
                        673–91 doi:10.1108/00220410310506312. </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Unsworth, J.</hi> (2000). Scholarly Primitives: What Methods
                        do Humanities Researchers Have in Common, and How Might our Tools Reflect
                        This?. King’s College London
                        http://people.brandeis.edu/~unsworth/Kings.5-00/primitives.html (accessed 5
                        August 2014). </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Warwick, C., Terras, M., Huntington, P. and Pappa, N.</hi>
                        (2008). If You Build It Will They Come? The LAIRAH Study: Quantifying the
                        Use of Online Resources in the Arts and Humanities. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi>, <hi rend="bold">23</hi>(1):
                        85–102. </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Weingart, S.</hi> (2014). The moral role of DH in a
                        data-driven world. Lawrence, Kansas http://www.scottbot.net/HIAL/?p=40944
                        (accessed 2 November 2018). </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">(2013). <hi rend="italic">The Legal Deposit Libraries
                            (Non-Print Works) Regulations 2013</hi>.
                        http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2013/777/contents/made (accessed 15
                        August 2013). </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
