<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>“Fear in your Eyes”: Analyzing Threat Perception and Its Influence on Deadly Use of Force by Police Officers against Civilians Using Hebrew NLP Tools</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Keydar</surname>
                        <forename>Renana</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Faculty of Law, Hebrew University, Israel</affiliation>
                    <email>renana.keydar@mail.huji.ac.il</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019-05-21T11:19:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Name, Institution</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Street</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>City</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Country</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Name</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Late breaking poster</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>topic modeling</term>
                    <term>sentiment analysis</term>
                    <term>legal linguistics</term>
                    <term>automated content analysis</term>
                    <term>non-english language</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>corpus and text analysis</term>
                    <term>natural language processing</term>
                    <term>law</term>
                    <term>content analysis</term>
                    <term>data mining / text mining</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                    <term>digital humanities (history</term>
                    <term>theory and methodology)</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p rend="paper_abstract">
                <hi rend="italic color(222222)">Overview</hi>
                <hi rend="color(222222)">: This study seeks to explore and empirically substantiate the effects of the gap between objective and subjective threat perceptions of police officers in cases of lethal use of force against civilians. It focuses on a newly accessible corpus of digitized transcripts of police officers who testified before an Israeli State Commission of Inquiry in Hebrew. Combining topic modeling and sentiment analysis to explore subjective threat perceptions of duty holders, we aim to establish a deeper, empirically validated, understanding of serious human rights violations. The study makes an important methodological contribution to the field of NLP for non-English languages and non-Latin characters, by applying, for the first time, newly developed NLP tools for Hebrew on a Modern spoken Hebrew corpus. As such, it also contributes to the diversification of the DH community be opening it to minor languages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="italic color(222222)">Background</hi>
                <hi rend="color(222222)">: Police has extensive powers to use force against civilians. The killing of a civilian is also within the legal and legitimate range of force as long as the police officer acts to protect human life or is in mortal danger himself. Justifying the decision to use lethal force should meet the test of proportionality of the “reasonable police officer.” While the emphasis in previous studies was on the extent of the objective threat posed to the security forces, mainly by analyzing the characteristics of the event, this study takes a broader approach, both theoretically and methodologically, seeking to understand the subjective threat perception of the officers; feelings - of danger, fear or distress – which are crucial in justifying the decision to use of lethal force against civilians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="color(222222)" xml:space="preserve">In order to explore, substantiate and understand the gap between objective and subjective threat perceptions, we aim to examine officers testimonies from the protocols of The Israeli State Commission of Inquiry to investigate clashes between security forces and Israeli civilians during the events of October 2000, in which 13 Arab citizens and a resident of Gaza were killed  (henceforth: “The Or Commission”). The Or Commission held 92 public hearings and interviewed security forces involved in the specific incidents, eye-witnesses, politicians, senior police officers, public figures, and journalists. Therefore, examining the totality of the transcripts of the Commission’s hearings will enable us to understand in depth the various aspects of the threat perception that lead to the use of lethal force against civilians. Through an empirical semantic examination of the corpus, we intend to point out the ways in which social constructs that shape subjective threat perceptions and influence decision-making regarding the use of force against civilians. </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="italic color(222222)">Corpus and Methodology</hi>
                <hi rend="color(222222)" xml:space="preserve">: Our corpus consists of the protocols of the Or Commission deliberations (comprising more than 2 million words) and the Commission’s final report (holding more than 700 pages). While the Commission’s report is available for online review, the protocols and testimonies are not easily accessible. </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="italic color(222222)">The methodological contribution of the study</hi>
                <hi rend="color(222222)" xml:space="preserve">: </hi>
                <hi rend="bold color(222222)">First,</hi>
                <hi rend="color(222222)" xml:space="preserve"> it develops and applies tools and algorithms of topic modeling and sentiment analysis to a corpus of Modern Hebrew legal transcripts. </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="color(222222)" xml:space="preserve">Recent years have seen a modest rise in studies using computational tools to analyze legal corpora such as constitutions </hi>
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"Y7OlBzj0","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Law, 2016)","plainCitation":"(Law, 2016)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":858,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/3143625/items/5496XSCN"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/3143625/items/5496XSCN"],"itemData":{"id":858,"type":"article-journal","title":"Constitutional Archetypes","container-title":"Tex. L. Rev.","page":"153","volume":"95","source":"Google Scholar","author":[{"family":"Law","given":"David S."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2016"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi rend="color(222222)" xml:space="preserve">, US Supreme Court decisions </hi>
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"GzNoJhj7","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Livermore et al., 2017)","plainCitation":"(Livermore et al., 2017)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1881,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/3143625/items/GV6QX4N2"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/3143625/items/GV6QX4N2"],"itemData":{"id":1881,"type":"article-journal","title":"The Supreme Court and the judicial genre","container-title":"Ariz. L. Rev.","page":"837","volume":"59","source":"Google Scholar","author":[{"family":"Livermore","given":"Michael A."},{"family":"Riddell","given":"Allen B."},{"family":"Rockmore","given":"Daniel N."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2017"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi rend="color(222222)" xml:space="preserve"> or constitutional debates in the US Congress</hi>
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"EgLl7tdT","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Pozen et al., 2019)","plainCitation":"(Pozen et al., 2019)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2150,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/3143625/items/N94IKDYW"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/3143625/items/N94IKDYW"],"itemData":{"id":2150,"type":"report","title":"A Computational Analysis of Constitutional Polarization","publisher":"Social Science Research Network","publisher-place":"Rochester, NY","genre":"SSRN Scholarly Paper","source":"papers.ssrn.com","event-place":"Rochester, NY","abstract":"This Article is the first to use computational methods to investigate the ideological and partisan structure of constitutional discourse outside the courts. We apply a range of machine-learning and text-analysis techniques to a newly available data set comprising all remarks made on the U.S. House and Senate floors from 1873 to 2016, as well as a collection of more recent newspaper editorials. Among other findings, we demonstrate:(1) that constitutional discourse has grown increasingly polarized over the past four decades; (2) that polarization has grown faster in constitutional discourse than in non-constitutional discourse; (3) that conservative-leaning speakers have driven this trend; (4) that members of Congress whose political party does not control the presidency or their own chamber are significantly more likely to invoke the Constitution in some, but not all, contexts; and (5) that contemporary conservative legislators have developed an especially coherent constitutional vocabulary, with which they have come to “own” not only terms associated with the document’s original meaning but also terms associated with textual provisions such as the First Amendment. Above and beyond these concrete contributions, this Article demonstrates the potential for computational methods to advance the study of constitutional history, politics, and culture.","URL":"https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=3351339","number":"ID 3351339","language":"en","author":[{"family":"Pozen","given":"David"},{"family":"Talley","given":"Eric L."},{"family":"Nyarko","given":"Julian"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2019",3,12]]},"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2019",3,26]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi rend="color(222222)" xml:space="preserve">. The scholarly potential, however, is far from exhaustion. In the Israeli field, such research has to overcome crucial language barriers, as in the current state of the field, there are no ready-made or sufficiently-tested NLP tools for modern Hebrew </hi>
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"DlGMan1e","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Amram et al., 2018)","plainCitation":"(Amram et al., 2018)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2230,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/3143625/items/37X3AJF8"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/3143625/items/37X3AJF8"],"itemData":{"id":2230,"type":"paper-conference","title":"Representations and Architectures in Neural Sentiment Analysis for Morphologically Rich Languages: A Case Study from Modern Hebrew","page":"2242-2252","source":"www.aclweb.org","event":"Proceedings of the 27th International Conference on Computational Linguistics","URL":"https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/papers/C/C18/C18-1190/","title-short":"Representations and Architectures in Neural Sentiment Analysis for Morphologically Rich Languages","language":"en-us","author":[{"family":"Amram","given":"Adam"},{"family":"Ben-David","given":"Anat"},{"family":"Tsarfaty","given":"Reut"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2018",8]]},"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2019",5,21]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi rend="color(222222)" xml:space="preserve">. Our study is first of its kind to employ NLP methods for empirical legal research in Hebrew. </hi>
                <hi rend="bold color(222222)">Second,</hi>
                <hi rend="color(222222)" xml:space="preserve"> it combines topic modeling and sentiment analysis in order to examine subjective perceptions of threat of duty holders. Applied together, these computational methods make it possible to uncover the hidden semantic themes and to identify the emotional and subjective affects expressed by the various voices in the corpus, thus providing an empirical-computational basis for examining the construction of threat perceptions of the security forces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p style="text-align:left; ">
                <hi rend="color(222222)">As such, the research presented here is innovative both in the corpus it examines, and in the methodologies that it implements, in order to establish a deeper understanding of serious human rights violations.</hi>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
