<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI.internal">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Formal Ontologies, Linked Data, and TEI Semantics</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Fabio</forename>
            <surname>Ciotti</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Fabio Ciotti is a <roleName>tenured assistant professor</roleName> at the
              <orgName>University of Roma Tor Vergata</orgName>, where he teaches digital literary
            studies and theory of literature. He is <roleName>president</roleName> of the
              <orgName>Associazione per l’Informatica Umanistica e la Cultura Digitale</orgName>
            (AIUCD, the Italian Digital Humanities association), a former elected member in the TEI
            Consortium Technical Council, and a current member of the EADH (European Association of
            Digital Humanities) Executive Board. His scientific and research work covers various
            aspects and themes of Digital Humanities and literary studies, from both the theoretical
            and the practical point of view. Fabio Ciotti has been a scientific consultant for text
            encoding and technological infrastructures in several digital libraries and archives
            projects, most notably Biblioteca Italiana (Italian literary tradition, <ptr
              target="http://www.bibliotecaitaliana.it"/>) and DigilibLT (Late Latin tradition, <ptr
              target="http://www.digiliblt.unipmn.it/"/>).</affiliation>
          <email>fabio.ciotti@uniroma2.it</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Francesca</forename>
            <surname>Tomasi</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Francesca Tomasi is <roleName>assistant professor</roleName> in Library and
            Archival Science in the School of Italian Studies at the <orgName>University of
              Bologna</orgName>, where she teaches courses on archives and computer, multimedia
            production, and Digital Humanities. Her research is focused in particular on digital
            editions, digital libraries, and digital historical archives. She is President of the
            Library of the School of Humanities in the University of Bologna. She is the editor of a
            scholarly digital edition (Vespasiano da Bisticci, Letters: <ptr
              target="http://vespasianodabisticciletters.unibo.it"/>, 2013). Among her last
            publications she counts the monograph <title level="m">The Digital Humanist. A Critical
              Inquiry</title>, with D. Fiormonte and T. Numerico, Punctum books, Brooklyn, NY 2015
            and several articles dedicated to data modeling and extraction in the context of
            Cultural Heritage objects.</affiliation>
          <email>francesca.tomasi@unibo.it</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>24/09/2016</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Martin Müller</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Anne Baillot</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="9">Selected Papers from the 2014 TEI Conference; TEI and
          Materiality</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Revues.org -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>ontology</term>
          <term>linked data</term>
          <term>XML semantics</term>
          <term>modeling</term>
          <term>Semantic Web</term>
          <term>text encoding theory</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>The debate on the semantic role of markup languages has been quite lively and the TEI
          community has played an active part in it. It is commonly acknowledged that markup conveys
          semantic information. However, XML is a poor language for semantic data modeling. Several
          proposals have previously been drawn up in the past to provide XML with formalized and
          computable semantics. In our opinion, the formalisms offered by the Semantic Web paradigm
          are mature enough to build a workable semantic extension of the TEI.</p>
        <p>Our model distinguishes three semantic layers in the TEI: one general and shared
          intensional semantic layer; one idiolectal specialized layer; and finally an extensional
          semantics. Our proposal is directed toward the first two layers. We propose to build such
          semantic layers by adopting a set of OWL formal ontologies.</p>
        <p>Furnishing the TEI with a semantics based on a formal ontology could have interesting
          outcomes: facilitating the management of and research using document collections in open
          and multi-standard contexts; aiding interoperability with other relevant standards in the
          digital cultural heritage context; and providing users with advanced formal tools to
          semantically define their interpretations of the texts and enable innovative computational
          processing. In order to allow a semantic interoperability between standards, the TEI
          ontology has to be aligned to other models; likewise mapping and merging procedures have
          to be evaluated. Finally, the idea of migrating XML/TEI documents following this semantic
          model into a linked open data dimension requires that we face important issues in order to
          facilitate the data interchange in the cloud.</p>
        <p>However, the cost and the practical complexity of such an extension are notable, and
          several theoretical problems, format choices, and implementation details are still to be
          defined.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="problem">
        <head>The Problem of XML Semantics</head>
        <p>The debate on the semantic role of markup languages has been quite lively during the last
          twenty years and the experience of the TEI community has played an active role in it. It
          is commonly acknowledged that markup conveys semantic information, ranging from local
            <soCalled>interpretations</soCalled> produced by a single scholar to general and shared
          visions of <quote source="#quoteref1">what is text, really</quote> (<ref type="bibl"
            xml:id="quoteref1" target="#derose97">De Rose et al. 1997</ref>).</p>
        <p>However, the widespread notion that markup and, in particular, XML markup has a semantic
          role or conveys semantic content, is flawed in a relevant sense. As Robin Cover observed
          some years ago: <cit>
            <quote source="#quoteref2">XML is a poor language for data modeling if the goal is to
              represent information objects in the problem domain such that they correspond
              transparently (<soCalled>one-to-one</soCalled>) to the user’s conceptual model of
              objects in this domain.</quote>
            <ref type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref2" target="#cover98">Cover 1998</ref>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p>XML is a powerful formalism to define the syntactic aspects of the markup language. It is
          based on formal grammars, making it possible to automatically parse a document and
          validate its formal structure against a predefined schema. Furthermore, XML implies a
          (meta) data model, the well-known <term>ordered tree</term>. This enables the adoption of
          the language as a modeling device for some structural relationships of document-like
          information objects: <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>hierarchy (A contains B)‏</item>
            <item>ordered adjacency (A followed by B)‏</item>
            <item>co-occurrence (if A then B)‏</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>Some recent <term>schema languages</term> (W3C Schema in particular) have also introduced
          strong data typing for element content and attribute values. Nonetheless, XML does not
          provide a computational semantics to markup (or to data). The fallacy of the belief in XML
          semantic awareness is hidden by the fact that XML markup is <term>human-readable</term>
          and usually by design XML vocabularies are meaningful lexical items in a natural language.
          But the meaning of those vocabularies is not accessible by an XML processor. As far as an
          XML parser is concerned, <code>&lt;title&gt;Finnegans Wake&lt;/title&gt;</code> and
            <code>&lt;blob&gt;Finnegans Wake&lt;/blob&gt;</code> are both acceptable and well-formed
          markup instances.</p>
        <p>XML owes its semantic value and consistency almost entirely to human interpretation and
          control. Any markup restriction or semantic role, accordingly, needs to be expressed in
          natural language as instructions or documentation for human users. The TEI Guidelines
            (<ref type="bibl" target="#tei15">TEI Consortium 2015</ref>) are one epitomizing example
          of that kind of documentation. A more formal and controlled approach is the <term>literate
            programming</term>–oriented<note>See <ref target="#knuth84" type="bibl">Knuth
            1984</ref>.</note> ODD formalism (<ref target="#burnard13" type="bibl">Burnard
            2013</ref>), developed by TEI in order to combine in a single meta-XML document the
          definition of an XML schema and all its relevant documentation.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="debate">
        <head>The XML Semantic Debate</head>
        <p>Several proposals have been drawn up to provide XML with formalized and computable
          semantics. The work of Renear, Dubin, Sperberg-McQueen, and Huitfeldt (e.g., <ref
            target="#msmq00" type="bibl">Sperberg-McQueen, Huitfeldt, and Renear 2000</ref> and <ref
            target="#renear02" type="bibl">Renear, Sperberg-McQueen, and Huitfeldt 2002</ref>)
          constitutes the first, explicit contribution in this direction. These authors, from the
          observation that semantic markup coincides with the set of inferences authorized by one of
          its constructs, propose a formal markup semantics based on Prolog clauses. More recent
          works on the topic have proposed an RDF-based model for text encoding (<ref
            target="#tummarello05" type="bibl">Tummarello, Morbidoni, and Pierazzo 2005</ref>; <ref
            target="#tummarello06" type="bibl">Tummarello et al. 2006</ref>); explored the potential
          of an OWL vocabulary that represents some core semiotic notions, in order to provide a
          better understanding of the semantics of markup (<ref target="#peroni11" type="bibl"
            >Peroni, Gangemi, and Vitali 2011</ref>); and revisited the idea of <q>transcriptional
            implicature</q> (<ref target="#msmq08" type="bibl">Sperberg-McQueen and Huitfeldt
            2008</ref>; <ref target="#msmq10" type="bibl">Sperberg-McQueen, Marcoux, and Huitfeldt
            2010</ref> and <ref target="#msmq14" type="bibl">2014</ref>).</p>
        <p>In these studies the range of application possibilities offered by the definition of a
          formal semantics for markup is widely recognized and justified: <cit>
            <quote source="#quoteref3">a formal description of the semantics of a markup language
              can bring several benefits. One of them is the ability to develop provably correct
              mappings (conversions, translations) from one markup language to another. A second one
              is the possibility of automatically deriving facts from documents, and feeding them
              into various inferencing or reasoning systems. A third one is the possibility of
              automatically computing the semantics of part or whole of a document and presenting it
              to humans in an appropriate form to make the meaning of the document (or passage)
              precise and explicit.</quote>
            <ref target="#msmq10" xml:id="quoteref3" type="bibl">Sperberg-McQueen, Marcoux, and
              Huitfeldt 2010</ref>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p>Nonetheless the same authors observe that if proposals for formal semantic approaches to
          markup have been very scarce, their practical applications are even fewer.</p>
        <p>The reasons for this lack of interest from the wider encoding community are manifold and
          complex: <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>theoretical complexity in a domain already hard to understand for the average
              humanist scholar;</item>
            <item>technical and practical difficulties in the application and exploitation of the
              approaches proposed;</item>
            <item>lack of tools and applications;</item>
            <item>excessively <soCalled>revolutionary</soCalled> scope of some proposals.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="ontology">
        <head>A Formal Ontology Approach for TEI Semantics</head>
        <p>Since the first discussions of the semantics of markup languages in the early ‘90s and
          today’s situation, the Semantic Web (or Web 3.0) paradigm and, more recently, linked data
          have developed and spread. This process has made available a number of syntactically
          rigorous and semantically well-founded languages and data-models, to represent (Resource
          Description Framework, RDF), logically define (RDF Schema; Ontology Web Language, OWL 2),
          and query (SPARQL) semantic data. In parallel with this diffusion of Web 3.0 architectural
          formalisms, a good number of systems and software components aimed at semantic data
          processing (storage, query, and inference) have appeared, mostly in the open source
          domain.</p>
        <p>Given this theoretical and technological context, we believe that a Semantic Web approach
          can represent the most viable solution, giving a formal definition to the implicit
          concepts underlying XML text encoding. In particular, in this paper we propose an
            <term>ontological</term> extension of the TEI framework to partially formalize the
          semantics of the markup constructs it provides.</p>
        <p>The term ontology is used to designate a large and varied class of objects, ranging from
          controlled vocabularies and thesauruses to proper formal ontologies. In this paper we
          refer to the latter meaning: a formalized and shared account of a conceptual description
          of a domain (<ref target="#gruber09" type="bibl">Gruber 2009</ref>).</p>
        <p>In the context of computer and information sciences, an ontology defines a set of
          representational primitives with which to model a domain of knowledge or discourse. The
          representational primitives are typically classes (or sets), attributes (or properties),
          and relationships (or relations among class members). The definitions of the
          representational primitives include information about their meaning and constraints on
          their logically consistent application.</p>
        <p>In Semantic Web architecture, formal ontologies have the role of logically defining and
          constraining the terms of the descriptive languages adopted to state the semantic
          properties of information resources. This has an obvious parallel with the problem of
          assigning a semantics to markup languages like TEI.</p>
        <p>The motivations for adopting a formal ontological approach in our proposal are both
          theoretical and practical. In the text-encoding domain (as in the entire field of Digital
          Humanities), models and modeling play a central methodological and foundational role. In
          the relevant literature we commonly find assertions stating that text encoding is a kind
          of modeling. The very problem with models and modeling is that they are <emph>umbrella
            terms</emph>, relating to an ample and diverse set of conceptual objects and
          practices.</p>
        <p>In our view the practice of ontological modeling is a good operationalist translation of
          the common definition of model. From the practical point of view, formal ontologies give
          access to a number of powerful computational tools and methods, like the application of
          inference and reasoning engines to analyze the textual data. Another relevant property of
          the Semantic Web ontology formalisms is the ability to compare and eventually merge
          different ontologies. This property has some desirable consequences in our context of
          application, especially in conjunction with another property of Semantic Web ontologies,
          the Open World Assumption (<ref target="#patel-schneider06" type="bibl">Patel-Schneider
            and Horrocks 2006</ref>). In brief, this assumption means that from the lack of an
          explicit assertion stating that some fact is true it does not follow that the fact is
          false (or its negation true), simply that it is not known. In a wider sense this means
          that knowledge can be incomplete and that it is possible that the attributes of a concept
          can be incomplete at any given moment. This property of a Semantic Web ontology is very
          helpful when the domain is very complex and subject to different points of view, and its
          modeling is conceived as a work in progress.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="rationale">
        <head>Rationales and Principles for a TEI Ontology</head>
        <p>In order to avoid, as far as possible, the shortcomings of the earlier proposals for
          markup semantics, we have identified some guiding principles to drive the development of
          our ontology-driven approach.</p>
        <list rend="ordered">
          <item>To adopt well-established Semantic Web formalisms and technologies, in order to
            ensure that our approach is theoretically sound and practically implementable.</item>
          <item>To extend, not attempt to replace, the current languages and practices; as long as
            Relax NG, W3C Schema, and ODD formalisms can do their job, there is no need to replace
            them. On the contrary, we believe that our ontological extension must cooperate and
            interoperate with the existing ecosystem of TEI technology.</item>
          <item>To limit our ontological modeling <foreign xml:lang="la">prima facie</foreign> to a
            subset of the TEI encoding scheme, the <soCalled>core</soCalled> markup facilities; it
            remains to be decided how to identify that core. The TEI community has historically
            tried to define subsets of the markup language to ease adoption and diffusion: TEI Lite
              (<ref target="#burnard12" type="bibl">Burnard and Sperberg-McQueen 2012</ref>) and TEI
            Tite are well-known examples. We think that the best candidate for a test bed of the
            ideas presented in this paper is the TEI Simple customization of the TEI scheme (<ref
              target="#turska16" type="bibl">Turska, Cummings, and Rahtz 2016</ref>). The main
            reason for this choice is that this subset has been defined in a bottom-up approach from
            the analysis of the actual markup usage in some big text encoding projects. We are aware
            that this choice will leave aside some important and widely adopted parts of the TEI;
            nonetheless it is the best <soCalled>ready-made</soCalled> approximation of a subset of
            the TEI emerging from the wide and diverse pragmatic uses of the language in the
            community.</item>
          <item>To provide a practical solution for some concerns that are relevant in the actual
            digital ecosystem in which TEI and XML live, especially interoperability and Linked Data
            exposition of XML TEI document content.</item>
          <item>To appropriately distinguish between three different semantic levels expressed by
            the markup and its content: <list rend="simple">
              <item>(a) general intensional semantics of TEI markup;</item>
              <item>(b) specific intensional semantics of TEI markup (defined by a particular user
                or community of practice);</item>
              <item>(c) extensional semantics of the markup elements.</item>
            </list>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>The terms <soCalled>intensional</soCalled> and <soCalled>extensional</soCalled> semantics
          are to be taken in the meaning that was given to those terms by Carnap (<ref
            target="#carnap47" type="bibl">1947</ref>): <soCalled>intension</soCalled> indicates the
          internal content (and structure) of a lexical term or concept, what constitutes its formal
          definition; and <soCalled>extension</soCalled> indicates the set of objects to which it
          can be applied.</p>
        <p>Level (a) is defined by the maximal shared assumptions and usage practices of the TEI
          markup constructs, and it is translated into a general TEI ontology. For example, the
          meaning of the <gi>seg</gi> element is <q>a phrase level sequence of linguistic units</q>.
          Level (b) relates to the particular interpretation of the markup adopted by a single or
          collective user. For example, in a given encoding project, the <gi>seg</gi> element might
          be used, for example, as a <q>linguistic manifestation of a character’s feature</q>. Level
          (c) concerns the extensional semantics of the individual XML element’s content within a
          document. We adopt the term <soCalled>extensional</soCalled> because, in general, it is
          suitable for fixing the referent of a linguistic expression identified by the markup
          through its reference to resources (information entities) via URI, or the connection to
          items in a linked data set. The current TEI scheme already handles the case of simple
          extensional links with one or more external resources through the <att>ref</att> attribute
          (whose value is one or more <ident>xsd:anyURI</ident>), or the <att>key</att> attribute,
          as already evaluated (<ref target="#ciula08" type="bibl">Ciula, Spence, and Vieira
            2008</ref>). More complex relations with external semantic data could require complex
          stand-off markup structures (e.g., <ref target="#huitfeldt01" type="bibl">Huitfeld and
            Sperberg-McQueen 2001</ref>; <ref target="#msmq04" type="bibl">Sperberg-McQueen and
            Huitfeld 2004</ref>; a general survey in <ref target="#schmidt10" type="bibl">Schmidt
            2010</ref>).</p>
        <p>The levels properly involved in our proposal are levels (a) and (b). Obviously the
          extensional semantics is not totally independent from the ontological and intensional
          levels, and we will need to find proper methods to formally link all those levels (cf.
            <ptr target="#mapping" type="crossref"/>). This paper, though, will only sketch the main
          picture of our general proposal, since many technical details are still to be defined.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="generalontology">
        <head>TEI General Ontology</head>
        <p>The first level, TEI general ontology, formalizes the common notion that the TEI
            <soCalled>is</soCalled> or <soCalled>expresses</soCalled> a general text ontology. In
          several aspects, this statement overlaps with the well-known statement made by
          Sperberg-McQueen that the <quote source="#quoteref4">markup reflects a theory of
            text</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref4" target="#msmq91" type="bibl">1991</ref>). There is
          no general agreement that the TEI can actually be reduced to one ontology. We concede that
          this is true for the TEI as a whole, and that in principle there is no way to identify the
            <soCalled>one true ontology</soCalled> of a text. But in practice we are confident that
          under normal conditions all encoders share the same single interpretation for many common
          markup constructs, because of cultural and dispositional factors. On the other hand, as
          Guarino (<ref target="#guarino09" type="bibl">2009</ref>) notes, a formal ontology always
          includes epistemological aspects as well as pure ontological assertions and therefore it
          is by nature prospective and amendable.</p>
        <p>The underlying ontology of TEI is partially formalized in the set of TEI XML schema
          constraints, and for the most part conveyed by the natural-language prose of the
          Guidelines. One possible and rapid approach to producing a formal ontology for TEI would
          be the adaptation of the aforementioned constraints into a set of ontological statements
          in OWL. The conversion of XML schemas into OWL ontologies has been discussed in many
          papers in the last ten years, and many theoretical and computational solutions have been
          proposed (e.g., <ref target="#bohring05" type="bibl">Bohring and Auer 2005</ref>; <ref
            target="#ghawi09" type="bibl">Ghawi and Cullot 2009</ref>). We cannot address the
          technical details of these solutions here. Most of them are based on the mapping of W3C
          Schema primitives into OWL primitives.</p>
        <p>The adoption of this kind of strategy could make the construction of a formal high-level
          TEI ontology a partially automated process. However, it is evident that the most relevant
          semantic properties of the markup, which cannot be expressed by common schema languages
          (and ODD), would not be modeled by this semi-mechanical translation.</p>
        <p>The TEI itself has made an attempt to define explicitly its underlying conceptual model
          with the notions of abstract models and of element classes: <cit>
            <quote source="#quoteref5">The <term>TEI Abstract Model</term> is the conceptual schema
              instantiated by the TEI Guidelines. These Guidelines define, both formally and
              informally, a set of abstract concepts such as <soCalled>paragraph</soCalled> or
                <soCalled>heading</soCalled>, and their structural relationships, for example
              stating that <soCalled>paragraph</soCalled>s do not contain
                <soCalled>heading</soCalled>s. These Guidelines also define classes of elements,
              which have both semantic and structural properties in common. Those semantic and
              structural properties are also a part of the TEI Abstract Model.<gap/></quote>
            <ref target="#tei15" xml:id="quoteref5" type="bibl">TEI Consortium 2015, 23.4.3</ref>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p>And specifically, regarding the design of the element classes and the naming conventions
          adopted to convey their typology, the Guidelines state: <cit>
            <quote source="#quoteref6">In fact, the nature of a given class of elements can be
              considered along two dimensions: as noted, it defines a set of places where the class
              members are permitted within the document hierarchy; it also implies a semantic
              grouping of some kind. For example, the very large class of elements which can appear
              within a paragraph comprises a number of other classes, all of which have the same
              structural property, but which differ in their field of application. Some are related
              to highlighting, while others relate to names or places, and so on.<gap/> If a model
              class has a name containing <soCalled>part</soCalled>,<gap/> then it is primarily
              defined in terms of its structural location.<gap/> If, however, a model class has a
              name containing <soCalled>like</soCalled>,<gap/> the implication is that its members
              all have some additional semantic property in common.<gap/></quote>
            <ref target="#tei15" xml:id="quoteref6" type="bibl">TEI Consortium 2014, 1.3.2</ref>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p>It is therefore possible to identify a set of strictly structural constraints, expressed
          in ODD or RelaxNG patterns, and a set of informal or semi-formal semantic/taxonomic
          directives. A proper ontological modeling should express both the abstract
          characterization of TEI elements’ semantics and the ontological definition of their
          structural role. In addition, the ontology should define a precise semantics of the
          elements that are characterized unambiguously in the official TEI documentation (e.g., the
          element <gi>p</gi>), while it should relax the semantical constraints if the elements in
          consideration can be used with different semantic connotations depending on the context
          (e.g., the element <gi>seg</gi>). Finally, it should be possible to extend the ontology,
          reuse it, and define alternative characterizations of element semantics without
          compromising the consistency of the ontology itself.</p>
        <p>In accordance with these overall principles we have decided to implement a complex
          ontological architecture, using some pre-existing meta-ontology frameworks to express the
          meaning of the TEI element set. The specification of markup semantics for the various TEI
          elements is done by means of LA-EARMARK classes and properties. The Extremely Annotational
          RDF Markup (EARMARK) is at the same time a markup metalanguage, which can express both the
          syntax and the semantics of markup as OWL assertions, and an ontology of markup that makes
          explicit the implicit assumptions of markup languages, providing a finer specification of
          their properties. LA-EARMARK is an extension of EARMARK with the Linguistic Act module of
          the Linguistic Meta-Model ontology, which allows the expression and assessment of facts,
          constraints, and rules about the markup structure as well as about the inherent semantics
          of the markup elements themselves (<ref target="#peroni09" type="bibl">Peroni and Vitali
            2009</ref>; <ref target="#peroni11" type="bibl">Peroni, Gangemi, and Vitali
          2011</ref>).</p>
        <p>The general EARMARK class to define any markup element is <ident>earmark:Element</ident>.
          For instance, the <gi>abbr</gi> element is defined as follows (in Manchester Syntax): <eg><![CDATA[
              Prefix earmark: <http://www.essepuntato.it/2008/12/earmark#>
              
              Prefix tei: <http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0/>
              
              Class: tei:abbr a
              earmark:Element that
              earmark:hasGeneralIdentifier "abbr" and
              earmark:hasNamespace "http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            ]]>
          </eg>
        </p>
        <p>We need to create appropriate restrictions of classes in order to identify and
          characterize possible subsets of elements described by the schema. This is achieved by
          adopting the classes and properties of the Collections Ontology (CO), which in OWL defines
          unordered and ordered collections (<ref target="#ciccarese14" type="bibl">Ciccarese and
            Peroni 2014</ref>). For instance, the class of all the <gi>tei:p</gi> elements that
          occur inside <gi>tei:text</gi> and not inside <gi>tei:teiHeader</gi>: <eg><![CDATA[
              <tei:teiHeader>:
              Prefix earmark: <http://www.essepuntato.it/2008/12/earmark#>
              Prefix co: <http://purl.org/co/>
              Prefix tei: <http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0/>

              Class: tei:pInText
              	EquivalentTo:
              		earmark:Element that
              			earmark:hasGeneralIdentifier "p" and
              			earmark:hasNamespace "http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" and
              			co:elementOf some (
              				earmark:Element that
              				 earmark:hasGeneralIdentifier "body" and
              				 earmark:hasNamespace "http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0")
            ]]>
          </eg>
        </p>
        <p>This class is disjoint from <ident>tei:pInTeiHeader</ident> class.</p>
        <p>LA-EARMARK allows us to link particular classes of elements with the actual semantics
          they express. From our point of view, as we said, there are at least two semantic levels
          that we are interested in defining explicitly: <list rend="ordered">
            <item>One level concerns the structural behavior of markup (e.g., the fact that an
              element is a block rather than an inline, a container rather than a field). This can
              be described by means of existing models such as the Pattern Ontology (<ref
                target="#diiorio14" type="bibl">Di Iorio et al. 2014</ref>).</item>
            <item>The other relates to the intended semantics of an element (e.g., the fact that an
              element is a paragraph rather than a section, a personal name reference rather than a
              geographical reference). This can be described by a specialized TEI Semantics Ontology
              or by a combination (and/or an extension) of already existing ontologies.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>The TEI Semantics Ontology component is the core layer in our architecture, and is
          actually under development. Its class hierarchy is defined on the base of the TEI abstract
          model classes, but a lot of work and refactoring is needed to achieve sound ontological
          structure.</p>
        <p>The lower-level classes are the concepts expressed by TEI markup construct. It is worth
          noting, though, that there is not a one-to-one relation between elements and lower-level
          semantic classes, since we can identify at least three different markup
            <soCalled>crystals</soCalled> that can have a different ontological meaning: <list
            rend="ordered">
            <item>one XML element on its own: e.g., <gi>abbr</gi>;</item>
            <item>an XML element/attribute couple or a compound of so-called <soCalled>Janus
                elements</soCalled>: e.g., <code>&lt;corr resp=></code> or
                <code><![CDATA[<choice><sic><corr>]]></code>
            </item>
            <item>one XML element in a given context: e.g., <gi>p</gi> in <gi>text</gi> vs.
                <gi>p</gi> in <gi>teiHeader</gi>.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>The link between the class describing kinds of elements and their related semantic
          characterization is expressed by means of the property <ident>semiotics:expresses</ident>
          provided by the Linguistic Act Ontology included in LA-EARMARK. The associations of
          semantics to markup elements can also be contextualized according to a particular agent’s
          point of view, in order to provide provenance data pointing to the entity who was
          responsible for such specification. This is possible by means of properties that allow one
          to assign agency and responsibility to all these markup-to-semantics relations, as proper
          linguistic acts performed by someone.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="intensionalsemantics">
        <head>Specific Intensional Semantics of TEI Markup</head>
        <p>The specific intensional semantics is the level where local or even idiolectal semantic
          specifications of the markup can be defined. At this level we can find the specific
          structures of meaning that a markup term has for a specific user or community. For
          example, think of a specialization in the use of abstract container elements such as
            <gi>div</gi>, <gi>ab</gi>, and <gi>seg</gi> by way of the <att>type</att> attribute that
          defines a restriction of the semantics compared to the one defined at the general ontology
          level.</p>
        <p>These ontology specializations can be expressed as: <list rend="ordered">
            <item>restrictions on properties and classes that extend the general ontology in
              OWL;</item>
            <item>a set of inference rules expressed through Rule Language (like SRWL), which extend
              the general OWL ontology;</item>
            <item>local contextual restrictions expressed as LA-EARMARK properties, as seen
              above.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>How can a user possibly declare these local semantic extensions? The obvious place to
          declare these user- or project-specific ontological specifications for the TEI is the ODD
          document. One possible and straightforward solution is to adopt the <gi>constraint</gi>
          element already provided by the ODD language. Admittedly this choice would represent a
          sort of tag abuse, since this element is thought to bear restrictions on XML elements or
          attributes that can be validated by a parsing process, not semantic constraints. So the
          advisable solution will be to introduce a dedicated element in the ODD personalization
          that allows a user to declare the relevant ontological constraints in OWL. Those formulas
          could then be added to the general ontology during ODD processing.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="mapping">
        <head>Ontology Mapping, Matching, and Merging</head>
        <p>Alignment of ontologies is a necessary step in the project. The creation of ontologies is
          the strongest example of knowledge conceptualization. This activity likewise requires a
          network dialogue in order to deal with interoperability issues and try to solve the
          problem of semantic heterogeneity in naming of classes and predicates. The TEI semantic
          enhancement proposed here has to compare the TEI general ontology with some selected,
          existent, and pertinent models already used in other domains and communities.</p>
        <p>Ontological modeling is a complex and iterative process, and it requires a deep
          understanding of the role of classes and predicates, and how they are used in different
          domains. So creating correspondences is the most difficult issue: the ontology is a
          subjective representation of reality and therefore it is natural that differences between
          points of view occur. Any attempt to classify the mismatches between ontologies must
          recognize possible issues at both the linguistic and the semantic levels. The most common
          issue derives from the different use of the same concepts in different domains. But the
          use of distinct names for the same concept also has to be considered. Problems could also
          emerge from other modeling features: the different scope of some classes or predicates;
          the different focus in classes and predicates definition; the possibility of using
          different constructs; different modeling conventions; and different levels of
          granularity.</p>
        <p>Mapping, matching, and merging are the common methods used in order to address issues
          related to semantic integration (<ref target="#noy04" type="bibl">Noy 2004</ref>; <ref
            target="#choi06" type="bibl">Choi, Song, and Han 2006</ref>). These processes require on
          the one hand the comparison between models and on the other the possible integration of
          single elements of different vocabularies into one single model.</p>
        <p>First of all it is necessary to understand that ontology alignment requires the creation
          of binary relationships between the vocabularies of two ontologies. This problem could be
          solved with an ontology-to-ontology mapping, but it could also make use of a common
          reference ontology (upper-level ontology) onto which the different models are mapped. A
          study of the existing tools and methods (<ref target="#kalfoglou03" type="bibl">Kalfoglou
            and Schorlemmer 2003</ref>) will be necessary in order to face the problem (from machine
          learning, concept lattices, and formal theories to heuristics, database schemas, and
          linguistics).</p>
        <p>If the mapping requires the selection of a method (<ref target="#yang07" type="bibl"
            >Yang, Steele, and Lo 2007</ref>), choosing which ontologies are potentially in conflict
          or in agreement with our semantic TEI proposal is not merely a secondary issue to face. A
          particularly relevant aspect of the conceptual model definition process will then be to
          check the pertinent existing ontologies in order to ensure maximum portability in all
          contexts. The TEI Ontologies SIG has already done some relevant work in this area,
          especially the work of Ore and Eide with CIDOC-CRM (<ref target="#ore09" type="bibl"
            >2009</ref>). In particular, the last paper by Eide (<ref target="#eide15" type="bibl"
            >2015</ref>) describes some mapping solutions. However, besides the most common
          ontologies devoted, for example, to cultural heritage (CIDOC-CRM), archives (EAD and
          EAC-CPF), and metadata (DC, DC terms, and EDM), other ontologies, developed in other
          domains, provide new forms of conceptualization. For example, an ontology such as FABIO or
          CiTO could be an interesting application case (<ref target="#peroni12" type="bibl">Peroni
            and Shotton 2012</ref>). FABIO is based on the FRBR approach to the document as a
          complex entity. The stratification of analysis levels enriches the description of cultural
          entities. CiTO is useful in order to manage the citation process, towards the definition
          of multiple relationships and cross-relationships between the data related to attribution
          statements. In particular, CiTO makes it possible to define the relationships between an
          interpretation and the source supporting that interpretation. But other common ontologies
          and models, such as FOAF, SKOS, Bibframe, or Schema.org, are a necessary reference for
          attempting semantic interoperability. But the analysis of the state of the art has to be
          combined with another fundamental step: integrating into the ontology information already
          conceptualized in other domains. This means that the TEI model will be refined by
          acquiring the vocabulary used in the domains mentioned above: already shared and
          public-domain classes and properties could be encapsulated in the TEI conceptual model. At
          the same time the TEI model could contribute to populating other models: specific classes
          and properties could be reused by other communities as a result of the TEI semantic
          extension. In both cases, the process must be done with the awareness of the objective
          impossibility of a complete overlapping of models. By adopting this hybrid approach we
          approximate semantic interoperability: interconnection, integration, and semantic dialogue
          are vital ingredients in the process. We could even try to approach the deepest
          interchange possible between conceptual models (<ref target="#bauman11" type="bibl">Bauman
            2011</ref>). The greater the sharing of principles inside the community of humanities,
          the better the process will work.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="lod">
        <head>LOD Conversion and Dissemination</head>
        <p>In order to test the outlined model the TEI ontology must be verified in a linked open
          data dimension (i.e., tested in <ref target="http://lov.okfn.org/dataset/lov/">Linked Open
            Vocabularies</ref>)<note> Pierre-Yves Vandenbussche and Bernard Vatant, Linked Open
            Vocabularies, <ptr target="http://lov.okfn.org/dataset/lov/"/>.</note> and, likewise,
          TEI documents must be analyzed in order to attempt a semantic enrichment. The TEI ontology
          proposal is thus helpful in exposing both the TEI semantic model and individual TEI
          documents as linked data. TEI conversion into LOD consists of a sequence of steps that
          covers two levels of analysis: the work on the TEI model at the schema level, and the work
          on TEI XML files in order to produce open and linked data using the modeled ontology.</p>
        <p>The first level is related to the above description of the TEI model formalization for a
          first macro-modelization. This level also encompasses mapping of the TEI ontological model
          onto selected ontologies in order to guarantee interchange and expressivity of the model
          from a reuse perspective. The second level is instead related to our definition of
            <soCalled>extensional semantics</soCalled>: adding identification mechanisms to in-line
          markup, eventually pointing to stand-off description, and refining the TEI markup in order
          to be LOD-compliant. This will mean going beyond data silos, opening towards the
            <soCalled>web of data</soCalled> in an integrated environment. In detail: <list
            rend="bulleted">
            <item>the user experience will improve through a machine-interpretable semantics (TEI
              will be more <soCalled>understandable</soCalled> by the machine);</item>
            <item>the recall, i.e., the fraction of the documents that are relevant to the query
              that are successfully retrieved, will be more precise (the specification of the TEI
              predicates’ role will refine the results);</item>
            <item>disambiguation, by using a conceptual model, will be more precise, especially in
              case of homography of classes and predicates (TEI classes and predicates will be
              mapped onto the same concepts in other ontologies);</item>
            <item>mashup practices (smart applications) will improve the knowledge base through new
              connections, even between heterogeneous domains (the TEI model will dialogue with
              other communities);</item>
            <item>inferences will be available, giving the possibility of new knowledge
              discovery.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>As Berners-Lee (<ref target="#bernerslee06" type="bibl">2006</ref>) states, many research
          and evaluation projects in the domain of Semantic Web technologies have produced
          ontologies. From the LOD perspective, i.e., a fundamental step in the direction of the
          Semantic Web realization, the ontology support would provide benefits in semantic
          expressivity, data interchange, and machine—but also users’—real exploitation (<ref
            target="#heath11" type="bibl">Heath and Bizer 2011</ref>). In the <soCalled><ref
              target="http://5stardata.info/">LOD 5 Stars</ref></soCalled><note><ptr
              target="http://5stardata.info/"/></note> idea, the use of ontology is not compulsory.
          In our model the ontological support will be the key to enriching data in order to augment
          the semantic of TEI documents, by transforming the information managed by the schema in
          knowledge defined by the ontology. The idea of a strong interconnection between ontologies
          and the possibility of creating relationships between vocabularies, from a reuse-oriented
          perspective, will be fundamental to making the TEI semantic model compliant with the
          cloud: <q>link your data to other data to provide context</q> (the five-star level in the
              <soCalled><ref target="http://5stardata.info/">5-star open data
              plan</ref></soCalled>);<note><ptr target="http://5stardata.info/"/></note> that is,
          the context is determined by the relationships. Siloed data are not able to express their
          semantic power. Information is the result of mutual connections between data. The
          knowledge graph approach, coined by Google in 2012 (<ref target="#singhai12" type="bibl"
            >Singhal 2012</ref>) is demonstrating that one of the natural consequences of the
          migration from document to data, inaugurated by the Semantic Web, enriches the user
          experience.</p>
        <p>In order to finalize the model from an LOD cloud perspective—as regards the collection of
          TEI-based documents—various methods will have to be explored, beginning with the creation
          of an RDF triple store by converting some pertinent elements of the refined TEI XML files
          into RDF through XSLT. Experiments in converting XML files into RDF have already been
          undertaken: <quote source="#quoteref7">a transformation to RDF has to create the URIs of
            its resources and connect them through the RDF triple structure consisting of subject,
            predicate and object</quote> (<ref target="#breitling09" xml:id="quoteref7" type="bibl"
            >Breitling 2009</ref>).</p>
        <p>The problem is double: how to define dereferenceable URIs for elements (concepts and/or
          real web documents) and how to work on a specific XML dialect, that is, the TEI
          vocabulary?</p>
        <p>These questions are not trivial because they require reflection on the TEI markup model.
          The topic is difficult and we are now trying to address this complexity. A first approach
          we are attempting is the following. In general we can assert that: TEI elements are
            <ident>rdf:description</ident> about a node id (e.g., through an <att>ref</att>) that we
          could manage in XSLT for transforming the <att>ref</att> value into a URI. This approach
          yields: <eg><![CDATA[
            SUBJECT = rdf:description about a TEI element (the @ref value)
            PREDICATE = an attribute of the element in the subject (for managing cross-references) or, simplest, the child element
            OBJECT = literal (the content of the element)
]]></eg>
        </p>
        <p>An example of an XML TEI markup in a document: <egXML
            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <person ref="#persona01">
              <persname>Vespasiano</persname>
            </person>
          </egXML> That is: an entity (person) with a value (a fragment) referring to a
            <att>xml:id</att> (<val>persona01</val>) to be converted in dereferenceable URI (e.g.,
            <ident>http://www.person.it/about#persona01</ident>) through XSLT, a predicate
          corresponding to the child element (<ident>persname</ident>) and a literal as the object
          (Vespasiano). Another fundamental issue is the identification of pertinent authorities for
          the data matching (e.g., VIAF, Geonames, Worldcat, SNAP, or DBpedia). In order for the
          datasets to be able to exchange information in a network dimension, sharing of authorities
          is a crucial point. Mechanisms such as <soCalled>see-also</soCalled> or even
            <soCalled>same-as</soCalled> could manage relationships between named entities.</p>
        <p>Likewise, the need for a really <soCalled>linked</soCalled> environment requires the
          discovery of links in the cloud by using semi-automatic methods of entity recognition
          (NER).</p>
        <p>Finally, populating the LOD cloud Data Catalog and the <ref target="https://datahub.io/"
            >Datahub</ref><note>Open Knowledge Foundation, Datahub, <ptr
              target="https://datahub.io/"/>.</note> with both the semantic vocabulary and the
          converted datasets will improve visibility and interchange.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="conclusion">
        <head>Conclusions and Perspectives</head>
        <p>In our opinion, the possibility of providing a TEI-formalized semantics using Semantic
          Web standard technology constitutes a good opportunity to achieve these objectives: <list
            rend="ordered">
            <item>Strictly set out the general semantics of the markup language in order to
              facilitate management and research in open and multi-standard contexts, such as
              large-scale general libraries and large institutional repositories.</item>
            <item>Facilitate interoperability with other standards relevant in the digital cultural
              heritage context include any XML TEI repository in the open linked data (LOD)
              environment (<ref target="#isaac11" type="bibl">Isaac et al. 2011</ref>). TEI could be
              redefined as a <soCalled>linked open vocabulary</soCalled> able to exchange
              information with other LOV datasets at either vocabulary or element level.</item>
            <item>Ease the conversion of existent TEI-based digital libraries into open and linked
              datasets able to be shared in the LOD cloud.</item>
            <item>Provide users with advanced formal tools to define their interpretations of the
              texts to which they apply the markup, and allow innovative computational processing
              based on semantics, using tools such as reasoners and semantic query engines.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>However, the cost and the practical complexity of such an extension are significant, and
          several theoretical problems, format choices, and implementation details remain to be
          defined.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bauman11"><author>Bauman, Syd</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title level="a"
              >Interchange vs. Interoperability</title>. In <title level="m">Proceedings of
              Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</title>. <series>Balisage Series on Markup
              Technologies</series>, <biblScope unit="volume">vol. 7</biblScope>. doi:<idno
              type="doi">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Bauman01</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bernerslee06"><author>Berners-Lee, Tim</author>. <date>2006</date>. <title
              level="u">Linked Data</title>. Personal Note, Last modified June 18, 2009. <ptr
              target="https://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/LinkedData.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bohring05"><author>Bohring, Hannes</author>, and <author>Sören
            Auer</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title level="a">Mapping XML to OWL
            Ontologies</title>. In <title level="m">Marktplatz Internet: Von e-Learning bis
              e-Payment. 13. Leipziger Informatik-Tage (LIT 2005)</title> Lecture Notes in
            Informatics P-72, edited by <editor>Klaus P. Jantke</editor>, <editor>Klaus-Peter
              Fähnrich</editor>, and <editor>Wolfgang S. Wittig</editor>,
              <biblScope>147–56</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="http://subs.emis.de/LNI/Proceedings/Proceedings72/GI-Proceedings.72-11.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="breitling09"><author>Breitling, Frank</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title
              level="a">A Standard Transformation from XML to RDF via XSLT</title>. <title level="j"
              >Astronomische Nachrichten</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">330</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">755–60</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="http://arxiv.org/abs/0906.2291"/>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1002/asna.200811233</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burnard13"><author>Burnard, Lou</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
              level="a">Resolving the Durand Conundrum</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the Text
              Encoding Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>. <ptr target="http://jtei.revues.org/842"/>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.4000/jtei.842</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burnard12"><author>Burnard, Lou</author>, and <author>C. M.
              Sperberg-McQueen</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="u">TEI Lite: Encoding for
              Interchange: An Introduction to the TEI</title>. Final revised edition for TEI P5,
            August. <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/Lite/index.xml"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="carnap47"><author>Carnap, Rudolf</author>. <date>1947</date>. <title
              level="m">Meaning and Necessity: A Study in Semantics and Modal Logic</title>.
              <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Chicago
            Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="choi06"><author>Choi, Namyoun</author>, <author>Il-Yeol Song</author>, and
              <author>Hyoil Han</author>. <date>2006</date>. <title level="a">A Survey on Ontology
              Mapping</title>. <title level="j">ACM SIGMOD Record</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">34–41</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1145/1168092.1168097</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ciccarese14"><author>Ciccarese, Paolo</author>, and <author>Silvio
              Peroni</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">The Collections Ontology:
              Creating and Handling Collections in OWL 2 DL Frameworks</title>. <title level="j"
              >Semantic Web</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">515–29</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.3233/SW-130121</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ciula08"><author>Ciula, Arianna</author>, <author>Paul Spence</author>, and
              <author>José Miguel Vieira</author>. <date>2008</date>. <title level="a">Expressing
              Complex Associations in Medieval Historical Documents: The Henry III Fine Rolls
              Project</title>. <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">311–25</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1093/llc/fqn018</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cover98"><author>Cover, Robin</author>. <date>1998</date>. <title level="a"
              >XML and Semantic Transparency</title>. Technology report. In <title level="m">Cover
              Pages</title>. Last modified November 24, 1998. <ptr
              target="http://xml.coverpages.org/xmlAndSemantics.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="derose97"><author>DeRose, Steven J.</author>, <author>David G.
              Durand</author>, <author>Elli Mylonas</author>, and <author>Allen H. Renear</author>.
              <date>1997</date>. <title level="a">What Is Text, Really?</title>. <title level="j"
              >ACM SIGDOC Asterisk: The Journal of Computer Documentation</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">1–24</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1145/264842.264843</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="diiorio14"><author>Di Iorio, Angelo</author>, <author>Silvio
            Peroni</author>, <author>Francesco Poggi</author>, and <author>Fabio Vitali</author>.
              <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">Dealing with Structural Patterns of XML
              Documents</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the Association for Information Science
              and Technology</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">1884–1900</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1002/asi.23088</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="eide15"><author>Eide, Øyvind</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title level="a"
              >Ontologies, Data Modeling, and TEI</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the Text
              Encoding Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>. <ptr target="http://jtei.revues.org/1191"/>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.4000/jtei.1191</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ghawi09"><author>Ghawi, Raji</author>, and <author>Nadine Cullot</author>.
              <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">Building Ontologies from XML Data Sources</title>.
              <title level="m">20th International Workshop on Database and Expert Systems
              Applications</title>, <biblScope unit="page">480–84</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1109/DEXA.2009.68</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gruber09"><author>Gruber, Tom</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="a"
              >Ontology</title>. In <title level="m">Encyclopedia of Database Systems</title>,
            edited by <editor>Ling Liu</editor> and <editor>M. Tamer Özsu</editor>. <pubPlace>New
              York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Springer</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="guarino09"><author>Guarino, Nicola</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title
              level="a">The Ontological Level: Revisiting 30 Years of Knowledge
              Representation</title>. In <title level="m">Conceptual Modeling: Foundations and
              Applications. Essays in Honor of John Mylopoulos</title>, edited by <editor>Alexander
              T. Borgida</editor>, <editor>Vinay K. Chaudhri</editor>, <editor>Paolo
              Giorgini</editor>, and <editor>Eric S. Yu</editor>. <series>Lecture Notes in Computer
              Science</series>
            <biblScope unit="issue">5600</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="page">52–67</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Heidelberg</pubPlace>: <publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>. doi:<idno
              type="doi">10.1007/978-3-642-02463-4_4</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="heath11"><author>Heath, Tom</author>, and <author>Christian Bizer</author>.
              <date>2011</date>. <title level="m">Linked Data: Evolving the Web into a Global Data
              Space</title>. <series>Synthesis Lectures on the Semantic Web: Theory and
              Technology</series>, lecture <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>. <pubPlace>San
              Rafael, CA</pubPlace>: <publisher>Morgan &amp; Claypool</publisher>. doi:<idno
              type="doi">10.2200/S00334ED1V01Y201102WBE001</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="huitfeldt01"><author>Huitfeldt, Claus</author>, and <author>C. M.
              Sperberg-McQueen</author>. <date>2001</date>. <title level="u">TexMECS: An
              Experimental Markup Meta-language for Complex Documents</title>. Working paper of the
            project Markup Languages for Complex Documents (MLCD). University of Bergen. Revised
            October 5, 2003. <ptr
              target="http://mlcd.blackmesatech.com/mlcd/2003/Papers/texmecs.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="isaac11"><author>Isaac, Antoine</author>, <author>William Waites</author>,
              <author>Jeff Young</author>, and <author>Marcia Zeng</author>. <date>2011</date>.
              <title level="u">Library Linked Data Incubator Group: Datasets, Value Vocabularies,
              and Metadata Element Sets</title>. W3C Incubator Group Report (25 October). <ptr
              target="http://www.w3.org/2005/Incubator/lld/XGR-lld-vocabdataset-20111025/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kalfoglou03"><author>Kalfoglou, Yannis</author>, and <author>Marco
              Schorlemmer</author>. <date>2003</date>. <title level="a">Ontology Mapping: The State
              of the Art.</title>
            <title level="j">The Knowledge Engineering Review</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">1–31</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="http://eprints.soton.ac.uk/260519/1/ker02-ontomap.pdf"/>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1017/S0269888903000651</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="knuth84"><author>Knuth, Donald E.</author>
            <date>1984</date>. <title level="a">Literate Programming</title>. <title level="j">The
              Computer Journal</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>),
              <biblScope unit="page">97–111</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1093/comjnl/27.2.97</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="noy04"><author>Noy, Natalya F.</author>
            <date>2004</date>. <title level="a">Semantic Integration: A Survey of Ontology-based
              Approaches</title>. <title level="j">ACM Sigmod Record</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>),
              <biblScope unit="page">65–70</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1145/1041410.1041421</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ore09"><author>Ore, Christian-Emil</author>, and <author>Øyvind
              Eide</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">TEI and Cultural Heritage
              Ontologies: Exchange of Information?</title>. <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic
              Computing</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">161–72</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1093/llc/fqp010</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="patel-schneider06"><author>Patel-Schneider, Peter F.</author>, and
              <author>Ian Horrocks</author>. <date>2006</date>. <title level="a">Position Paper: A
              Comparison of Two Modelling Paradigms in the Semantic Web</title>. In <title level="m"
              >Proceedings of the 15th International World Wide Web Conference</title>, <biblScope
              unit="page">3–12</biblScope>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>ACM</publisher>. doi:<idno type="doi"
            >10.1145/1135777.1135784</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="peroni11"><author>Peroni, Silvio</author>, <author>Aldo Gangemi</author>,
            and <author>Fabio Vitali</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title level="a">Dealing with
              Markup Semantics</title>. In <title level="m">Proceedings of the 7th International
              Conference on Semantic Systems (I-Semantics 2011)</title>, edited by <editor>Ciara
              Ghidini</editor>, <editor>Axel-Cyrille Ngonga Ngomo</editor>, <editor>Stefanie
              Lindstaedt</editor>, and <editor>Tassilo Pellegrini</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >111–18</biblScope>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>ACM</publisher>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.1145/2063518.2063533</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="peroni12"><author>Peroni, Silvio</author>, and <author>David
              Shotton</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">FaBiO and CiTO: Ontologies for
              Describing Bibliographic Resources and Citations</title>. <title level="j">Journal of
              Web Semantics: Science, Services and Agents on the World Wide Web</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>:<biblScope unit="page">33–43</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.1016/j.websem.2012.08.001</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="peroni09"><author>Peroni, Silvio</author>, and <author>Fabio
            Vitali</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">Annotations with EARMARK for
              Arbitrary, Overlapping and Out-of-order Markup</title>. In <title level="m"
              >Proceedings of the 9th ACM Symposium on Document Engineering (DocEng 2009)</title>,
              <biblScope unit="page">171–80</biblScope>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>ACM</publisher>. doi:<idno type="doi"
            >10.1145/1600193.1600232</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="renear02"><author>Renear, Allen</author>, <author>David Dubin</author>,
              <author>C. M. Sperberg-McQueen</author>, and <author>Claus Huitfeldt</author>.
              <date>2002</date>. <title level="a">Towards a Semantics for XML Markup</title>. In
              <title level="m">DocEng’02: Proceedings of the 2002 ACM Symposium on Document
              Engineering</title>, edited by <editor>Ethan Munson</editor>, <editor>Richard
              Furuta</editor>, and <editor>Jonathan I. Maletic</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >119–26</biblScope>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>ACM Press</publisher>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.1145/585058.585081</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="schmidt10"><author>Schmidt, Desmond</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title
              level="a">The Inadequacy of Embedded Markup for Cultural Heritage Texts</title>.
              <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">337–56</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1093/llc/fqq007</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="singhai12"><author>Singhal, Amit</author> (May 16, <date>2012</date>).
              <title level="a">Introducing the Knowledge Graph: Things, Not Strings</title>. <title
              level="j">Official Blog</title> (of Google). <ptr
              target="https://googleblog.blogspot.it/2012/05/introducing-knowledge-graph-things-not.html"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="msmq91"><author>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</author>
            <date>1991</date>. <title level="a">Text in the Electronic Age: Textual Study and Text
              Encoding, with Examples from Medieval Texts.</title>
            <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">34–46</biblScope>. doi:10.1093/llc/6.1.34</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="msmq04"><author>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</author>, and <author>Claus
              Huitfeldt</author>. <date>2004</date>. <title level="a">GODDAG: A Data Structure for
              Overlapping Hierarchies</title>. In <title level="m">Digital Documents: Systems and
              Principles</title> [Revised papers from the 8th International Conference on Digital
            Documents and Electronic Publishing (DDEP 2000) and the 5th International Workshop on
            the Principles of Digital Document Processing (PODDP 2000)], edited by <editor>Peter
              King</editor> and <editor>Ethan V. Munson</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >139–160</biblScope>. <series>Lecture Notes in Computer Science</series>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2023</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Springer</publisher>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1007/978-3-540-39916-2_12</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="msmq08"><author>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</author>, and <author>Claus
              Huitfeldt</author>. <date>2008</date>. <title level="a">Markup Discontinued:
              Discontinuity in TexMecs, Goddag structures, and Rabbit/Duck Grammars</title>. In
              <title level="m">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2008</title>.
              <series>Balisage Series on Markup Technologies</series>, <biblScope unit="volume">vol.
              1</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
            >10.4242/BalisageVol1.Sperberg-McQueen01</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="msmq00"><author>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</author>, <author>Claus
              Huitfeldt</author>, and <author>Allen Renear</author>. <date>2000</date>. <title
              level="a">Meaning and Interpretation of Markup</title>. <title level="j">Markup
              Languages: Theory &amp; Practice</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">215–34</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="http://cmsmcq.com/2000/mim.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="msmq10"><author>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</author>, <author>Yves
              Marcoux</author>, and <author>Claus Huitfeldt</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title
              level="u">Two Representations of the Semantics of TEI Lite</title>. Paper presented at
            Digital Humanities 2010, London, July 7–10. Abstract available at <ptr
              target="http://dh2010.cch.kcl.ac.uk/academic-programme/abstracts/papers/html/ab-663.html"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="msmq14"><author>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</author>, <author>Yves
              Marcoux</author>, and <author>Claus Huitfeldt</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title
              level="u">Transcriptional Implicature: A Contribution to Markup Semantics</title>.
            Paper presented at Digital Humanities 2014, Lausanne, Switzerland, July 7–12. Abstract
            available at <ptr target="http://dharchive.org/paper/DH2014/Paper-61.xml"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tei15"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2015</date>. <title
              level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>.
              <edition>Version 2.8.0</edition>. Last updated April 6. <ptr
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/2.8.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tummarello06"><author>Tummarello, Giovanni</author>, <author>Christian
              Morbidoni</author>, <author>Fabio Kepler</author>, <author>Francesco Piazza</author>,
            and <author>Paolo Puliti</author>. <date>2006</date>. <title level="a">A Novel Textual
              Encoding Paradigm Based on Semantic Web Tools and Semantics</title>. In <title
              level="m">Proceedings of the 5th Edition of the International Conference on Language
              Resources and Evaluation</title>, <biblScope unit="page">247–52</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>European Language Resources
              Association</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2006/pdf/225_pdf.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tummarello05"><author>Tummarello, Giovanni</author>, <author>Christian
              Morbidoni</author>, and <author>Elena Pierazzo</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title
              level="a">Toward Textual Encoding Based on RDF</title>. <title level="m">From Author
              to Reader: Proceedings of the 9th ICCC International Conference on Electronic
              Publishing (ELPUB 2005)</title>, <biblScope unit="page">57–63</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Leuven</pubPlace>: <publisher>Peeters</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://elpub.scix.net/data/works/att/206elpub2005.content.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="turska16"><author>Turska, Magdalena</author>, <author>James
              Cummings</author>, and <author>Sebastian Rahtz</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title
              level="a">Challenging the Myth of Presentation in Digital Editions</title>. <title
              level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>. <ptr target="https://jtei.revues.org/1453"/>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.4000/jtei.1453</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="yang07"><author>Yang, Kai</author>, <author>Robert Steele</author>, and
              <author>Amanda Lo</author>. <date>2007</date>. <title level="a">An Ontology for XML
              Schema Ontology Mapping Representation</title>. In <title level="m">Proceedings of the
              9th International Conference on Information Integration and Web-based Applications
              &amp; Services (iiWAS 2007)</title>, edited by <editor>Gabriele Kotsis</editor>,
              <editor>David Taniar</editor>, <editor>Eric Pardede</editor>, and <editor>Ismail
              Khalil Ibrahim</editor>. <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>: <publisher>Österreichische
              Computer Gesellschaft</publisher>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
