<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Materiality of TEI Encoding and Decoding</title>
        <title type="sub">An Analysis of the Western European Union Archives on Armament
          Policy</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Florentina</forename>
            <surname>Armaselu</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Florentina Armaselu is involved in text and technologies research at the
              <orgName>University of Luxembourg</orgName>. She obtained a PhD in comparative
            literature (2010) and a MSc in computational linguistics (2003) at the University of
            Montreal, Canada. Her current research focuses on digital editions, text encoding and
            text analysis.</affiliation>
          <email>florentina.armaselu@uni.lu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Verónica</forename>
            <surname>Martins</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Verónica Martins specialized in European Studies and her current research
            focuses on the Mediterranean region and security questions, mainly counter-terrorism.
            She attended the College of Europe where she got a MA in European Studies. In 2012, she
            obtained her PhD in Political Science, Europe specialisation, in a joint international
            supervision in Sciences-Po Paris and University of Minho. She worked as a researcher at
            the Centre Virtuel de la Connaissance sur l’Europe on a project on Franco-British
            relations within the Western European Union.</affiliation>
          <email>martinsveronica@yahoo.fr</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Catherine</forename>
            <forename>Emma</forename>
            <surname>Jones</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Dr Catherine (Kate) Jones is interested in the development of useful and
            usable systems and data analysis to form meaningful narratives. She is based at the
              <orgName>University of Luxembourg</orgName>. She studied for an MSc in Geographical
            Information Systems at University College London in 2002 and went on to complete a
            Knowledge Transfer Partnership, PhD and Post Doc at the same university, with a focus on
            interdisciplinary research and mapping technologies. </affiliation>
          <email>catherine.jones@uni.lu</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>19/09/2016</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Martin Müller</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Anne Baillot</editor>
        <editor role="technical" xml:id="RvdB">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="9">Selected Papers from the 2014 TEI Conference; TEI and
          Materiality</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Revues.org -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>WEU and armament digital edition</term>
          <term>text encoding</term>
          <term>text analysis</term>
          <term>digital hermeneutics</term>
          <term>materiality</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2018-01-12" who="#RvdB">technical editor applied changes per author request from
        email dated <date>2017-07-24</date></change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>By combining traditional historical enquiry with TEI XML encoding and decoding in a
          corpus analysis phase, the project aims at addressing research questions mainly related to
          the French and British positions on the topics of armament design and production and of
          armament control within the Western European Union (WEU) from 1954 to 1982. The paper
          focuses on the annotation of speakers (different countries and institutional
          representatives) and their discourse in a selection of institutional documents (minutes,
          notes, studies, memoranda) (encoding phase) and the identification of linguistic patterns
          on armament issues in their discourse, as well as the interpretation of results (decoding
          phase).</p>
        <p>From a larger perspective, the study considers the TEI encoding as adding to the original
          text a <soCalled>material</soCalled> layer that further supports both machine and human
          interpretation (decoding). In this sense, this study may move closer to the concept of
            <soCalled>material hermeneutics</soCalled>, by understanding code, and digital
          technology in general, as an instrument we can use in hermeneutic ways to produce
          knowledge.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="corrections">
        <p>This paper was revised on <date>2017-08-31</date> to include a missing reference:
            <q>(Heiden 2010)</q>. The previous version is archived at <ptr
            target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1733"/>.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="materiality">
        <head>On the Materiality of TEI Encoding and Decoding</head>
        <p>As Manoff (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref1" target="#manoff06">2006, 311</ref>) points
          out, the study of <quote source="#quoteref1">material aspects of digital objects</quote>
          may foster new concepts and theories explaining how these properties <quote
            source="#quoteref1">alter our ways of creating and consuming information</quote>.
          Through the lens of the history of the book, materiality may be related to things like
            <quote source="#quoteref1">typography, binding, illustration, and paper</quote>. In the
          world of digital artifacts, this can bring to light a <quote source="#quoteref2">whole new
            range of physical objects and processes, including platforms, interfaces, standards, and
            coding</quote> (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref2" target="#manoff06">312</ref>). From
          an editorial perspective, McGann (<ref xml:id="quoteref3" target="#mcgann01" type="bibl"
            >2001, 78</ref>) argues that a particular edition may draw attention to the <quote
            source="#quoteref3">dynamic engagement between text and its vehicular (material)
            form</quote> and in this respect, digital textuality differs from paper-based text as it
          can be designed for <quote source="#quoteref4">complex, interactive
            transformations</quote> (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref4" target="#mcgann01"
          >81</ref>). Referring to the transition from print, Hayles (<ref type="bibl"
            xml:id="quoteref5" target="#hayles05">2005, 1</ref>) assumes that the <quote
            source="#quoteref5">transformation of a printed document into an electronic text is a
            form of translation—<soCalled>media translation</soCalled></quote> that implies an
            <quote source="#quoteref5">act of interpretation</quote>, an edition representing an
          instantiation of a work in a <quote source="#quoteref5">physical form</quote>. In
          particular, relating the process of text encoding to hermeneutics, <quote
            source="#quoteref6">the art or science of interpretation</quote>, Burnard (<ref
            type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref6" target="#burnard98">1998, section 3</ref>) suggests that
          the <quote source="#quoteref6">markup maps a (human) interpretation of the text into a set
            of codes on which computer processing can be performed</quote>. Moreover, he sees this
          process as part of a decoding–encoding succession, the former implying <quote
            source="#quoteref7">a selection from the many features implicit in the reading of a
            text, and their re-encoding in explicit and unambiguous terms</quote>. (<ref type="bibl"
            xml:id="quoteref7" target="#burnard98">section 2</ref>)</p>
        <p>This article proposes a new perspective as a new link in the chain,
          decoding-encoding-decoding, by considering the aspects involved in the digitization, TEI
          XML encoding, and corpus analysis of a collection of documents from the Western European
          Union (WEU) paper archives specifically intended for web publication. Placing our approach
          at the crossroad of digital scholarly editing and digital philology (<ref
            target="#pierazzo14" type="bibl">Pierazzo 2014</ref>; <ref target="#andrews13"
            type="bibl">Andrews 2013</ref>), as well as digital hermeneutics (<ref
            target="#capurro10" type="bibl">Capurro 2010</ref>), we will focus on the TEI encoding
          as an addition to the original text, a <soCalled>material</soCalled> layer that further
          supports both machine and human interpretation. This type of materiality is actually
          related to the intrinsic performative quality of the code (either as markup or as part of
          a computer program), designed to be interpreted by the machine and to determine processing
          sequences and output that can become an object for further analysis. In this sense, we may
          move closer to Ihde’s (<ref target="#ihde03" type="bibl">2003</ref>) concept of
            <soCalled>material hermeneutics</soCalled> by understanding code, and digital technology
          in general, as an <soCalled>instrument</soCalled> we can use in <soCalled>hermeneutic
            ways</soCalled> to produce knowledge.</p>
        <p>In this context, by combining scholarly editing and hermeneutic perspectives, the paper
          discusses aspects related to building a digital edition of historical documents, the
          interpretation of documents (<term>decoding</term>) on which the XML-TEI annotation is
          based (<term>encoding</term>), as well as the elements and methods subsequently considered
          for corpus analysis in order to support interpretation of discursive phenomena
            (<emph>decoding</emph>). <ptr type="crossref" target="#description"/> describes the
          collection that forms the focus of the study, with reference to the original paper
          archives and the transformation into electronic form. <ptr type="crossref"
            target="#encoding"/> presents a selection of encoded samples and the rationale behind
          the encoding, from the perspective of its further usage in the decoding process. In <ptr
            type="crossref" target="#decoding"/>, we detail this process placing emphasis on the
          importing of the encoded data into the corpus analysis platform, the different types of
          analysis performed, and a discussion of results. <ptr type="crossref" target="#conclusion"
          /> concludes the paper with a review of both the benefits and limitations of the applied
          methods and the materiality underlying the encoding–decoding mechanism.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="description">
        <head>Description of the Collection</head>
        <p>The corpus (WEU-Diplo) chosen for TEI encoding represents a selection from the Archives
          nationales de Luxembourg<note>The exploitation of the WEU archives follows the decision
            C(11)05-Final of May 10, 2011, by the Permanent Council of the Western European Union,
            which appointed ANLux—the Archives nationales de Luxembourg—as the official depository
            of the WEU archives and gave the CVCE (<ptr target="http://cvce.eu/"/>), a research and
            documentary center in European Integration Studies, the task of scientifically
            exploiting these holdings, including their publication in any form.</note> of
          institutional documents concerning armament production and standardization, and armament
          control within the WEU,<note>The WEU was created on the October 23, 1954, with the signing
            of the <soCalled>Modified Brussels Treaty</soCalled> by France, Belgium, Luxembourg, the
            Netherlands, the United Kingdom—all five previously members of the Western Union created
            in 1948—and the Federal Republic of Germany invited to join the new organization. It
            became the first European Defence Organisation and its missions covered the settling of
            the problem of the Saar, the monitoring of German rearmament, and the promotion of the
            defense of Western Europe. The Treaty of Brussels contained a mutual defense clause in
            Article V. For more information, please consult <ptr
              target="http://www.cvce.eu/en/recherche/unit-content/-/unit/72d9869d-ff72-493e-a0e3-bedb3e671faa/1c06c877-402b-45d1-a126-792e99cf3fc3"
            />.</note> from 1954 to 1982. TEI XML has been considered an appropriate format both for
          building a scholarly online edition and for enabling corpus analysis. The general workflow
          was conceived with the aim of (partial) re-usability, albeit with some project-specific
          adaptations and readjustment, in order to support a variety of projects and document types
          in European integration history (primary/secondary sources: text, image, audio, video, and
          their transcriptions). As a matter of principle, an alternation of manual and automatic
          sequential processing has been applied to the corpus in such a way that, independently of
          the manual interventions, no information should be lost if it is needed to regenerate a
          certain state of the corpus in subsequent automatic phases (e.g., via XSLT).</p>
        <p>The first criterion for the selection of the documents was their relevance to a specific
          research question: what were the French and British positions on the major defense and
          security matters within WEU and, as subsidiary questions, the identification of the main
          defense and security matters discussed within the Council of the WEU and the importance
          placed on the WEU by the two member states, France and the United Kingdom, in their
          diplomatic strategy between 1954 and 1982.<note>Eric Rémacle referred to the <quote
              source="#quoteref8">instrumentalisation</quote> of WEU by these two countries, which
            he identified as <quote source="#quoteref8">successive leader states</quote> within the
            organization. See <ref type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref8" target="#remacle09">Rémacle 2009,
              197</ref>.</note> The choice of this case study was influenced by the fact that these
          two states played a key role in the birth, development, and organization of the WEU, as
          evidenced in the primary and secondary sources consulted. The idea was that by analyzing
          these issues we can also shed light on the organization’s contributions to European
          defense under the leadership (or lack thereof) of France and the UK.</p>
        <p>Other criteria influencing document selection were to obtain a balance among control,
          standardization, and production, together with a balanced number of documents across the
          decades, as well as taking into account that some documents are a logical follow-up of
          others (e.g., documents mentioning recommendations). Another criterion for selection, of
          secondary importance, was the actual form of the documents, since the research was also
          intended to evaluate the accuracy of OCR (optical character recognition) processing for
          different types of layout (title or content page), paper quality, and legibility of
          typewritten or handwritten characters and of particular markings as stamps.</p>
        <p>The selected sample contained 127 documents, 60 in English and 67 in French. For the
          first phase of the project, 55 documents in French were retained (a total of 290 pages)
          because of their importance for subsequent corpus analysis<note>Related to the specific
            research question, that is, the study of linguistic patterns in the discourse of
            different country/institutional representatives as described in <ptr type="crossref"
              target="#decoding"/>.</note> and publication. The majority of the documents were notes
          from the Secretary-General or Secrétaire Général (46, of which 37 were encoded because of
          their relevance to the research question), followed by minutes of meetings of the WEU
          Council or the Standing Armaments Committee (SAC) or of the working party on production
          and standardization of armament of the Interim Commission (15, all of which have been
          encoded). The sample also included 2 memoranda (both encoded) and 2 studies (1 of which
          has been encoded).</p>
        <p>The linguistic aspect was also considered. Although, given the availability of time and
          resources, the French version was prioritized for encoding (the English processing being
          planned for a later stage), in general, the chosen documents existed in both French and
          English versions, and when not mentioned as original language, the French documents were
          exact translations of the English ones or had the same status, since the documents were
          produced in both languages. The provider of the translations was the WEU itself (its daily
          work being undertaken in both languages) and, therefore, a source of official
          translations.</p>
        <p>From the 55 French documents selected for encoding, 5 had no English equivalent (3 notes,
          1 study, and 1 memorandum); the remainder (all the meeting minutes and remaining
          categories) were available in both languages. More precisely, there were 16 documents
          mentioning the original was in French (of which 1 had no English equivalent), 12 with the
          original indicated as being in English, 10 mentioning the original both in French and
          English, 11 with no indication of the original language but a comparison between the
          French and English documents showed a similar structure and content, 4 available only in
          French bearing no indication of the original language, and 2 with an ambiguous marker (1
          indicating French and English as original in the French version while the corresponding
          English document mentioned English as the original language, the other bearing no mention
          of the original in the French version but indicating English as the original in the
          corresponding English document).</p>
        <div xml:id="paperarchive">
          <head>The Paper Archive</head>
          <p>As a general rule, documents from the Secretary-General all exist in both French and
            English. In the nearly 400 folders consulted, there were very few exceptions; only
            occasionally were documents published in just one language. The French version was
            printed on blue paper and the English on white paper. Internal documents or notes from
            the Agency for the Control of Armaments (ACA) were only published in French, on very
            thin (<soCalled>tracing</soCalled>) paper. The notes and minutes were formal documents
            distributed to all the delegations of the Member States.</p>
          <p>The research aim was to gather a set of representative documents that expressed the
            French and British positions within the WEU’s different bodies, on different topics—the
            exploration of the design, production, and control of armament being only one of them.
            For this purpose, we used the WEU’s collection database, held in the Archives nationales
            de Luxembourg, and consulted several sections and collections including: <list
              rend="ordered inline">
              <item>Interim Period;</item>
              <item>Brussels Treaty Organisation (BTO);</item>
              <item>1954–87 within the Secretariat-General/Council’s archives;</item>
              <item>Armament Bodies—Agency for the Control of Armaments (ACA) and Standing Armaments
                Committee (SAC)</item>
            </list>. Other collections such as those relating to the military bodies or WEU
            operations were considered too recent to be consulted or still held a classified status.
            The documents were selected primarily based on their themes, strictly following the
            thirty-year rule. Each collection, comprised of several folders, with a
              <soCalled>fiche</soCalled> indicating the name of the section and collection, title of
            the folder, security classification such as WEU or NATO (NATO classified documents were
            not available), the period of time covered in the folder, the reference, and either
            keywords or a small summary of the main questions, although sometimes this was quite
            general. Once the folders or boxes were located in the WEU collection, they were
            consulted <foreign xml:lang="la">in situ</foreign> and a selection of several documents
            was made according to the general theme <mentioned>armament</mentioned>. Before the
            digitization, a closer reading and final selection was performed.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="papertoelectronic">
          <head>Paper to Electronic Text</head>
          <p>The initial documents were typewritten materials from the WEU archives. The
            transformation into electronic text necessitated the use of document scanning, OCR,
            manual post-processing error correction, conversion of the resulting styled Microsoft
            Word files to TEI XML P5 via <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/oxgarage/"
                >OxGarage</ref>,<note><ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/oxgarage/"/>.</note> and
            further XSLT transformation and enrichment using the oXygen XML Editor and GATE (General
            Architecture for Text Engineering) for NER (Named Entity Recognition). To prepare the
            digital documents for publication on the Web, further processing was carried out, to
            facilitate visualization and navigation in the browser at the document and collection
            level.</p>
          <p>Next we identified, for each document, principal metadata and semantic elements
            necessary for encoding, as well as the form of encoding required for the computational
            linguistic analysis in order to answer the main research question. The metadata included
            elements such as <list rend="inline ordered">
              <item>the author of the document: for the majority of documents the author is a
                collective entity (institution), except for rare cases—internal documents—where the
                author is an individual;</item>
              <item>the date on which the document was distributed or produced, such as the date of
                the meeting;</item>
              <item>the location (generally London, where the Council’s Secretariat-General was
                located, or Paris, home of the ACA and SAC headquarters);</item>
              <item>the title;</item>
              <item>the version (whether or not it is a final version);</item>
              <item>the language of the document with the mention of the original, when
                present;</item>
              <item>the classification: most of the documents were classified as
                  <term>confidential</term>, <term>secret</term>, or even <term>top secret</term>,
                according to the degree of sensitivity of the information</item>
            </list>. Likewise, documents of this type also had a copy number (element 8), since they
            often contained military and strategic information and were only distributed to a
            limited (sometimes very small) number of people, generally officials at national or
            institutional level. The organization had its own system of codes (references) for each
            document, which varied depending on the institution or the type of document.<note>For
              example, CR(58)8 = CR (for <foreign xml:lang="fr">compte-rendu</foreign>, or minutes,
              of a Council meeting), the year in brackets, then the document number; PWG/CR/4 = PWG
              (we think that PWG stands for Production Working Group), CR (for <foreign
                xml:lang="fr">compte-rendu</foreign>) and the number of the meeting (the fourth
              meeting); C(80)40—we have noticed that the letter C was generally used for the final
              version of the reply to a recommendation or written question, followed by the date in
              brackets, although the meaning of the second number is not clear. The letters WPM
              followed by a number in brackets were used for the various versions of replies to
              recommendations and/or written questions, but we think that the date was not indicated
              in brackets during the early years of WEU’s activity, until the end of the 1960s or
              the early 1970s; if a draft was amended by a working group, the version number was
              added after a solidus, e.g., WPM(77)25/1.</note> The document reference (element 9)
            only partially identifies a document, since the same code was sometimes used for several
            documents, particularly for minutes of meetings which were divided into thematic
            sections and incorporated into different folders. The folder code (element 10) is
            therefore an important means of identifying the theme and even the institution within
            the WEU.<note>Examples of file codes: CPA-043; ACA-200; 421.00; 200.400.11 vol
              1/1.</note>
          </p>
          <p>In order to address the research question, the main aim of the TEI XML encoding was to
            identify the speakers (element 11) in the various documents and the views (element 12)
            that can be attributed to them, whether directly or indirectly.<note>Speakers frequently
              referred to statements by other people from the same or another delegation.</note> The
            representatives (ministers, parliamentarians, ambassadors, and experts) from France and
            the United Kingdom were systematically identified, and, depending on their relevance to
            the research, the contributions of the German representatives were also encoded. Some
            examples of British speakers’ names are Christopher Steel, Samuel Hood, and Selwyn
            Lloyd; French speakers’ names included Alexandre Parodi, Jean Chauvel, and Geoffroy
            Chodron de Courcel.</p>
          <p>A generic nomenclature was developed to maintain consistency among the various speakers
            and to deal with cases when the speaker was not named: <ident>repres_fr</ident> (French
            representative), <ident>repres_uk</ident> (United Kingdom representative),
              <ident>repres_frg</ident> (German representative), <ident>repres_frg_fr_it</ident>
            (contribution on behalf of the German, French, and Italian representatives),
              <ident>repres_deleg_fr</ident> (French delegation), <ident>repres_deleg_uk</ident>
            (United Kingdom delegation),<note>The terms <soCalled>delegate</soCalled> and
                <soCalled>representative</soCalled> were used to distinguish the collective
              discourse of a country (for instance, in the answer to a recommendation) from the
              discourse of an individual (in a Council’s meeting for instance), although the
              individual was also speaking for a country.</note>
            <ident>repres_cons_weu</ident> (representative of the WEU Council),
              <ident>repres_assb_weu</ident> (representative of the WEU Assembly),
              <ident>repres_aca</ident> (representative of the Agency for the Control of Armaments),
              <ident>respres_sac</ident> (representative of the Standing Armaments Committee) (see
              <ptr type="crossref" target="#example1"/>).</p>
          <p>A semi-automatic NER processing involved the identification of other elements (13) in
            the texts, intended to be considered as whole units in the analysis, such as dates and
            the names of places, people, office positions, organizations, and bodies
              (<mentioned>Western European Union</mentioned>, the <mentioned>North Atlantic Treaty
              Organisation</mentioned>, the <mentioned>Standing Armaments Committee</mentioned>, and
            the <mentioned>Agency for the Control of Armaments</mentioned>), the event to which the
            document refers, as well as any other events mentioned.<note>Other meetings were often
              mentioned, such as a previous or forthcoming ministerial meeting or a meeting of the
              North Atlantic Council.</note> Finally, a series of <soCalled>products</soCalled>
            associated with armament were also encoded, for example <mentioned>Mirage</mentioned>,
              <mentioned>short-haul transport aircraft</mentioned>, <mentioned>light
              tank</mentioned>, <mentioned>Pluton</mentioned>, etc.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="encoding">
        <head>Encoding</head>
        <p>Although other types of elements were annotated in the corpus (metadata, e.g., title,
          author, availability date, origin place, and confidentiality status; and structure, e.g.,
          headers, footers, sections, paragraphs, and line breaks), the paper will focus on the
          content-related encoding—that is, speakers and their discourse—along with the
          above-mentioned categories of named entities, considered from the perspective of the
          subsequent decoding phase (analysis and interpretation). The TEI P5
                specifications<note><bibl><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2015</date>. TEI
              Guidelines <edition>Version 2.8.0</edition>. Last updated on April 6. <ptr
                target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/2.8.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"
            />.</bibl></note> were applied, with no need for adding new classes, elements, or
          attributes.</p>
        <div xml:id="participants">
          <head>Participants</head>
          <p>The identification of the agents responsible for the production of texts represents an
            important step in the analysis of institutional discourse, irrespective of the level of
            this analysis (<ref type="bibl" target="#thornborrow02">Thornborrow 2002</ref>; <ref
              type="bibl" target="#philips04">Phillips, Lawrence, and Hardy 2004</ref>; <ref
              type="bibl" target="#nikander08">Nikander 2008</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
              target="#vandijk93">Van Dijk 1993</ref>). Certain types of documents in the WEU-Diplo
            corpus (usually minutes) explicitly provided indications about the speakers and their
            position (<q><foreign xml:lang="fr">Etaient présents: République Fédérale d’Allemagne:
                Prof. Dr. L. ERHARD; Belgique: M. A. de STAERCKE <gap/></foreign></q>).<note>En.
                <q>PRESENT: Prof. Dr. L. ERHARD: Federal Republic of Germany; M. A. de STAERCKE:
                Belgium.<gap/></q> Union de l’Europe occidentale. Commission intérimaire. Groupe de
              travail sur la production et la standardisation des armements. Troisième séance
              plénière tenue au Palais de Chaillot le 21 janvier 1955 à 15 heures 30. Paris:
              22.01.1955. PWG/CR/2. Pp. 1–3; Annexe A; Annexe B. Archives nationales de Luxembourg
              (ANLux). <ptr target="http://anlux.lu/"/>. Western European Union Archives. Armament
              Bodies. CPA/SAC. Comité permanent des armements. File CPA-033. Volume 1/1.</note> For
            other cases, external knowledge or prior research was needed in order to be able to
            assign a role to the speaker (<q><foreign xml:lang="fr">M. Selwyn LLOYD déclare que
                <gap/></foreign></q><note>En. <q>Mr. Selwyn LLOYD considered that<gap/>.</q> Conseil
              de l’Union de l’Europe occidentale. Extract from minutes of the 108th meeting
              Ministers of WEU Council held on 5 March 1958. Rome. II. Echanges de vues sur la
              coopération en matière de recherche, développement et production d’armements. CR
              (58)8. Pp. 5–9. Archives nationales de Luxembourg (ANLux). <ptr
                target="http://www.anlux.lu"/>. Western European Union Archives. Secretariat
              General/Council’s Archives. 1954–1987. Subject dealt with by various WEU ORGANS. Year:
              1958, 01/06/1957–30/04/1958. File 442.00. Volume 1/4.</note> as a UK representative)
            or to identify the contributors to the discourse (the France representative, Geoffroy
            Chodron de Courcel, and the ACA representative).<note xml:id="note14">Agence pour le
              contrôle des armements. Note. 04.1966. 6 p. Archives nationales de Luxembourg (ANLux).
                <ptr target="http://anlux.lu/"/>. Western European Union Archives. Armament Bodies.
              ACA. Agency for the Control of Armaments. Year: 1957, 01/01/1957–31/12/1963. File
              ACA-035. Volume 1/1.</note></p>
          <figure xml:id="example1">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <particDesc>
                <p>Liste des représentants des pays/organisations.<list xml:id="repres_list">
                    <item xml:id="repres_fr">Représentant(s) de la France</item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_uk">Représentant(s) du Royaume-Uni</item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_frg">Représentant(s) de la République Fédérale
                      d&apos;Allemagne</item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_frg_fr_it">Représentant(s) de la République Fédérale
                      d&apos;Allemagne, de la France et de l&apos;Italie</item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_fr_uk">Représentant(s) de la France et du
                      Royaume-Uni</item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_deleg_fr">Représentant(s) de la délégation française</item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_deleg_uk">Représentant(s) de la délégation
                      britannique</item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_deleg_fr_be">Représentant(s) des délégations française et
                      belge</item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_deleg_fr_uk">Représentant(s) des délégations française et
                      britannique</item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_cons_weu">Représentant(s) du Conseil de l'U.E.O. (Union de
                      l'Europe occidentale)</item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_sac">Représentant(s) du C.P.A. (Comité permanent des
                      armements)</item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_wpbt">Représentant(s) du G.T.P.B. (Groupe de travail sur le
                      Pacte de Bruxelles)</item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_aca">Représentant(s) de l'A.C.A. (Agence pour le contrôle
                      des armements)</item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_assb_weu">Représentant(s) de l'Assemblée de l'U.E.O. (Union
                      de l'Europe occidentale)</item>
                  </list></p>
              </particDesc>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Generic list of participants. WEU-Diplo: CR/58/8</head>
          </figure>
          <p>The encoding of the participants (considered of interest for the research question)
            required two types of annotations:</p>
          <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>a mandatory, generic label identifying the participant as an institutional or
              country representative;</item>
            <item>an identifier (unique for the corpus) provided only when it was possible to refer
              to a particular person.</item>
          </list>
          <p>Since the conversion to TEI XML and the semantic enrichment of the corpus supposed both
            automatic transformation (via XSLT) and manual annotations, in a preliminary form for
            all of the documents, we generated a list of all generic labels for the
            country/institution representatives (<gi>profileDesc</gi> section of the
              <gi>teiHeader</gi>) (<ptr type="crossref" target="#example1"/>).</p>
          <p>Then the list was manually customized according to the particularity of each document
            and the specific <soCalled>actors</soCalled> involved in the production of the text.
              <ptr type="crossref" target="#example2"/> illustrates a case where only three
            representatives were retained and further details were provided on their identity. For
            other situations, the generic label was enough (when the identity was not required or
            not available).</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="discourse">
          <head>Discourse</head>
          <p>In order to be able to analyze the discourse of different participants within the WEU’s
            policy on armament issues, we have applied a <soCalled>kaleidoscopic</soCalled> approach
            to the corpus. More precisely, discrete fragments were identified and manually annotated
            inside each document, with reference to the speaker and his or her role as an
            institution or country representative manifested in the text (<ptr type="crossref"
              target="#example2"/>).</p>
          <figure xml:id="example2">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <particDesc>
                <p>Liste des représentants des pays/organisations.<list xml:id="repres_list">
                    <item xml:id="repres_fr">Représentant(s) de la France <name type="person"
                        xml:id="faure">Maurice Faure</name></item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_uk">Représentant(s) du Royaume-Uni <name type="person"
                        xml:id="lloyd">Selwyn Lloyd</name></item>
                    <item xml:id="repres_frg">Représentant(s) de la République Fédérale
                      d&apos;Allemagne <name type="person" xml:id="von_brentano">Heinrich von
                        Brentano</name></item>
                  </list></p>
              </particDesc>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Customized list of participants. WEU-Diplo: CR/58/8</head>
          </figure>
          <p>Given its flexibility of use (either inside a paragraph or encompassing several
            paragraphs), the <gi>said</gi> tag was chosen for delimiting the different pieces of
            discourse corresponding to a particular agent (<ptr type="crossref" target="#example3"
            />). The choice also facilitated assembling these pieces of information for analysis in
            the decoding phase (<ptr type="crossref" target="#decoding"/>).</p>
          <figure xml:id="example3">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <p><name type="person">M. Faure</name> souligne avec force que <said direct="false"
                  ana="#oral_disc" who="#faure" corresp="#repres_fr">le succès de
                  l&apos;entreprise<lb/>dépend de la volonté politique des gouvernements d'assurer
                  une<lb/>coopération effective. Les propositions de <name type="person">M. von
                    Brentano</name><w>cons<lb rendition="#hyphen_before" break="no"/>tituant</w> un
                  pas important dans cette direction et il s'y rallie.</said></p>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Excerpt from a discourse (oral). WEU-Diplo: CR/58/8</head>
          </figure>
          <p>The <att>corresp</att> and <att>who</att> attributes were used in order to link the
            marked-up fragment with its producer defined in the <gi>particDesc</gi> unit. Additional
            attributes (<att>ana</att> and <att>direct</att>) were needed to differentiate
            situations referring either to transcribed <term>oral</term> (direct or indirect speech)
            or to what we considered <term>written</term> discourse, such as the text of notes (<ptr
              type="crossref" target="#example4"/>) or studies usually resulting from internal
            meetings or discussions among institutional bodies (sometimes including
              <soCalled>narrative</soCalled> prose<note><ptr type="crossref" target="#example4"/>,
              En. <q>One year after, under analogous conditions, Minister LUNS had to assess as a
                president a position along the same lines <gap/>.</q> (Our translation, document for
              which we could not find an English equivalent in the WEU archives.)</note> or
            arguments not necessarily coming from an oral account), and then circulated for further
            discussion/approval within the WEU.</p>
          <figure xml:id="example4">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <said ana="#written_disc" corresp="#repres_aca">
                <p>Un an après, dans des conditions analogues, le <name type="person"
                    >Ministre<lb/>LUNS</name> était amené à prendre comme président une position
                  dans<lb/>le même sens.</p>[…] </said>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Excerpt from a discourse (written). WEU-Diplo: Note<note>See <ptr
                  type="crossref" target="#note14"/> for the document reference. The ellipsis
                indicates missing paragraphs, omitted here for concision.</note>
            </head>
          </figure>
          <p>A particular occurrence of <soCalled>discourse within a discourse</soCalled> is
            presented below (<ptr type="crossref" target="#example5"/>): a direct citation of the
            oral intervention of a WEU Council representative, M. Heath, from a previous meeting of
            the WEU Assembly, within the written account of the ACA.<note>Distinguished via the
              values of the <att>ana</att> attribute, as related to written versus oral
              discourse.</note></p>
          <figure xml:id="example5">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <said ana="#written_disc" corresp="#repres_aca"> […] <p>La réponse de <name
                    type="person">M. HEATH</name> était : <said direct="true" ana="#oral_disc"
                    who="#heath" corresp="#repres_cons_weu">&quot;Nous ne sommes<lb/>pas
                    juridiquement tenus d'autoriser l'inspection de ces dépôts,<lb/>car ils ont été
                    constitués dans le cadre de l&apos;<name type="org">OTAN</name>, et
                    sont<lb/>donc, strictement parlant, uniquement soumis à l’inspection
                    de<lb/>cette organisation.&quot;</said>[…].</p>[…]</said>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Excerpt from a discourse within a discourse. WEU-Diplo:
                Note<note>Agence pour le contrôle des armements. Division III. Note à l’intention du
                Directeur de l’ACA. Contrôle sur place des armes atomiques se trouvant dans des
                dépôts britanniques sur le continent européen. 22 juin 1962. Archives nationales de
                Luxembourg (ANLux). <ptr target="http://anlux.lu/"/>. Western European Union
                Archives. Armament Bodies. ACA. Agency for the Control of Armaments. Year: 1957,
                01/01/1957–31/12/1978. File ACA-218. Volume 1/1. The ellipsis indicates missing
                paragraphs or fragments, omitted here for concision. As far as the intervention of
                Mr. Heath is concerned, it is not specified anywhere that he was actually speaking
                English, but since it was a working language, it seems logical that he was
                expressing himself in his native language. Thus, this could be a translation, most
                probably from an internal translation service.</note></head>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="ne">
          <head>Named Entities (NE)</head>
          <p>The project also included the identification and annotation in the text of named
            entities intended for later use (such as indexing and linking to an authorities list) or
            as a prerequisite of the corpus analysis phase. This identification and annotation
            allows multiword expressions to be counted as single units of a given type (e.g.,
            organization) in the analysis, rather than as separate words (for instance, <mentioned
              xml:lang="fr">Union de l’Europe Occidentale</mentioned> instead of <mentioned
              xml:lang="fr">Union, de, l’, Europe, Occidentale</mentioned>).</p>
          <p>The NER task involved a semi-automatic approach using <ref target="https://gate.ac.uk/"
              >GATE</ref> (French NE, Gazetteer, and Gazetteer List Collector plugins)<note><ptr
                target="https://gate.ac.uk/"/>.</note> for the detection of seven classes of
            entities: persons, places, organizations, events, dates, products, and functions
            (official positions). Manual corrections were applied, when necessary, in a
            post-processing phase. Since the GATE XML output format was different from TEI, an XSLT
            dedicated stylesheet was created for the transformation of the GATE tags (such as
              <gi>Person</gi>, <gi>Location</gi>, <gi>Organization</gi>, and <gi>Date</gi>) into
            corresponding TEI tags (<gi>name</gi> with the attribute <att>type</att>, and
              <gi>date</gi>, respectively). A few examples of <tag>name
              type=&quot;person&quot;</tag>, <tag>name type="org"</tag> are presented in the
            previous examples. Further transformation was necessary during the importing of the
            annotated corpus into the software for textual analysis (see <ptr type="crossref"
              target="#importing"/>).</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="decoding">
        <head>Decoding</head>
        <p>The so called <soCalled>decoding</soCalled> phase, for corpus analysis and
          interpretation, consisted of importing and processing the TEI XML annotated documents
          within a specialized platform, <ref target="http://textometrie.ens-lyon.fr/?lang=en"><ptr
              type="software" xml:id="TXM" target="#TXM"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#TXM"
            >TXM</rs></ref> (<ref type="bibl" target="#heiden10">Heiden 2010</ref>),<note><ptr
              target="http://textometrie.ens-lyon.fr/?lang=en"/>.</note> that allows the analysis of
          a large body of texts by means of lexicometrical and statistical methods. The previous
          encoding served as a basis for discerning or grouping together different types of semantic
          or structural elements needed for analysis.</p>
        <div xml:id="importing">
          <head>Importing</head>
          <p>Since <ptr type="software" xml:id="TXM" target="#TXM"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#TXM"
              >TXM</rs> supports XSLT transformation at the moment of import (XML/w+CSV option), an
            XSLT stylesheet was created to accommodate particular formats or conversions required by
            the software. Therefore, it was not necessary to store different versions of the corpus,
            one for <ptr type="software" xml:id="TXM" target="#TXM"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#TXM"
              >TXM</rs> analysis, the other for Web publication.</p>
          <p>First, a lowercase conversion<note>All the examples of analysis presented in the paper
              will consequently be displayed in lowercase.</note> was provided for consistency
            reasons relating to the varying ways of capitalizing (e.g., <mentioned>Comité militaire
              de standardisation</mentioned>, <mentioned>Comité militaire de
              Standardisation</mentioned>, <mentioned>Comité Militaire de
              Standardisation</mentioned>). Second, for the named entities to be interpreted as a
            whole instead of as separate units, a supplementary conversion was needed, all the
              <gi>name</gi> tags being converted to <gi>w</gi> tags each denoting a
              <soCalled>word</soCalled> of a given type (e.g., person or organization). The special
            case of hyphenated words where the hyphen appears at a line break (see <ptr
              type="crossref" target="#example3"/>) had to be considered in an earlier
            transformation, before import, so that the whole word and not its parts could be counted
            in the analysis (in the example, <mentioned>constituant</mentioned> instead of
              <mentioned>cons</mentioned> and <mentioned>tituant</mentioned> as the software would
            treat it without a <gi>w</gi> tag).</p>
          <p>Part-of-speech tagging via the TreeTagger module integrated into <ptr type="software"
              xml:id="TXM" target="#TXM"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#TXM">TXM</rs> was also applied
            to the corpus at import in order to allow lemma and part-of-speech statistics and
            queries.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="analysis">
          <head>Analysis</head>
          <p>The annotated corpus (only the content inside <gi>text</gi> tags, without metadata)
            contained 6,512 items (unique words) with 76,558 occurrences in the text.<note>A
              subcorpus based on the <code>@lang=&quot;fr&quot;</code> property (an attribute of the
                <gi>text</gi> element) was created in <ptr type="software" xml:id="TXM"
                target="#TXM"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#TXM">TXM</rs> for the analysis of the
              documents’ content, excluding the data from the <gi>teiHeader</gi>. The whole corpus
                (<gi>teiHeader</gi> included) comprised 7,015 items and 105,897
            occurrences.</note></p>
          <div xml:id="partitioning">
            <head>Partitioning</head>
            <p>Given the identification and annotation of different semantic and structural elements
              in the encoding phase, <ptr type="software" xml:id="TXM" target="#TXM"/><rs
                type="soft.name" ref="#TXM">TXM</rs> allows the creation of partitions (<ref
                type="bibl" target="#textometrie14">Textométrie 2014, section Construire une
                partition</ref>) by selecting a <term>Structure</term> unit and a corresponding
                <term>Property</term> (i.e., an XML element and one of its attributes) from the list
              of structural units and properties recognized by the software for the imported
              corpus.</p>
            <p>For instance, as fragments of discourse spread throughout the documents were assigned
              to particular countries or institution representatives (<ptr type="crossref"
                target="#discourse"/>), a partition was created based on the <gi>said</gi> element
              and its <att>corresp</att> attribute. <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure1"/> shows
              the dimensions of the <mentioned>representatives’ discourse</mentioned> partition, in
              number of words (occurrences). One can observe that for the selection of documents,
              there is a <soCalled>dominance</soCalled> of the French (14,338 occurrences) and WEU
              Council (11,276 occurrences) representatives’ discourse, the categories with the
              lowest size being those corresponding to the French-English delegation (185) and WEU
              Assembly (72).</p>
            <p>Other types of partitions were also created and analyzed: by
                <mentioned>speaker</mentioned>, based on the <gi>said</gi> element and its
                <att>who</att> attribute, with dimensions varying from 41 (Brindeau) to 6,141
              occurrences (Parodi); by <mentioned>type of discourse</mentioned>, using <gi>said</gi>
              and <att>ana</att>, and counting 22,780 occurrences of oral discourse versus 32,355
              occurrences of written dicourse; and by <mentioned>subtype of institutional
                documents</mentioned>, taking into account the <gi>text</gi> element and its
                <att>subtype</att> attribute, with occurrences numbering between 2,684 for the study
              category and 38,565 for the minutes.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure1">
              <graphic url="images/figure1.jpg" height="595px" width="1280px"/>
              <head type="legend">Dimensions of the <mentioned>said_corresp</mentioned>
                partition</head>
            </figure>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="specificities">
            <head>Specificities</head>
            <p>The use of the <term>Specificities</term> feature (<ref type="bibl"
                target="#textometrie14">Textométrie 2014, section Spécificités</ref>) allows a
              comparison of the vocabularies: what is <soCalled>specific</soCalled> (either as
                <soCalled>overuse</soCalled> or <soCalled>deficit</soCalled>) in a part of a
              partition, as compared with the parent corpus and a certain threshold.<note>In <ptr
                  type="software" xml:id="TXM" target="#TXM"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#TXM"
                  >TXM</rs>, it is called the <term>banality threshold</term>, fixed by default at
                the value of +/- 2.0 for positive and negative specificities scores, respectively.
                In <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure3"/>, the banality thresholds are rendered by
                (red) horizontal lines.</note> The feature is based on a probabilistic model (<ref
                type="bibl" target="#lafon80">Lafon 1980</ref>) used in <ptr type="software"
                xml:id="TXM" target="#TXM"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#TXM">TXM</rs> to compute a
              log10 specificity score of a word property (e.g., word form, lemma, or part of speech)
              for a given part. In the analysis of the WEU-Diplo corpus, it was assumed that the
              specificity score may draw attention to forms <soCalled>specific</soCalled> to the
              discourse of different country/institutional representatives as compared with the
              whole. <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure2"/> shows an extract from the
              specificities table computed for the <mentioned>lemma</mentioned> property and the
                <mentioned>said_corresp</mentioned> partition, sorted by increasing order of the
              specificity score corresponding to the <mentioned>respres_aca</mentioned> part.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure2">
              <graphic url="images/figure2.jpg" height="187px" width="919px"/>
              <head type="legend">Specificities table extract (lemma,
                  <mentioned>said_corresp</mentioned>) sorted by increasing scores for
                  <mentioned>repres_aca</mentioned></head>
            </figure>
            <p>Each line in the table corresponds to a value of the chosen property (lemma or a
              group of lemmas) displayed in the <mentioned>Units</mentioned> column. The second
              column indicates the frequencies or number of occurrences of the property values in
              the corpus (with a total T). The other columns contain the number of occurrences of
              the property values in a part (cumulated by t) and are followed by a corresponding
              logarithmic score of specificity that can be positive or negative. The table may be
              sorted in increasing or decreasing order, according to a given column. In the case of
              an increasing score (as presented in the figure for
              <mentioned>repres_aca</mentioned>), the first property values displayed (e.g.,
                <mentioned xml:lang="fr">matériel, industrie(l)</mentioned>)<note>En.
                  <mentioned>material, industry-industrial</mentioned>.</note> indicate a deficit in
              use as compared to the whole corpus and the last ones displayed indicate an overuse,
              while the values with scores around 0 (inside a certain interval) are considered
                <soCalled>trivial</soCalled> (i.e., the specificity measure may not be pertinent for
              them).</p>
            <p>Before creating a specificities table, a set of basic operations (merge, delete,
              export, import) are allowed via the <mentioned>Lexical Table</mentioned> feature (<ref
                type="bibl" target="#textometrie14">Textométrie 2014, section Table lexicale</ref>).
              The groups of units presented in <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure2 #figure3"/>
              were created using <mentioned>Lexical Table</mentioned> and the <mentioned>Merge
                Lines</mentioned> feature, in order to merge units considered to be close from a
              semantic point of view in the context, like, for instance,
                <mentioned>harmonisation/harmoniser</mentioned>-<mentioned>norme/normalisation</mentioned>-<mentioned>règle/règlement</mentioned>-<mentioned>standard/standardisation/standardiser</mentioned>).<note>En.
                  <mentioned>harmonization/harmonize</mentioned>-<mentioned>norm/normalization</mentioned>-<mentioned>rule/regulation</mentioned>-<mentioned>standard/standardization/standardize</mentioned>.</note></p>
            <div xml:id="graphical">
              <head>Graphical Representation</head>
              <p>From a lexical table, a specificities table can be generated, as well as the
                corresponding diagram for a number of selected units, as shown in <ptr
                  type="crossref" target="#figure3"/>.</p>
              <p>According to the diagram, the ACA representative’s vocabulary is characterized by a
                high positive specificity score for the groups
                  <mentioned>control-inspection-verification</mentioned> and
                  <mentioned>limitation-restriction</mentioned>, and by negative specificity scores
                for the groups <mentioned>fabrication-production</mentioned>,
                  <mentioned>harmonization-normalization</mentioned>.</p>
              <figure xml:id="figure3">
                <graphic url="images/figure3.jpg" height="469px" width="641px"/>
                <head type="legend">Specificities diagram (lemma,
                    <mentioned>said_corresp</mentioned> partition). Selection:
                    <mentioned>armament-control-
                  production-standardization-limitation</mentioned>.</head>
              </figure>
              <p>The result is not very surprising given the role of the ACA: it was created to
                control the stocks of armament of its member states on the European continent (and
                less related to production/standardization). The negative specificity for <mentioned
                  xml:lang="fr">arme(ment)-abc-atomique-nucléaire</mentioned><note>En.
                    <mentioned>abc/atomic/nuclear arms/armament.</mentioned></note> in the
                  <ident>repres_uk</ident>’s discourse is not surprising either, considering that
                the United Kingdom, although interested in the topic, was not primarily concerned
                with this issue. Likewise, expected results are revealed for the positive
                specificity scores for <mentioned>fabrication-production</mentioned> and
                  <mentioned>harmonization-normalization</mentioned> and the negative specificity
                scores for <mentioned>control-inspection-verification</mentioned> in the
                  <ident>repres_fr</ident>’s discourse. The former are most probably linked to the
                selection of documents and, in particular, to the French memorandum presenting the
                armament agency which focuses on <mentioned>fabrication-production</mentioned> and
                  <mentioned>harmonization-normalization</mentioned> (PWG/A/2).<note>See <ptr
                    type="crossref" target="#note41"/> for the document reference.</note>
                Experiments excluding this document<note>The size of the <ident>repres_fr</ident>
                  part in <ident>said_corresp</ident> partition decreased from 14,338 to 10,269
                  words after excluding PWG/A/2.</note> from the corpus analysis have confirmed the
                hypothesis (with scores for <mentioned>fabrication</mentioned> and
                  <mentioned>harmonization</mentioned> groups being lowered to the positive banality
                area). However, the negative specificity score for the
                  <mentioned>control</mentioned> group in <ident>repres_fr</ident>’s discourse
                  persisted<note>In fact, it increased slightly, from -4.5257 (7 out of a total of
                  85 occurrences in the whole corpus) to -4.7338 (3 out of 81 occurrences).</note>
                after the exclusion of the document from the analysis and may be associated either
                with the assertion of France’s resistance to submitting its stocks to the ACA’s
                controls or with an underrepresentation of the <mentioned>control</mentioned> topic
                in the selection of documents.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="tables">
              <head>Synthesis Tables</head>
              <p>A more general, comparative analysis can be provided for the positive and negative
                specific forms appearing in the representatives’ discourse, as inspired by the
                synthesis tables proposed by Bergounioux et al. (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#bergounioux81">1981</ref>) and Bonnafous (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#bonnafous81">1981</ref>). <ptr type="crossref" target="#table1"/>
                synthesizes the results for seven participants, a selection of shared lemmas or
                groups considered of interest for the study, and a set of specificities scores (in
                brackets) above and under the positive and negative banality thresholds.</p>
              <table xml:id="table1">
                <head>Comparative view of specificities scores. Selection:
                    <ident>said_corresp</ident> partition</head>
                <row role="label" rows="1" cols="1">
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">Representative/lemmas</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><ident>repres_​aca</ident></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><ident>repres_​cons_​weu</ident></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><ident>repres_​sac</ident></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><ident>repres_​deleg_​fr</ident></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><ident>repres_​deleg_​uk</ident></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><ident>repres_​fr</ident></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><ident>repres_​uk</ident></cell>
                </row>
                <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><mentioned xml:lang="fr">améri(cain)(que du
                      nord)-états-unis</mentioned></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">+ (2.3)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (3.6)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                </row>
                <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><mentioned xml:lang="fr">anglais-britannique-
                      grande-bretagne - royaume-uni</mentioned></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (4.3)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">+ (5.9)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (5.0)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">+ (3.7)</cell>
                </row>
                <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><mentioned xml:lang="fr"
                      >continent_europeen-europ(e)(éen)(e occidentale)</mentioned></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (2.1)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">+ (2.7)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (2.8)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">+ (8.9)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (2.4)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                </row>
                <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><mentioned xml:lang="fr">contrôl(able)(e)(er)-inspection -
                      verifi(cation)(er)</mentioned></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">+ (31.4)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (3.0)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (4.5)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (4.6)</cell>
                </row>
                <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><mentioned xml:lang="fr"
                    >coopér(ation)(er)</mentioned></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (6.1)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">+ (11.1)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">+ (2.6)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (5.8)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                </row>
                <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><mentioned>finabel</mentioned></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (3.2)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">+ (32.5)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (2.4)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (2.8)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                </row>
                <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><mentioned>g.e.i.p.</mentioned></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (2.1)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">+ (14.0)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">+ (3.5)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (2.6)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (6.0)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (2.5)</cell>
                </row>
                <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><mentioned xml:lang="fr">harmonis(ation)(er) -
                      norm(e)(alisation) - règle(ment) - standard(isation)(iser)</mentioned></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (5.6)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">- (2.7)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">+ (5.0)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
                </row>
              </table>
              <p>The high positive specificity score for <mentioned xml:lang="fr"
                  >coopération/coopérer</mentioned><note>En.
                    <mentioned>cooperation/cooperate</mentioned>.</note> in the
                  <ident>repres_cons_weu</ident>’s discourse can be explained by the role of arbiter
                and conciliator of the WEU Council, which was intended to promote cooperation among
                its members in all the domains. A closer look at the contexts where this group
                appears shows recurrent, general patterns like <mentioned xml:lang="fr">coopération
                  en matière d’armements</mentioned>, <mentioned xml:lang="fr">coopération des pays
                  européens en matière d’armements</mentioned>, and <mentioned xml:lang="fr"
                  >cooperation européenne en matière d’armements</mentioned><note>En.
                    <mentioned>cooperation on armament matters, cooperation on armament matters
                    among European countries, European cooperation on armament
                  matters.</mentioned></note> occurring both in the <ident>repres_cons_weu</ident>
                and <ident>repres_deleg_fr</ident>’s discourse (which also displays a positive score
                but with a lower value) or more specific occurrences, such as <mentioned
                  xml:lang="fr">coopération intergouvernementale en matière de recherche,
                  coopération intergouvernementale en matière d’études</mentioned><note>En.
                    <mentioned>intergovernmental cooperation on research matters, intergovernmental
                    cooperation on study matters.</mentioned></note>
                (<ident>repres_cons_weu</ident>), <mentioned xml:lang="fr">coopération en matière de
                  missiles</mentioned>, or <mentioned xml:lang="fr">coopération européenne dans le
                  domaine aéronautique</mentioned><note>En. <mentioned>cooperation on missiles
                    matters, European cooperation in the aeronautic field.</mentioned></note>
                  (<ident>repres_deleg_fr</ident>).</p>
              <p>The highest positive score in the table (<mentioned>finabel</mentioned> for
                  <ident>repres_sac</ident>) may be explained by the frequent mentions of the
                organization during the meetings of the SAC (acting as a link between it and the
                United Kingdom, not a member of Finabel),<note>Finabel is a Land forces organization
                  created in 1953 with five initial members: France, Italy, Belgium, Luxembourg, and
                  the Netherlands. Germany became a member in 1956.</note> as well as by the
                adherence of Great Britain to this organization referred to in the
                  <ident>repres_sac</ident>’s discourse (see also <ptr type="crossref"
                  target="#queries"/>). The second highest positive and negative scores
                  (<mentioned>g.e.i.p.</mentioned>:<note><foreign xml:lang="fr">Groupe européen
                    indépendant de programme</foreign>. En. <mentioned>Independent European
                    Programme Group</mentioned> (IEPG).</note> for <ident>repres_cons_weu</ident>
                and <ident>repres_fr</ident>, respectively) are less clear but one can observe that
                the term tends to co-occur with the name of another organization
                  (<mentioned>c.d.n.a.</mentioned>)<note><foreign xml:lang="fr">Conférence des
                    directeurs nationaux des armements</foreign>. En. <mentioned>Conference of
                    National Armaments Directors</mentioned> (CNAD).</note> in the
                  <ident>repres_cons_weu</ident>’s discourse, while being completely absent (0
                occurrences) from the French representatives’ discourse. The main reason seems to be
                the substance of the discussions linked to the competences of different
                organizations about standardization. Further examination is also needed to interpret
                the deficit of the group <mentioned>control-inspection-verification</mentioned>
                reflected by negative specificity scores for <ident>repres_uk</ident> and
                  <ident>repres_fr</ident> (0 and 7 occurrences, respectively, out of a total of 85)
                that can be determined, as already mentioned, by the selection of documents,
                potentially more centered on the production and standardization of armaments than on
                their control.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="lexicalprofile">
              <head>Lexical Profile</head>
              <p>Another type of analysis resulting from the encoding was an exploration of the
                combination of lemma and part-of-speech (POS) tagging and specificity measures,
                which may be related to the so-called <soCalled>lexical profile</soCalled> (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#guyard81">Guyard 1981</ref>) of a participant in the
                institutional discourse. It consists of a list of relevant lemmas (with positive
                specificities above the banality threshold) and corresponding to certain parts of
                speech. <ptr type="crossref" target="#table2"/> illustrates this type of profile for
                two representatives (France, United Kingdom) as individuals and three categories of
                POS (noun, adjective, and verb), obtained by taking into account specificity scores
                for the <ident>said_who</ident> partition.</p>
              <table xml:id="table2">
                <head>Lexical profiles. Selection (lemmas, <ident>said_who</ident> partition)</head>
                <row role="label" rows="1" cols="1">
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">Part of speech / Name, occurrences</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">Noun</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">Adjective</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">Verb</cell>
                </row>
                <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">Chauvel (FR) (1072)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><mentioned xml:lang="fr">arme, accord_d’exécution,
                      recensement, mise, choix</mentioned></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><mentioned xml:lang="fr">commun, équitable, régional,
                      secret</mentioned></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><mentioned xml:lang="fr">procéder</mentioned></cell>
                </row>
                <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1">Lloyd (UK) (845)</cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><mentioned xml:lang="fr">pays, discussion, arrangement,
                      gouvernement_britannique, coopération</mentioned>
                  </cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><mentioned xml:lang="fr">bilatéral, déterminé,
                      multilatéral, analogue, final</mentioned></cell>
                  <cell rows="1" cols="1"><mentioned xml:lang="fr">engager,
                    associer</mentioned></cell>
                </row>
              </table>
              <p>For the adjectives, we can point out an opposition on the axis <mentioned
                  xml:lang="fr">commun</mentioned> versus <mentioned xml:lang="fr">bilatéral,
                  multilatéral</mentioned><note>En. <mentioned>common, joint, mutual</mentioned>
                  versus <mentioned>bilateral, multilateral.</mentioned></note> manifested in
                contexts such as <mentioned xml:lang="fr">programme (régional), intérêt, défense,
                  études, fonds commun(e)(s)</mentioned><note>En. <mentioned>joint regional
                    programme, common interest, common defence, common studies, mutual
                    funds.</mentioned></note> (Chauvel) versus <mentioned xml:lang="fr">base,
                  discussion, arrangements, comités directeurs
                  bilatéra(l)(le)(ux)</mentioned><note>En. <mentioned>bilateral basis, bilateral
                    discussion, bilateral arrangements, bilateral steering
                  committees.</mentioned></note> (Lloyd). The first profile is probably less clearly
                defined, but for the second one, the association of the lemmas provided for all
                three categories seems to convey a certain sense of action towards cooperation and
                dialogue.</p>
              <p>Similar specificities-based analyses (not described here in detail) were performed
                for other categories of word properties: POS, for instance, which indicates a high
                positive specificity score (17.95) for the conditional verbal form in the
                  <ident>repres_fr</ident> discourse (<ident>said_corresp</ident> partition); or
                other partitions, such as <ident>said_ana</ident> or <ident>text_subtype</ident>,
                that take into account the type of annotated discourse (oral/written) or the subtype
                of the document (minutes, note, study, or memorandum).</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="queries">
              <head>Queries, Concordances, and Co-occurrences</head>
              <p>The analysis of specificities was combined with other methods, both of a
                quantitative and qualitative nature, for examining the documents, for instance, by
                querying for specific word properties (lemmas, word forms, POS, or combinations of
                these elements) and by means of the concordances and co-occurrences features (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#textometrie14">Textométrie 2014, sections Construire une
                  concordance, Cooccurrences, Lexique et Index</ref>). <ptr type="crossref"
                  target="#figure4"/> presents the results of a query for <q>finabel</q> and the
                corresponding list of concordances that displays a left and right context, the file,
                and the representative’s discourse containing the word (i.e.,
                  <ident>repres_sac</ident> with the highest positive specificity score for this
                unit, as shown in <ptr type="crossref" target="#table1"/>).</p>
              <figure xml:id="figure4">
                <graphic url="images/figure4.jpg" height="327px" width="1041px"/>
                <head type="legend">Concordances. Extract (<q>finabel</q>,
                    <ident>said_corresp</ident> partition)</head>
              </figure>
              <p>A double click on a line in the concordances list provides a highlighted document
                view, as illustrated in <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure5"/>.</p>
              <figure xml:id="figure5">
                <graphic url="images/figure5.jpg" height="258px" width="1044px"/>
                <head type="legend">Document view with highlighted items. Extract. WEU-Diplo:
                    SAC/72/R-108<note>Compte rendu de la 108ème Réunion du Comité Permanent des
                    Armements, tenue à Paris, le 29 septembre 1972. Union de l’Europe occidentale.
                    Comité permanent des armements. Compte-rendu de la 108ème réunion du Comité
                    permanent des armements tenue à Paris le 29 septembre 1972. Paris: 18.10.1972.
                    SAC (72)R/108. pp.[s.p]; 3–4; annexe; pp.1–5. Archives nationales de Luxembourg
                    (ANLux). http://www.anlux.lu. Western European Union Archives.
                    Secretariat-General/Council’s Archives. 1954–1987. Organs of the Western
                    European Union. Year: 1967, 16/03/1956–30/04/1967. File 250.10. Volume
                    2/2.</note>
                </head>
              </figure>
              <p>Co-occurrences may also be displayed and sorted according to the frequency,
                co-frequency, specificity score, or the mean distance between the keyword and the
                co-occurrent, as in the example presented in <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure6"
                />. Some of the co-occurents can be observed in the document view as well, <ptr
                  type="crossref" target="#figure5"/> above.</p>
              <figure xml:id="figure6">
                <graphic url="images/figure6.jpg" height="440px" width="1035px"/>
                <head type="legend">Co-occurents of <mentioned>finabel</mentioned> sorted by mean
                  distance. Extract (<ident>said_corresp</ident> partition)</head>
              </figure>
              <p>As illustrated in the previous section and in <ptr type="crossref"
                  target="#figure4 #figure5 #figure6"/>, Great Britain and Finabel often co-occur in
                the discourse. This is probably <list rend="inline ordered">
                  <item>because of the particular attention of the SAC to informing the British
                    representatives about the activities of the organization and</item>
                  <item>because the adherence of the United Kingdom to Finabel and its consequences
                    is often brought into discussion</item>
                </list>.</p>
              <p>In order to avoid misinterpreting the specificities or to confirm some of the
                hypotheses suggested by this method, we often needed to combine it with
                co-occurrences, concordances, and visualization of the document. Therefore,
                co-occurrences can provide a quantitative perspective on the co-presence of some
                words, lemmas, or entities in the context of a given target, which in combination
                with concordances and document visualization may support qualitative analysis and
                interpretation.</p>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="discussion">
            <head>Results Discussion</head>
            <p>The TEI XML encoding and <ptr type="software" xml:id="TXM" target="#TXM"/><rs
                type="soft.name" ref="#TXM">TXM</rs> analysis related to the research questions on
              arms design, production, and control within the WEU have enabled a set of more or less
              predictable results, the latter needing further examination. Among the former, we can
              mention those referring to the SAC and ACA roles. Arms production and control was a
              major part of WEU’s work, despite its somewhat mixed record in this area. Protocol IV
              of the Modified Brussels Treaty established the ACA, while after advocating the
              establishment of an armaments agency in its memorandum of January 3, 1955,<note
                xml:id="note41">Western European Union. Interim Commission. Working Party on
                Production and Standardisation of Armaments. <title level="m">Secretary General’s
                  note</title>. Paris: 17.01.1955. PWG/A/2.18 p. Archives nationales de Luxembourg
                (ANLux). <ptr target="http://anlux.lu/"/>. Western European Union Archives. Armament
                Bodies. CPA/SAC. Comité permanent des armements. File CPA-032. Volume 1/1; <ref
                  type="bibl" target="#delhauteur91">Delhauteur 1991</ref>, p. 6.</note> France
              proposed the setting up of the SAC during a meeting of the working party on production
              and standardization of armaments, on the basis of Article VIII(2) of the Modified
              Brussels Treaty. The SAC was subsequently created on May 7, 1955. Although the United
              Kingdom never opposed the SAC’s activities, it actively attempted to restrict its
              role, both because of its resistance to any notion of supranationality<note>Western
                European Union. Interim Commission. Working Party on Production and Standardisation
                of Armaments. Statements made by the delegations at the first and second sessions of
                the Working Group. Paris: 21.01.1955. PWG/A/6. Annex A and Annex F. Archives
                nationales de Luxembourg (ANLux). <ptr target="http://anlux.lu/"/>. Western European
                Union Archives. Armament Bodies. CPA/SAC. Comité permanent des armements. File
                CPA-032. Volume 1/1.</note> and because it was convinced that NATO and the
              organizations related to it were more effective and better positioned to achieve
              standardization in the field of armaments.<note>The National Archives of the UK (TNA).
                Foreign Office, Western Organisations and Co-ordination Department and Foreign and
                Commonwealth Office, Western Organisations Department: Registered Files (W and WD
                Series). Western European Union (WEU). Future of Standing Armaments Committee of
                Western European Union. 01/01/1975–31/12/1975, FCO 41/1749 (Former <ptr
                  type="software" xml:id="Reference" target="#Reference"/><rs type="soft.name"
                  ref="#Reference">Reference</rs> Dep: WDU 11/1 PART B).</note> The interpretation
              of the less predictable results is not straightforward, since they may have been
              determined by an under- or overrepresentation of certain elements in the discourse,
              based on the selection of documents. The same could be said about the negative
              specificity score for the <mentioned>control</mentioned> group in
                <ident>repres_fr</ident>’s, but this finding is also likely to be associated with
              the assertion of France’s resistance to submitting its nuclear stocks to the ACA’s
              controls and the need to avoid making statements on the subject. Since the size of the
              corpus was relatively small, and not all the information for the documents on the
              selected topic and their types in the WEU archive was available, extrapolations about
              the <ptr type="software" xml:id="TXM" target="#TXM"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#TXM"
                >TXM</rs> probabilistic model and the observed linguistic patterns at a larger scale
              than the pilot sample should be avoided at this stage.</p>
            <p>The TEI XML combined with the <ptr type="software" xml:id="TXM" target="#TXM"/><rs
                type="soft.name" ref="#TXM">TXM</rs> analysis tools can also reveal inconsistencies
              which may draw attention to the need for further encoding and testing additional
              documents. On the other hand, it is also important to take into consideration how far
              (or how well) the researcher/user knows the content of the documents, as a lack of
              context can sometimes lead to misinterpretation.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="conclusion">
        <head>Conclusion</head>
        <p>The goal of the pilot project has been to address research questions mainly related to
          the French and British positions on the topic of arms design, production, and control
          within the WEU from 1954 to 1982. In particular, we were interested in combining
          traditional, historical inquiry with TEI XML encoding and decoding in a corpus analysis
          phase for the identification and interpretation of linguistic patterns in the discourse of
          different countries and institutional representatives on armaments issues.</p>
        <p>Given the small scale of the corpus used in the project and the fact that it may not be a
          sufficiently representative sample means that a generalization of the results should not
          be performed without extended testing on an additional set of documents, conducting
          further evaluation of the probabilistic model and an estimation of the sample as compared
          to the collection from which it was extracted. From a methodological perspective, however,
          the TEI XML encoding and decoding experiments have proved that the approach can assist
          qualitative and quantitative methods for the study of historical and discursive phenomena
          in a collection of institutional documents and a chosen theme. More precisely, the
          encoding may be quite helpful for researchers, even if they have no previous knowledge of
          the content of the documents. That is to say, if meaningful thresholds for analysis are
          set, one can find out the main topic of the documents, and the tags may help in
          discovering who the speakers are and the main <soCalled>orientation</soCalled> of their
          speech (i.e., their position) in terms of what is specific to their discourse. However, in
          order to enhance the reading of the specificities, combination with other methods, such as
          concordances, co-occurrences, and document visualization, is required.</p>
        <p>Going back to the initial idea of considering a new link in the decoding–encoding chain
          suggested by Burnard, we see the TEI <term>encoding</term> as adding a
            <soCalled>material</soCalled> layer to the original text, which further supports both
          machine and human interpretation (<term>decoding</term>). In a larger sense, despite the
          inherent bias and limitations related to the selection and the number of documents used in
          the study, we have attempted to prove the <soCalled>materiality</soCalled> of the TEI
          encoding and decoding as a basis for hermeneutic inquiry in the quest for producing
          knowledge via digital <soCalled>instruments</soCalled>, as <ref type="bibl"
            target="#capurro10">Capurro</ref> and <ref type="bibl" target="#ihde03">Idhe</ref> have
          previously stated in their accounts on a digital and material hermeneutics.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="andrews13"><author>Andrews, Tara</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
              level="a">The Third Way: Philology and Critical Edition in the Digital Age.</title>
            <title level="j">Variants: The Journal of the European Society for Textual
              Scholarship</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">61–76</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bergounioux81"><author>Bergounioux, Alain</author>, <author>Michel
              Launay</author>, <author>Josette Lefvre</author>, <author>René Mouriaux</author>, and
              <author>Jean-Pierre Sueur</author>. <date>1981</date>. <title level="a">Le vocabulaire
              des confédérations syndicales ouvrières: une analyse des spécificités.</title>
            <title level="j">Mots</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">139–56</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.3406/mots.1981.1025</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bonnafous81"><author>Bonnafous, Simone</author>. <date>1981</date>. <title
              level="a">Le vocabulaire spécifique des motions Mitterrand, Rocard et CERES au congrès
              de Metz (1979).</title>
            <title level="j">Mots</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">79–94</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.3406/mots.1981.1040</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burnard98"><author>Burnard, Lou</author>. <date>1998</date>. <title
              level="u">On the hermeneutic implications of text encoding</title>. Accessed March 6,
            2016. <ptr target="http://users.ox.ac.uk/~lou/wip/herman.htm"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="capurro10"><author>Capurro, Rafael</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title
              level="a">Digital Hermeneutics: An Outline.</title> In <title level="j">AI &amp;
              Society</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">35–42</biblScope>. Accessed March 6, 2016. <ptr
              target="http://www.capurro.de/digitalhermeneutics.html"/>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1007/s00146-009-0255-9</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="delhauteur91"><author>Delhauteur, Dominique</author>. <date>1991</date>.
              <title level="a">Les activités du Conseil de l’UEO en matière de coopération dans le
              domaine des armements.</title> In dossier <title level="u">notes et documents</title>
            no. 160. Brussels: GRIP (Groupe de recherche et d’information sur la paix et la
            securite). <ptr target="http://www.grip.org/fr/node/1014"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="guyard81"><author>Guyard, Marie-Renée</author>. <date>1981</date>. <title
              level="a">Spécificités d’auteurs dans <title level="m">Le Surréalisme au service de la
                Révolution</title></title>. <title level="j">Mots</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">95–122</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.3406/mots.1981.1023</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hayles05"><author>Hayles, Katherine</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title
              level="m">My Mother Was a Computer: Digital Subjects and Literary Texts.</title>
            <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>.
            Excerpt: <ptr target="http://www.press.uchicago.edu/Misc/Chicago/321487.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="heiden10"><author>Heiden, Serge</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title
              level="a">The <ptr type="software" xml:id="TXM" target="#TXM"/><rs type="soft.name"
                ref="#TXM">TXM</rs> Platform: Building Open-Source Textual Analysis Software
              Compatible with the TEI Encoding Scheme</title>. In <title level="m">Proceedings of
              the 24th Pacific Asia Conference on Language, Information and Computation</title>,
            edited by <editor>Ryo Otoguro</editor>, <editor>Kiyoshi Ishikawa</editor>,
              <editor>Hiroshi Umemoto</editor>, <editor>Kei Yoshimoto</editor>, and <editor>Yasunari
              Harada</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">389–398</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>: <publisher>Institute for Digital Enhancement of Cognitive
              Development, Waseda University</publisher>. Accessed July 24, 2017. <ptr
              target="http://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-00549764/en"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ihde03"><author>Ihde, Don</author>. <date>2003</date>. <title level="u">More
              Material Hermeneutics.</title> Paper presented at the meeting on <title level="u"
              >Hermeneutics and Science</title>, Tihany, Hungary, June 7 - 11, 2003. Accessed March
            6, 2016. <ptr
              target="http://humanitieslab.stanford.edu/23/admin/download.html?attachid=178178"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lafon80"><author>Lafon, Pierre</author>. <date>1980</date>. <title level="a"
              >Sur la variabilité de la fréquence des formes dans un corpus.</title>
            <title level="j">Mots</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">127–65</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.3406/mots.1980.1008</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="manoff06"><author>Manoff, Marlene</author>. <date>2006</date>. <title
              level="a">The Materiality of Digital Collections: Theoretical and Historical
              Perspectives.</title>
            <title level="j">portal: Libraries and the Academy</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">311–25</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1353/pla.2006.0042</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mcgann01"><author>McGann, Jerome</author>. <date>2001</date>. <title
              level="m">Radiant Textuality</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Palgrave</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="nikander08"><author>Nikander, Pirjo</author>. <date>2008</date>. <title
              level="a">Constructionism and Discourse Analysis.</title> In <title level="m">Handbook
              of Constructionist Research</title>, edited by <editor>James A. Holstein</editor> and
              <editor>Jaber F. Gubrium</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">413–28</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Guilford Press</publisher>. Accessed
            March 6, 2016. <ptr
              target="http://www.helsinki.fi/sosiaalipsykologia/arkisto/Nikander%20ch21%202008.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="philips04"><author>Phillips, Nelson</author>, <author>Thomas B.
              Lawrence</author>, and <author>Cynthia Hardy</author>. <date>2004</date>. <title
              level="a">Discourse and Institutions.</title>
            <title level="j">Academy of Management Review</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">635–52</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.5465/AMR.2004.14497617</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pierazzo14"><author>Pierazzo, Elena</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title
              level="m">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories, Models and Methods</title>.
              <pubPlace>Surrey, England</pubPlace>: <publisher>Ashgate</publisher>; <publisher>HAL
              open archive</publisher>, &lt;hal-01182162&gt;. Accessed March 6, 2016. <ptr
              target="http://hal.univ-grenoble-alpes.fr/hal-01182162/document"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="remacle09"><author>Rémacle, Eric</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title
              level="a">L’Union (de l’Europe) occidentale durant la guerre froide
              (1948–1989).</title> In <title level="m">L’Amérique, l’Europe, l’Afrique (1945–1973)
              [America, Europe, Africa (1945–1973]</title>, edited by <editor>Eric Rémacle</editor>
            and <editor>Pascaline Winand</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">187–234</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Brussels</pubPlace>: <publisher>PIE-Peter-Lang</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="textometrie14"><orgName>Textométrie</orgName>. <date>2014</date>. <title
              level="m">Manuel de <ptr type="software" xml:id="TXM" target="#TXM"/><rs
                type="soft.name" ref="#TXM">TXM</rs></title>, Version 0.7. Accessed March 6, 2016.
              <ptr target="http://textometrie.ens-lyon.fr/spip.php?rubrique64"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="thornborrow02"><author>Thornborrow, Joanna Sarah</author>. <date>2002</date>
            <title level="m">Power Talk: Language and Interaction in Institutional
              Discourse.</title>
            <pubPlace>Harlow</pubPlace>: <publisher>Longman</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="vandijk93"><author>Van Dijk, Teun A.</author>
            <date>1993</date>. <title level="a">Principles of critical discourse analysis.</title>
            <title level="j">Discourse &amp; Society</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">249–83</biblScope>. Accessed March 6, 2016. <ptr
              target="http://www.discourses.org/OldArticles/Principles%20of%20critical%20discourse%20analysis.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
