<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI.internal">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Editorial Introduction to Issue 9 of the Journal of the Text Encoding
          Initiative</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Martin</forename>
            <surname>Müller</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation><!-- [RvdB] complete --></affiliation>
          <email>martinmueller@northwestern.edu</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>23/04/2017</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Martin Müller</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Anne Baillot</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="9">Selected Papers from the 2014 TEI Conference; TEI and
          Materiality</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Revues.org -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="editorialIntroduction">
        <p>Earlier versions of the papers in this volume were presented at the 2014 conference at
          Northwestern University. Its theme, <q>Decoding the Encoded</q> was my idea because I had
          often wondered about the point of very intricate forms of encoding when there were not (or
          not yet) any ways of relatively easily getting out of an encoded text what someone had put
          into it, typically at a great cost of time and effort. Later I took part in TEI Board
          meetings where we spent a lot of time weighing the pros and cons of this or that tag line
          for the next conference.</p>
        <p>The papers in this volume are representative of the conference in that with one exception
          they do not really address problems of decoding the encoded. For that matter, the papers
          at other TEI conferences I have gone to also did not have a whole lot to do with the theme
          of the year. From which a reasonable person might conclude that worrying about themes does
          not take you very far. People will do what they feel like doing, and if a paper is
          interesting, the reviewers are unlikely to reject it as out of scope, especially not in
          the context of a far-flung but small and close-knit community like the TEI.</p>
        <p>That said, the papers in this volume are interesting. Stadler, Illetscko, and Seifert
          advance the case for correspondence, a curious stepchild of the TEI. The TEI is not a set
          of rules for the encoding of literature, but literature has a privileged position, and
          there are special chapters for verse and drama. Correspondence specific elements are found
          here and there in the Guidelines, but correspondence is arguably so fundamental a genre of
          writing that it deserves explicit recognition.</p>
        <p>A version of Pilate’s question <q>What is truth</q> shapes <title level="a">Challenging
            the Myth of Presentation in Digital Editions</title> (Turska, Cummings, Rahtz). Where is
          the <soCalled>real</soCalled> in a digital edition? Is it what it looks like on a page and
          all the technical stuff is just an incomprehensible way of getting there? That is the
          modal English professor’s view of his edition. Or is it the encoding that could support
          quite different presentations? The authors offer a Processing Model as a bridge between
          these conflicting views. On a practical level it is a standardizing move that helps reduce
          costs. At a theoretical level it carries the promise of making the English professor and
          the XML geek understand a little better what the other is up to.</p>
        <p><title level="a">Formal Ontologies, Linked Data, and TEI Semantics</title> (Ciotti,
          Tomasi) reminds me of two different forms of aphasia. Damage to <soCalled>Broca’s
            area</soCalled> in the brain leads to a loss of syntactic competence, while damage to
            <soCalled>Wernicke’s area</soCalled> leads to babble that is syntactically competent but
          utterly lacking in meaning. A TEI text reduced to its Xpaths will occasionally give you an
          idea of what the text is about, but mainly it is what the speech pathologists would call
            <soCalled>fluent aphasia</soCalled>. Ontologies and the Semantic Web in their
          pathological form (Casaubon in Middlemarch) are more like damage to Broca’s era. Ordinary
          humans do quite well at bringing meaning and syntax together. Whether you can fill the
          empty syntax of a TEI schema with the meaning of an ontology is a tricky question. I
          confess to some skepticism but salute the effort to square that circle.</p>
        <p><title level="a">Materiality of TEI Encoding and Decoding: an Analysis of the Western
            European Union Archives on Armament Policy</title> (Armaselu, Martins, Jones) is an
          excellent guided tour of what it takes to move documents from the era of the manual
          typewriter through OCR, TEI encoding, linguistic annotation to a subsequent decoding with
          the help of sophisticated linguistic analysis tools.</p>
        <p>The final paper takes us from the Cold War period to a much earlier world: the objects
          that once were considered worth collecting, were held in the treasure rooms of the rich or
          powerful, and now live in public museums if they survived at all. Many of them did not but
          sometimes their traces are found in contemporary descriptions. It is one thing to describe
          an object. It is another to describe a description of a lost object . How do you do this
          in TEI? That is the question Brent Nelson addresses in <title level="a">Curating
            Object-Oriented Collections Using the TEI</title>. That is a very technical question,
          but the lost objects tell touching stories, as in the case of a description of <q>a
            cravat, a shass or girdle, and small pair of gaiters of curious work</q> in the
          catalogue prepared by a seventeenth century English clergyman who got it as a present from
          a London merchant, who had been one among 162 slaves whose release the clergyman
          negotiated on behalf of Charles II.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
