<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Digital Humanities Storytelling Heritage Lab</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Ruiz Gonzalez Renteria</surname>
                        <forename>Mariana</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Arizona State University, United States of America</affiliation>
                    <email>mruizgo1@asu.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Amezcua</surname>
                        <forename>Angélica</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Arizona State University, United States of America</affiliation>
                    <email>aamezcu1@asu.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014-12-19T13:50:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Name, Institution</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Street</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>City</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Country</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Name</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Poster</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Spanish Heritage teaching</term>
                    <term>Mapping</term>
                    <term>Storyteling</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>audio</term>
                    <term>video</term>
                    <term>multimedia</term>
                    <term>teaching</term>
                    <term>pedagogy</term>
                    <term>and curriculum</term>
                    <term>multilingual / multicultural approaches</term>
                    <term>spanish and spanish american studies</term>
                    <term>linguistics</term>
                    <term>creative and performing arts</term>
                    <term>including writing</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p rend="Cuerpo">We are proposing to develop a storytelling tool that integrates multimodal mapping for use in language classrooms. Through a Digital Humanities approach on Storytelling Labs, we will be integrating the App StoryMapJS in order to create a storymap of their cultural heritages. This DH tool is very accessible and it will allow the student to engage mapping narrative through images, videos, music, writing and maps; so the heritage learners will interpret space by their personal print, and it will let to other readers from the course or outside the course, to confront other sociopolitical contexts.</p>
            <p rend="Cuerpo">The DH Storytelling Heritage Lab will reforge the spatial, and emotional relation from our heritage learners as individuals that can create their own mapping. In a pedagogical perspective the heritage learner will improve their writing, oral, listening and reading skills in Spanish. In a linguistic research approach we will analyze the outcome of the students, a qualitative discourse analysis. </p>
            <p rend="Cuerpo">The workshop will be divided in two sections: the narrative without the DH tool: the student will engaged their narratives through family albums, objects, drawings, and recordings. The second part is to transform the storytelling into a digital narrative with the StoryMapJS. At the end of the Lab the student will have the opportunity to exhibit their narratives maps. The final stories will be compiled in a single web page for their distribution in different areas.</p>
            <p rend="Cuerpo">The idea to expand the personal stories and experience in the US of the heritage learners is essential for the course; so the learners engaged Spanish in the sociopolitical context of bilingualism of their own families and community. Their narratives, our narratives, will enrich the course. </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
