<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="full">
                    <title type="main">Digital Experimentation, Courageous Citizenship and Caribbean Futurism</title>
                    <title type="sub">Experimentación Digital, Ciudadanía Valiente y Futurismo Caribeño</title>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Esprit</surname>
                        <forename>Schuyler</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Research Institute at Dominica State College</affiliation>
                    <email>schuyleresprit@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-04-27T01:58:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Name, Institution</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Street</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>City</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Country</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Name</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Invited Talks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Caribbean studies</term>
                    <term>afrofuturism</term>
                    <term>eco-criticism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>cultural studies</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                    <term>eco-criticism</term>
                    <term>digital activism and networked communities</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>The violence and trauma of climate change have arrived. The Caribbean region is the unfortunate recipient of the impacts of climate change and, much like its inheritance of plantation slavery and colonialism, it is left with the infrastructural, social and cultural pillage of imperial and neocolonial imposition. My talk will consider whether and how the humanities, and digital humanities in particular, can produce the ideal intersection between planetary responsibility, community accountability and sustainable living. </p>
            <p>In this talk I discuss Create Caribbean Research Institute’s digital humanities praxis through the example of the environmental sustainability project, 
                <hi rend="italic">Carisealand</hi>. Through the exploration and discussion of theories, tools, methodologies and praxis of digital humanities applied to the project, I position Caribbean afrofuturism in the context of contemporary Caribbean digital environments and the lived experience of Caribbean people in the aftermath of climate change. 
            </p>
            <p>I apply discourses of afrofuturism to imagine an alternate Caribbean future represented in the redesign, digital imagination and representation of selected Caribbean communities. By offering models for rethinking, visualizing and rebuilding physical spaces, I hope to raise questions and offer insights about the power of digital humanities for social and environmental justice in the contemporary and future Caribbean. The goal is to also offer the model as a template for developing other mapping projects that can propose an alternate future for the Global South.</p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold">Experimentación Digital, Ciudadanía Valiente y Futurismo Caribeño</hi>
            </p>
            <p>La violencia y el trauma del cambio climático ya comenzaron. La región del Caribe es la desafortunada receptora de los impactos del cambio climático y, al igual que con la herencia de esclavitud en las plantaciones y del colonialismo, sufre del saqueo infraestructural, social y cultural de la imposición imperial y neocolonial. Mi charla considerará si, y de qué forma, las humanidades, y las humanidades digitales en particular, pueden producir una intersección ideal entre la responsabilidad planetaria y comunitaria, y una vida sustentable. </p>
            <p>Asimismo, en mi charla, discuto la práctica de las humanidades digitales en el Instituto de Investigación Create Caribbean utilizando como ejemplo el proyecto de sustentabilidad ambiental 
                <hi rend="italic">Carisealand</hi>. Por medio de la exploración y discusión de las teorías, herramientas, metodologías y prácticas de las humanidades digitales aplicadas en el proyecto, ubico el afrofuturismo caribeño en el contexto de los ambientes digitales contemporáneos del Caribe y la experiencia de los caribeños que viven con las repercusiones del cambio climático.
            </p>
            <p>Finalmente, pongo en práctica los discursos del afrofuturismo para imaginar un futuro caribeño alternativo representado en el rediseño, la imaginación y representación digitales de ciertas comunidades caribeñas. Al ofrecer modelos para repensar, visualizar y reconstruir los espacios físicos, deseo despertar preguntas y ofrecer entendimiento acerca del poder que las humanidades digitales tienen para crear justicia social y ambiental en el Caribe contemporáneo y futuro. La meta es también ofrecer este modelo como una plantilla para desarrollar otros proyectos de mapeo que pueden proponer un futuro alternativo para el Sur Global.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
