<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="full">
                    <title type="main">Tramando la palabra</title>
                    <title type="sub">Weaving the Word</title>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Chávez Santiago</surname>
                        <forename>Janet</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Activista en lenguas indígenas / Indigenous Languages Activist</affiliation>
                    <email>jazoula.10@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-04-27T02:00:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Name, Institution</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Street</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>City</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Country</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Name</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Invited Talks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Zapotec</term>
                    <term>indigenous languages</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>teaching</term>
                    <term>pedagogy</term>
                    <term>and curriculum</term>
                    <term>lexicography</term>
                    <term>Spanish</term>
                    <term>indigenous studies</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>La trama es el hilo que se teje entre la urdimbre, son nuestro papel y lápiz para crear un lienzo. Juntos, trama y urdimbre, son el puente que unen los hilos con nuestro pasado y nuestro presente, tejemos las grecas de Mitla como una forma de leer o interpretar y escribir a nuestros ancestros, pero también para contar nuestros sueños y nuestras experiencias. Tramamos en zapoteco. Cuando terminamos un tapete lo compartimos con el mundo, y aunque el tejido está en zapoteco se puede interpretar en inglés, en español, en mixteco o en chatino.</p>
            <p>Los medios digitales se pueden ver como una urdimbre en donde hablantes de lenguas indígenas tengan la oportunidad de tramar su palabra y compartirla dentro de su propia comunidad y más allá.  Aunque hoy en día los medios digitales y las redes sociales son prácticamente parte de nuestra vida cotidiana y de nuestra interacción con el mundo, como hablantes de lenguas indígenas todavía nos hace falta apropiarnos realmente  de estos espacios, tramar bien nuestra palabra para liberarnos de la negación del presente.</p>
            <p>Weaving the Word</p>
            <p>The weft is a thread that is woven among the warp’s yarns; these are our paper and pencil in the creation of a rug.  Together, warp and weft are the bridge that unites the threads with our past and our present, and we weave the patterns of Mitla’s friezes as a form of reading, or of interpreting, and of writing our ancestors, but also as a way to recount our dreams and our experiences.  We weave in Zapotec. When we complete a rug, we share it with the world, and although the weave is in Zapotec, it can be interpreted in English, in Spanish, in Mixtec, or in Chatino.</p>
            <p>Digital media can be seen as a warp on which the speakers of indigenous languages have an opportunity to weave their word and to share it within their own community and beyond.  Although in our times digital media and social networks are a practical part of our daily lives and of our interactions with the world, we as speakers of indigenous languages must truly appropriate these spaces, to weave our word well, in order to liberate ourselves from the a denial of the present.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
