<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="full"><title type="main">Improving machine translation literacy to facilitate and enhance scholarly communication</title><title type="sub"/></title></titleStmt><author><persName><surname>Bowker</surname><forename>Lynne</forename></persName><affiliation>University of Ottawa, Canada</affiliation><email>lbowker@uottawa.ca</email></author><editionStmt><edition><date>43840</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Name, Institution</publisher><address><addrLine>Street</addrLine><addrLine>City</addrLine><addrLine>Country</addrLine><addrLine>Name</addrLine></address></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from an OASIS Open Document</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22"><label>DHConvalidator</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category"><term>Paper</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory"><term>Poster</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords"><term>digital literacy; machine translation; machine translation literacy; human-computer-interaction; scholarly communication</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics"><term>English</term><term>North America</term><term>Contemporary</term><term>artificial intelligence and machine learning</term><term>curricular and pedagogical development and analysis</term><term>Language acquisition</term><term>Translation studies</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>English is the main language of scholarly communication, but, most researchers are not native English speakers. Contemporary machine translation approaches such as neural machine translation (NMT) are data-driven and use artificial-intelligence-based machine learning techniques; however, such tools rarely produce high quality output of specialized text without human intervention. There is an emerging need for machine translation (MT) literacy among non-Anglpohone students and faculty who must both read and write in English in order to participate fully in the scholarly communication process. We designed and pilot tested a machine translation literacy workshop to help researchers use MT more effectively for scholarly tasks such as: 1) search and discovery of scholarly texts; 2) reading and evaluating scholarly texts; 3) research communication in international teams; and 4) writing for scholarly publishing. Pre- and post-workshop surveys were used to evaluate the success of the workshop and recommend improvements for future iterations.</p></body></text></TEI>