<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="full"><title type="main">How can science and knowledge be created for all and by all without #linguisticjustice?</title><title type="sub">Findings from a two-year study on the intersections between citizen science, social media, crowdsourcing, and Translation Studies.</title></title></titleStmt><author><persName><surname>Desjardins</surname><forename>Renée</forename></persName><affiliation>Université de Saint-Boniface, Canada</affiliation><email>rdesjardins@ustboniface.ca</email></author><editionStmt><edition><date>43838</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Name, Institution</publisher><address><addrLine>Street</addrLine><addrLine>City</addrLine><addrLine>Country</addrLine><addrLine>Name</addrLine></address></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from an OASIS Open Document</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22"><label>DHConvalidator</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category"><term>Paper</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory"><term>Long Presentation</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords"><term>Translation Studies</term><term>linguistic justice</term><term>knowledge dissemination</term><term>Citizen Science</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics"><term>Global</term><term>English</term><term>Contemporary</term><term>meta-criticism (reflections on digital humanities and humanities computing)</term><term>social media analysis and methods</term><term>Humanities computing</term><term>Translation studies</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>This paper presents the findings of a 2-year study examining the role of translation and language diversity in online citizen science initiatives. In the last 10 years, the proliferation of mobile technologies, the popularity of participatory culture and social media, as well as the uptick in crowdsourced models for conducting large-scale tasks has  impacted the academic landscape. Specifically, this project considers two platforms, Zooniverse and the Canadian Citizen Science Portal. The overarching framework is an amalgamation of methods and theories, situating the project in the transdisciplinary Digital Humanities. Because the project&#8217;s mandate is, in part, to informmore equitable exchange/dissemination of citizen science capitals in online and digital spaces, the underpinning philosophical worldview is one that is transformative. Within the purview of Translation Studies, this study falls under the umbrella of descriptive product-oriented research and context-oriented research. Social network analysis (data visualization) and social media analysis (qualitative) further supplements this framework.</p></body></text></TEI>