<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="full"><title type="main">Mind the gap</title><title type="sub">Filling gaps in cuneiform tablets using Machine Learning Algorithms</title></title></titleStmt><author><persName><surname>Homburg</surname><forename>Timo</forename></persName><affiliation>Mainz University Of Applied Sciences</affiliation><email>timo.homburg@gmx.de</email></author><editionStmt><edition><date>43997</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Name, Institution</publisher><address><addrLine>Street</addrLine><addrLine>City</addrLine><addrLine>Country</addrLine><addrLine>Name</addrLine></address></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from an OASIS Open Document</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22"><label>DHConvalidator</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category"><term>Paper</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory"><term>Poster</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords"><term>Cuneiform</term><term>Text</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics"><term>Asia</term><term>English</term><term>BCE-4th Century</term><term>artificial intelligence and machine learning</term><term>semantic analysis</term><term>Computer science</term><term>Linguistics</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Introduction</p><p>A presisting problem in near eastern studies is the existence of broken cuneiformtablets (listing 1.1). In recent years efforts have been undertaken to 3DScan Maraet al. (2010), to paleographically describe Homburg (2019) and to digitally recon-struct broken fragments Collins et al. (2014, 2017) of cuneiform tablets. However,not always broken fragments can complement each other and often parts of thecuneiform tablet remain destroyed. These fractures or gaps in the cuneiformtablet are not always easy for scholars to fill and take a considerable amount ofinterpretation time on their part. With the emergence of more digitally availablecuneiform text resources, this publication sees an opportunity to investigate ifauto-complete algorithms, based on machine learning and linguistic linked opendata (LLOD) resources Homburg (2017) can be useful in the reconstructionof cuneiform texts. The classification results are to be used to create a epochand language specific recommendation system to fill gaps on cuneiform tablets,therefore assisting cuneiform scholars.</p><p>Related Work</p><p>Related work has been done in autocompletion systems which face the similarchallenge of anticipating the users input derived from context and other featuresLeung &amp; Zhang (2008), Gikandi (2006), Hyv&#246;nen &amp; M&#228;kel&#228; (2006). Those tech-nologies are heavily relied on in input method engines1 which are powered withdifferent dictionary-based algorithms, but recently Chen et al. (2015), Huanget al. (2018) also with machine learning approaches and neural networks. Inputmethod engines for cuneiform have been developed by Homburg et al. (2015).</p><p>Methodology</p><p>Following Homburg &amp; Chiarcos (2016) machine learning methods applied areeither based on grammatical rules (POSTagging), dictionary-based methods ex-ploiting (third-party) dictionary resources or statistical approaches using thefollowing types of machine learning features:&#8211; Context-dependent features: e.g. for Hidden Markov Model Classifications&#8211; Grammatical features derived from POSTaggers&#8211; Semantic Features derived from the semantic meaning of surrounding words&#8211; Metadata Features e.g. text categorizations&#8211; Paleographic Features using PaleoCodage for a subset of manually annotatedtexts Homburg (2019)</p><p>Experimental Setup</p><p>The effectiveness of the algorithms and features is tested on a corpus of all CDLItexts in ATF which is split in a training and test set. Texts are prepared withrandom gaps for classification and evaluated using the original texts (the goldstandard) on unicode cuneiform and on the respective cuneiform transliterationfor different cuneiform languages (Sumerian, Hittite, Akkadian) and epochs. Theposter features selected peliminary results of the classification and a significanceanalysis of the features for further discussion for improvement. A possible futuregoal could be a shared task to improve classification accuracy similar to thecuneiform language identification challenge Jauhiainen et al. (2019)</p><p>Application</p><p>Lastly, the poster presents a prototypical application (fig. 1)displaying the results of the machine learning process which is currently in devel-opment. The implementation builds up on the concept of input method enginesHomburg et al. (2015) and will provide a self-learning component.</p><p>Caption Figure 1: (prototype.jpg)</p><p>Text Completion Prototype: &#8221;If...Enlil&#8221;. The dictionary knows, that Enlilis a gods name (NE) and is commonly preceded by a determinative character for god??(an), which is suggested in first place to fill the gap. Next likely options are aperson named Enlil (male or female), the people (tribe) of Enlil, or a location</p><p>Bibliography</p><p>Chen, S., Zhao, H. &amp; Wang, R. (2015), Neural network language model forchinese pinyin input method engine, in &#8216;Proceedings of the 29th Pacific AsiaConference on Language, Information and Computation&#8217;, pp. 455&#8211;461. 2Collins, T., Woolley, S. I., Ch&#8217;ng, E., Hernandez-Munoz, L., Gehlken, E., Nash,D., Lewis, A. &amp; Hanes, L. (2017), A virtual 3d cuneiform tablet reconstruc-tion interaction, in &#8216;Proceedings of the 31st British Computer Society HumanComputer Interaction Conference&#8217;, BCS Learning &amp; Development Ltd., p. 73.1Collins, T., Woolley, S. I., Munoz, L. H., Lewis, A., Ch&#8217;ng, E. &amp; Gehlken,E. (2014), Computer-assisted reconstruction of virtual fragmented cuneiformtablets, in &#8216;2014 International Conference on Virtual Systems &amp; Multimedia(VSMM)&#8217;, IEEE, pp. 70&#8211;77. 1Gikandi, D. (2006), &#8216;Predictive text computer simplified keyboard with word andphrase auto-completion (plus text-to-speech and a foreign language translationoption)&#8217;. US Patent App. 11/308,013. 2Homburg, T. (2017), Postagging and semantic dictionary creation for hittitecuneiform, in &#8216;DH2017&#8217;. 1Homburg, T. (2019), Paleo codage - a machine-readable way to describecuneiform characters paleographically, Utrecht, Netherlands.URL: https://dev.clariah.nl/files/dh2019/boa/0259.html 1, 3Homburg, T. &amp; Chiarcos, C. (2016), Word segmentation for akkadian cuneiform,in &#8216;LREC 2016&#8217;. 3Homburg, T., Chiarcos, C., Richter, T. &amp; Wicke, D. (2015), &#8216;Learning cuneiformthe modern way&#8217;.URL: http://gams.uni-graz.at/o:dhd2015.p.55 2, 4Huang, Y., Li, Z., Zhang, Z. &amp; Zhao, H. (2018), &#8216;Moon ime: neural-based chinesepinyin aided input method with customizable association&#8217;, Proceedings of ACL2018, System Demonstrations pp. 140&#8211;145. 2Hyv&#246;nen, E. &amp; M&#228;kel&#228;, E. (2006), Semantic autocompletion, in &#8216;Asian SemanticWeb Conference&#8217;, Springer, pp. 739&#8211;751. 2Jauhiainen, T., Jauhiainen, H., Alstola, T. &amp; Lind&#233;n, K. (2019), &#8216;Language anddialect identification of cuneiform texts&#8217;, arXiv preprint arXiv:1903.01891 .3.1Leung, B. &amp; Zhang, Q. (2008), &#8216;Providing relevant text auto-completions&#8217;. USPatent App. 11/751,121. 2Mara, H., Kr&#246;mker, S., Jakob, S. &amp; Breuckmann, B. (2010), Gigamesh andgilgamesh:&#8211;3d multiscale integral invariant cuneiform character extraction, in&#8216;Proceedings of the 11th International conference on Virtual Reality, Archae-ology and Cultural Heritage&#8217;, Eurographics Association, pp. 131&#8211;138. 1</p></body></text></TEI>