<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="full"><title type="main">Creating Structured and Reusable Data for Tourism and Commerce Images of Edo</title><title type="sub">Using IIIF Curation Platform to Extract Information from Historical Materials.</title></title></titleStmt><author><persName><surname>Suzuki</surname><forename>Chikahiko</forename></persName><affiliation>ROIS-DS Center for Open Data in the Humanities, Japan</affiliation><affiliation>National Institute of Informatics</affiliation><email>ch_suzuki@nii.ac.jp</email></author><author><persName><surname>Kitamoto</surname><forename>Asanobu</forename></persName><affiliation>ROIS-DS Center for Open Data in the Humanities, Japan</affiliation><affiliation>National Institute of Informatics</affiliation></author><editionStmt><edition><date>43996</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Name, Institution</publisher><address><addrLine>Street</addrLine><addrLine>City</addrLine><addrLine>Country</addrLine><addrLine>Name</addrLine></address></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from an OASIS Open Document</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22"><label>DHConvalidator</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category"><term>Paper</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory"><term>Lightning</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords"><term>Edo (formerly Tokyo)</term><term>pre-modern Japanese books</term><term>IIIF</term><term>curation</term><term>time machine project</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics"><term>Asia</term><term>English</term><term>18th Century</term><term>19th Century</term><term>data publishing projects, systems, and methods</term><term>digital research infrastructures development and analysis</term><term>Asian studies</term><term>Book and print history</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Purpose</p><p>Our final research goal is to restore Edo&#8217;s historical city conditions (Tokyo&#8217;s former name before the late 19th century) using historical materials. In particular, we focus on non-textual materials. For textual materials, TEI is the de facto standard. For non-textual materials, we need to find new ways as just collecting images is insufficient. We need to organize images as data for analysis across historical materials.</p><p>Material and Method</p><p>The tool used for this work is the IIIF Curation Platform (ICP)[1]. &#8220;Curation&#8221; with ICP is a generic method that allows us to gather IIIF images or parts of images and add metadata to each. Curation allows images to be organized as structured and reusable data[2].</p><p>A large number of digitized pre-modern Japanese books are being released by multiple Japanese institutions[3]. We used ICP to organize 1255 images from eight guidebooks in the Edo period[4] then organized 2489 images from the Edo shopping guidebook[5].</p><p>Findings and Discussion</p><p>The current curated data confirmed the relationship between famous places and commerce. Presently, our finding reconfirms previous studies[6],[7]. The Asakusa area has many shops around Sensoji Temple today. However, there were many medicine dealers in one corner of Nihonbashi area unlike today (Figure 1&#8211;2).</p><p>By applying our method to Edo period publications, we not only structure useful information for our research, but also provide reusable data for other researches.</p><p>Figure 1: Nihonbashi area illustration curated from Edo guidebooks. Nihonbashi was one of the most famous places in the Edo period.</p><p>Figure 2: Advertisement of Nihonbashi merchant curated from the Edo shopping guidebook . There are many Chinese and Japanese medicine dealers ?????? unlike today.</p><p>References</p><p>[1] IIF Curation Platform http://codh.rois.ac.jp/icp/index.html.en</p><p>[2] Suzuki, C. Kitamoto, A. (2019). &#8220;IIIF Curation Platform ni yoru Edo-Kaimono-Hitori-Annai no microcontents ka&#8221;, Jinmonkon2019, pp.11&#8211;18 </p><p>[3] Database of Pre-Modern Japanese Works, https://kotenseki.nijl.ac.jp/?ln=en</p><p>[4] Illustration of Edo Famous Places, http://www.ch-suzuki.com/icpedo/finder/?lang=en</p><p>Primary sources:</p><p>Asai, Ryoi. (1662). Edo-Meisho-Ki , Dataset of Pre-modern Japanese Works, doi: 10.20730/100000011</p><p>Kondo, Kiyoharu. (1663). Edo-Meisho-Hyakunin-Isshu, National Diet Library Digital Collection, doi: 10.11501/1183942</p><p>Burin, Shoufu. (1795). Ehon-Edo-Zakura, Dataset of Pre-modern Japanese Text, doi: 10.20730/200014989</p><p>Shinratei. (1795). Ehon-Edo-No-Mizu, Dataset of Pre-modern Japanese Text, doi: 10.20730/200013678</p><p>Saito, Choushu. (1834&#8211;1836). Edo-Meisho-Zue, Dataset of Pre-modern Japanese Text, doi: 10.20730/100249896</p><p>Utagawa, Hiroshige. (1850&#8211;1867) Ehon-Edo-Miyage, Dataset of Pre-modern Japanese Text, doi: 10.20730/200013687</p><p>[5] Curation of Merchant in Edo http://www.ch-suzuki.com/edoshop/finder/?lang=en</p><p>Primary source:</p><p>Nakagawa, Gorozaemon. (1824). Edo-Kaimono-Hitori-Annai, Dataset of Pre-modern Japanese Text, doi: 10.20730/100249503</p><p>[6] Ando, Y. (2005). Kankou Toshi Edo no Tanjo, Shinchosha.</p><p>[7] Yamamoto, M. (2005). Edo Kenbutsu to Tokyo Kanko, Rinsen Shoten</p></body></text></TEI>