<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="full"><title type="main">Close-Reading the Endnotes for Word-Frequency Signposts &amp; Polyvocal Citations</title><title type="sub"/></title></titleStmt><author><persName><surname>Yeager</surname><forename>Sean A.</forename></persName><affiliation>The Ohio State University, United States of America</affiliation><email>yeager.211@osu.edu</email></author><editionStmt><edition><date>43845</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Name, Institution</publisher><address><addrLine>Street</addrLine><addrLine>City</addrLine><addrLine>Country</addrLine><addrLine>Name</addrLine></address></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from an OASIS Open Document</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22"><label>DHConvalidator</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category"><term>Paper</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory"><term>Short Presentation</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords"><term>feminism</term><term>citations</term><term>bibliography</term><term>word-count</term><term>intersectional</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics"><term>English</term><term>North America</term><term>Contemporary</term><term>bibliographic analysis</term><term>meta-criticism (reflections on digital humanities and humanities computing)</term><term>Feminist studies</term><term>Gender and sexuality studies</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>This paper describes a machine-assisted bibliographic analysis of the intertextual networks which are housed in an academic text's endnotes. My method is a three step process: first, run a word-count algorithm over the endnotes; next, identify patterns by subjectively grouping high-frequency words into loose clusters; finally, use these high-frequency signposts to perform a symptomatic close-reading of the endnotes. This project falls under Alison Booth's paradigm of "mid-range reading" because it sacrifices both the granular details of close reading and the massive scalability of distant algorithms. The payoff, however, is a versatile methodology through which digital research is consciously co-constructed with a mechanical collaborator.</p><p>My test case is Michael Hardt and Antonio Negri's Empire. I not only identify how monovocal scholarship can intertextually reify hegemonic hierarchies, but also how polyvocal citation can produce the opposite effect. I hope to prompt discussions about the intersections of digital scholarship.</p></body></text></TEI>