<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="full"><title type="main">The Shakespeare and Company Project</title><title type="sub"/></title></titleStmt><author><persName><surname>Ermolaev</surname><forename>Natalia</forename></persName><affiliation>Princeton University, United States of America</affiliation><email>nataliae@princeton.edu</email></author><author><persName><surname>Koeser</surname><forename>Rebecca</forename></persName><affiliation>Princeton University, United States of America</affiliation><email>rebecca.s.koeser@princeton.edu</email></author><editionStmt><edition><date>43997</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Name, Institution</publisher><address><addrLine>Street</addrLine><addrLine>City</addrLine><addrLine>Country</addrLine><addrLine>Name</addrLine></address></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from an OASIS Open Document</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22"><label>DHConvalidator</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category"><term>Paper</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory"><term>Lightning</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords"><term>software development</term><term>design</term><term>collaboration</term><term>data publishing</term><term>interface</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics"><term>Europe</term><term>English</term><term>20th Century</term><term>data publishing projects, systems, and methods</term><term>software development, systems, analysis and methods</term><term>Humanities computing</term><term>Literary studies</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The Shakespeare and Company Project is one of the longest-running projects at the Center for Digital Humanities at Princeton (CDH). Based on archival materials from the Sylvia Beach Papers at Princeton&#8217;s Firestone Library, the project recreates the world of the Lost Generation by detailing what members of Beach&#8217;s lending library read and where they lived. The full site launched May 2020, and data on library members, books, and events will be published soon.</p><p>The Shakespeare and Company Project is an exemplar of CDH&#8217;s commitment to critical adoption of best practices (Koeser, 2019) and innovation in custom software. Our process leverages rigorous testing, including unit testing (over 95% coverage for Python code), automated accessibility testing with pa11y, and manual feature and usability testing. As a project with both popular and scholarly appeal, we&#8217;ve designed a site that foregrounds the complex detail and idiosyncrasy of Beach&#8217;s record-keeping practices, but is welcoming and accessible, and also fully responsive on mobile devices. Through collaborative and iterative data modeling, we developed a relational database that allowed the research team to aggregate data , which helped to identify and disambiguate members, and to associate events from different archival sources. This project also includes a sophisticated solution for storing and querying partially-known dates in a SQL database (Koeser, 2019).</p><p>Our lightning talk will demonstrate aspects of the public interface as well as the administrative backend, provide a brief overview of the published data, and discuss some of the scholarly and technical challenges we encountered.</p><p/><p>References</p><p>Shakespeare and Company Project. Center for Digital Humanities, Princeton University, 2020. https://shakespeareandco.princeton.edu/.</p><p>&#8220;Data Export.&#8221; Shakespeare and Company Project, version 1.1.0. Center for Digital Humanities, Princeton University. April 13, 2020. http://shakespeareandco.princeton.edu/about/data/. Accessed June 15, 2020.</p><p>Koeser, Rebecca Sutton, Nick Budak, Gissoo Doroudian, Benjamin W. Hicks, and Xinyi Li. 2020. Princeton-CDH/mep-django: v1.0. Zenodo. https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3834179.</p><p>Koeser, Rebecca Sutton. 2019. &#8220;Best Practices?&#8221; Panel &#8220;The State of Digital Humanities Software Development.&#8221; presented at the ACH2019, Pittsburgh, July 26. https://rlskoeser.github.io/2019/07/26/best-practices/.</p><p>Koeser, Rebecca Sutton. 2019. &#8220;Coding with Unknowns.&#8221; Center for Digital Humanities at Princeton University. December 5, 2019. https://cdh.princeton.edu/updates/2019/12/05/coding-unknowns/.</p></body></text></TEI>