<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Indexing and Linking Text in a Large Body of Family Writings</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Dal Bo</surname>
                        <forename>Beatrice</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Université Paul-Valéry Montpellier 3 - Praxiling UMR 5267 CNRS</affiliation>
                    <email>beatrice.dal-bo@univ-montp3.fr</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Frontini</surname>
                        <forename>Francesca</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Université Paul-Valéry Montpellier 3 - Praxiling UMR 5267 CNRS</affiliation>
                    <email>francesca.frontini@univ-montp3.fr</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Luxardo</surname>
                        <forename>Giancarlo</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Université Paul-Valéry Montpellier 3 - Praxiling UMR 5267 CNRS</affiliation>
                    <email>giancarlo.luxardo@univ-montp3.fr</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Steuckardt</surname>
                        <forename>Agnès</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Université Paul-Valéry Montpellier 3 - Praxiling UMR 5267 CNRS</affiliation>
                    <email>agnes.steuckardt@univ-montp3.fr</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014-12-19T13:50:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Name, Institution</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Street</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>City</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Country</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Name</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Poster</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>WW1</term>
                    <term>TEI</term>
                    <term>correspondences</term>
                    <term>archives</term>
                    <term>Named Entities annotation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>digital archives and digital libraries</term>
                    <term>text encoding and markup languages</term>
                    <term>spatial &amp; spatio-temporal analysis</term>
                    <term>modeling and visualization</term>
                    <term>history and historiography</term>
                    <term>french studies</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Corpus 14, a corpus of correspondences from World War I</head>
                <p>The processing of correspondences for a digital edition presents similarities with other textual genres, and therefore common methodologies and tools can be applied. However, as correspondence corpora display a reticular presentational organisation and since the related projects often require to progressively gather various sources, publishing through digital media has several advantages with respect to print publishing.</p>
                <p>As opposed to most correspondence projects, dedicated to well-known authors or scholarly writings
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For a list of projects see Stadler 
                            <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2016.
                        </p>
                    </note>, the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Corpus 14</hi> project deals with correspondences from ordinary people
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p>Another project dealing with the digitisation of this kind of correspondences is 
                            <hi rend="italic">Digitising experiences of migrations</hi>: 
                            <hi rend="italic">The development of interconnected letter collections</hi>, by Moreton and Nesi (2013-2014, 
                            <ref target="http://lettersofmigration.blogspot.com">http://lettersofmigration.blogspot.com</ref>). For further information, see also Moreton, 2016; Moreton 
                            <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2014.
                        </p>
                    </note>. In conjunction with the commemoration of the centenary of WWI, the project coincides with the French initiative to appeal to families in order to gather documents or objects related to the war (the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Grande Collecte</hi> was initiated by the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Mission Centenaire</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <ref target="http://www.centenaire.org/fr">http://www.centenaire.org/fr</ref>
                        </p>
                    </note> in 2013). The project allowed for the digitisation and the publication of a vast amount of data (letters, postcards) aimed at specialists in two fields:
                </p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>the study of the Great War and its legacy on social memory, including the cultural transformations that occurred during and because of the war,</item>
                    <item>the evolution of the linguistic uses that happened at that time, in particular among less-literate people (from different areas of France, mostly with rural origins), the propagation of a slang (the so-called 
                        <hi rend="italic">“argot des Poilus”</hi>) or the influence of regional variations, especially in areas characterised by diglossia situations.
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>As of August 2018, the corpus is comprised of almost 1800 correspondences written by 37 writers in 11 areas, for a total of almost 500,000 tokens
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The current size of the corpus is limited, but future additions are planned; the effort was so far concentrated on establishing a methodology, selecting relevant texts that have been accurately transcribed.</p>
                    </note>. The construction of the corpus has been carried out with the following requirements:
                </p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>the selection of exclusively less-literate writers,</item>
                    <item>the preference for writings that can be followed up over time for a network of related writers (although it is generally impossible to build a complete set of correspondences), </item>
                    <item>the accuracy of the transcription in terms of the encountered spelling, punctuation or syntax as well as characteristics of the sources (legibility, layout).</item>
                </list>
                <p>The transcripts were encoded in conformance with the TEI guidelines
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 
                            <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/activities/sig/correspondence/">http://www.tei-c.org/activities/sig/correspondence/</ref>
                        </p>
                    </note>, which preserves the alignment between the text and the facsimiles, to mark up the logical structure of the text as well as features of readability. Two versions of the text are kept: one accurate and one with a normalised orthography.
                </p>
                <p>The metadata, described by the 
                    <hi rend="italic">TEIheader</hi>, includes the 
                    <hi rend="italic">correspDesc</hi> element (as defined by the TEI SIG on Correspondence and introduced in the 2.8.0 version of TEI P5), allowing for the identification of sender(s), addressee(s), relationship, date and place of sending.
                </p>
                <p>In addition to the methodological approach followed in the transcription process, 
                    <hi rend="italic">Corpus 14</hi> relies on the data representation model provided by the TXM platform
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">You can access the 
                            <hi rend="italic">Corpus 14</hi> from 
                            <ref target="http://textometrie.univ-montp3.fr/">http://textometrie.univ-montp3.fr/</ref>
                        </p>
                    </note>, which is used for text querying and analysis. TXM distinguishes properties for structural units (either inherited from the TEI encoding or defined by the user annotation) and lexical units (through an automated morphosyntactic tagging and lemmatisation, which in fact is of limited usefulness for non-standard language). 
                </p>
                <p>The corpus is also available for download from the Ortolang platform
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p>Access via permanent identifier 
                            <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/11403/corpus14">https://hdl.handle.net/11403/corpus14</ref>
                        </p>
                    </note>, a repository for language resources, which provides long-term archiving and allows for metadata harvesting by means of the OAI-PMH protocol.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Semantic annotation of persons and places</head>
                <p>Recent developments of the project mainly concern the semantic annotation of Named Entities, especially persons and places. These are identified following a workflow including both an automated tool, REDEN Online (Frontini 
                    <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2016) and a manual annotation, and eventually marked up according to the guidelines of the TEI module for names, dates, people and places. Place references are linked to an external knowledge bases (DBpedia) whenever possible, whereas persons are referenced to an internal index. NEs in the 
                    <hi rend="italic">correspDesc</hi> and in the 
                    <hi rend="italic">body</hi> are annotated in the same way, but their position in the TEI tree determines their role, so that a simple XPath can return for instance only people and places that are mentioned in a letter. Such analysis shows that places and persons evoked in the correspondences between soldiers and their families are more likely to refer to their previous lives at home. This may be due to the wish of soldiers to maintain the connection with their network and their link to the household environment, which is one of the main functions of these letters (Caffarena, 2005; Gibelli, 2014).
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Ongoing work: organisation of correspondence networks</head>
                <p>Various ways of visualising information related to people, places and dates in correspondences, especially when it concerns metadata, have been developed by several projects. We cite among others 
                    <hi rend="italic">The Migrant letter</hi> (O'Leary and Moreton
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">, </hi>2017); 
                    <hi rend="italic">Visual Correspondence</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <ref target="http://www.correspondence.ie">http://www.correspondence.ie</ref>
                        </p>
                    </note>; 
                    <hi rend="italic">Mapping the Republic of Letters</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <ref target="http://republicofletters.stanford.edu/">http://republicofletters.stanford.edu/</ref>
                        </p>
                    </note>; 
                    <hi rend="italic">Early Modern Letters Online</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <ref target="http://emlo.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/home">http://emlo.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/home</ref>
                        </p>
                    </note>; 
                    <hi rend="italic">Clavius on the Web</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <ref target="http://claviusontheweb.it/">http://claviusontheweb.it/</ref>
                        </p>
                    </note>. Specifically, the investigation of spatial references can be facilitated by a cartographic visualisation. Our main aim in developing our own visualisation interface is to adhere to and exploit existing standards, such as TEI and Semantic Web technologies, so as to create a framework that could ideally be reused for similar corpora.
                </p>
                <p>The visualisation proposed for the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Corpus 14</hi> project displays each set of correspondences (a soldier and his wife/relatives at home) on the map, with its sender and receiver addresses identified by two distinct colors, as well as markers for places mentioned in the letter
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="color(222222)">The visualisation (which will be available as a demo on the project's website) was developed in collaboration with Pietro Barbieri, Chiara Capone and Luca Ciccone, MSc students in computer science, supervised by Marina Ribaudo, associate professor at DIBRIS, Università degli Studi di Genova.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note>.
                </p>
                <p>This way of visualising spatial and personal information contained in letters brings an additional layer to the reading, as well as to the analysis of 
                    <hi rend="italic">Corpus 14</hi> correspondences, which have already been carried out in Steuckardt 
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">et al. </hi>(2015) and Roynette 
                    <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> (2017) 
                    <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Caffarena, F. </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">(2005). </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">Lettere dalla Grande Guerra. Scritture del quotidiano, monumenti della memoria, fonti per la storia. Il caso italiano</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">. Milano: Unicopli.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">Frontini, F., Brando, C. and Ganascia, J. G.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (2016). REDEN ONLINE: Disambiguation, Linking and Visualisation of References in TEI Digital Editions. </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">Digital Humanities 2016: Conference Abstracts</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">. Kraków: Jagiellonian University &amp; Pedagogical University.</hi>
                        <ref target="http://dh2016.adho.org/abstracts/362">
                            <hi rend="color(1155CC)" style="font-size:11pt">http://dh2016.adho.org/abstracts/362</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (accessed 21 November 2018).</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">Gibelli, A.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (2014). </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">La guerra grande: storie di gente comune</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">. Bari: Laterza</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Moreton, E. </hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">(2016). Ph.D. thesis: The emigrant letter digitised: markup and analysis. Birmingham: University of Birmingham. Available from: </hi>
                        <ref target="http://etheses.bham.ac.uk/6416/">
                            <hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">http://etheses.bham.ac.uk/6416 </hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi style="font-size:11pt">(accessed 18 March 2019)</hi>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:11pt">.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Moreton, E., O'Leary, N. and O'Sullivan, P. </hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">(2014). Visualising the emigrant letter. </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Revue Européene des Migrations Internationales. Special issue: Traces of Dispersion</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(333333)" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">, vol. </hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">30 - n° 3 et 4. </hi>
                        <ref target="https://journals.openedition.org/remi/7081">
                            <hi rend="color(1155CC)" style="font-size:11pt">https://journals.openedition.org/remi/7081</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (accessed 18 March 2019).</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:11pt">O'Leary, N. and Moreton, E.</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (2017). The Migrant Letter Digitised: Visualising Metadata. </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Journal of Cultural Analytics</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">. doi: </hi>
                        <ref target="https://dx.doi.org/10.31235/osf.io/89xbp">
                            <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:11pt">10.31235/osf.io/89xbp</hi>
                            <hi rend="apple-tab-span"> </hi>
                        </ref>
                        <ref target="http://culturalanalytics.org/2017/03/the-migrant-letter-digitised-visualising-metadata">
                            <hi rend="color(1155CC)" style="font-size:11pt">http://culturalanalytics.org/2017/03/the-migrant-letter-digitised-visualising-metadata</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (accessed 19 March 2019).</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">Praxiling</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (2014).</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">Corpus 14</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">.</hi>
                        <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/11403/corpus14">
                            <hi rend="color(1155CC)" style="font-size:11pt">https://hdl.handle.net/11403/corpus14</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">Roynette, O., Siouffi, G. and Steuckardt, A. (eds).</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">(2017). </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">La langue sous le feu : mots, textes, discours de la Grande Guerre</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">. (Histoire). Rennes: Presses universitaires de Rennes.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">Stadler, P., Illetschko, M. and Seifert, S.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (2016). Towards a Model for Encoding Correspondence in the TEI: Developing and Implementing &lt;correspDesc&gt;. </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">(Issue </hi>
                        <hi rend="bold color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">9</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">) 
                            <lb/>doi:
                        </hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:11pt">10.4000/jtei.1433.</hi>
                        <ref target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1433">
                            <hi style="font-size:11pt">http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1433</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (accessed 21 November 2018).</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Steuckardt, A. (ed) </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(263033)" style="font-size:11pt">(2015). Entre villages et tranchées: l’écriture de poilus ordinaires. Uzès: Inclinaison.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
