<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Topographies of Digital Modern (Foreign) Languages research</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Spence</surname>
                        <forename>Paul Joseph</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Department of Digital Humanities, King's College London</affiliation>
                    <email>paul.spence@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Brandao</surname>
                        <forename>Renata</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Department of Digital Humanities, King's College London</affiliation>
                    <email>renata.brandao@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014-12-19T13:50:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Name, Institution</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Street</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>City</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Country</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Name</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>'Modern Foreign Languages'</term>
                    <term>multilingual</term>
                    <term>linguistic diversity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>multilingual / multicultural approaches</term>
                    <term>spanish and spanish american studies</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                    <term>digital humanities (history</term>
                    <term>theory and methodology)</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p style="text-align:left; ">Modern (foreign) languages have been under pressure in a number of countries for some time now, with reduced provision in many English-speaking countries, and options increasingly focusing on English elsewhere. In the English-speaking world, a long series of reports has catalogued these challenges at all levels of education, often using words like ‘crisis’ and ‘urgency’ (Tinsley 2013) and it has been suggested that the field of Modern Languages needs to re-configure itself to meet new cultural/media landscapes (Worton 2009).</p>
            <p style="text-align:left; ">Meanwhile, as the digital humanities have expanded and increasingly entered mainstream debates about the future of the humanities, there has been a growing focus on its terms of representation (Spence 2018) and commitment to diversity (Galina 2014). On a geocultural level, various initiatives have sought to address the immense Anglophone linguistic and cultural disparities (e.g. https://programminghistorian.org/ or http://www.globaloutlookdh.org/) which digital culture has amplified — and which DH has often, albeit unwittingly, reinforced within its own areas of influence — but there has been relatively little consideration given to possible interplay with ML, which seems strange given ML expertise in studying multilingual diversity, translation and transcultural perspectives.</p>
            <p style="text-align:left; ">This paper starts by tracing interactions between ML and DH based on detailed empirical research, and argues that there is much to gain from connecting current debates about the future of the Modern Languages (ML) with concerns about the linguistic diversity deficit in the digital humanities.</p>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Topography</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">So far there has been little systematic analysis of interactions between ML and digital humanities (or digital culture more generally), something the Digital Mediations strand on the AHRC-funded ‘Language Acts &amp; Worldmaking’ project aims to address (https://languageacts.org/digital-mediations/).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Through a series of landscape surveys – questionnaires, interview surveys, literature reviews, resource reviews and curricular studies - we have mapped the topography of digital ML research and found that the engagement of Modern Foreign Languages with digital is both wider and deeper than is widely understood by DH or indeed by ML itself, although recently it has started to surface more prominently through initiatives such as the ‘digital hispanisms’ panel at the Association of Hispanists of Great Britain and Ireland conference in 2018 (http://community.dur.ac.uk/hispanists/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/AHGBI-2018-Abstracts-Booklet.pdf) or the 2019 MLA forum on ‘Digital Humanities &amp; Modern Languages’ (https://mla.confex.com/mla/2019/forum/extra/index.cgi?EntryType=Session&amp;username=4494&amp;password=340557).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Digital mediation in ML is particularly strong around language learning/teaching, where researchers and teachers have an elevated understanding of the potential for authentic, multimodal, learner-centred, transcultural and polylingual interaction (Guikema and Williams 2014), but the focus of our research is principally on research into (foreign) languages and their related cultures, rather than language learning.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Our research first sought to establish the topography of ML-DH interactions through an open survey (158 respondents), interview study with ML respondents (35) across a range of different roles, course review (analysing 12 ML modules at 9 institutions) and resource review (analysing 1,327 digital ML resources across 8 portals/platforms).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">We have found that ML researchers have an elevated sense of digital affordances (and risks/limitations), but, generally speaking, low engagement with the kind of advanced digital methods represented by DH, beyond areas such as digital editing, linguistics, electronic literature and web archive studies of language communities (Spence and Brandao 2019).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; "> There were some interesting trends in both survey and interview studies: while transcultural and plurilinguistic expertise is valued, national and disciplinary boundaries are deemed less and less relevant to ML research (making future DH-ML collaboration all the more necessary); large scale data approaches are judged to be increasingly important in facilitating interesting comparisons of cultural reception and influence across many languages; digital is becoming increasingly important as a research object in itself; and there is support for the idea that ‘digital’ needs to (and will) be integrated more closely into ML practice, rather than being something different in future.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Towards a DHML agenda?</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">How does this connect to DH specifically? How can we start to theorise the connection between the digital humanities and ML, and what opportunities are there for deeper, bidirectional and equitably conceived/constructed collaboration?</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">In November 2015 a writing sprint on the theme of ‘Modern Language and the digital’, later published as an open access multi-author collaborative article on ‘The Shape of the Discipline’ edited by Claire Taylor and Niamh Thornton (2017), opened up debate about this. Conversation ranged from themes such as data-driven approaches to modern languages or the ML research process, to users/interfaces in ML and digital ethnography and while some contributors argued that DH often has too narrow a conception of ‘digital’ (which doesn’t always engage well with the digital cultural studies focus which is more common in ML), the article set the scene for greater possible collaboration between the field of ML and DH.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">In an article for Digital Humanities Quarterly, Thea Pitman and Claire Taylor expanded on this theme, arguing that ML bridge a gap between traditional DH praxis and “linguistically- and culturally-specific cultural studies approaches to digital materials” (2017). They went on to argue that more collaboration is needed “to optimise the potential of both disciplines” through what they call a “‘critical DHML’ approach.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Mutual disruption</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Debates about DH’s own communication practices have rightly received a fair amount attention in recent years, with various attempts to address linguistic and cultural diversity (http://go-dh.github.io/translation-toolkit/about/), but it has been much less common for linguistic diversity to be explicitly harnessed as part of DH’s research agenda. There is a substantial body of DH research involving language, but the overriding dynamic has historically been digital humanities disrupting ML-based research practices, rather than the other way around, and this naturally shapes discourse around the ML-DH relationship.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">DH2018, in many ways an exemplary conference in terms of representation, with ample discussion of cultural diversity and reappropriation of digital spaces – such as the keynote ‘Weaving the Word’, by Janet Chávez Santiago – addressed this balance to some extent, but even here the emphasis was largely on digital transformation of ML rather than vice versa, and where ML perspectives surfaced explicitly, it was generally in relation to pedagogy (e.g. ‘Global Perspectives On Decolonizing Digital Pedagogy’ panel).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">What if we were to change the direction of flow, or to look for challenges which are mutually transformative?</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">
                    <anchor xml:id="Hlk7423465"/>As a result of our research we propose some areas where DH might benefit from a greater, and more explicit, adoption of ‘ML’ sensibilities, which can be summarised as follows:
                </p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">The international classroom</hi>. Greater attention to the concept of the international and plurilingual classroom in DH pedagogy - including diversification of the DH curriculum, and the use of virtual communications to explore multilingual interactions between DH student cohorts, potentially in liaison with ML programmes.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Linguistic diversity as research topic</hi>. The growing consolidation of ‘supercentral’ languages and English as the ‘hypercentral’ language has major implications for language diversity (de Swaan 2001), a phenomenon which will increasingly become a major challenge for DH and scholarly communications as a whole (Ortega 2014). Digital humanists are already active in some great projects to protect endangered, minority or heritage languages, but there is a need for greater awareness of, and commitment to, linguistic diversity in the actual construction of DH resources and this is an area ML where can make an important contribution. 
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Linguistic/cultural interfaces</hi>. Early digital experiments like the work of Jiménez, Underberg and Zorn adopted key Andean concepts such as “complementary duality and the tripartite division of time and space” into web design (Underberg and Zorn 2013: 29). Closer attention from DH to how resources are constructed linguistically and culturally would help foster greater awareness about how resources work transculturally within the field.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Greater recognition and organisation of multilingual resources</hi>. With the exception of corpus-based resources such as CLARIN (https://www.clarin.eu/portal), it is not easy to find language-based DH research online, even on otherwise excellent resources such as the EADH project list (https://eadh.org/projects).
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Multilingual methods and tools</hi>. We know digital methods and tools are not culturally neutral, and yet much of the discussion about them still tacitly assumes that they operate globally and monolingually (in English) – we need more formal work in DH to explore how they operate differently in and across different linguistic and cultural contexts.
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Conclusions</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Languages (and their associated cultures) have been a key area of focus for the Digital Humanities from its origins as a field, and yet DH has rarely explored what this means in any real depth for its own research and pedagogical practices. In this paper, we have outlined a rationale for greater focus on ML-DH collaboration and have proposed some key elements of a possible future common research agenda.</p>
                <p rend="DH-Title" style="text-align:center; ">Topografias da pesquisa em Línguas (Estrangeiras) Modernas Digitais</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Língua (estrangeira) Moderna têm estado sob pressão em vários países já há algum tempo, com oferta reduzida em muitos países de língua inglesa, e preferências cada vez mais focadas no inglês em outros lugares. No mundo anglo-saxão, uma longa série de relatórios catalogou esses desafios em todos os níveis de ensino, frequentemente usando palavras como 'crise' e 'urgência' (Tinsley 2013) e sugerindo que o campo da Língua Moderna precisa se reconfigurar para conhecer novas paisagens culturais e midiáticas (Worton 2009).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Enquanto isso, à medida que as humanidades digitais se expandiram e entraram cada vez mais nos debates basilares sobre o futuro das humanidades, houve um foco crescente em seus termos de representação (Spence 2018) e compromisso com a diversidade (Galina 2014). Em nível geocultural, várias iniciativas têm procurado abordar as imensas desigualdades linguísticas e culturais anglófonas (por exemplo, https://programminghistorian.org/ ou http://www.globaloutlookdh.org/) que a cultura digital ampliou - e a qual as HD tem muitas vezes, embora inconscientemente, reforçado dentro de suas próprias áreas de influência - mas há relativamente pouca consideração dada a possível interação com a LM, o que parece estranho dada a experiência da LM em estudar a diversidade multilíngue, tradução e perspectivas transculturais.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Este artigo começa por traçar as interações entre LM e HD com base em pesquisas empíricas detalhadas, e argumenta que há muito a ganhar ao unir os atuais debates sobre o futuro da Língua Moderna (LM) com as apreensões sobre o déficit de diversidade linguística nas humanidades digitais.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Topografia</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Até o momento há pouca análise sistemática das interações entre a LM e as humanidades digitais (ou a cultura digital de forma mais geral), algo que a vertente Mediações Digitais do projeto 'Language Acts &amp; Worldmaking' financiado pela AHRC pretende abordar (https://languageacts.org/digital-mediations/)</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Através de uma série de pesquisas de panorama - questionários, entrevistas, revisões de literatura, revisões de recursos e estudos curriculares - mapeamos a topografia da pesquisa digital de LM e descobrimos que o engajamento das línguas estrangeiras modernas com o digital é mais amplo e profundo do que é amplamente entendido pelas HD ou mesmo pela própria LM, embora recentemente tenha começado a emergir de forma mais proeminente através de iniciativas como o painel "Digital Hispanists" na conferência da Associação de Hispanistas da Grã-Bretanha e Irlanda em 2018 (http://community.dur.ac.uk/hispanists/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/AHGBI-2018-Abstracts-Booklet.pdf) ou o fórum 2019 MLA sobre ‘Digital Humanities &amp; Modern Languages’ (https://mla.confex.com/mla/2019/forum/extra/index.cgi?EntryType=Session&amp;username=4494&amp;password=340557).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">A mediação digital na LM é particularmente forte em torno da aprendizagem / ensino de línguas, onde pesquisadores e professores têm uma compreensão elevada do potencial de interações autênticas, multimodais, centradas no aluno, transculturais e polilinguais (Guikema e Williams 2014), mas o foco da nossa pesquisa é principalmente sobre pesquisa em línguas (estrangeiras) e suas culturas relacionadas, ao invés da aprendizagem de línguas.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Nossa pesquisa primeiro buscou estabelecer a topografia das interações LM-HD através de uma pesquisa aberta (158 entrevistados), estudo de entrevista com profissionais de LM (35) em diversas funções, revisão de curso (análise de 12 módulos de LM em 9 instituições) e revisão de recursos (analisando 1.327 recursos digitais de LM em 8 portais / plataformas).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Descobrimos que os pesquisadores de LM têm um elevado senso de “oportunidades” digitais (e riscos / limitações), mas, em geral, baixo engajamento com o tipo de métodos digitais avançados representados pelas HD, afora de áreas como edição digital, linguística, literatura eletrônica e estudos de arquivo na web de comunidades linguísticas (Spence e Brandão, 2019).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Há algumas tendências interessantes em ambos os estudos de pesquisa e entrevista: enquanto a experiência transcultural e plurilinguística é valorizada, as fronteiras nacionais e disciplinares são consideradas cada vez menos relevantes para a pesquisa de LM (tornando futuras colaborações HD-LM ainda mais necessárias); considera-se que as abordagens de dados em grande escala são cada vez mais importantes para facilitar comparações interessantes de recepção cultural e influência em muitas línguas; digital está se tornando cada vez mais importante como objeto de pesquisa em si; e há apoio para a ideia de que o "digital" precisa (e será) integrado mais de perto na prática da LM, ao invés de ser algo diferente no futuro.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Para uma agenda da HDLM?</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Como isto se conecta especificamente as HD? Como podemos começar a teorizar a conexão entre as humanidades digitais e a LM, e quais oportunidades existem para uma colaboração mais profunda, bidirecional e equitativamente concebida / construída?</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Em novembro de 2015, um “writing sprint” sobre o tema “Modern Language and the digital”, mais tarde publicada como um artigo multi-autoral colaborativo sob o título “The Shape of the Discipline”, editado por Claire Taylor e Niamh Thornton (2017), abriu este debate. A conversa variou de temas como abordagens baseadas em dados para linguagens modernas ou o processo de pesquisa de LM, para usuários / interfaces em LM e etnografia digital, e enquanto alguns contribuintes argumentaram que as HD frequentemente tem uma concepção muito estreita do 'digital' (o qual nem sempre se empregou bem com o foco dos estudos culturais digitais que é mais comum na LM), o artigo estabeleceu o cenário para uma maior colaboração possível entre os campos de LM e HD. </p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Em um artigo para a Digital Humanities Quarterly, Thea Pitman e Claire Taylor desenvolveram este tema, argumentando que a LM cria uma lacuna entre a praxis tradicional de HD e “abordagens de estudos culturais linguisticamente e culturalmente específicos para materiais digitais” (2017). Elas argumentaram que são necessárias mais colaborações “para otimizar o potencial de ambas as disciplinas” através do que elas chamaram de “abordagem crítica de HDLM”.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Interrupção mútua</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Os debates sobre as práticas de comunicação das HD receberam justamente atenção nos últimos anos, com várias tentativas de abordar a diversidade linguística e cultural (http://go-dh.github.io/translation-toolkit/about/), mas tem sido muito menos comum para a diversidade linguística ser explicitamente aproveitada como parte da agenda de pesquisa das HD. Há um corpo substancial de pesquisas em HD envolvendo a linguagem, mas a dinâmica dominante tem sido historicamente que as humanidades digitais atrapalham as práticas de pesquisa baseadas em LM, e não o contrário, e isso naturalmente forma o discurso em torno da relação LM-HD.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">A DH2018, em muitos aspectos uma conferência exemplar em termos de representação, com ampla discussão sobre diversidade cultural e reapropriação de espaços digitais - como a palestra “Weaving the Word”, de Janet Chávez Santiago - abordou este equilíbrio até certo ponto, mas mesmo aqui a ênfase foi em grande parte na transformação digital da LM, e não vice-versa, e onde as perspectivas da LM surgiram explicitamente, foi geralmente em relação à pedagogia (por exemplo, painel 'Global Perspectives on Decolonizing Digital Pedagogy').</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">E se mudássemos a direção deste fluxo ou procurássemos desafios mutuamente transformadores?</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Como resultado da nossa pesquisa, propomos algumas áreas nas quais as HD podem se beneficiar de uma adoção maior e mais explícita das sensibilidades "LM", que podem ser resumidas da seguinte forma:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">A sala de aula internacional</hi>. Maior atenção ao conceito de sala de aula internacional e plurilingue na pedagogia das HD - incluindo a diversificação do currículo das HD e o uso de comunicações virtuais para explorar as interações multilíngues entre os coortes de alunos das HD, potencialmente em ligação com programas de LM.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Diversidade linguística como tema de pesquisa</hi>. A consolidação crescente das línguas "supercentrais" e do inglês como linguagem "hipercentral" tem implicações importantes para a diversidade de idiomas (de Swaan 2001), um fenômeno que se tornará cada vez mais um grande desafio para as HD e para as comunicações acadêmicas como um todo (Ortega 2014). As humanistas digitais já estão ativas em alguns projetos de porte para proteger línguas ameaçadas, minoritárias ou de herança, mas há uma necessidade de maior conscientização e comprometimento com a diversidade linguística na construção real dos recursos HD e esta é uma área que a LM pode fazer uma contribuição importante.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Interfaces linguísticas / culturais</hi>. Os primeiros experimentos digitais, como o trabalho de Jiménez, Underberg e Zorn, adotaram conceitos-chave Andinos como “dualidade complementar e a divisão “tripartite” do tempo e do espaço” no design da web (Underberg e Zorn 2013: 29). Uma atenção mais próxima das HD para a forma como os recursos são construídos linguisticamente e culturalmente ajudaria a promover uma maior conscientização sobre como os recursos funcionam transculturalmente dentro do campo.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Maior reconhecimento e organização de recursos multilíngues</hi>. Com a exceção de recursos baseados em corpus, como o CLARIN (https://www.clarin.eu/portal), não é fácil encontrar pesquisas de HD baseadas em idiomas, mesmo em recursos excelentes, como a lista de projetos EADH ( https://eadh.org/projects).
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Métodos e ferramentas multilíngues</hi>. Sabemos que os métodos e ferramentas digitais não são culturalmente neutros e, no entanto, grande parte da discussão sobre eles ainda pressupõe implicitamente que eles operem globalmente e monolingualmente (em inglês) – nós precisamos de mais trabalho formal nas HD para explorar como eles operam de forma diferente em diferentes contextos linguísticos e culturais.
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Conclusões</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">As línguas (e suas culturas associadas) têm sido uma área chave de foco para as Humanidades Digitais desde sua origem como campo de estudo, e ainda assim HD raramente explorou o que isso significa em qualquer profundidade real para suas próprias pesquisas e práticas pedagógicas. Neste artigo, delineamos uma justificativa para um maior foco na colaboração LM-HD e propusemos alguns elementos-chave para uma possível agenda de pesquisa comum futura.</p>
                <p rend="DH-Title" style="text-align:center; ">
                    <anchor xml:id="Hlk7426900"/>Topografías de la investigación digital en lenguas modernas
                </p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Las lenguas modernas (extranjeras) llevan tiempo bajo presión institucional en varios países. En países anglófonos se ha ido reduciendo la provisión de lenguas modernas sensiblemente, mientras que en varios otros países las opciones tienden a limitarse a estudiar inglés como lengua extranjera. En el mundo anglófono se ha producido una serie de informes sobre esta situación, catalogando estos retos a todos niveles de la educación, a menudo utilizando palabras como ‘crisis’ o ‘urgencia’ (Tinsley, 2013) y se ha llegado a sugerir que la lenguas modernas deben reconfigurarse para nuevos panoramas culturales y mediáticos (Worton, 2009).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Mientras tanto, las humanidades digitales se han expandido y se empiezan a entrar en debates más extendidos sobre el futuro de las humanidades, con el resultado de que se ha hecho cierto enfoque sobre sus términos de representación (Spence, 2018) y su compromiso con la diversidad (Galina, 2014). A nivel geocultural, varias iniciativas han buscado afrontar las inmensas desigualdades lingüísticas y culturales hacia lo anglófono (por ejemplo https://programminghistorian.org/ o http://www.globaloutlookdh.org/) que han sido amplificadas por la cultural digital – y que las humanidades digitales a menudo, aunque sin querer, ha agudizado bajo su propio dominio de influencia – pero se ha considerado poco la posible interacción con el campo de las lenguas modernas, lo cual resulta sorprendente, dada la experiencia de este campo en materia de diversidad plurilingüe, traducción y perspectivas culturales.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Esta presentación empieza por trazar las interacciones entre las lenguas modernas y humanidades digitales, apoyándose en investigación detallada empírica, y argumenta que se puede ganar mucho por conectar debates actuales sobre el futuro de las lenguas modernas con el déficit en términos de diversidad lingüística en las humanidades digitales.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Topografía</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Hasta ahora, ha habido poco análisis sistemático de las interacciones entre las lenguas modernas y las humanidades digitales (o incluso la cultura digital en general), algo que intentamos abordar con la investigación en la rama `Digital Mediations` del proyecto `Language Acts and Worldmaking` financiado por el AHRC (https://languageacts.org/digital-mediations/).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">A través de una serie de estudios – cuestionarios, entrevistas, revisión literaria, revisión de recursos digitales y estudios curriculares – hemos trazado la topografía de la investigación digital en lenguas modernas y hemos encontrado que el compromiso de las lenguas modernas con lo digital es más amplio y más profundo de lo que se aprecia, tanto en las humanidades digitales como en las mismas lenguas modernas, aunque últimamente ha empezado a salir al público más a través de iniciativas como el panel de `digital hispanisms` del congreso Association of Hispanists of Great Britain and Ireland en 2018 (http://community.dur.ac.uk/hispanists/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/AHGBI-2018-Abstracts-Booklet.pdf) o en el foro MLA 2019 sobre ‘Digital Humanities &amp; Modern Languages’ (https://mla.confex.com/mla/2019/forum/extra/index.cgi?EntryType=Session&amp;username=4494&amp;password=340557).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">La mediación digital de las lenguas modernas es más fuerte en el aprendizaje o la enseñanza de las lenguas, donde los investigadores y educadores tienen una comprensión elevada de la potencia para interacción auténtica, multimodal, transcultural, plurilingüe y centrada en la/el estudiante (Guikema y Williams, 2014), pero el enfoque principal de nuestra investigación ha sido sobre la investigación en lenguas y culturas modernas, más que en la enseñanza de lengua.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Nuestra investigación ha intentado establecer la topografía de las interacciones en lenguas modernas y humanidades digitales a través de una encuesta abierta (158 respuestas), entrevistas con personas en varios papeles asociados con las lenguas modernas (35), una revisión de programas educativos (analizando 12 módulos en nueve instituciones) y revisión de recursos (analizando 1, 327 recursos digitales a través de ocho portales/plataformas).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Hemos encontrado que los investigadores tienen un sentido elevado de las oportunidades digitales (y de sus riesgos/limitaciones), pero en general poco compromiso con el tipo de métodos digitales avanzados más familiares en las humanidades digitales, más allá de ciertos campos como la edición digital, la lingüística, la literatura electrónica y los estudios archivo web de comunidades lingüísticas (Spence y Brandao, 2019).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Hemos observado tendencias interesantes, tanto en la encuesta como en las entrevistas: mientras que se valora la habilidad transcultural y plurilingüe, las fronteras nacionales y disciplinares cobran menos importancia en la investigación en lenguas modernas (lo cual hace aún más necesaria la colaboración entre humanidades digitales y lenguas modernas); se aprecian cada vez más los enfoques con datos a gran escala para comparar la recepción cultural y la influencia a través de varias lenguas; lo digital empieza a cobrar mayor importancia como objecto de investigación proprio; y se apoya cada vez más la idea de que lo digital tiene que ser estrechamente integrado en la práctica de las lenguas modernas (y lo será), en vez de configurar algo nuevo en el futuro.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Hacia una agenda digital en lenguas modernas</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">¿Como podemos conectar todo esto con las humanidades digitales concretamente? ¿Cómo podemos empezar a teorizar sobre la conexión entre las humanidades digitales y las lenguas modernas, y qué oportunidades hay para una colaboración bidireccional y concebida/construida con igualdad en la relación entre ambos campos?</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">En noviembre de 2015 se abrió un debate sobre esto con un `writing sprint` acerca del tema de `Las lenguas modernas y lo digital` que después dio el resultado de un artículo colaborativo multi-autor de acceso abierto con el título `La forma de la disciplina`, editada por Claire Taylor y Niamh Thornton (2017). El debate tocó temas como el enfoque sobre datos digitales o el proceso de investigación en las lenguas modernas, los usuarios y las interfaces y la etnografía. Mientras que algunos de los autores sostenían que las humanidades digitales a menudo demuestran una concepción demasiado estrecha de lo digital (que no siempre comprende bien todas las posibilidades de un acercamiento de estudios culturales más común en las lenguas modernas), el artículo proponía una colaboración mayor entre ambos campos.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">En un artículo para Digital Humanities Quarterly, Thea Pitman y Claire Taylor (2017) siguen este hilo, aseverando que las lenguas modernas forman un puente entre la praxis tradicional de las lenguas modernas y un enfoque más cercano a los estudios culturales hacia los materiales digitales.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>La disrupción mutua</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Ha habido debates importantes sobre las prácticas comunicativas de las humanidades digitales en los últimos años, que en varias ocasiones han intentado abordar cuestiones de diversidad lingüística y cultural (http://go-dh.github.io/translation-toolkit/about/), pero es menos común ver la diversidad lingüística formar parte explícita de la agenda de investigación de las humanidades digitales. Existe un cuerpo significativo de investigación en humanidades digitales sobre las lenguas, pero el discurso histórico dominante es de una dinámica donde las humanidades digitales transforman las lenguas modernas, y no vice versa.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">DH2018, que fue ejemplario como congreso en muchos aspectos en términos de la representación, y donde se facilitó debate amplio sobre la diversidad cultural y la reapropiación de espacios digitales – como, por ejemplo, la presentación plenaria de Janet Chávez Santiago `Weaving the Word` - abordó este desequilibrio hasta cierto punto. No obstante, incluso en este caso, el énfasis fue más sobre la transformación digital de las lenguas modernas que al contrario, y las perspectivas explícitamente hacia las lenguas modernas generalmente se centraron en la pedagogía (como, por ejemplo, el panel ‘Global Perspectives On Decolonizing Digital Pedagogy’).</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">¿Y si cambiáramos el flujo de esta dinámica, para buscar retos que llevasen los dos campos a una transformación mutua?</p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Como resultado de nuestra investigación, queremos proponer áreas donde las humanidades digitales podrían beneficiarse de una adopción mayor y más explícita de sensibilidades hacia las lenguas modernas, resumidas de tal manera:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">El aula internacional</hi>. Se requiere una atención mayor hacia el aula internacional y plurilingüe en la pedagogía de humanidades digitales, que incluye la diversificación en el curriculo, el uso de comunicaciones virtuales en las interacciones plurilingües entre varios grupos de estudiantes, potencialmente a través de programas formales de enseñanza en HD.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">La diversidad linguística como tema de investigación. </hi>La consolidación creciente de las lenguas `supercentrales` y el inglés como lengua `hipercentral` tiene implicaciones importantes para la diversidad linguística (de Swaan, 2001), un fenómeno que será un reto importante para las humanidades digitales y la comunicación académica en general (Ortega, 2014). Los humanistas digitales ya son activos en proyectos para proteger las lenguas minoritarias, comunitarias o apeligradas, pero se necesita una mayor atención sobre, y compromiso con, la diversidad lingüística en la construcción de recursos HD, y esto es un área donde las lenguas modernas pueden aportar algo importante.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Las interfaces lingüísticas y culturales</hi>. Los experimentos tempranos como el trabajo de Jiménez, Underberg y Zorn adoptaron conceptos andinos de “la dualidad complementaria y la división tripartita entre el tiempo y el espacio” en el diseño web (Underberg y Zorn, 2013:29). Una atención mayor a cómo los recursos en HD están construidos ayudaría a fomentar mayor sensibilidad sobre cómo los recursos funcionan a nivel transcultural en el campo.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Mayor reconocimiento y organización de los recursos plurilingües</hi>. Con la excepción de recursos de corpus como CLARIN (https://www.clarin.eu/portal), no es fácil encontrar recursos filtrados por lengua, incluso en recursos excelentes como la lista de proyectos de EADH (https://eadh.org/projects).
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Métodos y herramientas plurilingües</hi>. Sabemos que los métodos y las herramientas no son culturalmente neutros, y sin embargo gran parte del discurso sobre ellos implica una suposición tácita de que estos métodos operan de manera global y monolingüe (en inglés). Se necesita más trabajo en HD para explorar cómo funcionan de manera diferente en distintos contextos lingüísticos y culturales.
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Conclusiones</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">Las lenguas (y las culturas de las que forman parte) han sido un área de enfoque clave para las humanidades digitales desde sus orígenes como campo, y sin embargo las humanidades digitales rara vez ha investigado lo que esta diversidad implica para sus prácticas investigación y pedagogía. En esta presentación, hemos trazado unas líneas generales de una propuesta para fortalecer la colaboración entre lenguas modernas y humanidades digitales y algunos elementos de una agenda común de investigación.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">Galina, I. (2014). ‘Geographical and linguistic diversity in the Digital Humanities’, 
                        <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi>, Volume 29, Issue 3, 1.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">Guikema, J. and Williams, L. (2014). ‘Digital Literacies in Foreign and Second Language Education’, 
                        <hi rend="italic">CALICO Monograph Series</hi> Volume 12.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">Ortega, E. (2014.) ‘Multilingualism’ in DH. 
                        <hi rend="italic">MLA Position Papers</hi> 2015. (Posted 2014).
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">Pitman, T. and Taylor, C. (2017). Where’s the ML in DH? And Where’s the DH in ML? The Relationship between Modern Languages and Digital Humanities, and an Argument for a Critical DHML. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi>, 11(1). Available at: http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/1/000287/000287.html [Accessed 23 April 2019].
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">Spence, P. (2018). ‘Las humanidades digitales y los retos de la representación’. In Galina I., Peña Pimentel, M., Priani, E. (eds.): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Humanidades Digitales 3: Edición, Literatura y Arte</hi>, Bonilla Artigas Editores, Mexico City, pp. 15-46.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">Spence, P. and Brandao, R. (2019). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Survey of Attitudes towards Digital Culture &amp; Technology in the Modern Languages</hi>. Language Acts &amp; Worldmaking, United Kingdom. http://doi.org/doi:10.18742/pub01-001 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">De Swaan, A. (2001). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Words of the World</hi>. Polity: Cambridge.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">Taylor, C. and Thornton N., eds. (2017). “Modern Languages and the Digital: The Shape of the Discipline”, 
                        <hi rend="italic">Modern Languages Open</hi>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">Tinsley, T. (2013). 
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Languages: The State of the Nation. Demand and supply of language skills in the UK. </hi>British Academy.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">Underberg, N. and Zorn, E. (2013). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Ethnography: Anthropology, Narrative, and New Media</hi>. Texas: University of Texas Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">Worton, M. (2009). 
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Review of Modern Language Provision in Higher Education in England. </hi>Higher Education Funding Council for England (HEFCE).
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
