<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>LiLa: Linking Latin. Building a Knowledge Base of Linguistic Resources for Latin</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Passarotti</surname>
                        <forename>Marco</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>marco.passarotti@unicatt.it</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Cecchini</surname>
                        <forename>Flavio M.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>flavio.cecchini@unicatt.it</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Franzini</surname>
                        <forename>Greta</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>greta.franzini@unicatt.it</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Litta</surname>
                        <forename>Eleonora</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>eleonoramaria.litta@unicatt.it</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Mambrini</surname>
                        <forename>Francesco</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>f.mambrini@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Ruffolo</surname>
                        <forename>Paolo</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>paolo.ruffolo@posteo.net</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Sprugnoli</surname>
                        <forename>Rachele</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>rachele.sprugnoli@unicatt.it</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014-12-19T13:50:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Name, Institution</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Street</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>City</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Country</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Name</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Poster</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>latin</term>
                    <term>linguistic resource</term>
                    <term>corpus</term>
                    <term>dictionary</term>
                    <term>thesaurus</term>
                    <term>NLP tools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>classical studies</term>
                    <term>lexicography</term>
                    <term>metadata</term>
                    <term>natural language processing</term>
                    <term>linguistics</term>
                    <term>semantic web and linked data</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">The spread of information technology has led to a substantial growth in the quantity, diversity and complexity of linguistic data available on the web. Today, although a large variety of linguistic resources (such as corpora, lexica and ontologies) exist for a number of languages, these are often not interoperable. Linking linguistic resources to one another would maximise their contribution to, and use in, linguistic analysis at multiple levels, be those lexical, morphological, syntactic, semantic or pragmatic. In an ideal virtuous cycle, linguistic resources benefit from the Natural Language Processing (NLP) tools used to build them, and NLP tools benefit from the linguistic resources that provide the empirical evidence upon which they are built. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>The project</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">The objective of the 
                    <hi rend="italic">LiLa: Linking Latin</hi> project (2018-2023) is to connect and, ultimately, exploit the wealth of linguistic resources and NLP tools for Latin developed thus far, in order to bridge the gap between raw language data, NLP and knowledge description.
                </p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">LiLa, which has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) European Union’s Horizon 2020 Research and Innovation programme, is building a Linked Data Knowledge Base of linguistic resources and NLP tools for Latin. The Knowledge Base consists of different kinds of objects connected through edges labelled with a restricted set of values taken from a vocabulary of knowledge description. LiLa collects and connects both existing and newly-generated (meta)data. The former are mostly linguistic resources (corpora, lexica, ontologies, dictionaries, thesauri) and NLP tools (tokenisers, lemmatisers, PoS-taggers, morphological analysers and dependency parsers) for Latin. These are currently available from different providers under different licences. As for the latter, LiLa assesses a set of selected linguistic resources by expanding their lexical and/or textual coverage. In particular, it (a) enhances the Latin texts made available by existing digital libraries and resources with PoS-tagging and lemmatisation, (b) harmonises the annotation of the three Universal Dependencies treebanks for Latin
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <ref target="http://universaldependencies.org/">http://universaldependencies.org/</ref>
                            <hi rend="Footnote_Characters" xml:space="preserve"> </hi>
                        </p>
                    </note>, (c) improves the lexical coverage of the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Latin WordNet</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <ref target="http://www.cyllenius.net/labium/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=21&amp;Itemid=49">
                                <hi rend="Footnote_Characters">http://www.cyllenius.net/labium/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=21&amp;Itemid=49</hi>
                            </ref>
                        </p>
                    </note> and the valency lexicon 
                    <hi rend="italic">Latin-Vallex</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <ref target="https://itreebank.marginalia.it/view/lvl.php">
                                <hi rend="Footnote_Characters">https://itreebank.marginalia.it/view/lvl.php</hi>
                            </ref>
                            <hi rend="Footnote_Characters" xml:space="preserve">  </hi>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                    <hi rend="italic">,</hi> and (d) expands the textual coverage of the 
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Index Thomisticus </hi>Treebank
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <ref target="https://itreebank.marginalia.it/view/ittb.php">
                                <hi rend="Footnote_Characters">https://itreebank.marginalia.it/view/ittb.php</hi>
                            </ref>
                        </p>
                    </note>. Furthermore, LiLa builds a set of newly-trained models for PoS-tagging and lemmatisation, and works on developing and testing the best performing NLP pipeline for such a task.
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="12.555361111111111cm" height="10.96786111111111cm" url="Pictures/5f460efbd5e0b0058a532023cb91eebe.png" rend="inline"/>
                    <head>Conceptual model of LiLa.</head>
                </figure>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">As can be observed from the simplified conceptual model illustrated in Figure 1, the LiLa Knowledge Base is highly lexically-based. 
                    <hi rend="bold">Lemmas</hi> are the key node type in the Knowledge Base. Lemmas occur in 
                    <hi rend="bold">Lexical Resources</hi> (as lexical entries), but may have one or more (inflected) 
                    <hi rend="bold">Forms</hi>. For instance, the lemma 
                    <hi rend="italic">puella</hi>, ‘girl’ has forms like 
                    <hi rend="italic">puellam</hi>, 
                    <hi rend="italic">puellis</hi> and 
                    <hi rend="italic">puellas</hi>. Forms, too, can occur in lexical resources; for instance, in a lexicon containing all the word forms of a language (e.g., 
                    <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus Formarum Totius Latinitatis</hi>, Tombeur, 1998). Both Lemmas and Forms can have one or more graphical variants (
                    <hi rend="italic">condicio</hi> vs. 
                    <hi rend="italic">conditio</hi>). The occurrences of Forms in real texts are 
                    <hi rend="bold">Tokens</hi>, which are provided by 
                    <hi rend="bold">Textual Resources</hi>. Texts in Textual Resources can be different editions/versions of the same Work (e.g., the various editions of the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Orator</hi> by Cicero, possibly provided by different Textual Resources). Finally, 
                    <hi rend="bold">NLP tools</hi> process either 
                    <hi rend="bold">Forms</hi> (e.g., a morphological analyser) or Tokens (e.g., a PoS-tagger).
                </p>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">LiLa develops across the following five Work Packages (WPs):</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>WP1: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Selecting and Improving Linguistic Resources for Latin</hi>. This WP assesses resources eligible to enter the Knowledge Base, i.e., linguistic data-sets.
                    </item>
                    <item>WP2: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Building the Knowledge Base</hi>. This WP represents the core of the project, as it aims to model the linguistic resources for Latin collected and selected in WP1 to build the Knowledge Base. Furthermore, this WP aims to make NLP tools for Latin interoperable and to connect them with linguistic resources in order to exploit the empirical evidence these provide for different NLP purposes.
                    </item>
                    <item>WP3: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Querying the Knowledge Base</hi>. This WP intends to build a user-friendly interface to allow users to write and run SPARQL queries on interconnected linguistic resources.
                    </item>
                    <item>WP4: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Testing and Evaluating the Knowledge Base</hi>. This WP tests the Knowledge Base by conducting research on its (meta)data.
                    </item>
                    <item>WP5: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Disseminating the Results</hi>. This WP is devoted to the dissemination of the results of the project through publications, conference presentations, tutorials and workshops.
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">This poster contribution presents the detailed structure of LiLa, describes how it meets the so-called 
                    <hi rend="italic">FAIR Guiding Principles</hi> for scientific data management and stewardship, which state that scholarly data must be 
                    <hi rend="italic">Findable</hi>, 
                    <hi rend="italic">Accessible</hi>, 
                    <hi rend="italic">Interoperable</hi> and 
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Reusable </hi>(Wilkinson, 2016), and elaborates on the progress made in WP1.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p style="text-align:left; ">The LiLa project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) European Union’s Horizon 2020 Research and Innovation programme under grant agreement No. 769994.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Tombeur, P.</hi> (1998). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus formarum totius Latinitatis: a Plauto usque ad saeculum XXum</hi>. Brepols, Turnhout, Belgium.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align:left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Wilkinson, M. D. et al.</hi> (2016). The FAIR Guiding Principles for scientific data management and stewardship. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Scientific Data</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="bold">3</hi>. http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18 
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
