<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:28+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">&quot;A Trace of this Journey&quot;: Citations of Digitised Newspapers in UK History PhD Theses</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Paul</forename><forename type="middle">Matthew</forename><surname>Gooding</surname></persName>
							<email>p.gooding@uea.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of East Anglia</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">&quot;A Trace of this Journey&quot;: Citations of Digitised Newspapers in UK History PhD Theses</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/tcbh/hwq007</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research context</head><p>In the last fifteen years several studies have proposed models for evaluating the impact of digital resources ( <ref type="bibr">Warwick et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Meyer et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tanner, 2012)</ref>. Citation analysis is commonly used in impact evaluation, and is a well-established bibliometric technique for impact analysis <ref type="bibr">(MacRoberts and MacRoberts, 1989)</ref>. As part of the wider field of bibliometrics, citation analysis has been used to judge the impact of academic publications and digital resources <ref type="bibr">(Meyer et al., 2009)</ref>. Citations are proxy measures of how frequently a document or resource is used, founded on the assumption that there is a strong positive correlation between the number of citations that a resource or article attracts, and the quality of that resource <ref type="bibr">(Smith, 1980)</ref>. The reality, though, is that citation practices are not always followed or understood by academics. <ref type="bibr">Smith (1980)</ref> noted several reasons a scholar may choose not to cite a document: inability to obtain the document; inability to read a foreign language; lack of relevance to their work; or lack of awareness of existing work. There are further reasons for digital resources; not least a lack of awareness of how to cite them (Sukovic, 2009), and disciplinary unwillingness to acknowledge their usage <ref type="bibr">(Meyer, 2009)</ref>. As a result, the traditional method of mining only citations provide an unreliable picture of citation levels of digital resources.</p><p>Furthermore, there is a need to account for the varied local and national context within which researchers operate. In Canada, for instance, there is a feeling among scholars that the "limited and fragmented" <ref type="bibr">(Kheraj, 2014)</ref> newspaper digitisation programme lags behind nations such as the USA, Australia and United Kingdom. The prominence of The Toronto Star and The Globe and Mail mirrors the early years of newspaper digitisation in the United Kingdom, where the ubiquity of the Times Digital Archive encouraged some to overstate its representativeness <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Bingham, 2010)</ref>. Contemporary digitised newspaper resources in the UK by contrast, tend to aggregate dozens of newspaper titles into a single resource. This paper therefore explores the likelihood that this aggregation process may have caused different citation patterns among UK researchers, who are the largest group to access these resources <ref type="bibr">(Gooding, 2014)</ref>, providing a comparison with the differing Canadian context presented by Milligan.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methodology</head><p>To achieve this, I will focus on newspaper titles from two British Library resources: British Library Nineteenth Century Newspapers (BNCN) and The British Newspaper Archive (BNA). I intend to identify mentions of newspapers by title within the full text of UK history theses. The dataset comes from EThOS, a national service which makes UK doctoral theses available online for searching and reading. EThOS contains approximately 440,000 records relating to theses awarded by over 120 institutions. It provides a comprehensive, systematically collected dataset for comparison of citation trends over time. Around 160,000 records provide access to searchable full text, and I have worked with British Library Labs to identify a subset of history theses published from 1999 to 2015; in total, over 6,000 theses were identified using Dewey Decimal Classifiers, covering eight years before and after the launch of BNCN in 2007. These theses will be searched using Natural Language Processing techniques to identify the incidence of specific newspaper titles that are included in BNCN and BNA, allowing me to identify how many theses use a given source, and how frequently each source was used.</p><p>This project also acts as a test case for text mining of British Library collections. In 2014, the UK government introduced an exception to copyright law to ensure that researchers undertaking text and data-mining for non-commercial purposes would no longer infringe copyright <ref type="bibr">(Intellectual Property Office, 2014</ref>), without requiring that publishers took steps to guarantee the availability of suitable datasets for text mining. In reality, this means that there are many potentially valuable data sources that could be legally studied, but no infrastructure to do so. Starting with the British Library's PhD thesis holdings, I intend to work with British Library Labs to explore the possibility of opening up further datasets for text mining.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>This paper will explore the ways in which historical newspaper digitisation have impacted upon historiography among early career researchers in the United Kingdom, by tracking citations of digitised newspaper titles over time in the full text of over 6,000 PhD theses. This is the first study to apply text mining of digital resource citations to the UK context. It also provides an important case study of text and data mining in legal deposit library collections, in the light of current limitations to the UK copyright exception. In doing so, this project will not only illuminate the ways in which digital resources can affect local research practices, but will demonstrate the utility of text mining in addressing the methodological limitations of citation analysis for digital resources. We must adopt new computational methods to ensure that the traces of this use are not wiped away by citation practices which continue to de-emphasise the role of digital resources in contemporary research.</p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Warwick, C., Terras, M., Pappa, N. and Galina, I. (2006). The LAIRAH project: log analysis of digital resources in the arts and humanities -Final report to the Arts and Humanities Research Council. School of Library, Archive</head><p>and Information Studies, University College London. http://www.ucl.ac.uk/infostudies/claire-warwick/publications/LAIRAHreport.pdf.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Digitization of Newspaper Archives: Opportunities and Challenges for Historians</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bingham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1093/tcbh/hwq007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Twentieth Century British History</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="231" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Opium: The Diary of His Cure</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cocteau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<publisher>Peter Owen Publishers</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
