<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:50+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A Survey of Digital Humanities Programs</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chris</forename><forename type="middle">Alen</forename><surname>Sula</surname></persName>
							<email>csula@pratt.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">The Amistad Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>United States of America, United States of America</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hackney</surname></persName>
							<email>s.hackney@pitt.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">The Amistad Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>United States of America, United States of America</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Phillip</forename><surname>Cunningham</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">The Amistad Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pittsburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>United States of America, United States of America</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A Survey of Digital Humanities Programs</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Pratt Institute, United States of America</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Existing studies of anglophone digital humanities (DH) curricula have examined course syllabi (Terras 2006; Spiro 2011) and the development of programs at specific institutions <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Rockwell 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Siemens 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Sinclair 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Unsworth 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Unsworth and Butler 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Drucker, Unsworth, and Laue 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Sinclair &amp; Gouglas 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">McCarty 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Smith 2014</ref>). This study adds to the literature on teaching and learning by presenting a survey of formal degree and certificate programs in anglophone DH.</p><p>While these programs represent only part of the entire DH curricula, they are important in several respects: First, they reflect intentional groupings of courses, concepts, skills, methods, and techniques, purporting to represent the field in its broadest strokes. Second, these programs include explicit learning outcomes, and their requirements form one picture of what all DHers are expected to know upon graduation. Third, formal programs organize teaching, research, and professional development in the field; they are channels through which material and symbolic capital flow and thereby shape the field itself. Finally, these programs, their requirements, and coursework are one way-perhaps the primary wayin which prospective students encounter the field and make choices about whether to enroll in a DH program and, if so, which one.</p><p>In addition to helping define the field, a study of DH programs also has the capacity to comment on pedagogical discussions in the literature. Hockey, for example, has long wondered whether programming should be taught in the field (1986) and asks, "How far can the need for analytical and critical thinking in the humanities be reconciled with the practical orientation of much work in humanities computing?" <ref type="bibr">(2001)</ref>. Also skeptical of mere technological skills, <ref type="bibr">Mahony and Pierazzo (2002)</ref> argue for teaching methodologies or "ways of thinking" in DH, and Clement examines multiliteracies in DH (e.g., critical thinking, commitment, community, and play), which help to push the field beyond "training" to a more humanistic pursuit <ref type="bibr">(2012,</ref><ref type="bibr">372)</ref>. Others have called on DH to engage more fully in critical reflection, especially in relation to technology and the role of the humanities in higher education <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Brier 2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">, Liu 2012</ref><ref type="bibr">, Walzer 2012</ref>).</p><p>These and other concerns point to longstanding questions about the proper balance of skills and reflection in DH. While a study of DH programs cannot address the value of critical reflection, it can report on its presence (or absence). These findings, together with our more general observations about DH activities, give pause to consider what is represented in, emphasized by, and omitted from the field at its most explicit levels of educational training.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methodology</head><p>We compiled a list of 37 DH programs active in 2015, drawn from public listings (UCLA Center for Digital Humanities 2015; Clement 2015), background literature, and web searches (e.g., "digital humanities masters"). In addition to degrees and certificates, we included minors and concentrations in which humanities content was the central focus, and omitted digital arts and media programs in which this was not the case. Because our sources and searches are all English-language, it limits what we can say about global DH.</p><p>We recorded the URL and basic information (e.g., title, level, location) about each program and looked up descriptions of any required courses in the institution's course catalog. To analyze topics addressed in these programs, we applied the Taxonomy of Digital Research Activities in the Humanities (TaDiRAH 2014), which attempts to capture the "scholarly primitives" of the field ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Perkins et al. 2014</ref>). TaDiRAH contains forty activities terms organized into eight parent terms ('Capture', 'Creation', 'Enrichment', 'Analysis', 'Interpretation', 'Storage', 'Dissemination', and 'Meta-Activities'). TaDiRAH was chosen for its basis in the literature on "scholarly primitives" (Unsworth 2000), as well as three earlier sources (an arts-humanities.net taxonomy, DIRT categories and tags, and a Zotero bibliography) and community feedback and revision.</p><p>We applied terms to program/course descriptions independently and then tested intercoder agreement, which was extremely low. We attribute this to the many terms in TaDiRAH, complexity of program/course description language, questions of scope (i.e., using a broader or narrower term), and general vagueness. We did find discussing our codings helpful and, in doing so, were able to agree. Accordingly, each of us read and coded every program/course description and discussed them until we reached consensus. Often, this involved pointing to specific language in the descriptions and referencing TaDiRAH definitions or notes from previous meetings when interpretations were discussed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Findings and discussion</head><p>The number of DH programs has risen sharply over time, beginning in 1991 and growing steadily by several programs each year since 2008 (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Geography</head><p>Most of the programs studied here were located in the US (22 programs, 60%), followed by Canada (6 programs, 16%), the UK (5 programs, 14%), Ireland (3 programs, 8%), and Australia (1 program, 3%). We note that these programs are all located in Anglophone countries and that TaDiRAH, too, originates from this context, which necessarily limits what we can say about DH programs from a global perspective.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Structure</head><p>Less than half of these DH programs grant degrees: some at the level of bachelor's (8%), most at the level of master's (22%), and some at the doctoral level (8%) <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 2</ref>). The majority of these programs are certificates, minors, or specializations-certificates being more common at the graduate level and nearly one-third of all programs studied here. We also examined special requirements of these programs, finding that half require some form of independent research (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3)</ref>, and half require a final deliverable, referred to variously as a capstone, dissertation, portfolio, or thesis (see <ref type="figure">Figure 4)</ref>. About one-quarter of these programs require fieldwork, often an internship (see <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Location &amp; disciplinarity</head><p>Most of these programs are housed in colleges/schools of arts and humanities, but about one-third are outside of traditional schools/departments, in centers, initiatives, and, in one case, jointly with the library (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 6</ref>). Most DH concentrations and specializations are located within English departments, commensurate with Kirschenbaum's claim that DH's "professional apparatus…is probably more rooted in English than any other departmental home" <ref type="bibr">(2010,</ref><ref type="bibr">55)</ref>. in this study Elective courses for these programs span myriad departments and disciplines, from humanities departments (art history, classics, history, philosophy, religion, and various languages) to along with computer science, education, information and library science, design, media, and technology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DH activities</head><p>We analyzed our TaDiRAH codings in two ways: overall term frequency (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 7</ref>) and weighted frequency across programs (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 8</ref>). To compute weighted frequencies, each of the eight parent terms were given a weight of 1, which was divided equally among the subterms in each area. These subterm weights were summed to show how much of an area is represented, regardless of its size.</p><p>Analysis and meta-activities (e.g., 'Community building', 'Project management', 'Teaching/Learning') make up the largest share of activities, along with creation (e.g., 'Designing', 'Programming', 'Writing'). It is worth noting that 'Writing' is one of the most frequent terms (11 programs), but this activity certainly occurs elsewhere and is probably undercounted because it was not explicitly mentioned in program descriptions. The same may be true for other activities.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>. Digital humanities programs in this study and their required courses (by area)</head><p>Enrichment and storage terms (e.g., 'Archiving', 'Organizing', 'Preservation') were generally sparse (only 1.9% of all codings), but we suspect these activities do occur in DH programs and courses-in fact, they are assumed in broader activities such as thematic research collections, content management systems, and even dissemination. Generally, there seems to be less emphasis on content <ref type="bibr">('Capture', 'Enrichment', and 'Storage' terms)</ref> and more focus on platforms and tools ('Analysis' and 'Meta-Activities' terms) in the programs studied here-or at least, those may be more marketable to prospective students and institutions, two important audiences of program webpages.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theory and critical reflection</head><p>To analyze theory and critical reflection, we focused our analysis on two terms: 'Theorizing' and 'Meta: GiveOverview', which we used to code theoretical or historical introductions to DH itself. We found that all programs studied here included some mention of theory or historical/systematic overview (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 9</ref>). Our codings, of course, do not reveal anything further about the character of this reflection, whether it is the type of critical reflection called for in the literature, or how it interfaces with skills and techniques in these programs. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Further directions</head><p>We plan to publish our data and visualizations publicly for researchers, students, and those developing curriculum: http://bit.ly/DHprograms. We believe it provides a baseline of field growth, areas, structure, and learning experiences, which can be used to measure changes in future, in addition to providing a data-driven perspective on the field today.</p><p>In that respect, we hope this study gives the community pause to consider how DH is described, represented, and taught. If there are common expectations not reflected here, perhaps we could be more explicit about those, at least in building our taxonomies and describing our formal programs and required courses. Conversely, if there are activities that seem overrepresented here, we might consider why those activities are prized in the field (and which are not) and whether this is the picture of DH we wish to present publicly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bibliography</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Growth of digital humanities programs in this study</figDesc><graphic url="image-1.png" coords="2,54.30,342.55,277.69,150.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Digital humanities programs in this study (by degree and level)</figDesc><graphic url="image-2.png" coords="2,316.86,78.00,241.44,291.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Independent research requirements of digital humanities programs in this study</figDesc><graphic url="image-4.png" coords="2,316.86,596.23,241.20,79.19" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Institutional location of digital humanities programs in this study</figDesc><graphic url="image-6.png" coords="3,54.30,336.92,241.20,84.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. TaDiRAH term coding frequency (grouped)</figDesc><graphic url="image-7.png" coords="3,316.86,146.22,241.44,210.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8. Digital humanities programs in this study and their required courses (by area)</figDesc><graphic url="image-9.png" coords="4,316.86,59.24,241.44,478.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. Theory in digital humanities programs in this study</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Where&apos;s the Pedagogy? The Role of Teaching and Learning in the Digital Humanities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>
		<editor>Matthew K. Gold</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Minneapolis</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Univ Of Minnesota Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="390" to="401" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiliteracies in the Undergraduate Digital Humanities Curriculum</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Clement</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.openbookpublishers.com/prod-uct/161/digital-humanities-pedagogy--practices--prin-ciples-and-politics" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Digital Humanities Pedagogy: Practices, Principles and Politics</title>
		<editor>Brett D. Hirsch</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Open Book Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="88" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digital Humanities Inflected Undergraduate Programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Clement</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://tanyaclement.org/2009/11/04/digital-humanities-inflected-undergraduate-programs-2/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tanyaclement.org</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-01-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Final Report for Digital Humanities Curriculum Seminar</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Drucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Unsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Laue</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/hcs/dhcs/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Media Studies Program, College of Arts and Science: University of Virginia</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hockey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Workshop on Teaching Computers and Humanities Courses</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="228" to="257" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a Curriculum for Humanities Computing: Theoretical Goals and Practical Outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hockey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Humanities Computing Curriculum / The Computing Curriculum in the Arts and Humanities Conference</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Nanaimo, British Columbia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Malaspina University College</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What Is Digital Humanities and What&apos;s It Doing in English Departments?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kirschenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ADE Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">150</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Where Is Cultural Criticism in the Digital Humanities?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/de-bates/text/20" />
		<editor>Matthew K. Gold</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<publisher>Univ Of Minnesota Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="490" to="509" />
			<pubPlace>Minneapolis, Minn</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>In Debates in the Digital Humanities</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Teaching Skills or Teaching Methodology</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mahony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pierazzo</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.openbookpublishers.com/prod-uct/161/digital-humanities-pedagogy--practices--prin-ciples-and-politics" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Digital Humanities Pedagogy: Practices, Principles and Politics</title>
		<editor>Brett D. Hirsch</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Open Book Publishers</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="240" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The PhD in Digital Humanities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Mccarty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.openbookpublishers.com/prod-uct/161/digital-humanities-pedagogy--practices--prin-ciples-and-politics" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Digital Humanities Pedagogy: Practices, Principles and Politics</title>
		<editor>Brett D. Hirsch. Open Book Publish</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Project Report: Building Bridges to the Future of a Distributed Network: From DiRT Categories to TaDiRAH, a Methods Taxonomy for Digital Humanities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Perkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Dombrowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Borek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Schöch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Conference on Dublin Core and Metadata Applications</title>
		<meeting>the International Conference on Dublin Core and Metadata Applications<address><addrLine>Austin, Texas</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="83" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Is Humanities Computing and Academic Discipline?&quot; presented at An Interdisciplinary Seminar Series, Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rockwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-11-12" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Virginia</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Siemens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://web.ar-chive.org/web/20051220181036/http://web.mala.bc.ca/siemensr/HCCurriculum/abstracts.htm#Hockey" />
		<title level="m">The Humanities Computing Curriculum / The Computing Curriculum in the Arts and Humanities: Presenters and Presentation Abstracts</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>November 9-10</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sinclair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://dhhumanist.org/Ar-chives/Virginia/v15/0351.html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Report from the Humanities Computing Curriculum Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-11-16" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theory into Practice A Case Study of the Humanities Computing Master of Arts Programme at the University of Alberta</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sinclair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Gouglas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1177/1474022202001002004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arts and Humanities in Higher Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Advocating for a Digital Humanities Curriculum: Design and Implementation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://dharchive.org/paper/DH2014/Paper-665.xml" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Presented at Digital Humanities</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowing and Doing: Understanding the Digital Humanities Curriculum</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Spiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Presented at Digital Humanities</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Stanford University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TaDiRAH - Taxonomy of Digital Research Activities in the Humanities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Tadirah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://github.com/dhtaxonomy/TaDiRAH" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">GitHub</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-05-13" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Disciplined: Using Educational Studies to Analyse &apos;Humanities Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Terras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">doi:10.1093/llc/fql022</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="275" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Literary and Linguistic Computing</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digital Humanities Programs and Organizations</title>
		<ptr target="https://web.ar-chive.org/web/20150108203540/http://www.cdh.ucla.edu/resources/us-dh-academic-programs.html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">UCLA Center for Digital Humanities</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-01-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scholarly Primitives: What Methods Do Humanities Researchers Have in Common, and How Might Our Tools Reflect This</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Unsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://peo-ple.brandeis.edu/~unsworth/Kings.5-00/primi-tives.html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Presented at Symposium on Humanities Computing: Formal Methods, Experimental Practice</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>King&apos;s College London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Presented at 2001 Congress of the Social Sciences and Humanities. UniversitéLavalsitéLaval</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Unsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www3.isrl.illi-nois.edu/~unsworth/laval.html" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<pubPlace>QuébecQuébec, Canada</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>A Masters Degree in Digital Humanities at the University of Virginia</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Masters Degree in Digital Humanities at the University of Virginia</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Unsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Presnted at ACH-ALLC 2001</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York University</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-06-13" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digital Humanities and the &apos;Ugly Stepchildren&apos; of American Higher Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Waltzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>
		<editor>Matthew K. Gold</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Minneapolis</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Univ Of Minnesota Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="384" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
