<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:27+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Real and Imagined Geography at City-Scale: Sentiment Analysis of Chicago&apos;s &quot;One Book&quot; Program</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ana</forename><surname>Lucic</surname></persName>
							<email>alucic@depaul.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">DePaul University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>United States of America</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Shanahan</surname></persName>
							<email>jshanah1@depaul.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">DePaul University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>United States of America</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Real and Imagined Geography at City-Scale: Sentiment Analysis of Chicago&apos;s &quot;One Book&quot; Program</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1) The Book Thief (2007) by Markus Zusak 2) The Amazing Adventures of Kavalier and Clay (2000) by Michael Chabon 3) Gold Boy, Emerald Girl (2010) by Yiyun Li</head><p>We are keen to answer whether a Chicago setting and, more particularly, particular measures of linguistic sentiment about Chicago people and places, have measurable influence on the popularity of books across Chicago. Specifically, we are interested in examining the question of whether "Chicago" books, fictional and nonfictional, checked out in greater numbers when they feature characters, events, and places situated close to the readers' own neighborhood library branch? (We use CPL library branch as a proxy for patron home address, which we cannot know from the library system's anonymized checkout data.)</p><p>The results of this analysis have the potential to provide empirical answers to long-standing questions in digital humanities research: in his Atlas of the European Novel 1800-1900, for example, Franco Moretti speculated that perhaps "fictional spaces are particularly suited to happy endings," but did not have hard numbers to judge one way or the other at the time (18 n.6). More recently, in The Bestseller Code, Jodie Archer and Matthew Jockers argue that "while it does matter whether an author chooses a city or the wilderness, the specific city does not matter all that much when it comes to bestselling" (227). Our sentiment analysis findings will contribute to open research questions: maybe in fact the city matters when readers are in that city, and when the places and people in that same city are written about in particular linguistic registers. If literary form and real geography do have detectable ties to one another, our project ought to be able to capture the effect.</p><p>To compare the circulation pattern of non-Chicago and Chicago-related OBOC books, we used one year of city-wide circulation data for each book, starting with the date of the title's public announcement as the OBOC choice. This data was normalized by dividing the circulation raw numbers with the total number of visitors for that year and multiplying the result by 1000. Normalizing by the number of circulated copies was sometimes difficult because some branches did not have any copies (but could borrow them from other branches). Given that libraries oftentimes allocate books based on the size of the library and based on the number of visitors, we decided to normalize by the overall number of visitors. Distribution patterns for Chicago and non-Chicago related sets of books are represented through the histograms and QQ plots in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. As this analysis indicates, the circulation distribution across 79 Chicago library branches does not follow bell-shape distribution and is positively skewed. The Wilcoxon signed rank test was used to test to what degree the difference in the distribution for these two sets can be attributed to chance. Results indicate that the probability that the difference in the circulation distribution across 79 Chicago library branches for the two (paired) sets of books can be attributed to chance is very low (p &lt; .01). and three non-Chicago related books. The y-axis in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> represents the difference between the checkouts per 1000 visitors for Chicago related and non-Chicago related books. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> indicates that the three non-Chicago related books circulated more than the set of Chicago related books in some library branches in the Chicago area (where the line drops into negative difference). In some branches, however, the difference is almost minimal. The plot also indicates that, in some branches, the OBOC Chicago-related choices had, in fact, more checkouts than the non-Chicago OBOC choices (where the difference is positive). Although it is difficult to establish which factors contribute to this difference in circulation and although we cannot attribute this difference between the two distributions to the mere fact that one set contains references to Chicago whereas the other does not, we plan to represent the library branches that are associated with a larger number of checkouts for Chicago non-related books and those that are associated with a larger number of related books on the Chicago map and analyze them against the sociodemographic and socioeconomic characteristics of different branches (obtained from the American Community Survey data). In the future, we plan to add more Chicago related books to the analysis and observe how this may affect this observed pattern.</p><p>A further question of interest to us is, do the sentiment measures for these texts map in consistent ways for different neighborhoods? To examine these questions, we rely on Stanford CoreNLP natural language processing capabilities ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Manning et al., 2014</ref>, http://stanfordnlp.github.io/CoreNLP/). Given that the identification of places and locations is important for our analysis, we use a tool that has consistently achieved good rankings and, in general, boasts superior accuracy rates when compared to other named entity recognizers ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Rodriquez et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Atdağ &amp; Labatut, 2013)</ref>: the Stanford Named Entity Recognizer, a part of the CoreNLP suite of tools. Before running the named entity recognizer, the text is first tokenized into sentences using the NLTK sentence tokenizer (http://www.nltk.org/). The CoreNLP program then tokenizes sentences into words, identifies lemma for each individual word, uses the Penn Treebank part of speech information <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Toutanova &amp; Manning, 2000</ref>), and also notes Persons, Locations, Time Reference, and Numbers in the sentences ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Finkel et al., 2005</ref>). We are specifically interested in locations as this category would not only identify Chicago as a location but also its streets and landmark buildings. For sentiment analysis, we are using the Stanford sentiment analysis tool <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Socher et al., 2013</ref>)-also part of the Stanford CoreNLP-to annotate each sentence with the sentiment score on the following scale: Very Positive, Positive Neutral, Negative, Very Negative.</p><p>Preliminary analysis on the sentiment associated with sentences that contain the word Chicago in the three Chicago-related books is indicated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>: The raw count of sentences with their sentiment ratings was normalized by the total number of sentences that contain the word Chicago. Noticeable in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref> is that although these three books differ according to genre, and although they differ in terms of topical coverage and date of publication, we see a rather similar sentiment score pattern with respect to sentences that contain the word Chicago. We suspect that this overall similarity pattern will start to change as we dig deeper into the location data: we must note here that this initial analysis above does not yet take into account local references such as Pizzeria Uno, Pullman, the South Side, Monroe Street, and the like, but do not also use the word Chicago in the sentence. We plan to obtain a set of place names associated with Chicago through resources such as Open Street Maps and GeoNames and search for all the occurrences of Chicago place names. Additionally, we plan to use the indexes in the back of some of the books as trusted sources of local place names. Bibliography</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. On top, histograms representing checkouts per 1000 visitors for non-Chicago related and Chicago related books. Below, the QQ plots for non-Chicago and Chicago related books checkouts.</figDesc><graphic url="image-2.png" coords="2,296.02,207.94,241.44,263.28" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. The y-axis indicates the difference in the checkouts (1-year of circulation data) for three Chicago related and three non-Chicago related books.</figDesc><graphic url="image-4.png" coords="2,317.14,427.54,241.44,187.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3 Sentiment distribution of sentences that contain the word Chicago in Augie March, The Warmth of Other Suns, and The Third Coast</figDesc><graphic url="image-5.png" coords="3,317.14,146.02,241.44,144.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incorporating non-local information into information extraction systems by Gibbs sampling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Finkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Grenager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Manning</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 43rd Annual Meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics</title>
		<meeting>the 43rd Annual Meeting on Association for Computational Linguistics<address><addrLine>Ann Arbor, Michigan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Paper presented at the</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Stanford CoreNLP natural language processing toolkit</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Manning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Surdeanu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Finkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bethard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mcclosky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</title>
		<meeting>the Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Atlas of the European Novel 1800-1900</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Moretti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<publisher>Verso</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of named entity recognition tools for raw OCR text</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rodriquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bryant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Blanke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Luszczynska</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">KONVENS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="410" to="414" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Recursive Deep Models for Semantic Compositionality Over a Sentiment Treebank</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Socher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Perelygin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Manning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Potts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Paper presented at the EMNLP</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enriching the knowledge sources used in a maximum entropy part-ofspeech tagger</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Toutanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Manning</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2000 Joint SIGDAT conference on Empirical methods in natural language processing and very large corpora: held in conjunction with the 38th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</title>
		<meeting>the 2000 Joint SIGDAT conference on Empirical methods in natural language processing and very large corpora: held in conjunction with the 38th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics<address><addrLine>Hong Kong</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Paper presented at the</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
