<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:35+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Humanities At Scale - Creating A Network Of Expertise And A Sustainable Infrastructure For Digital Humanities Projects In Europe</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Markus</forename><surname>Matoni</surname></persName>
							<email>matoni@sub.uni-goettingen.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">State and University Library Göttingen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Potsdam</settlement>
									<country>Germany, Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jenny</forename><surname>Oltersdorf</surname></persName>
							<email>oltersdorf.jen@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">State and University Library Göttingen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Potsdam</settlement>
									<country>Germany, Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dirk</forename><surname>Roorda</surname></persName>
							<email>dirk.roorda@dans.knaw.nl</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">State and University Library Göttingen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Potsdam</settlement>
									<country>Germany, Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Humanities At Scale - Creating A Network Of Expertise And A Sustainable Infrastructure For Digital Humanities Projects In Europe</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Data Archiving and Networked Services, Netherlands Digital Humanities (DH), as a growing field, generates lots of innovative new tools and methods to enhance work in humanities disciplines. To ensure a sustainable digital European infrastructure for long-term availability of digital research data and tools the DARIAH infrastructure (Digital Research Infrastructure for the Arts and Humanities) aims at the development of a strong cooperation and information exchange between research communities and institutions in the arts and humanities. The ambition to extend this community and create a European-wide network of expertise was one of the reasons to initiate the new Horizon 2020 project Humanities at Scale (HaS). The project coordinated by DARIAH-EU aims to evolve the DARIAH community, offer training and information material, set up a number of training workshops and develop core services within a sustainable framework. Within this framework a research infrastructure to connect DH research tools, services and data will be established and the challenge is to build technical systems to support this. The poster will highlight and answer the following questions from a technical perspective: • How can a decentralized framework (archi-tecture of participation) of tools and services be developed and maintained? • Which kind of technologies are useful to establish a sustainable framework for DH-tools and-services? • What is needed to integrate externally developed tools into such a framework? The DH community, as a network of expertise, created and still creates a lot of important tools and services often only in a specific project context or for one particular research question. To make these tools and services accessible, re-usable, and open for DH, HaS is building a sustainable technical framework which will advance the creation and enhancement of digital tools. This will improve applications, enlarge possibilities for publication and enable long-term preservation of research data and digital methods. Just hosting digital tools is not sufficient. Code and server configuration require constant maintenance and ongoing development an elementary issue for a decentralized and unified infrastructure. Thus, within the HaS project, researchers and developers get conceptual and technical support for their tools and services to enable a better integration into the community. Furthermore, projects in the Digital Humanities need key central services. They often must spend a large proportion of their available resources on basic infrastructure components. To investigate demands regarding service requirements and tools a survey was conducted in summer 2016. Its aim was to get an overview of the currently used services and tools and the ones, which will become relevant in the future. The survey design enabled a gap analysis focusing on the following three kinds of tools and services: • Development services such as Git/SVN, Chili or Open Project. They support developers in code hosting, code review, the development of workflows and documentation. They improve the organization and quality of code and the workflows for writing it. • Hosting services comprise virtual machines, storage and repository solutions, configuration management tools and monitoring environments. They provide basics for a sustainable development and ongoing operation of DH services. • Collaboration tools support the whole area of DH. Collaborative writing and managing of</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
