<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:52+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Topic Patterns in an Academic Literary Journal: The Case Of Teksty Drugie Modelling Literary Scholarship</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Maciej</forename><surname>Maryl</surname></persName>
							<email>maciej.maryl@ibl.waw.pl</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Literary Research Polish Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="PL">Poland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Maciej</forename><forename type="middle">Eder</forename></persName>
							<email>maciejeder@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Literary Research Polish Academy of Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="PL">Poland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Topic Patterns in an Academic Literary Journal: The Case Of Teksty Drugie Modelling Literary Scholarship</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Institute of Polish Language Polish Academy of Sciences, Poland</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Material</head><p>Teksty Drugie is a Polish literary journal dedicated to literary scholarship. It has been published since 1990 by the Institute of Literary Research of the Polish Academy of Sciences. It focuses on literary theory, criticism and cultural studies, while also publishing articles by authors from neighbouring disciplines (philosophy, sociology, anthropology). The journal publishes monographic issues dedicated to particular topics or approaches within literary and cultural studies. All those features make it a good example for exploring the vicissitudes of Polish literary scholarship.</p><p>The corpus consists of the entire collection of papers published in Teksty Drugie (excluding letters, surveys, notes, etc.) in the years 1990-2014 (2,553 texts, 11,310,638 words). The material covering the years 1990-1998 was digitised, OCR-ed, and then manually edited, in order to exclude running heads, editorial comments, and so forth. Obviously, some textual noise -e.g. a certain number of misspelled characters -could not be neutralised. The material from 1999 onwards was digitally-born, but even though a small number of textual issues might have occurred. We believe, however, that distant reading techniques are resistant to small amounts of systematic noise <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Eder, 2013)</ref>.</p><p>Given the nature of Polish, which is highly inflected, lemmatization was necessary for a reliable processing of texts. The corpus has been lemmatised with LEM 1.0. (Literary Exploration Machine) developed by CLARIN-PL (see: Piasecki, Walkowiak, Maryl 2017).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head><p>To scrutinise the formulated hypothesis, we applied one of the methods of information retrieval that recently attracts a good share of attention in Digital Humanities circles, namely topic modelling in its classical variant known as Latent Dirichlet Allocation (LDA). The method, introduced by Blei (2012), allows for finding co-occurring cohorts of words that presumably reveal (latent) semantic relations.</p><p>The experiments were performed using a tailored script in the R programming language, supplemented by the package 'stylo' ) for text preprocessing, and the package 'mallet' <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(McCallum, 2002)</ref> for the actual LDA analysis. A bimodal network of the relations between topics were produced using the software Gephi ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bastian et al., 2009)</ref>.</p><p>Topic modelling relies on the assumption that particular topics are defined by words co-appearing in a given context. Hence, the definition of "context" is crucial to allow for any reliable observations. A few different solutions have been suggested (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Blei, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Jockers, 2013)</ref>. In our approach, we did not split input texts into smaller samples, which was motivated by the fact that the vast majority of the studies published in Teksty Drugie are rather short.</p><p>Other parameters used in the study included: a stop word list containing 327 words (mostly function words, numerals, and very common adverbs), 100 topics extracted in 1,000 iterations, with the obvious caveat that this choice was arbitrary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>A general overview of the obtained results shows a few interesting patterns. Firstly, we analysed and categorised the topics on the basis of their predominant words. The categories are as follows: literary theory (e.g. literature, fiction, text), poetics (e.g. verse, novel, short story, rhetoric) and methodological approaches (e.g. deconstruction, comparative literature, postcolonial studies, psychoanalysis); history of literature (e.g. romanticism, contemporary poets) and cross-cutting research themes (e.g. death, politics, literacy).</p><p>A thorough exploration of such models requires a topographical visualisation capable of showing the connections between various topics, which often share a key word (cf. Goldstone and Underwood, 2012). The network <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1)</ref> is too large to be adequately rendered in this paper (a higher resolution image of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> is available online), yet even without the knowledge about concrete topics presented, we may see (partly thanks to ForceAtlas2 layout, which highlighted this feature) that groups of topics in our corpus are concentrically distributed. This onion-like distribution allows us to distinguish between the central topics (i.e. those who appear in many different papers) and those who appear less often or sporadically and hence are not particularly well-connected with other topics. For instance, in the geometrical centre of the network we may find topics and words pertinent to literary scholarship: literature, literary, comparative literature, national literatures, Jewish studies, fiction, together with some names of contemporary authors. Outliers are also interesting, and could be assigned to 3 groups: (1) expressions in foreign languages, (2) particular research topics or discourses which introduce quite a hermetic language, not shared in other topics, (3) noise (e.g. word bits generated through some errors in OCR). Yet it has to be noted that even the most accurate rendering of the topical distribution is still only a static snapshot insensitive to changes. In order to see the evolution of topics, we need to visualise them on a temporal axis. Due to a shortage of space we present here only a few examples, to show the application of our method. All dot plots are presented below with a trend line based on two period moving average. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref> represents the gradual shift of interest from more literature-oriented approaches, to the cultural ones. Both red (topic 19: literature, literary, writer, work) and green (topic 5: literature, research, theory) seem to be dominating until approx. 2007, when the blue line (topic 49: culture, cultural, social) overtakes the green line for the first time. Three years later it becomes the dominant approach, marking the shift in the overall content of Teksty Drugie. Topic analysis allows us to not only trace the evolution of the journal itself but also to see how the real-world events shape the topics undertaken by literary scholars. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref> shows the influence of the political transformation in Poland on the content of Teksty Drugie. We see a similar pattern in trends of all topics presented: grey (topic 60: power, society, state, fight, war, law), red (topic 36: political, communism, Polish People's Republic), blue (topic 7: Polish, Pole, national), yellow (topic 94: censorship, exile, novel, positivism, country, London, political). All of them are quite important in the early 1990s and the interest gradually fades until the end of this decade. The spikes around 2001/2002 are caused by the publication of monographic issues which make certain topic more dominant. E.g. Issue No.1-2/2000 was dedicated to socialist realism hence the spike of "communismrelated" issue in that year.</p><p>This trend shows how political events (namely the transformation and forming of the new democracy) are dominating even the literary scholarship. It could be also the case that more politically charged issues (e.g. history of censorship in Poland) could have been published only after the fall of the communism, hence so many articles in that period. The last trend we would like to discuss is the emergence of the Holocaust studies in Teksty Drugie. As we can see in the <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 4</ref>, the red trend line (topic 59: Jew, Jewish, antisemitic) is visible on the fairly same level all through the 25 years, whereas the blue one (topic 18: testimony, Holocaust) is virtually nonexistent until 2001. This sudden boom can be linked to the publishing of the Polish edition of Neighbors by Jan <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Gross (2000)</ref> and the investigation into the role of Polish civilians in the genocide perpetrated in the city of Jedwabne during the World War II. This case opened a long process of re-investigating the troubled Polish-Jewish past, which could be traced also in the issues of Teksty Drugie.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>In this study we tried to show how extra-textual events influence the content of literary scholarship on the example of Holocaust studies and political transformation, which entailed the prevalence of topics related to politics, power, society, state, and communism in the early 1990s. In the subsequent studies we plan to compare the results of topic modelling with bibliographical data in order to check whether the dominance of a certain topic stems from the large number of scholars who pursue it, or if it instead depends on the fact that a small group of authors published more often than others.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Relationships between topics in Teksty Drugie.</figDesc><graphic url="image-1.png" coords="2,316.86,429.18,241.44,198.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. A temporal distribution of three topics related to literature and culture.</figDesc><graphic url="image-2.png" coords="3,54.30,232.38,241.44,177.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Temporal shift of topics related to politics.</figDesc><graphic url="image-3.png" coords="3,316.86,121.50,241.44,164.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Temporal distribution of topics related to Jewish studies and the Holocaust.</figDesc><graphic url="image-4.png" coords="3,316.86,419.34,241.44,134.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgement</head><p>The authors wish to thank Dr Tomasz Walkowiak for his extensive help with cleaning and lemmatizing the corpus.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gephi: An open source software for exploring and manipulating networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bastian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Heymann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jacomy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Third International ICWSM Conference</title>
		<meeting>the Third International ICWSM Conference<address><addrLine>San Jose</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="361" to="62" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Reading by Numbers: Recalibrating the Literary Field</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bode</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<publisher>Anthem Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London &amp; New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic Topic Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Blei</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mind your corpus: systematic errors in authorship attribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="603" to="617" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stylometry with R: a package for computational text analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rybicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kestemont</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">R Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Historical Linguistics&apos; New Toys, or Stylometry Applied to the Study of Language Change</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Górski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Digital Humanities 2016: Conference Abstracts</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Kraków</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="182" to="184" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Jagiellonian University &amp; Pedagogical University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What can topic models of PMLA teach us about the history of literary scholarship?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goldstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Underwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Digital Humanities</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The quiet transformations of literary studies: What thirteen thousand scholars could tell us</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goldstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Underwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New Literary History</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sąsiedzi: Historia zagłady żydowskiego miasteczka. Sejny: Fundacja Pogranicze</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Gross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Jockers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Macroanalysis: Digital Methods and Literary History</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Illinois Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Network science and literary history</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>So</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="274" to="274" />
			<pubPlace>Leonardo</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">MALLET: A machine learning for language toolkit</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Mccallum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://mallet.cs.umass.edu/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Graphs, Maps, Trees: Abstract Models for a Literary History</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Moretti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>Verso</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Distant Reading</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Moretti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<publisher>Verso Books</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Literary Exploration Machine (LEM 1.0) -New Tool for Distant Readers of Polish Literature Collections</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Piasecki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Walkowiak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maryl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
			<pubPlace>Montreal</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Paper accepted for presentation at ADHO Digital Humanities conference at McGill Universiy</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network analysis and the sociology of Modernism</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>So</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Boundary</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
