<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:26+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Site-specific Cultural Infrastructure: Promoting Access and Conquering the Digital Divide</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andre</forename><surname>Goodrich</surname></persName>
							<email>andre.doodrich@nwu.ac.za</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">North-West University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ZA">South Africa</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gustaf</forename><surname>Templehoff</surname></persName>
							<email>mrgustaft@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">North-West University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ZA">South Africa</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Juan</forename><surname>Steyn</surname></persName>
							<email>juan.steyn@nwu.ac.za</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">North-West University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ZA">South Africa</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Site-specific Cultural Infrastructure: Promoting Access and Conquering the Digital Divide</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Site-specific digital literature project</head><p>Site-specific digital literature, by allowing users to access place-bound, multimodal digital literature via mobile devices, opens doors for creative expression, place making as well as experiencing traditional texts in a new way. It can also contribute to a better understanding of the relationship between digital interfaces, spatiality and people and empower people in terms of what is called place-making practices <ref type="bibr">(Kaye, 2000:203;</ref><ref type="bibr">Turner &amp; Davenport, 217-220)</ref>.</p><p>Byderhand <ref type="bibr">(Byderhand.net, 2016)</ref>, is a site-specific digital literature project launched during the 2015 Aardklop National Arts Festival in Potchefstroom, South Africa. Users accessed multimodal texts on their mobile devices through QR-codes deployed around various sites at the North-West University. Byderhand was awarded the Aartvark prize for a ground breaking production, and the team was approached to host similar productions elsewhere. In 2016 the Byderhand-project and platform were used in various educational contexts. Most recently, the Byderhandteam, assisted 1st additional language (Afrikaans) learners at a Potchefstroom secondary school to publish their own site-specific digital literature on the school grounds.</p><p>Although there is a demand for expansion of the Byderhand-project, cost and scalability are limiting factors. First, in its current form, implementing the project requires a team of dedicated members. is Second, functionality depends on the provision, maintenance and upgrading of infrastructure such as servers and physical QR-codes. On the user end, mobile data cost is a constraining factor. Therefore, we explored the design of the infrastructure for an automated platform that could empower a low-skilled user, to create, publish and access their own projects. This was important as usability of a platform can ether promote access or restrict it through the way the interface is developed <ref type="bibr">(Shneiderman, B. 2003)</ref>.</p><p>The infrastructure chosen was a single-board computer (Raspberry Pi) and a platform was developed based on open standards.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Virtual museum project</head><p>South Africa's heritage landscape remains largely skewed in ways that exclude intangible heritage such as stories and memories of such events as apartheidera forced removals. A virtual museum of forced removals aids in remedying this by offering an in situ space where people can give voice to their experience and preserve it for future generations.</p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Educational applications:</head><p>a. How the platform could be ported into other applications such as freestanding, free-access libraries for schools and community centers. b. Educational possibilities created that can introduce students to the world of digital literature. c. A lesson in the value of interdisciplinary collaborations. 5. Building collaborative communities and empowering them to tell their own stories. 6. Mini-showcase of the project </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Kaye, N. (2000) Site-Specific Art: Performance, Place and Documentation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Shneiderman, B. (2003) "Promoting universal usability with</head><p>multi-layer interface design." In ACM SIGCAPH Computers and the Physically Handicapped <ref type="bibr">(No. 73-74, pp. 1-8)</ref>. ACM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Turner, P. &amp; Davenport, E. eds. (2006) Spaces, Spatiality and Technology</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
