<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:23+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The VSim Repository and Archive: Knowledge Mobilization for 3D Research</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lisa</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Snyder</surname></persName>
							<email>lms@ats.ucla.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">UC</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
									<country>United States of America</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The VSim Repository and Archive: Knowledge Mobilization for 3D Research</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>With the explosion of academic interest in 3D mod-eling and interactive environments, two questions dominate: How can scholars and educators access these models? And how can they be integrated into the classroom? Enter VSim-a much-needed software interface for academics exploring applications for 3D computer models in humanities research and teaching-and the VSim Repository and Archive, both now available through the UCLA Library. VSim is an easy-to-use software interface that allows real-time exploration of highly detailed, academically generated 3D computer models in both formal and informal educational settings across grade levels and humanities disciplines. The VSim Repository and Archive provides a platform for the dissemination of academically generated 3D content. This poster presentation is both a launch announcement and a solicitation for submissions from content creators. If you are working in 3D, please consider sharing your projects for teaching and learning through the VSim Repository and Archive.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body/>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
