<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-cc-ra-bermudez-sabel-137-source.xml 877 2019-12-19 21:18:04Z ron $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Encoding of Variant Taxonomies in TEI</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Helena</forename>
            <surname>Bermúdez Sabel</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Helena Bermúdez Sabel is a <roleName>postdoctoral researcher</roleName> at
            the <orgName>Université de Lausanne</orgName>. Currently, she is working for the
            SNFS-funded project <title level="m">A world of possibilities. Modal pathways on the
              extra-long period of time: the diachrony of modality in the Latin language</title>
            which aims at reconstructing the evolution of modal meanings from the prehistory of the
            Latin language up to the seventh century CE. In this project, Helena supervises the
            technical aspects of the annotation workflow, including the automation of corpus
            pre-processing, annotation and publication.</affiliation>
          <email>helena.bermudez@usc.es</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>19/12/2019</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Claudia Resch</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Tanja Wissik</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Vanessa Hannesschlaeger</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Anne Baillot</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="11">Selected Papers from the 2016 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals
          in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish
          full-text articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>feature structures</term>
          <term>textual variants</term>
          <term>scholarly editions</term>
          <term>taxonomies</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2019-12-17">RvdB encoded the file.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>The inherent flexibility of the digital format has favored the rise of editions that
          enable access to every witness of a particular textual work. These types of editions might
          have different goals and seek to answer different research questions, but they usually
          coincide in drawing attention to the importance of textual variants. To maximize the
          computational analysis that may be practiced with the variants in different witnesses, a
          complex taxonomy that reflects the diversity of cases is required.</p>
        <p>Many scholars have followed the recommended TEI method for encoding types of
          variants—that is, through the attributes <att>cause</att> or <att>type</att> inside the
          element <gi>rdg</gi>—while others find that method insufficient. These attributes are not
          able to enclose the hierarchy intrinsic to complicated taxonomies or the overlap of
          classes in an efficient way. However, the TEI Guidelines do offer a module that addresses
          this complex encoding issue: feature structures. The method proposed in this paper does
          not advocate for a controlled vocabulary to categorize types of variants. What it offers
          instead is a pliable encoding method that allows the editor to include multiple layers of
          information in each apparatus tagset.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="acknowledgements">
        <p>This work was supported by the Ministerio de Educación, Cultura y Deporte (Spanish
          Government) as part of its predoctoral training program (FPU grant AP2012–4518) and by the
          Ministerio de Economía, Industría y Competitividad as part of the project <title level="m"
            >Paleografía, Lingüística y Filología. Laboratorio on-line de la lírica
            gallego-portuguesa</title> (FFI2015–68451–P).</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="introduction">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>This paper proposes a method for introducing multilayered analytical information as part
          of the critical annotation of an edition. <ptr type="crossref" target="#rationale"/> gives
          a brief introduction about the importance of variation studies, justifying the subject of
          analysis. The method, explained in <ptr type="crossref" target="#features #validation"/>,
          explores the use of feature structures for the creation of complex taxonomies describing
          textual variation. <ptr type="crossref" target="#edition"/> offers examples of one of the
          ways in which the variant taxonomy may be linked to the body of the edition.</p>
        <p>Although this paper is TEI-centered, other XML technologies will be mentioned. <ptr
            type="crossref" target="#validation"/> includes a brief commentary on using XSLT to
          transform a TEI-conformant definition of constraints into schema rules. However, the
          greatest attention to an additional technology is in <ptr type="crossref"
            target="#analyses"/>, which discusses the use of XQuery to retrieve particular
            <foreign>loci critici</foreign> and to deploy quantitative analyses.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="rationale">
        <head>Rationale</head>
        <p>In textual scholarship, two founding concepts shape the methodology of analysis: text and
          variant. While <term>text</term> is a broad concept that requires a theoretical approach
          to define it with precision, the concept of <term>variant</term> is intrinsic to the
          philological tasks involved in the editorial process, that is, the empirical operations
          that define what constitutes a variant and its role in the analysis of the text:
          normalizations, the selection of contents of the critical apparatus and how this
          information will be structured, and explanatory annotations, among others.</p>
        <p>The amount of data we can collect from the analysis of variation depends on the
          complexity of the transmission process. Scholars who study textual traditions transmitted
          by scribes are familiar with the use of variants to help identify how many hands
          participated in the creation of the witness, and where these people came from or where
          they were trained. Furthermore, variants account for the modifications of the text that
          may help clarify the political and cultural context in which a work is copied, edited, and
          published. In addition, variants are also of great importance in modern and contemporary
          works: the typographer, the editor or editors, and the author at different stages of the
          composition process must also be studied through the analysis of variants (<ref
            type="bibl" target="#segre95">Segre 1995</ref>).</p>
        <p>The most common issues addressed through the study of variation include the following:
            <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>The analysis of the results of the collation of witnesses is a mandatory step to
              establish the relationships of filiation among them and, consequently, the
              construction of the <term>stemma</term>—when possible—or local <term>stemmata</term>
              in highly contaminated traditions (<ref type="bibl" target="#mink00">Mink
              2000</ref>).</item>
            <item>Stemmatic analysis sheds light on stages of transmission that are not preserved
              directly, but that can nonetheless be identified as sources for the extant
              witnesses—that is, it helps in the description of an archetype and hyparchetypes (<ref
                type="bibl" target="#maas58">Maas 1958</ref>).</item>
            <item>The exploration of internal variants may reveal different stages during which the
              textual materials that form a work were compiled.</item>
            <item>Alongside codicological analysis, variants may contribute information about the
              time and geographical location in which a particular witness was created.</item>
            <item>Variants present data of interest for the development of the history of writing
              and the history of a language.</item>
            <item>Variants may provide evidence for the identification of copyists, historical
              owners, editors, and other persons who may have participated in the transmission of a
              work or in the alteration of its contents. In addition, variants may provide
              sociohistorical information through the study of the motivation underlying those
              alterations.</item>
            <item>The study of variation is a key feature of genetic editions that allows one to
              analyze the creative process of a particular writer or editor.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>Considering all of the above, it goes without saying that any type of scholarly edition
          that takes into account a multi-witness tradition needs to refer to variation somehow. How
          these references will be made depends on the theoretical background and the editorial
          model. Textual scholarship is very rich in its treatment of the relation of variants and
          the final result of the edited text, but both <soCalled>materialistic</soCalled>
          approaches to the edition of texts (for example, <ref type="bibl" target="#cerquiglini89"
            >Cerquiglini 1989</ref>) and methods that look for a curated version (for example, <ref
            type="bibl" target="#chiesa02">Chiesa 2002</ref>) require the analysis of variants.</p>
        <p>The information a scholar might want to retrieve from the analysis of variants is so
          dependent on the circumstances of the text and on their interests that a generic taxonomy
          able to enclose the complexity of variation and reflect all the nuances is impractical.
          Thus, the goal of this paper is to provide an encoding mechanism that would formalize, for
          all intents and purposes, textual variants.</p>
        <p>Among the studies concerning textual variation that can be conducted through a taxonomy
          of variants, there is the possibility of combining both quantitative and descriptive
          approaches.</p>
        <p>A fine categorization of the types of textual variants enriches the critical annotation
          of any scholarly edition because of the ways in which this information can be embedded in
          a digital environment. In addition, the analysis of a work after the ordering and
          categorization of all variants may open a window onto new research questions. For example,
          a classification regarding content—that is, addition, omission, and mutation—can be
          systematized according to subdivisions that offer possible explanations for the variation.
          Applying this kind of analysis to the oeuvre of an author or authors could shed light on
          the composition process, as well as <!-- [RvdB] changed "serving" to "serve" -->serve as a
          source for different types of genetic and stylometric studies.</p>
        <p>When the object of study is a textual tradition transmitted by acts of copying, a
          multilayered analysis is especially appropriate. The analysis of linguistic variation
          between witnesses brings to attention the <term>core</term>, original language of the
          text, and the <term>patina</term>, the linguistic layers left by the copyists (<ref
            type="bibl" target="#trovato14">Trovato 2014</ref>). In addition, linguistic variants
          shed light on the distinctive features of every witness, which makes the study of
          linguistic aspects of the textual tradition as a whole more practicable. Furthermore,
          linguistic variants may occur as a result of self-dictation by copyists after reading and
          memorizing the extracts they intend to copy, and thus may reflect features of their
          idiolects. The study of those features contributes to a better understanding of the
          history of a witness, since it provides evidence of the agents that participated in its
          creation.</p>
        <p>Additionally, the linguistic data that can be retrieved by the classification of
          linguistic variants are of interest to historical linguistics in ways that may transcend
          the critical analysis of a particular textual work. Any linguistic variant must be
          analyzed first in a synchronic context: the oldest variants coexist with newer variants in
          the same linguistic community, but in different contexts or registers (<ref type="bibl"
            target="#jakobson71">Jakobson 1971, 528</ref>). Thus, by identifying linguistic variants
          in a multi-witness tradition, we are discerning the variants that are competing in a
          specific chronological framework. Historical corpora used for linguistic studies have
          sometimes relied on scholarly curated texts or on a transcription of only the oldest
          witness, and in those cases linguistic variation within the tradition may be
            neutralized.<note>This statement is especially significant when dealing with corpora
            that have been compiled over a long period of time. As is clearly explained in the
            introduction to the Helsinki Corpus that Irma Taavitsainen and Päivi Pahta prepared for
            the <ref
              target="http://www.helsinki.fi/varieng/CoRD/corpora/HelsinkiCorpus/meintro.html"
              >Corpus Resource Database</ref> (CoRD) (<bibl xml:id="quoteref1"><title level="a"
                >Placing the Helsinki Corpus Middle English Section Introduction into
                Context</title>, <ptr
                target="http://www.helsinki.fi/varieng/CoRD/corpora/HelsinkiCorpus/meintro.html"
              /></bibl>): <quote source="#quoteref1">The idea of basing corpus texts directly on
              manuscript sources has been presented more recently<gap/> The principles of preparing
              manuscript texts for print have undergone changes during the history of
              editing<gap/></quote>.</note></p>
        <p>Depending on the historical period to which a tradition belongs, even graphic variants,
          often dismissed as nonsignificant variation because they may not be <emph>textually</emph>
          significant, may nonetheless provide a rich source of cultural information. A graphemic
          analysis derived from a taxonomy allows an efficient computation of frequencies that can
          be filtered according to different codicological or historical aspects encoded in the
          corpus, such as the quire or folio number. This analysis may clarify certain elements of
          the genesis of the witnesses, such as the identification of hands or editorial
          interventions. Similarly, scribal errors may provide information related to the sources,
          such as the distinctive features of a hyparchetype (for example, an unusual graphic
          substitution might mean that the affected letters had similar shapes in the model) or
          linguistic data.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="features">
        <head>Feature Structures</head>
        <p>From the TEI documentation (see the <ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-att.textCritical.html"
            >set of attributes</ref> specific to elements representing variant readings: <bibl><ref
              type="bibl" target="#TEI16">TEI Consortium 2016</ref>, Appendix B: Attribute Classes,
              <title level="a">att.textCritical</title></bibl>) we can assume that the recommended
          way to describe the motivation behind a variant and its categorization is done through the
          attributes <att>type</att> and <att>cause</att>. However, the complexity of variation,
          with overlapping categories and complex hierarchies of variation types, cannot be recorded
          with a straightforward use of these two attributes.<note>For examples of different variant
            classifications, see Colwell and Tune (<ref type="bibl" target="#colwell64">1964</ref>)
            and Italia, Vitali, and Di Iorio (<ref type="bibl" target="#italia15"
            >2015</ref>).</note></p>
        <p>The TEI offers a module well suited for the encoding of complex taxonomies: the <ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/FS.html">Feature
            Structures</ref> module (<ref type="bibl" target="#TEI16">TEI Consortium 2016,
          18</ref>). A feature structure is a group of <ident>attribute:value</ident> pairs, where
          the values may be either atomic or nested feature structures. As described by Witt and
          Stegmann (<ref type="bibl" target="#witt09">2009</ref>), feature structures are a generic
          method to organize data with a metarepresentation format that presents numerous
          advantages, some of which will be discussed in greater detail below. For a more detailed
          description of feature structures and their rationale see Pose, Lopez, and Rosemary (<ref
            type="bibl" target="#pose14">2014, 9–10</ref>).</p>
        <p>One argument in support of the use of feature structures is the official recognition of
          the model in 2012 as an international standard (ISO 24612) (<ref type="bibl"
            target="#romary15">Romary 2015</ref>), which bestows a certain stability on the
          methodology and confirms, at least to some extent, its importance and influence within a
          user community.</p>
        <p>With respect to the model itself, by describing an object as a sum (and convergence) of
          multiple individual features, we can implement a complex description with a fine level of
          granularity. See, for example, in <ptr type="crossref" target="#example1"/> a proposed
          definition of a phenomenon of <term>progressive nasalization</term>, a type of linguistic
          variation characterized by the addition of a nasal sound. <figure xml:id="example1">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <fs xml:id="pro-nas">
                <f name="taxonomy">
                  <fs type="linguistic">
                    <f name="category">
                      <fs type="phonetic">
                        <f name="process">
                          <fs type="alteration">
                            <f name="mode">
                              <fs type="assimilation">
                                <f name="procedure">
                                  <symbol value="nasalization"/>
                                </f>
                                <f name="direction">
                                  <symbol value="progressive"/>
                                </f>
                              </fs>
                            </f>
                          </fs>
                        </f>
                        <f name="position">
                          <symbol value="end"/>
                        </f>
                        <f name="constriction">
                          <binary value="true"/>
                        </f>
                      </fs>
                    </f>
                  </fs>
                </f>
                <f name="description">
                  <string xml:lang="en">Progressive nasalization</string>
                </f>
              </fs>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Entry in the taxonomy for a particular linguistic phenomenon</head>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>Let us briefly describe the encoding presented in <ptr type="crossref" target="#example1"
          /> by going through the different layers of data employed to describe this type of
          variant. This and other samples presented throughout this paper are part of a dissertation
          project that studies linguistic variation phenomena between two different manuscript
          branches that transmit secular Galician-Portuguese medieval poetry. For that reason, the
          examples used here reflect the research questions of that project, which are related to
          the study of variation as a source of information for the genesis of the different
          witnesses.</p>
        <p>The two features that primarily describe the variant presented in <ptr type="crossref"
            target="#example1"/> are the taxonomy that will be used (in this case, the linguistic
          one) and a feature called <val>description</val> that contains a definition of the
          phenomenon.</p>
        <p>The category of the linguistic taxonomy to which this variant belongs is the phonetic
          one, and the phenomenon of progressive nasalization is further defined by the features
            <val>process</val>, <val>position</val>, and <val>constriction</val>. As we can see, the
            <val>process</val> feature is more complex than the others and it requires further
          decomposition. The selection of features to define the phenomenon was based on their
          relevance for the work in which this taxonomy is applied. For example, in medieval poetry
          it is important to know which phonetic phenomena occur at the end of a word creating a
          consonantic coda (constriction): the metrical analysis of the medieval Galician-Portuguese
          tradition depends on the number of syllables, and progressive nasalization can alter that
          count through a literary device known as <term>synalepha</term>. A synalepha is the
          merging of two syllables into one whenever a word ends in a vowel and the next word also
          begins with a vowel. This means that progressive nasalization, with the addition of a
          nasal consonant, would prevent that merging. If one witness presents a regular metric
          paradigm and in the other the paradigm is broken because of the presence or the absence of
          this phenomenon, it is the deviant witness that presents a <soCalled>spurious</soCalled>
          variant.</p>
        <p>One of the advantages of the internal organization of feature structures is that any
          layer of information may be referenced during the description of the value of other
          features. This facilitates the creation of long and complex taxonomies on the foundation
          of a small set of shared features. For example, in the case of a linguistic variation
          taxonomy, it could be convenient to define a feature structure that would represent any
          phonetic phenomenon that implies the addition of a sound. In this manner, we could refer
          to that structure when defining <term>paragoge</term> (addition at the end of a word),
            <term>epenthesis</term> (addition within a word), <term>prothesis</term> (addition at
          the beginning of a word), etc. In <ptr type="crossref" target="#example2"/> the attribute
            <att>feats</att> refers to the features related to the sound addition, so that the
          phenomena <soCalled>paragoge</soCalled> and <soCalled>prothesis</soCalled> can be
          characterized simply by adding the features that define them more precisely. <figure
            xml:id="example2">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <fs xml:id="sound-addition">
                <f name="taxonomy">
                  <fs type="linguistic">
                    <f name="category">
                      <fs type="phonetic">
                        <f name="process">
                          <symbol value="addition"/>
                        </f>
                      </fs>
                    </f>
                  </fs>
                </f>
              </fs>
              <fs xml:id="paragoge">
                <f name="taxonomy">
                  <fs feats="#sound-addition">
                    <f name="position">
                      <symbol value="end"/>
                    </f>
                    <f name="constriction">
                      <binary value="false"/>
                    </f>
                  </fs>
                </f>
                <f name="description">
                  <string xml:lang="en">Paragoge</string>
                </f>
              </fs>
              <fs xml:id="prothesis">
                <f name="taxonomy">
                  <fs feats="#sound-addition">
                    <f name="position">
                      <symbol value="start"/>
                    </f>
                  </fs>
                </f>
                <f name="description">
                  <string xml:lang="en">Prothesis</string>
                </f>
              </fs>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend"><soCalled>Reusing</soCalled> features to define phenomena that
              entail the addition of a sound</head>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>Furthermore, the feature structure system is so flexible that it allows the combination
          of heterogeneous types of categorizations using the same methods. This may be especially
          convenient when working with variant taxonomies and scholarly editions, since different
          theories and models may require different categories, and it may be of interest to
          incorporate them simultaneously. See <ptr type="crossref" target="#example3"/> for a
          description of dittography, a type of scribal error characterized by a repetition, that
          could be represented within the same master taxonomy that would include <ptr
            type="crossref" target="#example1 #example2"/>. <figure xml:id="example3">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <fs xml:id="dittography">
                <f name="taxonomy">
                  <fs type="error">
                    <f name="category">
                      <fs type="involuntary">
                        <f name="process">
                          <symbol value="eye-skip"/>
                        </f>
                        <f name="result">
                          <symbol value="repetition"/>
                        </f>
                      </fs>
                    </f>
                  </fs>
                </f>
                <f name="description">
                  <string xml:lang="en">Dittography</string>
                </f>
              </fs>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Entry in the taxonomy for a particular scribal error</head>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>In this case, the outer layers of the definition relate the three examples to one
          another, although the inner elements used to analyze them further are completely
          different.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="validation">
        <head>Internal Validation of the Taxonomy</head>
        <p>Because a taxonomy may have many diverse layers of information, it would be easy to lose
          track of the features, adversely affecting the accuracy of data retrieval. That is why the
            <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/FS.html#FD"
            >Feature System Declaration</ref> (<ref type="bibl" target="#TEI16">TEI Consortium 2016,
            18.11</ref>) is crucial: it is the instrument for declaring all attributes and their
          possible values, that is, for listing all feature names and feature values, to which a
          prose description may be added to explain what each represents. This declaration forces
          the creation of well-documented taxonomies, which provides advantages for the reuse and
          especially the development of these taxonomies.</p>
        <p>Additionally, the feature system declaration provides a means for defining constraints,
          describing what a well-formed and valid feature structure is according to the theory and
          praxis of the research that is being developed. Alongside the documentary value of this
          definition, its typed-feature modeling facilitates the creation of schema constraints. For
          instance, I process my declaration to further constrict my schema so the feature structure
          declaration and its actual application are always synchronized and up to date.<note>I use
            XSLT to process the feature structure declaration in order to create all required
            Schematron rules that will constrict the feature library accordingly. I am currently
            working on creating a more generic validator (see my <ref
              target="https://github.com/HelenaSabel/FS-Validator">Github repository</ref>, <ptr
              target="https://github.com/HelenaSabel/FS-Validator"/>).</note>
          <figure xml:id="example4">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <fsdDecl>
                <fsDecl type="variants.taxonomy">
                  <fDecl name="description">
                    <fDescr>Prose description of the phenomenon</fDescr>
                    <vRange>
                      <vNot>
                        <string/>
                      </vNot>
                    </vRange>
                  </fDecl>
                  <fDecl name="taxonomy">
                    <fDescr>Main categorization for type of variant</fDescr>
                    <vRange>
                      <vAlt>
                        <fs type="linguistic"/>
                        <fs type="error"/>
                        <fs type="material"/>
                        <fs type="equipollent"/>
                        <fs type="graphic"/>
                      </vAlt>
                    </vRange>
                  </fDecl>
                </fsDecl>
                <fsDecl type="linguistic">
                  <fDecl name="category">
                    <vRange>
                      <vAlt>
                        <fs type="phonetic"/>
                        <fs type="morphosyntatic"/>
                        <fs type="lexical"/>
                        <fs type="language-transfer"/>
                      </vAlt>
                    </vRange>
                  </fDecl>
                </fsDecl>
                <fsDecl type="phonetic">
                  <fsDescr>Features to describe phonetic change</fsDescr>
                  <fDecl name="process">
                    <fDescr>Feature to represent the main type of sound change</fDescr>
                    <vRange>
                      <vAlt>
                        <symbol value="addition"/>
                        <symbol value="reduction"/>
                        <fs type="alteration"/>
                      </vAlt>
                    </vRange>
                  </fDecl>
                  <fDecl name="constriction">
                    <fDescr>Vowel or consonant phenomenon</fDescr>
                    <vRange>
                      <vAlt>
                        <binary value="true"/>
                        <binary value="false"/>
                      </vAlt>
                    </vRange>
                  </fDecl>
                  <!-- Continue with the description of other features -->
                </fsDecl>
              </fsdDecl>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Excerpt of a feature system declaration</head>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>In the sample presented in <ptr type="crossref" target="#example4"/>, there are two
          features in the outer layer, the feature <val>description</val>, whose value cannot be an
          empty string, and the <val>taxonomy</val>, which can contain any of the following nested
          feature structures: <val>linguistic</val>, <val>error</val>, <val>material</val>,
            <val>equipollent</val>, or <val>graphic</val>. Similar declarations are built according
          to the same model to describe linguistic feature structures and the individual features
          that define them. When there is no need to go more deeply into the decomposition of a
          feature structure, and the possible values conform to a limited list, the <gi>symbol</gi>
          element is used to define this controlled vocabulary. In the case of boolean-type values,
          as in the feature <val>constriction</val> seen in <ptr type="crossref" target="#example1"
          />, the <gi>binary</gi> element is declared instead in order to define the
          constriction.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="edition">
        <head>Encoding Textual Variation in TEI</head>
        <p>As is also often the case elsewhere in the TEI Guidelines, there are several ways to
          encode variants, as well as alternative methods for linking the apparatus information to
          the text (see the <ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html">Critical
            Apparatus</ref> documentation for more information: <ref type="bibl" target="#TEI16">TEI
            Consortium 2016, 12</ref>). Of the available methods, the <ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPPS"
            >parallel segmentation</ref> method (<ref type="bibl" target="#TEI16">TEI Consortium
            2016, 12.2.3</ref>) seems to be a popular encoding technique for multi-witness editions,
          in terms of both the specific tools that have been created for this method and the number
          of projects that apply it.<note>Tools include <ref target="http://v-machine.org/"
              >Versioning Machine</ref>, <ref target="https://collatex.net/">CollateX</ref> (both
            the Java and Python versions), and <ref target="http://www.juxtasoftware.org/"
              >Juxta</ref>. For representative projects using the parallel segmentation method see
              <ref target="http://scholarlyediting.org/2015/editions/lowelledition_wit-Courier.html"
              >Satire in Circulation: James editions Russell Lowell’s Letter from a volunteer in
              Saltillo</ref>, <ref target="http://digitalthoreau.org/fluid-text-toc">Walden: A
              Fluid-Text Edition</ref>, or <ref
              target="http://digitalmitford.org/literature/Julian.html">Digital Mitford: The Mary
              Russel Mitford Archive</ref>, to name a few.</note> The discussion below explores the
          integration of a variant taxonomy into an edition that follows this method by inserting an
            <gi>app</gi> element for each variation unit, that is, in every <term>locus</term> in
          the text where at least two concurrent readings exist
            <!-- [RvdB] corrected author order -->(<ref type="bibl" target="#mace12">Macé, De Vos,
            and Geuten 2012, 113</ref>).</p>
        <p>Taxonomies can be formalized as complex modules of structured information, and in the
          interest of maintaining legibility for human editors, an efficient way to incorporate
          analytic information into an edition involves the use of stand-off annotation methods
            (<ref type="bibl" target="#banski10">Bański 2010</ref>). Stand-off refers to annotation
          that is not inserted in line. It usually entails the development of the annotation of a
          primary document in a different file or files from the one that contains the primary
          textual data. The process of relating the primary document to its annotation involves
          linking between specific locations of the primary source and the information that
          describes them, whether through byte offsets, elements, attributes, or other methods (<ref
            type="bibl" target="#ide04">Ide and Romary 2004, 218</ref>).</p>
        <p>In simpler traditions, a semantic correspondence through the use of the attribute
            <att>ana</att>, as in the examples below, may also be suitable. Each entry of the
          taxonomy has an ID that is referred to in an <att>ana</att> attribute in the edition. <!-- [RvdB] check / fix encoding of glyphs -->
          <figure xml:id="example5">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <l n="13">
                <app>
                  <rdg wit="#A" ana="#np">se<seg>n</seg>pre</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#B" ana="#abb"
                      ><choice><abb>sempᷓ</abb><expan>semp<ex>re</ex></expan></choice></rdg>
                </app>
                <app>
                  <rdg wit="#A" ana="#reg"><seg>ll</seg>e</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#B" ana="#li">lh<seg>i</seg></rdg>
                </app>
                <app>
                  <rdg wit="#A" ana="#pal-stem">qui<seg>ge</seg></rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#B" ana="#abb"
                      ><choice><abb>qͥs</abb><expan>q<ex>ui</ex>s</expan></choice></rdg>
                </app>
                <app>
                  <rdg wit="#A" ana="#gap"/>
                  <rdg wit="#B">muj</rdg>
                </app>
                <app>
                  <rdg wit="#A" ana="#reg">me<seg>ll</seg>or</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#B" ana="#abb"
                      ><choice><abb>melhᷣ</abb><expan>melh<ex>or</ex></expan></choice></rdg>
                </app> toda <app>
                  <rdg wit="#A">uia</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#B" ana="#y-minim">uya</rdg>
                </app>
              </l>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Excerpt from a multi-witness edition</head>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p><ptr type="crossref" target="#example5"/> shows a line of the corpus, encoded according
          to the TEI parallel segmentation method. The text nodes that are direct children of
            <gi>l</gi> are common text shared by all witnesses, and an <term>apparatus</term>
          element, <gi>app</gi>, is introduced wherever there are divergences. If there is more than
          one variant per <gi>app</gi>, the element <gi>seg</gi> encloses the affected characters in
          order to avoid ambiguities regarding which part of the token refers to which variant. If
          there were two or more variants inside the same token, then the <gi>seg</gi> element would
          contain a <att>corresp</att> attribute whose value would be the ID of the variant. When
          there are additional elements that provide the required semantics for the identification
          of the characters related to the variant, the use of <gi>seg</gi> is avoided (see in <ptr
            type="crossref" target="#example5"/> how the variants related to the use of
          abbreviations are encoded with specific markup which prevents any possible ambiguity).
          This strategy allows an accurate retrieval of any instance of the phenomena defined in the
          taxonomy.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="analyses">
        <head>Additional Analyses</head>
        <p>One of the functions that the variant taxonomy can fulfill in the publication of the
          edition is the provision of an accurate description for each textual variant. One way to
          explore the use of the taxonomy is through enhancing the edition by using visual cues to
          define the type of variant. <figure xml:id="figure1">
            <graphic url="images/figure1.png" height="685px" width="468px"/>
            <head type="legend">HTML edition sample</head>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>The screenshot presented in <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure1"/> shows two lines of
          the edition of one of the compositions of my corpus. I have used the higher categories to
          color-code the variants: graphic variants are bold, linguistic ones are indigo, errors are
          red, and equipollent readings are underlined. The use of colors is complemented with
          tooltips, so there is no information that it is only conveyed through color. If we click
          on any of the variants, we retrieve their more specific descriptions, that is, the
          contents of <code>f[@name eq "description"]</code>, as shown in <ptr type="crossref"
            target="#figure2"/>
          <figure xml:id="figure2">
            <graphic url="images/figure2.png" height="736px" width="663px"/>
            <head type="legend">HTML edition sample</head>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>In the same way that we access the different hierarchies of the taxonomy to enrich the
          edition, we can query the textual variants.</p>
        <p>For instance, we can create a web form following the classification of the different
          subcategories. This would allow us to explore the frequencies of these variants in the
          corpus (<ptr type="crossref" target="#figure3"/>). This type of approach makes it possible
          to study each variation phenomenon by calculating its distribution according to witness
          and scribe, by period of composition, and, of course, by analyzing all its occurrences in
          the corpus (<ptr type="crossref" target="#figure4"/>). <figure xml:id="figure3">
            <graphic url="images/figure3.png" height="769px" width="709px"/>
            <head type="legend">HTML web form of variation phenomena</head>
          </figure>
          <figure xml:id="figure4">
            <graphic url="images/figure4.png" height="1182px" width="696px"/>
            <head type="legend">Results after selecting a phenomenon</head>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>The strong hierarchical organization of feature structures allows us to access
          efficiently any of the layers of data used in its definition. For example, considering the
          structure of the taxonomy partially declared in <ptr type="crossref" target="#example4"/>,
          it might be of interest to retrieve all instances of a linguistic variant related to a
          phonetic change and compare them numerically to variation related to morphological
          change.</p>
        <p>However, the full potential of feature structures becomes clearer with complex queries.
          Consider, for example, the corpus of syllabic verse compositions mentioned earlier. In
          such a tradition it would be important to be able to retrieve all lines in which either a
          linguistic variant or a divergent reading would result in a change in the number of
          syllables. Such composite queries could determine which linguistic phenomena are likely to
          represent innovations according to whether they provoke a metrical irregularity, and they
          could detect a correlation among linguistic phenomena and consequential
            <term>emendationes</term>.</p>
        <p>Complex queries can be implemented with a small piece of code such as the one presented
          in <ptr type="crossref" target="#example6"/>. First, I look in the taxonomy for the
          feature structure IDs in whose definition there are features that would alter the number
          of syllables: those containing the element <gi>symbol</gi> with the attribute values
            <val>addition</val> or <val>repetition</val> (the <code>$additionPhenomena</code>
          variable) or those with the <val>reduction</val> and <val>omission</val> values
            (<code>$reductionPhenomena</code> variable). These include both linguistic variants and
          scribal errors. Then I look for all lines of the corpus that contain <gi>rdg</gi> elements
          with at least one reference to each of these two groupings of variant typologies. <figure
            xml:id="example6">
            <eg> declare namespace tei = "http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"; declare variable $lines as
              node()+ := collection('/db/edition')//tei:div[@type eq 'poem']//tei:l; declare
              variable $features as node()+ := doc('/db/feature-library.xml')//tei:fvLib/tei:fs;
              declare variable $additionPhenomena as xs:string+ := $features[.//tei:symbol/@value =
              ('addition', 'repetition')]/concat('#', @xml:id); declare variable $reductionPhenomena
              as xs:string+ := $features[.//tei:symbol/@value = ('reduction',
              'omission')]/concat('#', @xml:id); for $line in $lines[descendant::tei:rdg[some $ana
              in tokenize(@ana, '\s+') satisfies $ana = $reductionPhenomena]] return
              $line[descendant::tei:rdg[some $ana in tokenize(@ana, '\s+') satisfies $ana =
              $additionPhenomena]] </eg>
            <head type="legend">Query for combining features</head>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>Such queries retrieve occurrences like the one presented in <ptr type="crossref"
            target="#example5"/>, an authentic example of my corpus in which a linguistic phenomenon
          might have motivated the scribe to correct the contents of the line in order to regularize
          the metric pattern. In this line (<q>Yet, I always loved her more</q>) there is a
          linguistic phenomenon that creates an extra syllable, the palatalization of the past stem
          of an irregular verb, which requires a paragogic vowel for pronunciation
            (<mentioned>quige</mentioned> versus <mentioned>quis</mentioned>). The witness that does
          not contain this phenomenon presents extra textual content, the monosyllabic word
            <mentioned>muj</mentioned>, which has an emphatic sense and is therefore omissible
          without changing the denotative meaning of the line. A plausible hypothesis for explaining
          this variation is that <q>quige</q> is an innovation that motivated a conscious omission
          of <q>muj</q> in order to maintain the correct number of syllables per verse. These
          nonaccidental omissions or additions are effectively retrieved when the description of
          linguistic phenomena includes a feature that mentions the addition or reduction of
          phonemes (as seen in the sample presented in <ptr type="crossref" target="#example4"/>),
          which enables us to construct queries that look for the co-occurrence of those types of
          variation with variants related to the textual content.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="conclusions">
        <head>Conclusions</head>
        <p>Variation is a complex and multifaceted issue. For that reason, a hierarchical model
          based on the accumulation and nesting of layers of information and able to represent any
          concepts that depend on categories, subcategories, and even the overlapping of categories
          is necessary for representing all of these nuances.</p>
        <p>The examples presented in this paper were modeled based on a specific project and its
          research questions,<note>The working hypothesis of the aforementioned project entailed a
            quantitative analysis of linguistic variants to provide evidence that the concentration
            of certain archaisms on the one hand and innovations on the other will depict the
            different stages in the compilation of textual materials. The objects of study were
            medieval songbooks and the transmission of the particular tradition under analysis is
            based on the reuniting of smaller songbooks that were disseminated independently before
            creating the preserved compilations.</note> but the intention was to present a more
          general method through a particular application. Nevertheless, the tradition used for
          exemplification is quite homogeneous and the maximum number of witnesses for the same
          piece of text is three. This means that a semantic correspondence presented through the
          use of an attribute in the edition whose value points to the taxonomy might not be
          suitable for more complex traditions. However, alternative stand-off methods should
          overcome those limitations. This will be one of the focus points in the future development
          of a more solid editorial model whose defining feature will be its aptness for descriptive
          and quantitative analyses of textual variants. Following the distinction made by Jannidis
          and Flanders (<ref type="bibl" target="#jannidis13">2013</ref>), the future work will
          entail the transformation of an egoistic modeling, designed for a specific research
          question, to an altruistic one.</p>
        <p>In spite of its limitations, the core of the methodology presented here might be of
          interest for other projects. The creation of a variant taxonomy encoded using the feature
          structures model is a flexible method which brings multiple advantages for textual
          scholarship. On the one hand, a granular definition of variation phenomena whose
          information can be embedded later into the edition entails a descriptive model that helps
          the user browse through the witnesses’ readings. On the other hand, it enables
          quantitative analyses with greater precision and efficiency.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="banski10"><author>Bański, Piotr</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title
              level="a">Why TEI Stand-off Annotation Doesn’t Quite Work: And Why You Might Want to
              Use It Nevertheless.</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup
              Conference 2010</title>. <series>Balisage Series on Markup Technologies</series>, vol.
              <biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.4242/BalisageVol5.Banski01</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cerquiglini89"><author>Cerquiglini, Bernard</author>. <date>1989</date>.
              <title level="m">Éloge de la variante: Histoire critique de la philologie</title>.
              <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>Éditions du Seuil</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="chiesa02"><author>Chiesa, Paolo</author>. <date>2002</date>. <title
              level="m">Elementi di critica testuale</title>. <pubPlace>Bologna</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Pàtron Editore</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="colwell64"><author>Colwell, E. C.</author>, and <author>E. W. Tune</author>.
              <date>1964</date>. <title level="a">Variant Readings: Classification and Use</title>.
              <title level="j">Journal of Biblical Literature</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">253–61</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
            >10.2307/3264283</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ide04"><author>Ide, Nancy</author>, and <author>Laurent Romary</author>.
              <date>2004</date>. <title level="a">International Standard for a Linguistic Annotation
              Framework</title>. <title level="j">Natural Language Engineering</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">3–4</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">211–25</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1017/S135132490400350X</idno>. <ptr
              target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S135132490400350X"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="italia15"><author>Italia, Paola</author>, <author>Fabio Vitali</author>, and
              <author>Angelo Di Iorio</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title level="a">Variants and
              Versioning Between Textual Bibliography and Computer Science</title>. In <title
              level="m">Proceedings of the Third AIUCD Annual Conference on Humanities and Their
              Methods in the Digital Ecosystem</title> (AIUCD ’14). <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>ACM</publisher>. doi:<idno type="doi"
            >10.1145/2802612.2802614</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jakobson71"><author>Jakobson, Roman</author>. <date>1971</date>. <title
              level="m">Selected Writings</title>. Vol. <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>,
              <title level="m">Phonological Studies</title>. <pubPlace>The Hague</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Mouton</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jannidis13"><author>Jannidis, Fotis</author>, and <author>Julia
              Flanders</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a">A Concept of Data Modeling for
              the Humanities</title>. In <title level="m">Digital Humanities 2013: Conference
              Abstracts</title>, <biblScope unit="page">237–39</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Lincoln,
              NE</pubPlace>: <publisher>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</publisher>.
              <ptr target="http://dh2013.unl.edu/abstracts/ab-313.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="maas58"><author>Maas, Paul</author>. <date>1958</date>. <title level="m"
              >Textual Criticism</title>. <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Clarendon
              Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mace12"><author>Macé, Caroline</author>, <author>Ilse De Vos</author>, and
              <author>Koen Geuten</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">Comparing
              Stemmatological and Phylogenetic Methods to Understand the Transmission History of the
                <soCalled>Florilegium Coislinianum</soCalled>.</title> In <title level="m">Ars
              Edendi</title> Lecture Series, edited by <editor>Alessandra Bucossi</editor> and
              <editor>Erika Kihlman</editor>, <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>:<biblScope
              unit="page">107–29</biblScope>. Studia Latina Stockholmiensia 58.
              <pubPlace>Stockholm</pubPlace>: <publisher>Stockholm University Library</publisher>.
              urn:<idno type="urn">nbn:se:su:diva-79673</idno>; PDF available at <ptr
              target="http://www.diva-portal.org/smash/get/diva2:551286/FULLTEXT01.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mink00"><author>Mink, Gerd</author>. <date>2000</date>. <title level="a"
              >Editing and Genealogical Studies: The New Testament.</title>
            <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">51–56</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1093/llc/15.1.51</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pose14"><author>Pose, Javier</author>, <author>Patrice Lopez</author>, and
              <author>Laurent Romary</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">A Generic
              Formalism for Encoding Stand-off Annotations in TEI</title>. <ptr
              target="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01061548"/>, version 1.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="romary15"><author>Romary, Laurent</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title
              level="u">Standards for Language Resources in ISO — Looking Back at 13 Fruitful
              Years.</title>
            <ptr target="https://arxiv.org/abs/1510.07851"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="segre95"><author>Segre, Cesare</author>. <date>1995</date>. <title level="a"
              >Critique des variantes et critique génétique</title>. <title level="j">Genesis
              (Manuscrits-Recherche-Invention)</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">29–45</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.3406/item.1995.994</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="TEI16"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2016</date>. <title
              level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>.
              <edition>Version 3.1.0</edition>. Last updated December 15. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
              target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="trovato14"><author>Trovato, Paolo</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title
              level="m">Everything You Always Wanted to Know about Lachmann’s Method. A Non-Standard
              Handbook of Genealogical Textual Criticism in the Age of Post-Structuralism,
              Cladistics, and Copy-Text</title>. <pubPlace>Padova</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>libreriauniversitaria.it</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="witt09"><author>Witt, Andreas</author>, and <author>Jens Stegmann</author>.
              <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">TEI Feature Structures as a Representation Format
              for Multiple Annotation and Generic XML Documents</title>. In <title level="m"
              >Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</title>. <series>Balisage Series
              on Markup Technologies</series>, vol. <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>. doi:<idno
              type="doi">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Stegmann01</idno>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
