<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-11-intro-source.xml 975 2020-06-25 09:46:19Z ron $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Editorial Introduction to Issue 11 of the Journal of the Text Encoding
          Initiative</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Claudia</forename>
            <surname>Resch</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Claudia Resch is a <roleName>senior researcher</roleName> and
              <roleName>project leader at the Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</roleName>
            (ACDH) of the <orgName>Austrian Academy of Sciences</orgName>. Her current research
            focuses on German literature of the early modern period and the application of literary
            and linguistic computing in a corpus-based approach to textual issues. Key areas covered
            are historical linguistics, text stylistics, and annotation problems associated with
            non-standard varieties of early modern German. Since 2012 Claudia Resch has been a
              <roleName>lecturer</roleName> in the Department for German Philology of the
              <orgName>Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität</orgName> in Munich, where she teaches digital
            approaches to textual sources.</affiliation>
          <email>claudia.resch@oeawac.at</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Tanja</forename>
            <surname>Wissik</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Tanja Wissik is a <roleName>senior researcher</roleName> at the ACDH of the
              <orgName>Austrian Academy of Sciences</orgName> and <roleName>teaches</roleName> at
            the Department of Translation Studies of the <orgName>University of Graz</orgName>. She
            works on numerous national and international research projects in the field of language
            resources and digital humanities. Her research interests include digital language
            resources and technologies, especially terminological resources and corpora, workflow
            research, variational linguistics, and the teaching of DH technologies and
            methods.</affiliation>
          <email>tanja.wissik@oeawac.at</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Vanessa</forename>
            <surname>Hannesschläger</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Vanessa Hannesschläger is a <roleName>researcher</roleName> at the Austrian
            Centre for Digital Humanities of the <orgName>Austrian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
            (ACDH-OEAW), where she is responsible for legal issues. She is involved in several
            projects in which she works on data modeling, on digital editing, and in the outreach
            department. In addition, she is completing her PhD with the German department of the
            University of Vienna. Her research interests include legal frameworks of digital
            research, biography theory, archive theory, modern Austrian literature, and the
            contemporary developments of gender issues in society. For more information, please
            visit <ptr target="https://vanessahannesschlaeger.wordpress.com/"/>.</affiliation>
          <email>vanessa.hannesschlaeger@oeaw.ac.at</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>25/05/2020</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Claudia Resch</editor>
        <editor role="guest managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Vanessa Hannesschlaeger</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo (Universität Hamburg)</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia (Newcastle University)</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="11">Selected Papers from the 2016 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Revues.org -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="editorialIntroduction">
        <p>It is with great pleasure that we present another issue of the <title level="j">Journal
            of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> with papers selected from the sixteenth annual
          TEI Conference and Members’ Meeting, which was hosted by the Austrian Academy of Sciences
          in Vienna in 2016.</p>
        <p>This issue illustrates the variety of research that is being done within the TEI
          community. The call for papers was issued by the Program Committee without limitation to a
          specific topic. Participants submitted proposals reflecting their wide range of interests,
          disciplines, and fields of research, opening a huge range of possible approaches.</p>
        <p>The open call brought almost two hundred participants to Vienna to enjoy a rich <ref
            target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/MembersMeetings/2016/program.html">conference
            program</ref><note><ptr
              target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/MembersMeetings/2016/program.html"/></note> comprising
          thirty-eight papers, seventeen posters, five workshops, and four demos, which are
          described in the <ref target="https://tei2016app.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">Book of
              Abstracts</ref>.<note><ptr target="https://tei2016app.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/"/>.</note> The
          conference opened with a keynote address, and continued in seventeen plenary or parallel
          sessions, a poster session, and four special interest group meetings. As we write these
          introductory lines—at a time when conference attendance and travel have been limited by a
          global health crisis—we think back to the conference’s social program, review the
          light-hearted photos, and are reminded of how joyful this meeting was and how enduring to
          the present moment are the connections and encounters that were made by researchers who
          came from all over the world.</p>
        <p>TEI 2016 was also a conference of openness. Following the local committee´s suggestion,
          for the first time all abstracts—both digital and print—were published under a Creative
          Commons Attribution license (CC-BY 4.0). This innovation was adopted at a time when
          openness was not quite as established within the humanities community as it is today. Such
          a policy allows both authors and readers (as stated) to redistribute and adapt each
          other’s work as long as the creators are credited, greatly helping to sustain the work of
          the TEI community and keeping it at the edge of current research trends.</p>
        <p>The selection of the six papers in this issue are an immediate result of this open sky
          policy, and reflect the wealth and diversity of topics the TEI community is currently
          engaged in. As we prepared the volume, we realized the difficulty in finding a planned,
          coherent order, so we opted for a loose sequence:</p>
        <p>Claudia Resch, Daniel Schopper, Tanja Wissik, and Daniela Fasching give an overview of
          the digitization process of a collection of early modern broadsheets from Vienna with
          particular emphasis on the encoding scheme.</p>
        <p>Vanessa Hannesschläger discusses the concept of copyright in the context of global laws.
          She argues that open licenses are vital for ensuring the sustainability of (digital)
          research data and she showcases the transformation of the abstracts of the TEI2016
          conference as an example of how proper licensing can advance research.</p>
        <p>Helena Bermúdez Sabel describes a method for encoding textual variants that allows the
          editor to include multiple layers of information in each apparatus tagset.</p>
        <p>Anja Morgenstern and Agnes Amminger report on the project of editing the early <title
            level="m">Biographie W. A. Mozart’s</title> (1828) by Georg Nikolaus Nissen.</p>
        <p>Meridith Beck Mink, Michelle Dalmau, Wallace Hooper, William R. Newman, James R. Voelkel,
          and John A. Walsh describe the Chymistry of Isaac Newton Project, with special attention
          to the encoding of the citations and references. </p>
        <p>Nils Geißler and Daniela Schulz describe the building of a collaborative editorial
          workbench for legal texts with complex structures.</p>
        <p>There are many persons to whom the guest editors of the present issue wish to express
          their gratitude. We should like to take the opportunity to thank all those who were
          involved in preparing this volume: the members of the editorial board, who engaged in the
          process and offered essential advice, as well as the authors, who submitted their papers,
          diligently revised them for publication, and provided a high level of professionalism and
          commitment.</p>
        <p>Enjoy the reading.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
