<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-cc-pn-dalmau-139-source.xml 931 2020-04-15 22:17:29Z ron $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Encoding Newton’s Alchemical Library</title>
        <title type="sub">Integrating Traditional Bibliographic and Modern Computational
          Methods</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Meridith</forename>
            <surname>Beck Mink</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Meridith Beck Mink is the <roleName>Constellations program
              coordinator</roleName> at the <orgName>University of Wisconsin–Madison</orgName> and a
              <roleName>freelance consultant</roleName>. She was a postdoctoral fellow specializing
            in data curation for early modern studies at Indiana University, where she contributed
            to the bibliography of the Chymistry of Isaac Newton project and consulted on digital
            scholarship in the Scholars’ Commons. She has taught at Knox College and in Galesburg,
            Illinois, and was the lead researcher on the Council for Library and Information
            Resources’assessment of the National Digital Stewardship Residency (<ptr
              target="https://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub173"/>).</affiliation>
          <email>meribecks@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Michelle</forename>
            <surname>Dalmau</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Michelle Dalmau is an <roleName>associate librarian</roleName> and
              <roleName>head of Digital Collections Services</roleName> (DCS) at the
              <orgName>Indiana University Libraries</orgName> and <roleName>co-director</roleName>
            for the Institute for Digital Arts &amp; Humanities (IDAH), a research center of the
            Office of the Vice Provost for Research, <orgName>Indiana University
              Bloomington</orgName>. As head of DCS, Michelle manages and coordinates digital
            library services for the Libraries and affiliated cultural heritage organizations across
            all IU campuses. As co-director for IDAH, Michelle fosters the development of digital
            arts and humanities infrastructure projects and initiatives through outreach,
            collaborative research and creative pursuits, consultation, professional development,
            and credit-bearing programs. Along with Beck Mink, Dalmau managed the bibliography
            component for the <title level="m">Chymistry of Isaac Newton</title>
            project.</affiliation>
          <email/>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Wallace</forename>
            <surname>Hooper</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Wallace Hooper is the <roleName>project manager</roleName> and
              <roleName>programmer/analyst</roleName> of the <orgName>Chymistry of Isaac Newton
              Project</orgName>, <roleName>assistant scientist/scholar</roleName> in the Department
            of History and Philosophy of Science and Medicine at <orgName>Indiana
              University</orgName>, and <roleName>co–principal investigator</roleName> with William
            R. Newman of NSF Project 1556846, <title level="m">Multidimensional Chronological
              Analysis of Manuscript Corpora Using Isaac Newton’s Chymical Papers as a Test
              Platform</title>. He holds a PhD in history and philosophy of science from Indiana
            University. He held two postdoctoral fellowships at the Museum of the History of Science
            in Florence, 1992–93 and 1995–96, where he attempted to establish the order of
            composition of the fragmentary notes on motion using analysis of concepts, orthographic
            changes, watermark distributions, and the elemental analysis of inks by proton-induced
            X-ray emissions (PIXE).</affiliation>
          <email>whooper@indiana.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>William R.</forename>
            <surname>Newman</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>William R. Newman <roleName>teaches</roleName> in the Department of History
            and Philosophy of <orgName>Science at Indiana University</orgName>. Most of his career
            has focused on the history of alchemy and chymistry (the expanded, early modern version
            of the field), premodern matter theory, and the long debate about the powers of art and
            nature that alchemy helped to perpetuate. Newman is general editor of the Chymistry of
            Isaac Newton project (<ptr target="http://www.chymistry.org"/>), which is editing
            Newton’s chymical papers and replicating his processes where possible. His book <title
              level="m">Newton the Alchemist</title> was recently published by Princeton University
            Press.</affiliation>
          <email>wnewman@iu.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>James R.</forename>
            <surname>Voelkel</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>James R. Voelkel is <roleName>curator of rare books</roleName> at the Other
            Library of Chemical History at the <orgName>Chemical Heritage Foundation</orgName>, and
              <roleName>senior consulting editor</roleName> at the <orgName>Chymistry of Isaac
              Newton project</orgName>. He holds a PhD in history of science from Indiana
            University, and a Certificate of Proficiency in Bibliography from the Rare Book School
            at the University of Virginia, Charlottesville. His research interests are in early
            modern science and the history of the book. He is the author of <title level="m">The
              Composition of Kepler’s</title> Astronomia nova (Princeton University Press, 2001) and
              <title level="m">Johannes Kepler and the New Astronomy</title> (Oxford University
            Press, 1999).</affiliation>
          <email>jvoelkel@chemheritage.org</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>John A.</forename>
            <surname>Walsh</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>John A. Walsh is an <roleName>associate professor</roleName> in the School of
            Informatics and Computing at <orgName>Indiana University</orgName>. His research
            involves the application of digital and computational methods to the study of literary
            and historical documents. Walsh is an editor of digital scholarly editions (<ptr
              target="http://petrarchive.org"/>, <ptr target="http://swinburneproject.org"/>, and
              <ptr target="http://chymistry.org"/>). He developed the Comic Book Markup Language
            (CBML) (<ptr target="http://www.cbml.org/"/>) for scholarly encoding of comics and
            graphic novels and TEI Boilerplate (<ptr target="http://teiboilerplate.org/"/>) for
            publishing TEI documents on the web. Walsh’s research interests include digital and
            computational literary studies; textual studies and bibliography; text technologies;
            book history; nineteenth-century British literature, poetry, and poetics; and comic
            books. <ptr target="https://github.com/paregorios/Zotero-RDF-to-TEI-XML"
            />.</affiliation>
          <email>jawalsh@indiana.edu</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>18/02/2020</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Claudia Resch</editor>
        <editor role="guest managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Vanessa Hannesschlaeger</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo (Universität Hamburg)</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia (Newcastle University)</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="11">Selected Papers from the 2016 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals
          in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish
          full-text articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>bibliography</term>
          <term>alchemy</term>
          <term>quasi-facsimile transcription</term>
          <term>Zotero</term>
          <term>latent semantic analysis</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2020-04-15">Ron Van den Branden applied authors’ proofing corrections.</change>
      <change when="2020-02-14">Ron Van den Branden encoded the file.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>The <title level="m">Chymistry of Isaac Newton</title> (<ptr
            target="http://chymistry.org"/>) project team has digitized and encoded, following the
          TEI Guidelines, the complete corpus of Newton’s alchemical manuscripts, which total more
          than two thousand pages and over one million words. Newton cited more than five thousand
          published and unpublished works in these manuscripts; many of his annotations reference
          items in his own library, as he was an exceptionally dedicated reader of alchemical texts.
          Newton’s extensive citations and annotations provide a window into his alchemical research
          and practices, and serve as the basis for our authoritative bibliography of his alchemical
          sources. The bibliography is being developed as both a stand-alone reference work and an
          integrated resource with the alchemical manuscripts, providing additional context for
          Newton’s citations and florilegia. Once finished, the bibliography will provide complete,
          structured citations—which often would appear very abbreviated or incomplete in the
          manuscripts—that can be formatted to comply with modern bibliographic conventions and
          bibliographic management systems. Our bibliography will also link to digitized online
          versions of the source texts available through Early English Books Online, HathiTrust
          Digital Library, and other digital repositories. The citations include quasi-facsimile
          title page transcription, a technique used for bibliographic description of rare books, to
          enable richer forms of citation analysis. By analyzing the citations, we will be able to
          date Newton’s manuscripts, cluster manuscripts that cite the same or related sources, and,
          ultimately, generate network graphs that will reveal connections between the cited authors
          and texts and how they influence Newton’s own ideas and work.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="introduction">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>Best known for his contributions to gravitational theory, calculus, and optics, Newton
          was also a serious student and practitioner of alchemy. His library was full of dog-eared
          alchemical books and manuscripts, and he wrote and transcribed close to a million words on
          the subject, although he never published any of them. His notes and unfinished manuscripts
          contained over five thousand references to alchemical texts and practices (<ptr
            type="crossref" target="#figure1"/>). Newton even employed his own citation methods
          within his manuscripts and notes. It is unusual to see this level of specificity in
          citation practices in the seventeenth century. <figure xml:id="figure1">
            <graphic url="images/figure1.jpg" height="1415px" width="1200px"/>
            <head type="legend">Manuscript excerpt with citations from Isaac Newton, Keynes MS. 30/1
              (King’s College Library, Cambridge University), page image 3r in the Chymistry of
              Isaac Newton, edited by William R. Newman, 2005–, accessed December 13, 2019, <ptr
                target="http://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/newton/ALCH00200"/>.</head>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>In an effort to better understand Newton’s alchemical scholarship—as well as the study of
          alchemy in the seventeenth century more broadly—our team seeks to reconstruct, from the
          fragmentary citations in his personal papers, a comprehensive list, with more complete
          bibliographic information, of the hundreds of alchemical texts that Newton read and
          referenced. This work is meant as a complement to the larger <title level="m">Chymistry of
            Isaac Newton</title> (<ptr target="http://chymistry.org"/>) project,which began in 2003
          with a focus on transcribing and TEI-encoding the complete corpus of Newton’s alchemical
          manuscripts, which total more than two thousand pages and over one million words. Along
          with a scholarly edition of diplomatic and normalized transcriptions and facsimile page
          images of Newton’s alchemy, the <title level="m">Chymistry of Isaac Newton</title> project
          also includes pedagogical resources primarily focused on recreating experiments, including
          a lab unit that features video recordings of reenacted experiments, and online tools that
          include reference works and a Latent Semantic Analysis Tool to enable a deeper
          understanding of Newton’s writings.</p>
        <p>Our aim is to produce a comprehensive bibliography that accurately represents Newton’s
          extensive alchemical reading and research, identifying his sources down to the specific
          edition of the printed texts he referenced. Once completed, Newton’s alchemical
          bibliography will: <list rend="inline ordered">
            <item>assist us in dating Newton’s manuscripts;</item>
            <item>allow for the clustering of manuscripts that cite the same or related sources;
              and, ultimately,</item>
            <item>generate network graphs that will reveal connections between the cited authors and
              texts and how they influence Newton’s own ideas and work</item>
          </list>.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="bibliography">
        <head>The Bibliography</head>
        <p>The methods for generating Newton’s alchemical bibliography required traditional
          bibliographic research as well as compiling and encoding the bibliography following the
          TEI P5 Guidelines (<ref type="bibl" target="#tei17">TEI Consortium 2017</ref>).</p>
        <div xml:id="biblref">
          <head>Tracing the Bibliographic References</head>
          <p>The team started the bibliography by simply identifying and tagging citations to
            printed works and manuscripts in Newton’s alchemical papers. To date we have located
            over five thousand citations, which have been encoded with <gi>bibl</gi> elements that
            will all soon point to the full citation in the bibliography using the
              <att>corresp</att> attribute (<ptr type="crossref" target="#figure2"/>). As part of
            the process of tracing the citations and adding the corresponding link to the main entry
            in the bibliography, the project team will also be checking to make sure all citations
            are tagged. We do have a few manuscripts that were published without the <gi>bibl</gi>
            tagging so we expect the total number of citations to grow to considerably over five
            thousand as we revisit the corpus. <figure xml:id="figure2">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <p><del rend="strike" hand="#in"><g ref="#UNx263f">☿</g><hi rend="super"><choice>
                        <orig>ij</orig>
                        <reg>ii</reg>
                      </choice></hi></del>
                  <add place="supralinear" rend="caret">lapidis</add> pro ejus solutione seu
                  liquefactione in decoctione<lb/> ab albedine ad rubedinem <bibl>Philal on Ripl. G
                    p. <add place="supralinear">61, 62,</add> 180, 365.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Artef p 5 lin 12</bibl><lb/></p>
                <p><del rend="strike" hand="#in">lapidis</del> vel Ceratio lapidis pro ejus
                  liquefactione <add place="supralinear" rend="caret">&amp; ablutione</add> post
                  nigredinem <bibl>Flammel annot<lb/> p 770.</bibl><lb/></p>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">Example of encoded citations provided by Newton using the
                  <gi>bibl</gi> tag.</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>The tagging was the easy part. Next, identifying exactly what Newton was referring to
            in each of these citations was a meticulous process requiring detective work by several
            specialists—subject experts and rare books and special collections librarians. Newton’s
            citations were often fragmentary because he used abbreviated notes intended for himself.
            Considering that he was working before formal citation practices were developed, his
            references are remarkably consistent and clear to the modern reader. That said, in some
            cases we were able to see that Newton was referencing <emph>something</emph>—page
            numbers and abbreviations to titles—but exactly what he was citing, as in <ptr
              type="crossref" target="#figure3"/>, is not immediately obvious. <figure
              xml:id="figure3">
              <graphic url="images/figure3.png" height="274px" width="867px"/>
              <head type="legend">Manuscript with citation missing a page number, Isaac Newton,
                Portsmouth Add. MS. 3975, page image 16v in the Chymistry of Isaac Newton, edited by
                William R. Newman, 2005–, accessed December 16, 2019, <ptr
                  target="http://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/newton/ALCH00110"/>.</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>For example, Newton used the term <soCalled>Th. Ch.</soCalled> to refer to the <title
              level="m">Theatrum Chemicum</title>, a multivolume compilation containing a multitude
            of alchemical tracts, which he cited numerous times throughout his manuscripts. Newton
            referenced a handful of other collections as well as the <title level="m">Theatrum
              Chemicum</title>, such as the <title level="m">Artis Auriferae</title>, published
            several times in ever-expanding form during the sixteenth and early seventeenth
            centuries, and the <title level="m">Musaeum Hermeticum</title>, another work that grew
            over time as it was republished. We compiled the tables of contents for each of these
            collections to properly identify the individual tracts that Newton referenced. The
            project team agreed to enter referenced tracts as individual entries in the bibliography
            with a complete citation to the anthologized source. Newton occasionally cited
              <soCalled>second hand</soCalled> references in which he would attribute something to
            one author that was actually stated by another author. Clarifying this is critical for
            pointing to the correct reference from the alchemical manuscripts.</p>
          <p>Bibliographic tagging of the manuscripts also allowed us to do a rudimentary text
            analysis to study the words that frequently occurred in the citations. After generating
            the output of the existing <gi>bibl</gi>s encoded in the manuscripts, we used the <ref
              target="http://tapor.ca/">TAPoRware Text Analysis Tool</ref><note>TAPoRware Text
              Analysis Tool: <ptr target="http://tapor.ca/"/>.</note> and the <ref
              target="https://voyant-tools.org">Voyant Tools</ref><note>Votantes Tools: <ptr
                target="https://voyant-tools.org"/>.</note> to check for frequency of terms and
            distribution of terms across the corpus. This allowed us to determine that Newton’s most
            frequently cited text was George Starkey’s <title level="m">Secrets Reveal’d,</title>
            published posthumously in 1669, a result which provided quantitative evidence that
            Newton had studied this work carefully. Starkey, writing under the pseudonym Eirenaeus
            Philalethes, was irregularly cited by Newton as philal.philaletha, philal, philos, and
            other variants. In addition, running the citations through the text analysis tools
            confirmed the degree to which name variants would benefit from normalization through the
            compilation of the bibliography. The text analysis also showed that Newton frequently
            cited George Ripley, a well-known fifteenth-century British alchemist, and Raymond Lull,
            a thirteenth-century philosopher, among others (<ptr type="crossref" target="@figure4"
            />). <figure xml:id="figure4">
              <graphic url="images/figure4.png" height="498px" width="900px"/>
              <head type="legend">Visualization generated with Voyant Tools and a concordance
                generated with the TAPoRware Text Analysis Tool of approximately 5,000 bibliographic
                citations encoded in the Newton alchemical corpus revealing most cited authors and
                issues with name variants.</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>Newton’s alchemical manuscripts reflect not only his own original work, but the work of
            other scholars, alchemists, and philosophers. By compiling an authoritative
            bibliography, we are able to correctly attribute the paraphrases, quotes, or
            transcriptions of long passages that appear in Newton’s alchemical manuscripts, as well
            as the extent to which Newton drew from other authors.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="buildingbibl">
          <head>Building the Bibliography</head>
          <p>Owing to the iterative nature of the process of compiling the bibliography, which
            required extensive research, the project team decided to use <ref
              target="https://www.zotero.org">Zotero</ref><note>Zotero: <ptr
                target="https://www.zotero.org"/>.</note> because of the ease of data entry and
            availability of the Zotero-to-TEI XSLT stylesheet as an initial way to generate the
            bibliography.</p>
          <p>A key resource for building our bibliography was John Harrison’s <title level="m">The
              Library of Isaac Newton</title> (<ref type="bibl" target="#harrison78">1978</ref>),
            which is the most comprehensive catalog of Newton’s working library. It lists the
            approximately 2,100 volumes of books and manuscripts in Newton’s possession when he died
            in 1727. While the catalog captures the whole of Newton’s library, Harrison did not
            necessarily record precise bibliographic information. Therefore, we also consulted John
            Ferguson’s <title level="m">Bibliotheca Chemica: A Catalogue of the Alchemical, Chemical
              and Pharmaceutical Books in the Collection of the Late James Young of Kelly and
              Durris</title> (<ref type="bibl" target="#ferguson06">1906</ref>) for clarification
              (<ptr type="crossref" target="#figure5"/>). The citations compiled in Zotero retain a
            reference to Harrison by recording the identifier system Harrison himself devised (i.e.,
            [H11]) and include supplemental information provided by Harrison when appropriate.</p>
          <p>Once the correct editions were identified, metadata were often imported from cataloging
            systems, especially WorldCat records in addition to catalog records from the Chemical
            Heritage Foundation and the University of Wisconsin, both of which hold important early
            modern alchemical monograph collections, to ensure the most complete bibliographic
            metadata. The metadata were either corrected or enriched following the guidelines
            provided by <title level="m">Descriptive Cataloging of Rare Materials</title> (<ref
              type="bibl" target="#dcrm07">2007</ref>) (known earlier as <title level="m"
              >Descriptive Cataloging of Rare Books</title>), or DCRM(B), Bowers’s <title level="m"
              >Principles of Bibliographic Description</title> (<ref type="bibl" target="#bowers05"
              >2005</ref>, ch. 4), and Gaskell’s <title level="m">A New Introduction to
              Bibliography</title> (<ref type="bibl" target="#gaskell72">1972, 321–35</ref>).
              <figure xml:id="figure5">
              <graphic url="images/figure5.jpg" height="422px" width="753px"/>
              <head type="legend">Diagram representing the bibliographic research workflow for
                verifying Newton’s citations.</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <div xml:id="quasifacsimile">
            <head>Use of Quasi Facsimile Transcription</head>
            <p>Writing in the late seventeenth century, Newton typically referenced texts written
              and/or published during the fifteenth through seventeenth centuries. He also cited
              medieval sources, but these were usually reprinted in some of the contemporary printed
              editions and compilations in his library. According to print practice during the early
              modern period, all the bibliographic information about a work—such as author, date of
              publication, and place of publication—was contained on the title page. Title pages
              were critical to the Newton bibliography because we want to pinpoint as precisely as
              possible which edition or printing of a text Newton cited. This level of precision was
              important to the project team because the exact printing dates of the material Newton
              cited in his work allow us to better date when he was producing his alchemical
              manuscripts and to accurately identify his citations.</p>
            <p>However, the fine detail of these title pages is frequently garbled by modern
              bibliographic protocols; it is not uncommon, for instance, for catalogers to replace
              the original punctuation with modern punctuation. Moreover, the titles commonly used
              to refer to books of this period may bear little resemblance to the title as printed
              on the title page. To give an obvious example, Newton’s masterwork of gravitational
              theory is often referred to in brief as <soCalled>the <title level="m"
                  >Principia</title></soCalled>, the third word of its actual title, <title
                level="m">Philosophiae naturalis principia mathematica</title>. Harrison’s <title
                level="m">The Library of Isaac Newton</title> frequently abbreviates long-winded
              seventeenth-century titles, undoubtedly in the interest of conserving space, but at
              the same time creating the potential for confusion.</p>
            <p>In order to precisely record the fine nuances of an early-modern title page,
              bibliographers and catalogers have long used a method called <term>quasi-facsimile
                transcription (QFT)</term>. The goal of QFT—as it was put by Fredson Bowers, who
              clarified and codified its rules in his magisterial <title level="m">Principles of
                Bibliographical Description</title>—is <quote source="#quoteref1">bringing an absent
                book before the eye of the reader</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref1" type="bibl"
                target="#bowers05">2005</ref>). The method involves using a very specific set of
              rules to transcribe every letter, punctuation mark, rule, and page break on the title
              page, capturing as much detail as possible, down to the use of small caps and swash
              italics (<ptr type="crossref" target="#figure6"/>). <figure xml:id="figure6">
                <graphic url="images/figure6.png" height="764px" width="1376px"/>
                <head type="legend">Example of a title from the Theatrum Chemicum and accompanying
                  quasi-facsimile transcription.</head>
              </figure>
            </p>
            <p>Small variations in the title pages of books from this period are sometimes the only
              way to distinguish different editions or printings. Though there has long been debate
              among bibliographers over whether photographic title page facsimiles are superior to
              QFT, the method has undeniable advantages. For any encoding project, of course, QFT
              offers transparent searching. And there are in practice very few examples of title
              pages that were reset with such precision that QFT cannot distinguish one edition from
              another.</p>
            <p>To give one example from the project, Newton frequently cited Robert Boyle’s <title
                level="m">Some Considerations Touching the Usefulness of Experimental Natural
                Philosophy</title>. The book was originally published in Oxford in 1663. It was
              reprinted in 1664, listing the same Oxford printer (Henry Hall) and publisher (Richard
              Davis), but there is a note in the book that the edition was committed to several
              presses—not an uncommon practice in seventeenth-century English publishing—and the
              details of the printing suggest that half if not all of the printing was done in
              London. In 1671, Boyle issued a second volume of the book, at which time a reprint of
              the second edition of the first volume was made but still with the original
              publication information: Oxford, Henry Hall for Richard Davis, 1634. So, there are two
              versions of the second edition (of the first volume) with identical publication
              information, one published largely in London (not Oxford) in 1664, and one published
              in Oxford in 1671 (not 1664). As Fulton (<ref type="bibl" target="#fulton61">1961,
                38–41</ref>) notes, to make the problem of identification acute, these two editions
              can only be distinguished by three inconsistencies in the spelling and punctuation as
              seen in <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure7"/>, the one spelling <q>Naturall</q>
              with two l’s instead of one, with commas rather than periods after <q>philosophy</q>
              and <q>it</q>, and spelling <q>Ric: Davis</q> rather than <q>Ri: Davis</q>. Harrison’s
              citation for this book, as compiled in <title level="m">The Library of Isaac
                Newton</title> (<ref xml:id="quoteref2" type="bibl" target="#harrison78">1978,
                109</ref>), <quote source="#quoteref2">Some considerations touching the usefulnesse
                of experimental naturall philosophy... 2 vols. 4°, Oxford, 1664–1671</quote>, is
              utterly incapable of distinguishing which edition Newton might have owned. <figure
                xml:id="figure7">
                <graphic url="images/figure7.png" height="600px" width="879px"/>
                <head type="legend">Title pages from Robert Boyle’s Some Considerations Touching the
                  Usefulness of Experimental Natural Philosophy illustrating the nuances of
                  different editions, and how the act of quasi-facsimile transcription assists in
                  identifying the precise text that Newton referenced.</head>
              </figure>
            </p>
            <p>We used QFT in order to record the most accurate information possible about the texts
              Newton cited. We chose QFT over discrete TEI elements for representing bibliographic
              metadata found in the title pages mostly for practical reasons. It would have been too
              resource-intensive to reflect the typographic conventions of transcribing a title page
              from an early modern edition using TEI, and we did not want to break new ground given
              the well-established and widely accepted conventions of QFT. Using QFT consistently
              was essential to the bibliographic research process. Including the QFT in the TEI
              document, even if the title page elements were not granularly encoded, allows the team
              to maintain the TEI XML document as the authoritative source for the bibliography. The
              QFT transcription is encoded in the title element that is part of the
                <gi>biblStruct</gi> along with a supplied title to streamline metadata display for
              readability (<ptr type="crossref" target="#figure8"/>). <figure xml:id="figure8">
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book" xml:id="Boyle1672">
                      <monogr>
                        <title type="short">New Experiments, touching the relation betwixt flame and
                          air</title>
                        <title level="m"
                          ref="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/e/eebo2/A29057.0001.001?view=toc">TRACTS |
                          Written | By the Honourable | Robert Boyle, | CONTAINING | New
                          EXPERIMENTS, touching the | Relation betwixt Flame and Air. And about |
                          EXPLOSIONS. | An HYDROSTATICAL Di∫cour∫e oc- | ca∫ion'd by ∫ome Objections
                          of Dr. Henry More | again∫t ∫ome Explications of New Experiments | made by
                          the Author of the∫e Tracts: To which | is annex't, An Hydrostatical
                          Letter, dilucidating | an Experiment about a Way of Weighing Water | in
                          Water. | Of the Po∫itive or Relative Levity of Bo-| dies under Water. | Of
                          the Air's Spring on Bodies under | Water. | About the Differing Pre∫∫ure
                          of Heavy So- | lids and Fluids. | [Double Rule] | LONDON, | Printed for
                          Richard Davis, Book-∫eller in Oxon | M DC LXXII.</title>
                        <author><forename>Robert,</forename><surname>Boyle</surname></author>
                        <imprint>
                          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                          <publisher>Printed for R. Davis, book-seller in Oxon.</publisher>
                          <date>1672</date>
                        </imprint>
                      </monogr>
                      <note>[H275] __ Tracts, containing new experiments, touching the relation
                        betwixt flame and air. And about explosions. An hydrostatical discourse
                        occasion'd by some objections of Dr. Henry More ...  8°, London, 1672.  (A
                        few signs of dog-earing.) Tr/NQ.10.100   CHF   [Rare Book Storage QD27 .B695
                        1672]</note>
                      <note>not sure if url is to correct edition, MA</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                  </listBibl>
                </egXML>
                <head type="legend">Example of how QFT is captured in the TEI encoding.</head>
              </figure>
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="zotero2tei">
            <head>Zotero to TEI</head>
            <p>As mentioned earlier, we compiled the bulk of the bibliography using Zotero. Once the
              bibliography was close to completion, we exported the bibliography from Zotero to RDF,
              then used stylesheets provided by the TEI Community (available on GitHub<note>Code for
                robustly converting RDF Zotero exports to TEI XML bibliographies, latest commit on
                January 25, 2012,</note>) to convert from RDF to P4. Finally, another stylesheet was
              used to conform to the most current version of the TEI Guidelines, P5.</p>
            <p>The entries in the bibliography are grouped using a <gi>listBibl</gi> with individual
              citations in a <gi>biblStruct</gi> (<ptr type="crossref" target="#figure9"/>). The
              bibliography is still a work in progress as new <gi>bibl</gi> s are encoded in the
              manuscripts that cite sources not yet compiled. Those newer citations are shorthand
              encoded with a <gi>bibl</gi> and identifier so that the linking mechanism from the
              manuscripts to the bibliography can continue smoothly. Entries tagged with
                <gi>bibl</gi>s in the bibliography will be collocated and individually traced
              following the methodology detailed earlier. <figure xml:id="figure9">
                <graphic url="images/figure9.png" height="427px" width="482px"/>
                <head type="legend">The entries in the bibliography are grouped using
                    <gi>listBibl</gi> with individual citations in a <gi>biblStruct</gi>. As new
                  citations are encoded in the manuscripts for which reference sources have not yet
                  been compiled, they are encoded with an identifier attribute as part of the
                    <gi>bibl</gi> tag.</head>
              </figure>
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="integratingbibl">
        <head>Integrating the Bibliography with the Manuscripts</head>
        <p>We envision Newton’s bibliography as a standalone online reference and also as a resource
          tightly integrated with the alchemical manuscripts. At this point in the project, we have
          preliminary conceptual designs of how to display full citations in context in light of
          other critical apparatus conventions we are currently employing for the alchemical
          manuscripts. We have identified a couple of challenges regarding integration of the
          bibliography with the alchemical manuscripts that the project team needs to further
          consider: <list rend="inline ordered">
            <item>contextualizing citations that reference longer quotes, and</item>
            <item>properly attributing quotes that reference multiple authors</item>
          </list>. The standalone version of the bibliography is still under development and is
          relying on <ref target="http://teiboilerplate.org/">TEI Boilerplate</ref><note>TEI
            Boilerplate: <ptr target="http://teiboilerplate.org/"/>.</note> for online publication.
          Our goal is to include full text access via persistent URLs to the source materials hosted
          by HathiTrust, the Internet Archive, or EEBO, giving preference to the most optimal scans
          and open access resources.</p>
        <p>To help us efficiently and accurately integrate the bibliography, the project team
          created a series of stylesheets to output the citation (contents within a <gi>bibl</gi>),
          the value of the <att>corresp</att> attribute, and the manuscript source (<ptr
            type="crossref" target="#figure10"/>). This serves two distinct purposes: <list
            rend="inline ordered">
            <item>it provides the encoders with a quick way to reference whether an entry in the
              bibliography already exists, and</item>
            <item>it facilitates review by the project editors to ensure that passages were properly
              cited</item>
          </list>. <figure xml:id="figure10">
            <graphic url="images/figure10.png" height="827px" width="1302px"/>
            <head type="legend">XSLT output of citations encoded in the alchemical manuscripts that
              assists in the encoding and editorial review process.</head>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="nextsteps">
        <head>Next Steps</head>
        <p>Once the bibliography is complete, the Newton project team, through careful analysis of
          the citations, will be better able to date Newton’s manuscripts, to cluster manuscripts
          that cite the same or related sources, and, ultimately, to generate network graphs that
          will reveal connections between the cited authors and texts and how they influenced
          Newton’s ideas and work. The citation analysis will be combined and integrated with
          parallel work being done in other veins by this team to establish the order of composition
          of the alchemical manuscripts.</p>
        <p>We have also been working on Newton’s watermarks; on the evolution of his orthography; on
          the elemental composition of his inks by XRF spectrometry; and on mapping the overall
          semantic structure of the corpus through latent semantic analysis, with its observable
          patterns of reuse and reengagement.</p>
        <div xml:id="lsa">
          <head>The Newton Corpus and Latent Semantic Analysis</head>
          <p>The team has had a conceptual map of the corpus in hand for several years, drawn from
              <ref target="http://www.scholarpedia.org/article/Latent_semantic_analysis">latent
              semantic analysis</ref> (LSA<note>Latent semantic analysis (LSA) <quote
                source="#quoteref3">is a mathematical method for computer modeling and simulation of
                the meaning of words and passages by analysis of representative corpora of natural
                text</quote> (<bibl xml:id="quoteref3"><author>Thomas K. Landauer</author> and
                  <author>Susan Dumais</author>, <title level="a">Latent Semantic Analysis</title>,
                  <title level="j">Scholarpedia</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>, no. <biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
                  (<date>2008</date>): 4356, revision 142371, <ptr
                  target="http://www.scholarpedia.org/article/Latent_semantic_analysis"
              />.</bibl>)</note>), but the ideas themselves do not suggest an obvious order of
            progress. Newton’s scholarly progression in topics like calculus, mechanics, and
            gravitation, for which we have well-founded intuitions, seems to unfold in his
            manuscripts in a discernible order. Yet, we still do not understand the directions
            Newton took in his alchemical studies because the ideas remain largely mysterious to us.
            As a result, we have a map of his alchemical ideas but we still need other clues to
            clarify their order of development, and the citations will constitute one of the
            foundations on which we can determine ordering and dating of manuscripts.</p>
          <p>LSA is well established method in the field of information retrieval. It was originally
            designed to accomplish basic tasks in search (<ref type="bibl" target="#berry95">Berry,
              Dumais, and O’Brien 1995</ref>), and was subsequently used to try to model human
            cognition (<ref type="bibl" target="#landauer97">Landauer and Dumais 1997</ref>). It
            starts with word counts from a set of documents, usually a large set, that are used to
            create a term-document matrix, which is a simple numerical representation of the corpus.
            Linear algebra and its vector-space methods give us a numerical model of the structure
            of Newton’s alchemical manuscripts based ultimately on shared vocabulary and ideas. We
            have discovered in our work with Newton that the mathematical foundations of LSA make it
            particularly well suited to identifying the reuse of text passages and phrases in large
            corpora produced by one or more authors, and that makes LSA a valuable tool for
            structural text analysis of large corpora.</p>
          <p>the <title level="m">Chymistry of Isaac Newton</title> project has published the
            results of its LSA work in interactive, online component on its public <ref
              target="http://webapp1.dlib.indiana.edu/newton/lsa/index.php"
              >website</ref>.<note>Chymistry of Isaac Newton LSA Tool: <ptr
                target="http://webapp1.dlib.indiana.edu/newton/lsa/index.php"/>.</note> The LSA
            component can produce a list of chunks or passages that are strongly linked by shared
            vocabulary and provide a measure of the strength of the relationship using cosine
            similarities. More simply, LSA represents documents as <soCalled>bags</soCalled> or
              <soCalled>buckets</soCalled> of words with emphasis on how many times a word appears
            in a document. To identify concepts, since words have multiple meanings, LSA looks for
            patterns that group words together: for example, <q>sublimation</q>, <q>dissolve</q>,
            and <q>bodies</q> might appear in passages in which Newton is noting the transition of
            substances from solid to gas without passing the liquid phase (see <ptr type="crossref"
              target="#figure11"/>). <figure xml:id="figure11">
              <graphic url="images/figure11.png" height="1304px" width="1684px"/>
              <head type="legend">Results from running the Latent Semantic Analysis Tool and two
                different manuscripts from Newton’s alchemical corpus that reveal strongly
                correlated passages (denoted by the yellow highlighting).</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>LSA also gives us numerical measures of the semantic similarity of any two passages in
            the whole corpus. Mathematically, that measure is a cosine calculated from vector
            representations of the two passages in an eigenvector space, and it has a value between
            zero and one. When two texts have a cosine nearly equal to one, it implies that the two
            are virtually identical, likely word-for-word from one end to the other. The cosines are
            a convenient measure of the degree of semantic entanglement of the two passages.</p>
          <p>High cosine pairs, 0.8 and above (as seen in <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure12"
            />), point to promising locations where we are likely to find Newton reusing or
            rethinking text: working over the same ground, recalling or copying the same sentences
            or phrasing from one member of the pair to the other—and, always, one of the two must
            have been written before the other. In a mysterious corpus like these alchemical papers,
            large amounts of this kind of low-level information about otherwise hard-to-recognize
            shared structure can help us to see the shape of this work in much greater detail, and,
            perhaps, thereby make sense of larger trends in Newton’s evolution as a practical
            chymist and a student of alchemy.<note>In the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, the
              term <soCalled>chymistry</soCalled> was used interchangeably with
                <soCalled>alchemy</soCalled>. Chymistry was a field that included not only the
              attempt to transmute base metals into gold and silver, but a host of other activities
              as well. Early modern chymists distilled alcoholic spirits from wine and beer, made
              mineral acids for use in metallurgy and mining, produced sophisticated
              pharmaceuticals, and fabricated pigments for artists, among other pursuits. One could
              almost say that chymistry combined pursuits linked nowadays to the disciplines of
              nuclear physics (at least in the case of transmutation), pharmacology, and industrial
              or technical chemistry.</note>
            <figure xml:id="figure12">
              <graphic url="images/figure12.png" height="910px" width="1200px"/>
              <head type="legend">Screen shot of the Latent Semantic Analysis Tool, available as
                part of the Chymistry of Isaac Newton project, revealing pairs of manuscript
                passages that highly overlap with cosine similarities of 0.9 and greater.</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>As the cosines decrease toward 0.7 and below, there can still be a fair amount of
            shared vocabulary in the two, but often less shared phrasing, if any at all. Inspection
            of these pairs can suggest that they belong to some subgenre because of the language,
            but Newton is clearly doing different work with the same language. In pairs much below
            0.7, there may be apparent likenesses in the use of one or two co-occurring terms that
            suggest a possible connection, but usually there is little else to support the idea. In
            LSA’s spectrum-like vector representations of the text passages, even the co-occurrence
            of a few words in two passages must increase their cosine. It may be an indication of
            the general semantic similarity of these documents that the lowest observed cosine of
            any pair in the alchemical corpus was just above 0.4 and not lower.</p>
          <p>LSA also gives us network graphs of all the passages as clouds of individual nodes,
            connected with other nodes only when their cosine exceeds a given threshold like 0.7, or
            0.8, or 0.9, and these graphs help us to visualize the shape of the whole corpus, or
            pieces of it. The network graph (<ptr type="crossref" target="#figure13"/>), for
            example, shows all the pairs of passages in Newton’s alchemical manuscripts that have a
            cosine similarity of 0.7 or greater. It is a stable pattern because the underlying
            foundations—the collection of documents and the word counts in their tranches—do not
            change as a rule, but the graph shows that the whole collection does separate into many
            smaller semantic subnets. The graph can serve as a kind of map or atlas of locations
            where Newton worked with the same ideas across the entire corpus of 119 manuscripts.
              <figure xml:id="figure13">
              <graphic url="images/figure13.png" height="961px" width="1006px"/>
              <head type="legend">Network graph produced by Chymistry of Isaac Newton’s Latent
                Semantic Analysis Tool that shows pairs of passages in the corpus with a cosine
                similarity of 0.7 or greater.</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>The yellow nodes in <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure13"/> come from Portsmouth Add.
            MS 3973 and the blue nodes come from Portsmouth Add. MS 3975, both of which record
            Newton’s experiments in alchemy. They are central documents in the project’s research
            program. The dense network of nodes at the center represents reading notes from
            traditional alchemical sources with their metaphorical language, while the outlying
            networks represent experimental notes and compositions written in the practical
            alchemical language emerging in laboratories in the late seventeenth century. We are
            interested in using the LSA tool to find recurring ideas, semantic structure, phrasing,
            and vocabulary. The list of results lets us work systematically through the pairs of
            documents, assessing their possible semantic relationships.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="citations">
          <head>Using Latent Semantic Analysis to Track Citations</head>
          <p>The passages shown side by side in <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure14"/> are Dibner
            1024 B, f.2r, on the left, and Royal Society MM/6/5, f.3r2. The yellow highlighting
            identifies significant shared vocabulary and usually provides some sense of what might
            be shared. In this case, with a cosine of 0.989, there is a significant amount of
            overlapping text. The overlap is probably predictable from the titles alone, because
            both manuscripts address the work of French alchemist Pierre Jean Fabré, but here the
            LSA output shows us Newton referencing the same source materials in both documents,
            while only providing the citation in MM/6/5 (<ptr type="crossref" target="#figure14"/>).
            The next question is whether there is obvious conceptual evidence to determine which of
            the two manuscripts is likelier to be the earlier composition based on the citations
            referenced. <figure xml:id="figure14">
              <graphic url="images/figure14.png" height="411px" width="666px"/>
              <head type="legend">Results from the Latent Semantic Analysis Tool showing two
                passages from different manuscripts from Newton’s alchemical corpus that have a
                similarity cosine of 0.989. The yellow highlighting indicates significant words that
                appear in both passages, which, in this case, is almost every word.</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>The graph in <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure15"/> displays the location of textual
            similarities across six different manuscripts, including Royal Society MM/6/5 which we
            have just seen in part, where Newton worked over the same ideas at various times. All
            the connected pairs have cosine similarities of 0.9 or greater, and share a considerable
            amount of text. Connected passages from the same document have the same color and are
            organized vertically in page order. The six different documents are arranged
            horizontally. <figure xml:id="figure15">
              <graphic url="images/figure15.png" height="882px" width="1156px"/>
              <head type="legend">Network graph produced from the Latent Semantic Analysis Tool
                represents six documents that are found by LSA to share a large amount of text in
                certain sections of each of these documents. Each node represents a span of around
                250 words of manuscript text, a lengthy passage with a quill and ink. In the
                passages shown in the graph, Newton rewrote the same material or revisited the same
                authors a number of times, and so this concatenation may represent a persistent
                locus of interest over a period of months or years.</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>Passages or nodes in <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure15"/> that possess many
            connections will also likely contain direct quotations from the alchemical books that
            Newton was reading. The nodes or passages to which they are connected also often make
            the same citations, or paraphrase the quotations and contents found in the multiply
            connected passages. This graph therefore serves as a map of citation patterns across
            these six documents.</p>
          <p>As it is everywhere else, the basic problem here is to discern the order of composition
            of these six documents. Sometimes Newton’s editorial marks provide clues, but not as
            often as we would like. This is where we rely on the citations, bibliography, and the
            orthographic, watermark, and ink evidence to fill in the gaps in the analysis. The
            resulting clusters will not only have the benefit of showing the gradual increase of
            authoritative sources by Newton; they will also lay the groundwork for network analysis
            to reveal the connections that he saw among authors’ works and ideas.</p>
          <p>The citations constitute an independent order of evidence with its own rules that will
            have an impact on how to determine the order of composition of Newton’s work in alchemy.
            When the improved and expanded citation analysis and the ink and paper evidence are all
            integrated with the semantically distinct clusters of passages and manuscripts that we
            have already discovered with our LSA tool, we should achieve a highly articulated view
            of how each cluster of related passages was constructed and gain a better sense of what
            Newton was doing in each.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dcrm07"><orgName>Association of College and Research Libraries</orgName>,
            and <orgName>Library of Congress</orgName>. <title level="m">Descriptive Cataloging of
              Rare Materials</title>. <date>2007</date>. <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Library of Congress</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="berry95"><author>Berry, Michael W.</author>, <author>Susan T.
              Dumais</author>, and <author>Gavin W. O’Brien</author>. <date>1995</date>. <title
              level="a">Using Linear Algebra for Intelligent Information Retrieval.</title>
            <title level="j">SIAM Review</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">573–95</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
            >10.1137/1037127</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bowers05"><author>Bowers, Fredson</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title
              level="m">Principles of Bibliographical Description</title>. <pubPlace>New Castle,
              Delaware</pubPlace>: <publisher>Oak Knoll Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ferguson06"><author>Ferguson, John</author>. <date>1906</date>. <title
              level="m">Bibliotheca Chemica: A Catalogue of the Alchemical, Chemical and
              Pharmaceutical Books in the Collection of the Late James Young of Kelly and
              Durris[...]</title> 2 vols. <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>: <publisher>J. Maclehose and
              Sons</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fulton61"><author>Fulton, John F.</author>
            <date>1961</date>. <title level="m">A Bibliography of the Honourable Robert Boyle,
              Fellow of the Royal Society</title>. <edition>2nd ed.</edition>,
              <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gaskell72"><author>Gaskell, Phillip</author>. <date>1972</date>. <title
              level="m">A New Introduction to Bibliography</title>, <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="harrison78"><author>Harrison, John</author>. <date>1978</date>.<title
              level="m">The Library of Isaac Newton</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="landauer97"><author>Landauer, Thomas K.</author>, and <author>Susan T.
              Dumais</author>. <date>1997</date>. <title level="a">A Solution to Plato’s Problem:
              The Latent Semantic Analysis Theory of Acquisition, Induction, and Representation of
              Knowledge.</title>
            <title level="j">Psychological Review</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">211–40</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1037/0033-295X.104.2.211</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tei17"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2017</date>. <title
              level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>.
              <edition>Version 3.2.0</edition>. Last updated July 10. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
              target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.2.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
