<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI" xml:lang="es">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main" xml:lang="es">Treinta años de TEI en español: usos y
               comunidad</title>
            <title type="sub" xml:lang="en">Thirty years of TEI in Spanish: uses and
               community</title>
            <!-- author information in separate <author> elements per author -->
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Gimena</forename>
                  <surname>del Rio Riande</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <roleName> Investigadora Adjunta</roleName>. <orgName>IIBICRIT,
                  CONICET</orgName></affiliation>
               <email>gdelrio.riande@gmail.com</email>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Susanna</forename>
                  <surname>Allés-Torrent</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation><roleName>Profesora</roleName>. <orgName>Department of Modern Languages
                     and Literatures de la University of Miami (Fl, Estados
                  Unidos)</orgName></affiliation>
               <email>susanna_alles@miami.edu</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>01/08/2023</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor role="guest">Gimena del Rio Riande</editor>
            <editor role="guest">Susanna Allés-Torrent</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="16">Spanish Issue</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Encoded from .docx copyedited version, and encoded according to the jTEI schema.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for
               journals in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking
               to publish full-text articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="es">es</language>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="editorialIntroduction">

            <div xml:id="espanol" xml:lang="es">
               <head>Treinta años de TEI en español: usos y comunidad</head>
               <p>En el campo de las Humanidades Digitales, pocas son las iniciativas que han
                  demostrado tener un recorrido tan sólido y una comunidad de usuarios e interesados
                  tan activos como la Text Encoding Initiative (TEI). En funcionamiento desde 1987,
                  el estándar de codificación de la TEI ha sido utilizado para documentos escritos
                  en lenguas tan diversas como el chino, el maya, el copto, el japonés, el español o
                  el árabe, entre otras. Sus Guías Directrices <q>están dirigidas a cualquier
                     persona que trabaje con cualquier tipo de recurso textual en formato
                     digital.</q><note>Fecha de consulta 16 de julio de 2023, <ptr
                        target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.6.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/AB.html"
                     />.</note> Es tal vez por ello que el alcance global de la TEI se vuelve a
                  veces tan difícil de aprehender y definir.</p>
               <p>En los países hispanohablantes, al igual que en otras latitudes, el interés
                  creciente por la fijación de textos y su transformación en formato electrónico
                  vino en un primer momento motivado por el análisis de textos más tradicional, como
                  las concordancias, los diccionarios, o la creación de léxicos específicos.
                  Indudablemente, muchos de los recursos desarrollados hasta ese momento vendrían de
                  centros europeos o norteamericanos, como la tesis de doctorado de Leopoldo Sáez
                  Godoy sobre el léxico de Lope de Rueda, defendida en 1968 en la Universidad de
                  Bonn, o la <title level="m">Computerized version of the Dictionary of the Old
                     Spanish Language</title> en el Hispanic Seminary of Medieval Studies (HSMS) de
                  la Universidad de Wisconsin. Más tarde, la adopción del sistema Madison para la
                  transcripción de manuscritos, desarrollado en el HSMS y ampliamente adoptado para
                  textos medievales en España, colaboraría con la necesidad de echar mano de un
                  estándar de codificación que fuera más allá de los formatos y que incluyera tanto
                  información lingüística como semántica. En ese contexto, si bien la TEI surge en
                  ámbito anglosajón en los años ochenta, no tarda en interesar a algunos
                  investigadores activos en los estudios hispánicos durante la siguiente década. </p>
               <p>En 1992, en el marco del Congreso de la Lengua Española celebrado en Sevilla, se
                  organizó el panel <title level="u">La lengua española y las nuevas
                     tecnologías.</title><note>Fecha de consulta 16 de julio de 2023, <ptr
                        target="https://cvc.cervantes.es/obref/congresos/sevilla/indice.htm"
                     />.</note> En él se ofrecieron contribuciones que trataban temas todavía hoy
                  esenciales como el procesamiento del lenguaje natural y la inteligencia
                  artificial, diferentes ramas de la lingüística computacional y tecnologías
                  lingüísticas (Jaime Carbonell, Ángel G. Jordán, Luis de Sopeña), la creación de
                  bases de datos tanto textuales como acústicos (Joaquin Llisterri, Dolors Poch), o
                  de diccionarios electrónicos del español (Carlos Subirats Rüggeberg). Además, a la
                  siempre presente actividad filológica y de crítica textual, mientras se hablaba de
                  edición crítica de textos históricos (Germán Orduna, Alberto Varvaro), se
                  discutían también los problemas de transcripción electrónica enfrentados en el
                  Hispanic Seminary of Medieval Studies (David Mckenzie), o la necesidad de
                  estándares para el entonces pionero ADMYTE (Archivo Digital de Manuscritos y
                  Textos Españoles) (Francisco A. Marcos Marín). En este congreso también se empezó
                  a discutir –quizás por primera vez y gracias a Charles Faulhaber– sobre la TEI
                  para textos en español. Surgían en ese momento problemas hoy superados, como
                  cuestiones relativas al marcado tipográfico y codificación de caracteres (acentos,
                  mayúsculas, minúsculas, etc.), y otros esenciales a los lenguajes de marcado (en
                  ese momento, el Standard Generalized Markup Language o SGML) para distinguir entre
                  aspectos formales y semánticos, así como el establecimiento de una codificación
                  explícita y resolutiva para ambigüedades lingüísticas. No es un dato menor el
                  hecho de que en este evento se presentó la traducción al español de las primeras
                  Guías Directrices de la TEI, elaboradas entre 1988 y 1990. Las <title level="a"
                     >Guidelines for the Encoding and Interchange of Machine-Readable Texts</title>
                  (TEI P1), traducidas al español por Francisco Marcos Marín y las bibliotecarias
                  argentinas Verónica Zumárraga y Marcela Tabanera, pueden entenderse hoy como claro
                  ejemplo del temprano interés de la comunidad hispanohablante en este estándar. </p>
               <p>En esta década encontramos también, de manera más aspiracional que real, la
                  creación de ediciones hipertextuales, actividad que para el decenio siguiente
                  florecería a un lado y al otro del Atlántico y reconocería como central la
                  adopción de la TEI en tanto iniciativa internacional para la codificación y el
                  intercambio de cualquier tipo de texto, independientemente de la lengua, época o
                  procedencia.</p>
               <p> Tomando como punto de partida ese congreso y el conjunto de intervenciones
                  académicas que de ahí surgieron, este número especial lleva como título <title
                     level="a">Treinta años de TEI en español: usos y comunidad.</title> Creemos
                  que, después de tres décadas de trabajo, aunque en muchos casos aislado y
                  desfinanciado, pueden ya ofrecerse una serie de reflexiones sobre los derroteros
                  que esta práctica digital ha tenido en los estudios hispánicos y que ha generado
                  una red de colaboraciones y una comunidad de práctica con un conjunto de
                  características propias. </p>
               <p>Las seis contribuciones que aquí se publican tienen como hilo conductor el uso de
                  la TEI para la codificación y edición filológica de textos en español y aspiran a
                  ser una muestra representativa del trabajo que se viene llevando adelante en este
                  ámbito en los diferentes hemisferios.</p>
               <p>Cuatro contribuciones se sitúan en el ámbito de la edición filológica digital,
                  pero lo hacen desde perspectivas ecdóticas, contextos de investigación, épocas y
                  géneros literarios, y audiencias diferentes. Gabriel Calarco propone el uso de la
                  TEI para una edición digital de fragmentos de un texto medieval, el <title
                     level="m">Libro de Alexandre</title>, en el marco de su tesis doctoral llevada
                  a cabo en la Universidad de Buenos Aires y siguiendo los principios de la
                     <soCalled>minimal computing</soCalled>. Antonio Rojas, Grisel Terrón, Alaina
                  Solernou y Tobias Kraft ofrecen un panorama general sobre su proyecto editorial
                     <title level="s">Humboldt Digital</title>, una iniciativa internacional
                  sostenida conjuntamente por instituciones alemanas y cubanas, que ha dado lugar a
                  una plataforma en línea donde se están publicando los escritos de Humboldt
                  relacionados con su estancia en la isla de Cuba. Marta López Izquierdo aborda la
                  edición del género epistolar ofreciendo en primer lugar un informativo panorámico
                  sobre iniciativas de investigación internacionales afines, y trayendo a colación
                  retos y soluciones adoptados en el proyecto <title level="u">Cartas de
                     Republicanos Españoles Refugiados y exiliados en Francia</title> (CAREXIL-FR).
                  Desde un abordaje pedagógico, la contribución de Clayton McCarl y su equipo –Lyn
                  Hemmingway, Stacey Lowey-Ball, Sara Menéndez y Georgina Wilson Aranguren– se sitúa
                  en un contexto académico de estudiantes de grado, concretamente en Estados Unidos,
                  en el que la edición digital se concibe como una herramienta y una actividad de
                  enseñanza que sirve para la apropiación y exploración de una serie de textos
                  coloniales. </p>
               <p>Las dos contribuciones restantes ofrecen puntos de vista alternativos pero
                  complementarios a los anteriores. Por un lado, José Calvo Tello y Nanette
                  Rißler-Pipka tratan el problema del uso de textos digitales publicados con algún
                  tipo de derecho de autor y que por consiguiente no pueden ser reutilizados
                  libremente. La solución propuesta es la creación de datos derivados en TEI. Los
                  autores exponen algunas estratégias útiles para tal fin siguiendo la filosofía de
                  los criterios FAIR (en sus siglas en inglés, Findable, Accesible, Interoperable,
                  Reproducible). A modo de cierre, las editoras de este volumen, Susanna
                  Allés-Torrent y Gimena del Rio Riande, ofrecen un panorama genérico sobre el uso
                  de la TEI en el mundo hispanohablante. La mayoría de los resultados obtenidos y
                  discutidos en el artículo proceden de una encuesta que se llevó a cabo durante
                  2022 gracias a la financiación del proyecto <title level="u">Communicating the TEI
                     to a Multilingual User Community</title> por parte de la Mellon Foundation.</p>
               <p> El <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> y las
                  editoras invitadas apuestan con este primer número especial en español por el
                  multilingüismo y la apertura a diferentes comunidades académicas, con la esperanza
                  de que se dé la bienvenida a otros números en diferentes lenguas y que la revista
                  ejerza así una función de observatorio real de los usos de la TEI a nivel global.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="english" xml:lang="en">
               <head>Thirty years of TEI in Spanish: uses and community</head>
               <p> In the field of the Digital Humanities, few initiatives have such a well grounded
                  background and an active community of users and practitioners as the Text Encoding
                  Initiative (TEI). Active since 1987, the TEI encoding standard has been used for
                  documents written in languages as diverse as Chinese, Mayan, Coptic, Japanese,
                  Spanish, and Arabic, among others. Its Guidelines <q>are addressed to anyone who
                     works with any kind of textual resource in digital form.</q><note>Accessed July
                     16, 2023, <ptr
                        target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.6.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/AB.html"
                     />.</note> This is perhaps why the global scope of TEI is so difficult to grasp
                  and define. </p>
               <p> In the Spanish speaking countries, as well as in other latitudes, the growing
                  interest in text standardization and its transformation into electronic format
                  arrived initially motivated by traditional text analysis, such as concordances,
                  dictionaries, or the creation of specific lexicons. Undoubtedly, many of the
                  resources developed so far would come from European or North American centers,
                  such as Leopoldo Sáez Godoy’s doctoral thesis on the lexicon of Lope de Rueda,
                  defended in 1968 at the University of Bonn, or the <title level="m">Computerized
                     version of the Dictionary of the Old Spanish Language</title> at the Hispanic
                  Seminary of Medieval Studies (HSMS) at the University of Wisconsin at Madison.
                  Afterwards, the adoption of the Madison system for manuscript transcription,
                  developed at the HSMS and widely adopted for medieval texts in Spain, would insist
                  on the need for an encoding standard that needed to go beyond formats and include
                  both linguistic and semantic information. In this context, although the TEI
                  emerged in the Anglophone world in the late 1980s, it did not take long for some
                  researchers active within Hispanic studies to become interested in it during the
                  following decade.</p>
               <p>In 1992, within the framework of the Congreso de la Lengua Española held in
                  Seville, a group of participants organized the panel <title level="u">The Spanish
                     language and new technologies.</title><note>Accessed July 16, 2023, <ptr
                        target="https://cvc.cervantes.es/obref/congresos/sevilla/indice.htm"
                     />.</note> Some contributions dealt with topics that are still essential today,
                  such as natural language processing and artificial intelligence, different
                  branches of computational linguistics and linguistic technologies (Jaime
                  Carbonell, Ángel G. Jordán, Luis de Sopeña), the creation of both textual and
                  acoustic databases (Joaquin Llisterri, Dolors Poch), or electronic dictionaries of
                  Spanish (Carlos Subirats Rüggeberg). In addition to the ever-present interest for
                  philology and textual criticism in these type of conferences and popular
                  discussions about critical editing of historical texts (Germán Orduna, Alberto
                  Varvaro), issues emerged surrounding electronic transcription at the Hispanic
                  Seminary of Medieval Studies (David Mckenzie), along with the need for standards
                  for the then pioneering ADMYTE project (Archivo Digital de Manuscritos y Textos
                  Españoles) (Francisco A. Marcos Marín). At this conference, discussions began to
                  take place -perhaps for the first time and thanks to Charles Faulhaber- about the
                  Text Encoding Initiative for texts in Spanish. The challenges that arose at that
                  time have already been overcome nowadays, such as issues related to typographic
                  markup and character encoding (accents, capitalisation, lowercase, etc.). Others,
                  instead, pointed to essential notions of markup languages (at that time, the
                  Standard Generalized Markup Language or SGML) to distinguish between formal and
                  semantic textual aspects, the establishment of an explicit encoding, and the
                  resolution of linguistic ambiguities. It is important to note that for the first
                  time the translation in Spanish of the TEI Guidelines, drafted between 1988 and
                  1990, was presented at this event. <title level="a">The Guidelines for the
                     Encoding and Interchange of Machine-Readable Texts</title> (TEI P1), translated
                  into Spanish by Francisco Marcos Marín and the Argentinean librarians Verónica
                  Zumárraga and Marcela Tabanera, demonstrate the enormous early interest of the
                  Spanish-speaking community for this standard.</p>
               <p> In this decade we also find, more as an aspiration than a reality, the creation
                  of hypertext editions, an activity that would flourish in the following decade on
                  both sides of the Atlantic. Hence, the adoption of the TEI would be recognised as
                  central, because it provided an international initiative for the codification and
                  exchange of any type of text, regardless of language, time or origin. </p>
               <p>Taking that conference and the group of academic contributions that emerged from
                  it as a starting point, this special issue is entitled <title level="a">Thirty
                     years of TEI in Spanish: uses and community.</title> We believe that, after
                  three decades of work, albeit in many cases isolated and unfunded, we can now
                  offer a set of reflections on the directions that this digital practice has taken
                  in Hispanic studies. Also, we aim to highlight the networks of collaborations and
                  the distinct community of practice that have appeared during these years.</p>
               <p> The six contributions published here focus on the use of the TEI for the encoding
                  and scholarly editing of Spanish texts. They aim to be a representative sample of
                  the work being done in this field in the different hemispheres.</p>
               <p> Four contributions are situated within the field of digital scholarly editing,
                  but they do so from different ecdotical perspectives, research contexts, literary
                  periods and genres, and are conceived for different audiences. Gabriel Calarco
                  proposes the use of the TEI for a digital edition of fragments of an Iberian
                  medieval text, the <title level="m">Libro de Alexandre</title>. His work is done
                  within the framework of his doctoral thesis carried out at the University of
                  Buenos Aires and follows the principles of <soCalled>minimal computing</soCalled>.
                  Antonio Rojas, Grisel Terrón, Alaina Solernou and Tobias Kraft give an overview of
                  their editing project <title level="s">Humboldt Digital</title>, an international
                  initiative jointly supported by German and Cuban institutions, which offers an
                  online platform where Humboldt’s writings related to his stay on the island of
                  Cuba are published. Marta López Izquierdo addresses the editing of the epistolary
                  genre by, first, offering an informative overview of related international
                  research initiatives, and bringing up challenges and solutions adopted in her
                  project <title level="u">Letters of Spanish Republican Refugees and Exiles in
                     France</title> (CAREXIL-FR). From a pedagogical approach, the contribution by
                  Clayton McCarl and his team -Lyn Hemmingway, Stacey Lowey-Ball, Sara Menéndez, and
                  Georgina Wilson Aranguren- is situated in an academic context of undergraduate
                  students, specifically in the United States, in which digital editing is conceived
                  as a teaching device and practise that serves for the appropriation and
                  exploration of Spanish colonial texts.</p>
               <p> The two remaining contributions offer alternative but complementary points of
                  view to the previous ones. On the one hand, José Calvo Tello and Nanette
                  Rißler-Pipka address the problem of using digital texts published under some form
                  of copyright and which therefore cannot be freely reused. The proposed solution is
                  the creation of derived data in TEI. The authors outline some useful strategies
                  for this purpose following the philosophy of the FAIR criteria (Findable,
                  Accessible, Interoperable, Reproducible). In closing, the editors of this volume,
                  Susanna Allés-Torrent and Gimena del Rio Riande, offer a general review of the TEI
                  use in the Spanish-speaking world. Most of the results obtained and discussed in
                  the article come from an online survey carried out during 2022 thanks to the
                  funding of the project <title level="u">Communicating the TEI to a Multilingual
                     User Community</title> by the Mellon Foundation.</p>
               <p> With this first special issue in Spanish, the <title level="j">Journal of the
                     Text Encoding Initiative</title> (JTEI) an the guest editors of this issue
                  commit to multilingualism and opening the dialogue to different scholarly
                  communities, in the hope that the journal will welcome other issues in different
                  languages and will thus serve as a real observatory of the uses of the TEI at a
                  global scale.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
