<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-baillot-giovacchini-191-source.xml 1029 2021-04-28 19:08:16Z pietro.liuzzo $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI.internal">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">TEI Models for the Publication of Social Sciences and Humanities
          Journals: Opportunities, Challenges, and First Steps Toward a Standardized
          Workflow</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Anne</forename>
            <surname>Baillot</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Anne Baillot is a full <roleName>professor</roleName> in German studies at
              <orgName>Le Mans Université</orgName>. She is the editor of <title level="j">Letters
              and Texts. Intellectual Berlin around 1800</title> and former managing editor of the
              <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>.</affiliation>
          <email>anne.baillot@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name><forename>Julie</forename>
            <surname>Giovacchini</surname></name>
          <affiliation>Julie Giovacchini is a<roleName> research engineer</roleName> in Classics at
              <orgName>French CNRS (Centre Jean Pépin UMR8230 CNRS-ENS-PSL)</orgName>. She is
            co-editor of <title level="j">Philosophie antique</title>, a journal dedicated to the
            history of ancient philosophy.</affiliation>
          <email>Julie.GIOVACCHINI@cnrs.fr</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>2021</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Georg Vogeler</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="14">Selected Papers from the 2019 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encoded from .docx copyedited version, transformed with pandoc to tei simple and encoded
          according to the jTEI schema.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals
          in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish
          full-text articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>workflow</term>
          <term>digital publications</term>
          <term>schemas</term>
          <term>scholarly publishing</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="Pietro Liuzzo" when="2021-04-27">Encode text</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>The TEI Guidelines are developed and curated by a community whose main purpose is to
          standardize the encoding of primary sources relevant for humanities research and teaching.
          But other communities are also working with TEI-based publication formats. The first goal
          of this paper is to raise awareness of the importance of TEI-based scholarly publishing as
          we know it today. The second goal is to contribute to a reflection on the development of a
          TEI customization that would cover the whole authoring-reviewing-publishing workflow and
          guarantee archiving options that are as solid for journal publications as what we now have
          for primary sources published in TEI.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <!-- text divisions, each with an @xml:id and <head> -->

      <p>The TEI Guidelines are developed and curated by a community whose main purpose is to
        standardize the encoding of primary sources relevant for humanities research and teaching.
        This common focus on a research and dissemination goal, which is rooted in the history of
        the TEI, gives the community a great strength, but it leads to a lack of recognition for
        other areas of digital textuality that also use the TEI. We mostly encode primary sources
        relevant to our research and concentrate development efforts in their direction. But other
        communities are now also working with TEI-based publication formats.</p>
      <p>Looking at the number of encoded documents, the production of the TEI community as
        described above (e.g., actively developing the guidelines and doing so with a focus on
        primary sources) is by far not the most productive among those who currently use TEI. The
        best-known example for this uneven situation is that of the European Patent Office: all its
        patents are encoded in TEI, amounting to a total of two hundred million documents and two
        billion TEI annotations (Laurent Romary, personal communication). This kind of magnitude is
        far from that achieved by all TEI-based humanities primary sources put together.</p>
      <p>A lack of balance also exists within the humanities ecosystem, where the TEI is used to
        encode not only primary sources, but also secondary sources, especially journal
        publications. In that context, the quantity of TEI-based documents is quite impressive
        without there being much theoretical or research-oriented development made in the field of
        journal publications, even though it is a growing one. TEI publication formats for secondary
        sources are evolving and being developed, but rather like a by-product. They are seldom
        addressed on TEI-L, at the Annual Conference, or in the <title level="j">Journal of the Text
          Encoding Initiative</title>. The latest example of such a publication, for instance,
        addresses OJS-based workflow issues, but not the encoding per se (<ref type="bibl"
          target="#homenda2016">Homenda and Pekala 2016</ref>).</p>
      <p>This paper draws on the questions that were at the core of Holmes and Romary (<ref
          type="bibl" target="#holmes2011">2011</ref>) and that initiated the creation of the jTEI
        format, now used among others by the <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding
          Initiative</title>.<note>
          <p>As explained on the TEIWiki page <title level="a">JTEI Authoring Tools</title>, last
            edited May 14, 2015, <ptr
              target="https://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php?title=JTEI_Authoring_Tools"/>.</p>
        </note> It is not our purpose to discuss this schema or possible amendments to it, nor to
        discuss the respective technical benefits of TEI vs. JATS (Journal Article Tag Suite, <ptr
          target="http://jats.niso.org/1.1/"/>). We have two distinct goals in building upon Holmes
        and Romary (<ref type="bibl" target="#holmes2011">2011</ref>). The first goal is to raise
        awareness of the importance of TEI-based scholarly publishing as we know it today. The
        second is to contribute to a reflection on the development of a TEI customization that would
        cover the whole authoring-reviewing-publishing workflow and guarantee archiving options that
        are as solid for journal publications as what we now have for primary sources published in
        TEI. The encoding ideas we propose are to be considered as explorative.</p>
      <p>In a first step, we will present a panorama of the use of TEI in social sciences and
        humanities (SSH) scholarly publishing and consider the advantages and challenges of using
        TEI-based formats in scholarly publishing in the humanities. Which organs are currently
        doing so and how much text does this represent? Why are these journals using a TEI format?
        We will then relate our experience as editors, with the main aim of initiating a discussion
        within the community on the role of TEI-based formats for scholarly publishing at large,
        focusing on the copyediting and reviewing process. We will argue that such formats have the
        potential to be a powerful leverage to increase the TEI’s impact on the scholarly community
        and to empower humanities scholars for better dissemination of their own research. We will
        propose some preliminary ideas for encoding a complete publishing workflow of secondary
        sources that include the reviewing and copyediting process.</p>
      <div xml:id="scholarly">
        <head>Scholarly Publishing in TEI: An Overview</head>
        <p>Scholarly publishing practices are in many ways connected to the existing research
          infrastructures that are available to researchers and librarians. The development of
          TEI-based infrastructures and services on different continents and in different countries
          is the result of personal engagement by members of the TEI community and of the historical
          development of infrastructures in these different environments. It also has an economic
          dimension (who is paying how much for which service) that impacts greatly the digital
          publishing landscape as we know it today.</p>
        <p>The following is an overview of TEI-based journal publications that was gathered mainly
          by initiating an informal survey on the TEI-L discussion list.<note>
            <p>See Anne Baillot, <title level="a">Scholarly journals publishing in TEI</title>,
              TEI-L archives, August 22, 2019, and replies, <ptr
                target="https://listserv.brown.edu/cgi-bin/wa?A1=ind1908&amp;L=TEI-L#9"/>.</p>
          </note> Since there is no other overview of this type known to us in this area, we assume
          it is the best summary of the current situation.<note>
            <p>If the topic gains momentum, it would be thinkable to reactivate the currently
              dormant TEI Special Interest Group (SIG) on Scholarly Publishing and manage to keep
              the information on the SIG’s wiki up to date.</p>
          </note></p>
        <div xml:id="europe">
          <head>In Europe</head>
          <p>The largest actor in Europe is France, where a long history of political centralization
            led to the development of national infrastructures and services that has allowed the
            deployment of TEI-based publishing formats and TEI-compliant platforms on a national
            scale. France has three main providers for secondary sources that rely on the TEI:
            OpenEdition, HAL, and Istex.</p>
          <p>OpenEdition<note>
              <p>Accessed February 15, 2021, <ptr target="https://www.openedition.org/"/>.</p>
            </note> is a platform hosting four different services: an academic calendar announcing
            events such as conferences and call for papers (Calenda), a scholarly blog platform
            called Hypotheses, a scholarly book service (OpenEdition Books), and a scholarly
            journals platform (OpenEdition Journals, called revues.org in the past). The <title
              level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> is hosted by OpenEdition.
            Almost all of the journals published on the journals.openedition platform are TEI-based.<note>
              <p>The schema documentation is found on L’Édition Électronique Ouverte, one of the
                Hypotheses blogs hosted by the platform: see Jean-François Rivière, <title level="a"
                  >Schema XML TEI OpenEdition</title>, last updated September 15, 2014, <ptr
                  target="https://leo.hypotheses.org/10717"/>.</p>
            </note> The articles published as of February 15, 2021 amount to a total of 310,515 documents.<note>
              <p>Current figures available through the search interface: <ptr
                  target="https://search.openedition.org/results?s=&amp;pf=OJ"/>.</p>
            </note> The book platform also provides many TEI-based documents (204,869 as of February
            15, 2021),<note>
              <p>Current figures available through the search interface: <ptr
                  target="https://search.openedition.org/results?s=&amp;pf=OB"/>.</p>
            </note> which adds up to a total of over half a million documents, some of them being
            books, that is, rather large documents.</p>
          <p>Although the TEI files for these articles and books are theoretically available for
            reuse and can be used for research purposes, there is currently no direct access like a
            download link or button that would make harvesting easy. When asked about the
            feasibility of such an endeavor, OpenEdition mentions<note>
              <p>Information from Pierre Mounier, private communication.</p>
            </note> local legal issues but a clear willingness to support research projects that
            would need to download these files, should such a research project issue a request
            (which has never yet ever happened).</p>
          <p>The second French infrastructure to be TEI-based is not strictly a platform for
            scholarly publishing but a publication repository that can be used for either preprint
            or postprint open access (OA) publication. Unlike OpenEdition, which was initiated by a
            research project and gained momentum because it met the needs of the scholarly community
            and the national political agenda, the open archive HAL<note>
              <p>Accessed February 15, 2021, <ptr target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/"/>.</p>
            </note> was from its onset a national infrastructure, conceived as a service to the
            French scholarly community at large, with a specific effort directed towards humanities
            disciplines that had resisted noncommercial archiving strategies even long after other
            communities relied on them. Scholars can either register metadata concerning their
            publication or additionally archive one or several preprint versions. It is the metadata
            that are stored in a TEI format, potentially allowing a wide overview of French
            scholarly publications.</p>
          <p>The significance of the HAL data has grown since July 2018 when the French Ministry for
            Higher Education and Research issued an Open Science Plan that led the main funding
            agency ANR to require HAL publications of research output they fund from then on.<note>
              <p>Accessed February 15, 2021, <ptr
                  target="https://anr.fr/fr/lanr-et-la-recherche/engagements-et-valeurs/la-science-ouverte/"
                />.</p>
            </note> It was followed in this constraining requirement by the national research
            evaluation organ HCERES, which issued a statement that they would only take into
            consideration full-text HAL publications when evaluating universities.<note>
              <p>Agnes Magron, <title level="a">L’Hcéres choisit la plateforme HAL pour l’archivage
                  et la diffusion des rapports d’évaluation</title>, Centre pour la Communication
                Scientifique Directe, April 9, 2019, <ptr
                  target="https://www.ccsd.cnrs.fr/2019/04/hceres-choisit-la-plateforme-hal-pour-archivage-et-la-diffusion-des-rapports-evaluation/"
                />.</p>
            </note> As for the CNRS (a national organization employing only researchers and research
            assistants) and Inria (national organization for research in informatics), they also
            require researchers to use HAL for evaluation purposes on both the lab and the
            individual level. At the CNRS, HAL import functionalities are currently being
            transferred into the internal databases that harvest annual reports.<note>
              <p>Individual researchers are to use HAL imports in the CRAC system (accessed [march
                2021], <ptr target="https://www.science-ouverte.cnrs.fr/les-actions-du-cnrs/"/>)
                from 2019 on and in the RIBAC system for SSH scholars (accessed February 15, 2021,
                  <ptr target="https://www.ribac-shs.cnrs.fr/"/>) from 2020 on.</p>
            </note> Moving to the TEI-based HAL is a political evolution that took some time to be
            implemented throughout the research ecosystem, but as of 2020 there is virtually no
            single publication produced in France that will not have at the very least a set of TEI
            metadata associated with it. The centralization of information which these evaluation
            and archiving constraints have imposed on a wide range of scholarly communities has not
            always been well received. In the humanities and social sciences, it was occasionally considered<note>
              <p>A rather vigorous discussion has been going on since the early 2000s on this
                subject. It concerns on the one hand the centralizing approach of HAL, and on the
                other hand the progressive use of the open archive for bibliometric purposes, in
                order to produce objective indicators intended to direct the public policy of
                support for research. For a record of the first branch of the discussion, see the
                debate between Stevan Harnad and Franck Laloë on the American Scientist Open Access
                Forum during 2006 (Franck Laloe, <title level="a">Re: France’s HAL, OAI
                  interoperability, and Central vs Institutional Repositories</title>, October 3,
                2006, <ptr
                  target="https://web.archive.org/web/20120403072426/http://listserver.sigmaxi.org/sc/wa.exe?A2=ind06&amp;L=american-scientist-open-access-forum&amp;D=1&amp;O=D&amp;F=l&amp;S=&amp;P=75655"
                />); for a record of the second branch, see the conversation that took place on the
                French open access list on June 25, 2018, entitled <title level="a">Fichiers audio
                  de: <title level="a">HAL et les autres archives ouvertes: libre accès aux savoirs,
                    centralisation des données et quantifications néo-managériales ou marketing
                    académique?</title> séminaire PDS/EHESS, 14/06/2018 18h–21h</title> (<ptr
                  target="https://groupes.renater.fr/sympa/arc/accesouvert/2018-06/msg00002.html"
                />). The problem is very well addressed by Girard (<ref target="#chloe2017"
                  type="bibl">2017</ref>).</p>
            </note> to have the potential for enabling political control, and hence to be
            detrimental to the freedom of research. This was especially a concern for those who were
            not familiar with the underlying technologies or the values of the community that
            develops them.</p>
          <p>The third French publication organ hosting TEI-based information is ISTEX.<note>
              <p>Accessed February 23, 2021, <ptr target="https://www.istex.fr/"/>.</p>
            </note> ISTEX is a platform that integrates content from private scholarly publishers
            (OpenEdition being one of them) with whom national licenses are being negotiated.
            University libraries usually contribute a yearly amount to benefit from the deal, which
            is managed at a national level by a negotiation consortium (<ref
              target="https://www.couperin.org/">Consortium Couperin</ref>,
            https://www.couperin.org/). ISTEX contains metadata from publications, but also
            full-text PDF files, that are being transformed into TEI and added to the server. ISTEX’
            API is used by university libraries to retrieve information as well as for bibliometric
            purposes. ISTEX currently hosts twenty-three million documents.<note>
              <p>See Pascale Viot, <title level="a">American Chemical Society’ ou ACS désormais
                  disponible sur la plateforme ISTEX,</title> ISTEX blog, August 2, 2019, <ptr
                  target="https://blog.istex.fr/american-chemical-society-ou-acs-desormais-disponible-sur-la-plateforme-istex/"
                />.</p>
            </note></p>
          <p>All of this together amounts to a considerable mass of documents, but not all of them
            are available in TEI and not all of them are available in full OA from the onset. There
            still are accessibility restrictions, whereas in the case of the examples we gathered
            from other countries, all journals are completely TEI-based (including both metadata and
            text) and OA.</p>
          <p>Germany has a different strategic approach, but it still presents a series of
            initiatives in the field of TEI-based scholarly publishing. Until recently, Germany
            relied solely on the good will (political and economic) of its regions, and more
            specifically of their universities, to build and maintain the infrastructures that are
            necessary for hosting reliable publication platforms. A funding scheme for a national
            infrastructure has recently been negotiated for hosting scholarly data at large in a
            stable environment.<note>
              <p><foreign xml:lang="de">Nationale Forschungsdateninfrastruktur (NFDI), Deutsche
                  Forschungsgemeinschaft</foreign>, last updated January 11, 2021, <ptr
                  target="https://www.dfg.de/foerderung/programme/nfdi/"/>.</p>
            </note> Building such an infrastructure will certainly change the overall approach of
            scholarly publishing in the middle and long run. At this stage though, it has not been
            fully implemented and we still are in a rather fragmented situation, despite the
            coordination efforts provided by the DARIAH<note>
              <p>DARIAH (Digital Research Infrastructure for the Arts and Humanities), accessed
                February 24, 2021, <ptr target="https://www.dariah.eu/"/>.</p>
            </note> and CLARIN<note>
              <p>CLARIN—European Research Infrastructure for Language Resources and Technology,
                accessed February 24, 2021, <ptr target="https://www.clarin.eu/"/>.</p>
            </note> research infrastructures (both are European Research Infrastructure Consortiums,
            or ERICs).<note>
              <p>On ERICs in general, see <title level="a">European Research Infrastructure
                  Consortium (ERIC)</title>, European Commission, accessed February 24, 2021, <ptr
                  target="https://ec.europa.eu/info/research-and-innovation/strategy/european-research-infrastructures/eric_en"
                />.</p>
            </note></p>
          <p>Several academic actors in the social sciences and humanities are positioned in the
            field of TEI-based scholarly publishing. The <title level="j">Zeitschrift für digitale
              Geisteswissenschaften</title><note>
              <p>Accessed March 21, 2021, <ptr target="http://www.zfdg.de/"/>; 90 articles available
                as of March 21, 2021.</p>
            </note> was created together with the German-speaking branch of the Alliance of Digital
            Humanities Organizations (ADHO), DHd (Digital Humanities im deutschsprachigen Raum). It
            focuses on digital humanities at large, and the articles are mostly in German.
            Eighty-one articles are currently published, all in TEI P5.</p>
          <p>R-I-D-E<note>
              <p>RIDE: A Review Journal for Digital Editions and Resources, accessed February 24,
                2021, <ptr target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/"/>.</p>
            </note> does not follow a similar institutional logic in the sense that it is not
            carried by one scholarly society, but by the virtual Institute for Documentology and
            Edition sciences, the I-D-E.<note>
              <p><title level="a">Über Uns</title>, Institut für Dokumentologie und Editorik,
                accessed February 24, 2021, <ptr target="https://www.i-d-e.de/uber-uns-about-us/"
                />.</p>
            </note> After the institute concentrated for several years on teaching and research, its
            publication organ R-I-D-E has gained momentum over the past several years. All of their
            publications are TEI-based and the data can be retrieved easily.<note>
              <p>See the RIDE GitHub repository, accessed February 24, 2021, <ptr
                  target="https://github.com/i-d-e/ride"/>. There is also an evaluation of all
                questionnaires in TEI XML available for further usage (<ptr
                  target="https://github.com/i-d-e/ride/tree/questionnaire_data"/>). The schema
                documentation was being revised at the time of writing this article; it is based on
                the jTEI Article schema and only deviates for specific aspects related to the nature
                of the publication.</p>
            </note></p>
          <p>Finally, the <title level="j">Jahrbuch für historische Bildungsforschung</title><note>
              <p><title level="a">Jahrbuch</title>, Deutsche Gesellschaft für
                Erziehungswissenschaft, accessed February 24, 2021, <ptr
                  target="https://www.dgfe.de/sektionen-kommissionen-ag/sektion-1-historische-bildungsforschung/jahrbuch"
                /></p>
            </note>—a publication backed by a solid institution, in this case, the Leibniz institute
            for the History of Education —has also been preparing to convert to a full TEI-based, OA
            publication in an eXist database. While it will use the jTEI Article schema for the
            scholarly journal, the goal is to generate continuity between other scholarly resources
            that will also be published in TEI, and the journal itself.</p>
          <p>Elsewhere in Europe, Slovenia has one journal that is TEI-based: <title level="j"
              >Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino / Contributions to Contemporary History</title>,<note>
              <p>Accessed February 14, 2021, <ptr target="http://ojs.inz.si/pnz"/>.</p>
            </note> following the jTEI Article schema. The journal has published 181 articles as of
            2019.</p>
        </div>

        <div xml:id="usa">
          <head>In North America</head>
          <p>Among the scholarly journals based on a TEI format, <title level="j">Digital Humanities
              Quarterly</title> is the most prominent. It has strong ties to the TEI community (its
            editorial board including several active members of the TEI community) and uses a
            customization of TEI P5. <title level="j">Scandinavian-Canadian Studies</title>, which
            had published 185 articles and reviews as of March 21, 2021, uses P4 converted to P5.
            Indiana University has two TEI-based journals: <title level="j">Indiana Magazine of
              History</title> (IMH) and <title level="j">The Medieval Review</title> (TMR) (<ref
              type="bibl" target="#homenda2016">Homenda and Pekala 2016</ref>). The journal of Beth
            Mardutho: The Syriac Institute, <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac
              Studies</title>, has recently been migrated to TEI and is currently converting all
            back issues to TEI.<note>
              <p>See the journal’s home page, accessed February 11, 2021, <ptr
                  target="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/index.html"/>.</p>
            </note>
            <title level="j">Romantic Circles</title> (University of Colorado Boulder) has been
            working with TEI since 2011.<note>
              <p>Accessed February 11, 2021, <ptr
                  target="http://romantic-circles.org/about/about.html"/>.</p>
            </note></p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="advantages">
        <head>Advantages and Challenges of using a TEI-based Format for Scholarly Publishing</head>
        <p>Publishing scholarly journals in TEI offers several advantages on different levels.</p>
        <p>On an economic level, using the jTEI Article schema on top of an OJS workflow allows
          low-budget production of scholarly publications like journals. OJS is an open-source
          platform that can be customized and maintained with the support of an active user
          community. The jTEI Article schema is available for any journal to reuse, and there exist
          transformation scenarios for the OpenEdition platforms. In this process, the development
          needed is limited. In terms of output, the result is clean, and in case of problems or
          bugs, the editors can mostly rely on the community to tweak minor issues. In other words,
          you do not need to invest a lot to publish your journal using such an infrastructure and
          in return, there is little economic gain to be expected from it.</p>
        <p>The low cost and the easy transfer to open science allowed by such an infrastructure can
          appeal to decision makers like university presidents, especially for scholarly domains
          that are comparatively not too impact factor–dependent. There is, on a more political
          level, a growing interest in stable, sustainable publishing solutions that are now
          increasingly being recognized as economically valuable.<note>
            <p>Tony Ross-Hellauer, Benedikt Fecher, Kathleen Shearer, and Eloy Rodrigues, <title
                level="a">Pubfair: A Distributed Framework for Open Publishing Services</title>, v.
              2, November 27, 2019, <ptr
                target="https://www.coar-repositories.org/news-updates/pubfair-version-2-now-available/"
              />.</p>
          </note></p>
        <p>These arguments can explain why convincing decision makers, and more generally people
          from outside the TEI community, to <soCalled>invest</soCalled> in a TEI-based workflow for
          scholarly publishing has become a worthwhile effort, especially in times when the values
          of open science—a philosophy with which the TEI technology is compatible—are being
          promoted.</p>
        <p>We base this assessment on the existence of still-isolated but real attempts, which show
          the ability of TEI schemas to propose a satisfactory processing that complies with the
          main principles of accessibility and interoperability<note>
            <p>On the TEI’s proposed compromise between precision and ability to share, see Bauman
                (<ref type="bibl" target="#bauman2011">2011</ref>). On the challenge posed to the
              TEI by the notion of interoperability and on the need to build a general ecosystem
              conducive to achieving the full ability to share primary or secondary documents, see
              Unsworth (<ref type="bibl" target="#Unsworth2011">2011</ref>). Automatic conversion of
              SSH documents into a common form of markup is currently being explored by the MONK
              project, as described in Pytlik Zillig (<ref type="bibl" target="#Zillig2009"
                >2009</ref>). The Abbot transformation tool developed by the members of the MONK
              project opens promising perspectives for the harvesting of very important XML
              corpuses, and thus contributes to solving the issue of TEI document searchability,
              which is still important today.</p>
          </note> of academic data and metadata.<note>
            <p>Among these attempts we can list the traditional OJS that is the basis of many small
              and medium-sized editorial endeavors, but also major journal hosting initiatives such
              as Érudit (accessed February 25, 2021, <ptr target="https://www.erudit.org/en/"/>);
              other examples are described above in section 1.</p>
          </note></p>
        <p>Two major needs can indeed be identified in the context of SSH journals. The first is the
          need for an interoperable and stable workflow that would be integrated to open source
          publication infrastructures. The second need is for an evaluation and publication process
          that would include transparency as a core virtue. While our proposition, described in more
          detail in the third part of this paper, is aiming at massively improving interoperability
          and stability by relying on certain characteristics of TEI particularly adapted to these
          problems (use of a controlled vocabulary, possibilities of semantic and descriptive
          markup), it is also our goal to encourage discussion of transparency and interoperability
          as key quality criteria in SSH journals. In that sense, the use of TEI technology in an
          editorial process is likely to affect not only workflows but also evaluation criteria in
          general. It is indeed intended to increase the consideration for editorial tasks in the
          context of Open Science in particular, but also of SSH research in general.</p>
        <p>For the TEI community, pushing forward secondary sources in TEI (as opposed to primary
          sources) presents several advantages. The first aspect worth mentioning is an assessment
          of current realities such as was provided in the first part of this paper: we have reached
          more than a critical mass already, one that calls for better coordination and
          sustainability of how the community integrates its outputs.</p>
        <p>Why does TEI encoding work so well for scholarly publishing of secondary sources? There
          are several possible reasons. First, the TEI is flexible in its vocabulary, which means
          that it allows us to manage and bring together heterogeneous sources of information.
          Second, the TEI is not closed. On the contrary, it is conceived so as to allow resources
          to communicate: it enables us to avoid silos of internal formats developed for the use of
          one specific publication platform that will need further specific development to remain
          sustainable, costing a lot to be maintained and stay in use. What makes the TEI valuable
          for secondary scholarly publications is what makes it valuable for any publication: its
          stability, its interoperability, its openness, its reusability. TEI-based scholarly
          publications are made available in a nonproprietary format, which can also easily be
          transferred to OA publication models.</p>
        <p>There is one final argument, proposed by Laurent Romary in the course of the TEI-L
          discussion on the topic, that is less obvious than the previous ones. To him, the main
          advantage of the TEI being the same basis format for primary and secondary sources is that
          it allows scholars to use the same format for primary and secondary scholarly
          publications: for example, for digital editions and articles on the digital editions. This
          continuity between the two major publication dimensions of SSH research activity allows
          both fluidity and solidity. Fluidity means here that integrating elements from primary
          resources to secondary resources (and reciprocally) is made particularly easy. Solidity
          means that the same people who have the expertise in one field can contribute to the
          other: the brainpower available is considerable. But it also means that issues of nesting
          TEI structures are of central importance in this context.</p>
        <p>In terms of research content, the continuum between primary and secondary scholarly
          publications could have another consequence: the TEI community could (or should?) become
          more attractive for scholars interested in less philological questions than the core
          community is: for instance, sociological aspects of knowledge transfer, community
          building, or evolution of research strategies. Journal material could easily be turned
          into a primary source. And there are enough documents available at this point to make this
          corpus interesting to sociologists, sociolinguists, and historians of science. What is
          still missing most of the time is a more obvious download button—that is, a structural
          incentive to use TEI corpora.</p>
        <p>The advantages of expanding TEI-based models to secondary publications would not only
          benefit the TEI community by widening it. It would also make it possible to bypass the
          dead end of reputation mechanisms in the SSH at large. We are currently in a situation
          where scholars, assistants, and research engineers are sacrificing a great deal of time
          and work for the profit of publishing houses that are negotiating reputation for money.
          Coming up with a TEI-based format has the potential to break these reputation rules
          because it is nonprofit, requires little technical maintenance, and allows scholars to
          dedicate more time to reading papers than evaluating their impact factor or abiding by
          publishers’ editorial guidelines (see <ref target="#Kosmopoulos2008" type="bibl"
            >Kosmopoulos and Pumain 2008</ref>).</p>
        <p>What are TEI-based scholarly publications aiming at in general? Mainly, stable and wide
          dissemination. What makes reputation in the realm of such values is neither primarily
          quantity nor established publishing houses but mostly a dissemination strategy based on
          core virtues like FAIR (Findability, Accessibility, Interoperability, and Reuse),<note>
            <p>See <title level="a">FAIR Principles</title>, GO FAIR, accessed February 25, 2021,
                <ptr target="https://www.go-fair.org/fair-principles/"/>.</p>
          </note> and a common set of values and improvements carried out by the community.
          Researchers need relevant papers to be accessible and easy to find, to evaluate and to
          reuse; TEI-based formats can help meet these needs. They are already doing so for
          publishing in the situations described in part 1, and sometimes also for authoring, but
          never so far for reviewing and copyediting.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="improvements">
        <head>TEI-based Workflow Improvements</head>
        <p>To be able to provide a complete publication workflow in TEI, we would not only need to
          improve and develop customizations for publishing and for authoring as they already exist.<note>
            <p>See also Thoden (<ref type="bibl" target="#Thoden2019">2019</ref>) on the strategy of
              converting the workflow and document basis from a proprietary format to a fully
              standards-compliant system in the context of a publishing platform.</p>
          </note> We need to conceive a complete TEI-based workflow, to take into account the
          reviewing and copyediting phase as well—phases that are currently dealt with in other
          formats.</p>
        <p>Complex workflows are at the core of editorial work for scholarly journals. The
          coordination chain usually includes authors, editors, reviewers, and copyeditors.
          Depending on the journal and the reviewing format (single-blind, double-blind, open), this
          can easily add up to ten people working on one text. Our own editorial experience,
          respectively at the <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> and
            <title level="j">Philosophie Antique</title>, can give significant insight into such
          workflows. <title level="j">JTEI</title>, for instance, foresees three different reviewers
          for each paper and three rounds of copyediting (some of which are done by the editors, but
          not all). <title level="j">Philosophie Antique</title><note>
            <p>See the journal’s OpenEdition page, accessed February 25, 2021, <ptr
                target="https://journals.openedition.org/philosant/"/>.</p>
          </note> has a printed edition in addition to the digital one; this implies, in addition to
          double-blind review for each article, a double copyedit for each of the two formats. With
          different issues running in parallel as is now the case in most online publications, this
          means having an editorial interface that makes it possible to deal with different workflow
          timelines at the same time and to assign different editorial roles to one single
          person.</p>
        <p><title level="j">JTEI</title> is working with OJS, as are many TEI-based journals. The
          recent update to version 3.0 has made some improvements to OJS’s functionalities and
          interface, but OJS still suffers from being developed for too many different uses, making
          it occasionally tricky to tailor for specific needs. For years, the overall management of
            <title level="j">JTEI</title> was actually dealt with not in OJS itself, but in tables
          archived in separate Google documents (one Google document for each issue of the journal),
          because OJS proved unable to offer such an overview in the way that was needed. This type
          of management has the inconvenience that the text and the information on the status of the
          text are separated, making an overview difficult to gain for the different actors involved
          in the process of text production. <title level="j">Philosophie Antique</title> is even
          worse off. The workflow does not use any content management interface. The editorial team
          works by document exchange, archiving successive versions, with two parallel workflows for
          the preparation of the PDF to be printed and the uploading of texts in HTML, using the
          Lodel tool on the OpenEdition interface.</p>
        <p>These two examples are symptomatic of the situation in many journals. Compared to this
          reality, it is clear that, to be able to deal with the complexity of workflows as we know
          them today, the texts should ideally contain metadata allowing one to see at first glance,
          as well as to process automatically, their editorial status. This is one of the many
          improvements that the TEI can provide.</p>
        <p>To conceive a TEI encoding that would fulfill the reviewing and copyediting function and
          allow for an overview of the editorial status of the text, let us first consider the
          different roles (author, reviewer, copyeditor) and the different types of interventions in
          the text. In an ideal world, each role would correspond to a type of intervention, but in
          actual editorial practice, it might well be that the copyeditor who checks for content
          coherence also finds typos to correct. One can divide roughly into two categories the
          types of interventions that will be done on the text: one intervention type encompasses
          content (editorial requirements and their application), while the other one deals with the
          form (ortho-typographical aspects). This corresponds to two workflows that run in
          parallel: one checking for the scholarship, adequacy, and coherence of the article, and
          one checking for its conformance to the typographical guidelines of the journal. The TEI
          encoding for reviewing and copyediting should reflect these two aspects as well as the two
          work phases that are the reviewing and the copyediting processes.</p>
        <p>The first step in a TEI-based workflow will be to define on the one hand roles (e.g.,
          reviewer A, reviewer B, and reviewer C) and on the other hand types of modifications that
          can be undertaken: an editorial schema (<code>EdSchema</code>), a tagset for modifications
          of formal aspects, and a redactorial schema (<code>RedSchema</code>) that allows the
          tagging of content-related modifications. To illustrate the prototype we have in mind, we
          used existing examples of articles already published or in the process of being published
          and converted the copyediting/reviewing process from the Word document to a TEI-based version.<note>
            <p>We would like to thank the authors, reviewers, and copyeditors who allowed us to use
              for this purpose data that are usually not made public but considered part of the
                <soCalled>black box</soCalled> of academic publishing.</p>
          </note></p>

        <figure xml:id="workflow">
          <graphic url="media/image1.png" width="1216px" height="789px"/>
          <head type="legend">Workflow pattern</head>
        </figure>

        <p>The graph in <ptr target="#workflow" type="crossref"/> is a simplified representation of
          the annual workflow of the journal <title level="j">Philosophie Antique</title>. Each
          article submitted and published by the journal goes through the same process.</p>
        <p>The first part of the process is dedicated to the scholarly evaluation of the paper’s
          content; it concerns the reviewers (whose names remain unknown to the authors), the
          authors, and the journal’s editors. All this part would be encoded using the
            <code>RedSchema</code> subscheme.</p>
        <p>The work of formal preparation for publication takes place in a second stage that
          partially overlaps the first one. It partly concerns the authors (at two different
          moments: delivery of the last version of the text, and proofreading) and the editorial
          team. It would be encoded using the <code>EdSchema</code> subscheme.</p>
        <p>We find a strong advantage to this visualization of the workflow by task cycle and not by
          agent because it allows us to de-individualize the different interventions on the text,
          which must essentially be approached not according to their source (who intervenes) but
          according to their nature (what type of intervention). The actors within each stage are
          then only differentiated by a <att>resp</att> attribute, which can be anonymized according
          to the editorial needs (especially in the first stage for a double-blind review), and
          their interventions fit into one or the other of the subschemes depending on whether they
          concern content, or form and presentation.</p>
        <p><code>EdSchema</code> allows the tagging of elements from the review process as well as
          from the copyediting process. The tags are attributed to the different <gi>resp</gi>s
          defined in the <gi>respStmt</gi> part of the header and associated with an
            <att>xml:id</att> (see <ptr target="#ex1a #ex1b" type="crossref"/> and <ptr
            target="#ex5a #ex5b #ex5c" type="crossref"/>). <code>EdSchema</code> contains primarily
          the <gi>lem</gi>, <gi>add</gi>, <gi>del</gi>, and <gi>choice</gi> elements.</p>

        <figure xml:id="ex1a">
          <graphic url="media/image2.png" width="1216px" height="789px"/>
          <head type="legend">Review process with track changes</head>
        </figure>
        <figure xml:id="ex1b">
          <graphic url="media/image3.png" width="1216px" height="789px"/>
          <head type="legend">Tags from <code>EdSchema</code> used for the review process</head>
        </figure>

        <p><code>RedSchema</code> consists of a tagset that is in part similar to that of
            <code>EdSchema</code>, with each tag attributed to its corresponding role (author,
          reviewer, editor ; see <ptr target="#ex2a #ex2b" type="crossref"/>).</p>

        <figure xml:id="ex2a">
          <graphic url="media/image4.png" width="1216px" height="789px"/>
          <head type="legend">Scholarly evaluation and comments in a word processor</head>
        </figure>
        <figure xml:id="ex2b">
          <graphic url="media/image5.png" width="1216px" height="789px"/>
          <head type="legend">Scholarly evaluation and comments with <code>RedSchema</code></head>
        </figure>

        <p>Both types of interventions are likely to involve short alterations (changes in
          punctuation marks, for instance), bibliographical elements (see <ptr target="#ex4a #ex4b"
            type="crossref"/>),<note>
            <p>It should be possible to add a bibliographical entry using the <gi>resp</gi> to
              indicate that it comes from a specific reviewer or a copyeditor.</p>
          </note> and longer text passages that need re-writing, this last category being more
          likely to be relevant to <code>RedSchema</code>.</p>
        <p>To address remarks that require the rewriting of a longer text passage,
            <code>RedSchema</code> needs to include an anchor-based tagset that allows pointing to a
          comment, which in turns should allow the author(s) and/or editor(s) to answer this comment
          (see <ptr target="#ex3a #ex3b" type="crossref"/>, <ptr target="#ex4a #ex4b"
            type="crossref"/>, <ptr target="#ex5a #ex5b #ex5c" type="crossref"/> and <ptr
            target="#ex6a #ex6b" type="crossref"/>).</p>

        <figure xml:id="ex3a">
          <graphic url="media/image6.png" width="1216px" height="789px"/>
          <head type="legend">Copyediting discussion in a word processor</head>
        </figure>
        <figure xml:id="ex3b">
          <graphic url="media/image7.png" width="1216px" height="789px"/>
          <head type="legend"><code>RedSchema</code> with discussion</head>
        </figure>

        <figure xml:id="ex4a">
          <graphic url="media/image9.png" width="1216px" height="789px"/>

          <head type="legend"><code>RedSchema</code> with bibliographical improvement from
            reviewer</head>
        </figure>

        <figure xml:id="ex4b">
          <graphic url="media/image8.png" width="1216px" height="789px"/>
          <head type="legend">Comment in word processor with bibliographical improvement from
            reviewer</head>
        </figure>

        <figure xml:id="ex5a">
          <graphic url="media/image10.png" width="1216px" height="789px"/>
          <head type="legend">Discussion leading to modification of a footnote in word
            processor</head>
        </figure>
        <figure xml:id="ex5b">
          <graphic url="media/image11.png" width="1216px" height="789px"/>
          <head type="legend">Modification of a footnote following a discussion in word
            processor</head>
        </figure>
        <figure xml:id="ex5c">
          <graphic url="media/image12.png" width="1216px" height="789px"/>
          <head type="legend"><code>RedSchema</code> with discussion and modification of a
            footnote</head>
        </figure>

        <figure xml:id="ex6a">
          <graphic url="media/image13.png" width="1216px" height="789px"/>
          <head type="legend"><gi>teiHeader</gi> of examples in <ptr target="#ex3b #ex5c"
              type="crossref"/></head>
        </figure>
        <figure xml:id="ex6b">
          <graphic url="media/image14.png" width="1216px" height="789px"/>
          <head type="legend">Examples in <ptr target="#ex3b #ex5c" type="crossref"/></head>
        </figure>

        <p>To generate a clean text, in the end, the last modification would be considered as final,
          which means that the last copyeditor should validate with their <att>resp</att> attribute
          the earlier modification layers according to the final editorial decision.</p>
        <p>The main advantage of such an encoding system is that it sums up in one file all the
          editorial evolution of a text, from submission to publication, displaying precisely its
          evolution and the contribution of each one of those who were involved in this process. It
          is, therefore, a question of including within the chain that structures and edits content
          the part corresponding to the evaluation and formatting, and thus making it visible and
          shareable. In this way, the data are made open to the point of the preparation of the data
          themselves. It is worth noting that recent efforts made by scientific publishers to
          automate workflows have focused on publishing content but did not include the preparation
          of such content.<note>See, for instance, the METOPES XML editorial workflow, which is
            based on the principle of single-source publishing but leaves aside the preparation of
            content itself: <title level="a">Environnement Métopes</title>, pôle Document numérique,
            Maison de la recherche en sciences humaines (CNRS / Université de Caen Normandie),
            accessed February 25, 2021, <ptr
              target="http://www.unicaen.fr/recherche/mrsh/document_numerique/outils/metopes"/>,
            which is not making its schemas openly available at this stage. </note></p>
        <p>All of this is summed up not only in one file but also in one unique file format,
          guaranteeing conversion without information loss. It allows splitting the editorial work
          on form and content, giving the editor the final hand on the last version of the text. And
          finally, it should be conceived as a fairly minimal combination of tagsets, meaning that
          these schemas should be easy to share with other scholars and journals.</p>
        <p>It would have, on the downside, the inconvenience that comes with its advantages: being
          multilayered, such a document might quickly become complex. Transformation scenarios
          filtering specific tagsets to gain readability will be made necessary: both readability
          for the human eye and information extraction for digital tools would rely on the
          development of such transformation scenarios. But all in all, the development of such
          schemas and transformation scenarios seems in the realm of the doable considering what the
          TEI has been able to develop over the last three decades.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="structural">
        <head>Structural Workflow Improvements beyond the TEI</head>
        <p>The main reason why corrections are implemented, and the correction process hidden from
          the public eye, is a need for control. Editors and authors want to have control over each
          modification in the text, be it punctuation, bibliography formatting, or a sentence that
          seems a bit difficult to understand. This is all the more important in the case of papers
          written by nonnative speakers. Those need close linguistic attention to reach the same
          level of readability as those written by native speakers.</p>
        <p>But looking at it more closely, the whole workflow inherent to this control of
          modifications and corrections is based on reputation control. It is based on editorial
            <soCalled>black boxes</soCalled> that keep articles away from the public eye as long as
          they are not <soCalled>perfect</soCalled> or <soCalled>finished</soCalled>. It is based on
          the idea that work in progress can damage reputation. This is exactly what started to
          change with the publishing of digital scholarly editions online. The fact that it is
          possible to update a digital scholarly edition suggests that we could at least imagine
          that such plasticity can be envisioned for journal articles too. Making it possible to
          work with sources that are not fixed in time is one of the greatest instances of
          intellectual progress not only made possible but actually realized by the TEI. Taking it
          one step further for scholarly journals is a fascinating intellectual challenge in terms
          of data dissemination quality assurance.<note>
            <p>Easy access to all the data from the editing process in a structured format could be
              a decisive step in promoting open peer-review practices. Langlais (<ref type="bibl"
                target="#langlais2016">2016</ref>) thus questions the relationship between the
              success of recent attempts at open review and the tools used, and suggests that new
              devices in this direction remain rare and experimental (26–27). We can also refer to
              Fitzpatrick and Santo, who propose an interesting specification of a tool or an
              ecosystem of tools favorable to open peer review; the notion of aggregation (<title
                level="a">An open review system must be able to gather and display the complete
                contributions of an individual user</title>) (<ref type="bibl"
                target="#fitzpatrick2012">2012, 24</ref>) seems particularly interesting to us and
              convergent with what we propose.</p>
          </note> It is also the logical next step in terms of data empowerment.</p>
        <p>This could easily be encouraged by two (infra)structural lines of action. The first one
          is to further foster pre-print publications (JTEI encourages such publications for papers
          submitted to it). The second one consists in improving the academic recognition of
          editorial expertise. There are already many experts in TEI working as research engineers
          or editorial assistants. They are in general working for specific journals: for example,
          for an editor or publisher. This expertise should be better recognized than it is now, and
          valued more explicitly in advertisements for editorial jobs. The TEI community should
          encourage this expertise to be better represented, for instance in the special interest
          groups (SIGs) or through the awarding of prizes. The academic publishing market has been
          intensely professionalized in terms of digital competence for several years, particularly
          through the emergence of networks such as the Medici network,<note>
            <p><title level="a">Médici (Métiers de l’ÉDition sCIentifique publique)</title>,
              accessed February 25, 2021, <ptr target="http://medici.in2p3.fr/?lang=fr"/>.</p>
          </note> which has helped in the continued training of editors. The profession is now ready
          to integrate such a workflow and support its development.</p>
        <p>If we were to alter the workflow in such a way that the versioning occurring alongside
          reviewing and copyediting was easily manageable, it would mean that successive updated
          versions could be published online in preprint archives until the journal publication
          appears. For instance, it would be possible to filter through customized transformations
          what would be suitable for predefined publication steps up to the final version. It would
          be possible to tailor the review process to make it completely open, open for
            <code>EdSchema</code>, open for <code>RedSchema</code>, or not open at all, according to
          the author’s wish and/or the journal’s policy. The same goes for copyediting.</p>
        <p>In this situation where the dialogue between authors, reviewers, and editors can be made
          transparent within the text, scholars would be in a different position than that of
          accepting or refusing a correction suggestion. The dynamics of the relationships between
          those involved in the process of generating the text could benefit from this change. The
          TEI community could be actively involved in providing schematrons, stylesheets, and
          publishing environments for journals that would allow researchers to access TEI documents
          directly, be it their own for additional editorial work or others’ for queries.</p>
        <p>One relatively easy way to implement such a workflow consists in building overlay
          journals like those hosted on the Episciences platform,<note>
            <p>Accessed February 25, 2021, <ptr target="https://www.episciences.org/"/>.</p>
          </note> which only provides an additional review layer on top of preprint publications.
          The interface allows a journal to set up a review process and link to the evaluated and
          selected preprints to make up a journal issue. While this greatly simplifies the review
          process, especially because of the easy-to-adjust interface, it does not really address
          the online presentation of publications in a reader-friendly way, for which other
          solutions have to be implemented and which would require an additional investment.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="conclusion">
        <head>Conclusion</head>
        <p>Workflows are complicated because, in theory, they address all the needs of the editorial
          process. In terms of scholarly publishing workflows, there is some development work to do
          before we will be able to disseminate an encompassing TEI schema for authoring, reviewing,
          and publishing. The encoding we have proposed here could serve as a basis; potential users
          are already working with a TEI-based publishing format, and the TEI community has a great
          deal of expertise to build upon. Looking at the many journals that are already working
          with a TEI-based publishing format, there is one major thing required to take it to the
          next step: good documentation everywhere.</p>
        <p>The TEI community is in a position to impact access to knowledge for future
          generations—not only through our digital editions of manuscripts, but also through the way
          we disseminate all the information we gather from working with manuscripts and with
          digital editions. Fostering TEI-based scholarly publications is worthwhile: first, it has
          been done at different scales for publishing and is working; second, our knowledge of it
          allows us to reflect on the specificities of the different disciplines we come from; and
          third, it is up to us to initiate this change because nobody else can do it the way the
          TEI community can. There is no reason why the coming generations should be plagued by
          time- and money-consuming requirements from publishing houses now that there is a real
          political awareness of the need for solid archiving formats and now that the TEI has
          established itself as a standard in so many fields.</p>
      </div>

    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <!-- the bibliography for the article, organized as a series of <bibl> elements inside <listBibl> -->
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bauman2011"><author>Bauman, Syd</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title
              level="a">Interchange vs. Interoperability.</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings of
              Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</title>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies
            7. doi:<idno type="DOI">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Bauman01</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fitzpatrick2012"><author>Fitzpatrick, Kathleen</author>, and <author>Avi
              Santo</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="j">Open Review: A Study of Contexts
              and Practices</title>. Andrew W. Mellon Foundation White Paper. Final version,
            December. Produced by MediaCommons and NYU Press for the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.
              <ptr target="http://mcpress.media-commons.org/open-review/"/>; <ptr
              target="https://mellon.orgmedia/filer_public/20/ff/20ff03e0-17b0-465b-ae82-1ed7c8cef362/mediacommons-open-review-white-paper-final.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="chloe2017">Girard, Chloé. 2017. <title level="a">Les mécanismes de
              centralisation des données de la recherche: Étendre l’accès libre à l’hébergement
              libre</title> [Mechanisms of Centralization of Research Data: Extending Open Access to
            Open Hosting]. <title level="j">Revue française des sciences de l’information et de la
              communication</title>, no. 11. doi:<idno type="DOI">10.4000/rfsic.3255</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="holmes2011"><author>Holmes, Martin</author>, and <author>Laurent
              Romary</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title level="a">Encoding Models for Scholarly
              Literature: Does the TEI Have a Word to Say?</title> In <title level="m">E-Publishing
              and Digital Libraries: Legal and Organizational Issues</title>, edited by
              <editor>Ioannis Iglezakis</editor>, <editor>Tatiana-Eleni Synodinou</editor>, and
              <editor>Sarantos Kapidakis</editor>, 88–110. Hershey, PA: IGI Global. <idno type="doi"
              >doi:10.4018/978-1-61692-834-6.ch005</idno>. Authors’ version available at <ptr
              target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00390966v2"/> .</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="homenda2016"><author>Homenda, Nicholas</author>, and <author>Shayna
              Pekala</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">Migrate, Publish, Repeat: TEI
              Journals in the Open Journal Systems Platform.</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> 10. <ptr
              target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1746"/>; doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.4000/jtei.1746</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Kosmopoulos2008"><author>Kosmopoulos, Christine</author>, and <author>Denise
              Pumain</author>. <date>2008</date>. <title level="a">Révolution numérique et
              évaluation bibliométrique dans les sciences humaines et sociales.</title>
            <title level="j">Revue européenne des sciences sociales</title>, no. XLVI‑141: 73–86.
              doi:<idno type="DOI">10.4000/ress.151</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="langlais2016"><author>Langlais, Pierre-Carl</author>. <date>2016</date>.
              <title level="a">Étude critique des nouveaux modes ‘d’éditorialisation’ de revues
              scientifiques en accès-ouvert.</title> Research report, Bibliothèque Scientifique
            Numérique (Digital Scientific Library). <ptr
              target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01388556"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Zillig2009"><author>Pytlik Zillig, Brian L.</author>
            <author>2009</author>. <title level="a">TEI Analytics: Converting Documents into a TEI
              Format for Cross-Collection Text Analysis.</title>
            <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 24 (2): 187–92. doi:<idno
              type="doi">0.1093/llc/fqp005</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Thoden2019"><author>Thoden, Klaus</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title
              level="a">Modeling Scholarly Publications for Sustainable Workflows.</title>
            <title level="m">ELPUB 2019. 23rd edition of the International Conference on Electronic
              Publishing.</title> June 2019, Marseille, France. hal-02143240, v. 1. <ptr
              target="https://elpub.episciences.org/5560/"/>; doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.4000/proceedings.elpub.2019.2</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Unsworth2011"><author>Unsworth, John</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title
              level="a">Computational Work with Very Large Text Collections: Interoperability,
              Sustainability, and the TEI.</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> 1. <ptr
              target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/215"/>; doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.4000/jtei.215</idno>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
