<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-truan-203-source.xml 1117 2022-06-07 09:19:28Z tiago.sousa-garcia $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI.internal">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Building, Encoding, and Annotating a Corpus of Parliamentary Debates
               in TEI XML: A Cross-Linguistic Account</title>
            <!-- author information in separate <author> elements per author -->
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Naomi</forename>
                  <surname>Truan</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Naomi Truan is a <roleName>Research and Teaching Fellow in German
                     Linguistics</roleName> at the <orgName>University of Leipzig</orgName>,
                  Germany. Her research interests include political discourse, digital interactions,
                  multilingual practices, educational contexts, and language ideologies. Her first
                  book, <title level="m">The Politics of Person Reference</title> (2021), explores
                  various instantiations of the third person in British, German, and French
                  parliamentary debates. As an Alumna of the <orgName>Open Science Fellows
                     Program</orgName>, she is committed to open science and science communication.
                  You can find her publications in open access here: <ptr
                     target="https://cv.archives-ouvertes.fr/naomi-truan"/>.</affiliation>
               <email>naomi.truan@uni-leipzig.de</email>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Laurent</forename>
                  <surname>Romary</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Laurent Romary is <roleName>Senior Researcher</roleName> at
                     <orgName>Inria</orgName>, France, and former initiator and director general of
                  the <orgName>DARIAH European infrastructure</orgName>. He carries out research on
                  the modeling of semi-structured documents, with a specific emphasis on texts and
                  linguistic resources. He has been active in standardization activities with
                     <orgName>ISO</orgName>, as chair of the ISO/TC 37/SC 4 (2002–2014) and ISO/TC
                  37 (2016–) committees, and with the <orgName>Text Encoding Initiative</orgName>,
                  as member (2001–2011) and chair (2008–2011) of its technical council. He has been
                  involved in scientific information (now called open science) policies and
                  corresponding infrastructure deployments (HAL and Episciences) since 2005 within
                  various research-performing organizations.</affiliation>
               <email>laurent.romary@inria.fr</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>06/05/2022</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor role="guest">Georg Vogeler</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="14">Selected Papers from the 2019 TEI Conference</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for
               journals in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking
               to publish full-text articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>annotation</term>
               <term>contrastive linguistics</term>
               <term>parliamentary debates</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="TSG" when="2022-06-22">Final author corrections and editors note</change>
         <change who="TSG" when="2022-06-07">Further author corrections</change>
         <change who="TSG" when="2022-05-20">Inserting author corrections</change>
         <change who="TSG" when="2022-05-06">Initial Encoding</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p>This paper introduces an integrative and comprehensive method for the linguistic
               annotation of parliamentary discourse. Initially conceived as documentation for a
               specific and small-scale research project, the annotation scheme takes into account
               national specificities and is geared to proposing an annotation scheme that is both
               highly standardized and adaptable to other research contexts. In this paper we
               present a specific application of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) framework
               applied to a subset of official transcripts of plenary proceedings in three
               parliamentary cultures. The TEI annotation scheme proposed here has two main
               applications: first, it serves as a basis for encoding parliamentary corpora by
               providing a systematic way of annotating both elements within the text (e.g., turns,
               incidents, and interruptions) and the metadata associated with it (e.g., variables
               pertaining to the speaker or the speech event); second, it provides a
               cross-linguistic empirical basis for further annotation projects.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="acknowledgements" xml:id="acknowledgements">
            <p>We would like to thank Erzsébet Tóth-Czifra, Tomaž Erjavec, and Andrej Pančur for
               valuable comments on earlier versions of this paper.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="editorNotes" xml:id="editor-notes">
            <p>Although this article was submitted to our rolling issue, it was added <foreign
                  xml:lang="la">ex post facto</foreign> with the authors’ consent to <title
                  level="s">Selected Papers from the 2019 TEI Conference</title> given its thematic
               similarities to some of the other articles in this issue.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <!-- text divisions, each with an @xml:id and <head> -->
         <div xml:id="introduction">
            <head>Introduction: Parliamentary Talk as a Linguistic Object of Annotation</head>
            <p> Linguistic annotation can be defined as <quote source="#quote1">the practice of
                  adding interpretative, linguistic information to an electronic corpus of spoken
                  and/or written language data</quote> (<ref xml:id="quote1" type="bibl"
                  target="#leech2013">Leech 2013, 2</ref>). As reflections on linguistic annotation
               go hand in hand with the development of corpus studies (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#ideetal2017">Ide and Pustejovsky 2017</ref>), we argue that there is
               still a need for a context-sensitive, fine-grained annotation of parliamentary
               corpora, specifically in the context of linguistic research. Since linguistic
               annotation shapes linguistic research (i.e., allows for specific research questions,
               but also potentially limits the interpretation), we maintain that the issues and
               decisions pertaining to linguistic annotation are an integral part of linguistic
               research, and, therefore, should be part of the annotated corpus once released and
               should become available to the research community together with the data. </p>
            <p>This paper aims at tackling this issue by offering methodological reflections on what
               doing linguistic annotation within the TEI framework means, especially when the
               annotation serves a small-scale contrastive research project but is geared toward
               further applications and intends to distribute an open and reusable language
               resource. In other words, what can be learned from cross-linguistic research on
               parliamentary discourse for other, potentially more comprehensive, annotation
               frameworks for parliamentary discourse? In this paper, we do not propose any analysis
               or substantive discussion of the data. Rather, we intend, through a focus on
               specialized discourse, to show how and why a reflection on annotation practices
                  <emph>belongs</emph> to the analysis, and is not only a preliminary step. </p>
            <p>On this ground, we present an integrative and comprehensive approach for the
               linguistic annotation of parliamentary discourse on the basis of <quote
                  source="#quote2">small specialised corpora</quote> (<ref xml:id="quote2"
                  type="bibl" target="#koester2010">Koester 2010</ref>). We apply the annotation
               scheme to three electronic corpora based on the stenographic protocols of the British
               House of Commons, the German Bundestag, and the French Assemblée nationale (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#truan2016a">Truan 2016a</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#truan2016b">2016b</ref>, <ref type="bibl" target="#truan2016c"
                  >2016c</ref>). The novelty of this approach is that it integrates three different
               parliamentary traditions. In order to ensure not only the interoperability but also
               the comparison between different parliamentary cultures, we need a common annotation
               framework, flexible enough to accommodate national specificities, yet standardized
               enough to be valid for, we expect, any type of parliamentary discourse. Based on the
               Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) Guidelines (<ref type="bibl" target="#tei2022">TEI
                  Consortium 2022</ref>), the annotation framework combines a high degree of
               standardization with a flexible structure: it is both specific to the methodological
               and technical difficulties encountered while dealing with these particular types of
               corpora and generalizable to other types of linguistic projects that may aim at
               extending or refining the annotation scheme presented here.</p>
            <p>The following discussion proceeds in four steps: first, we explain the rationale
               behind a cross-linguistic encoding of parliamentary debates. Second, we show why the
               TEI is a sustainable, reproducible, highly standardized, yet equally flexible
               annotation framework suited to capturing parliamentary interaction. Third, we
               describe the annotation scheme at the level of the metadata contained in the TEI
               header, more specifically the variables associated with each speaker (each member of
               Parliament in our case). We also detail the annotation scheme at the level of the
               text, delineating why the transcription of speech vocabulary should be preferred to a
               more drama-oriented markup for parliamentary data. Finally, in order to invite
               further applications of the TEI framework, we discuss documenting and archiving the
               data from an open-access perspective.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="section2">
            <head>Adopting a Contrastive View on the Annotation Scheme</head>
            <p> The corpus annotation and documentation takes place in a specific research project
               focusing on the uses and functions of third-person forms in three communities of
               practice: the German, French, and British parliaments (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#truan2018">Truan 2018</ref>, <ref type="bibl" target="#truan2021">Truan
                  2021</ref>). The dissertation project and, subsequently, the manual annotation of
               the three subcorpora and its documentation in open access were conducted by Naomi
               Truan only, but the decisions behind the use of specific tags within the TEI
               framework were made in concertation with Laurent Romary. While the focus of this
               research project and the reasons for the comparison of these three
                  linguacultures<note>A concept that refers to culture in language or the cultural
                  dimensions of language (see <ref type="bibl" target="#risager2014">Risager
                     2014</ref>).</note> will not be discussed in this paper, it appears necessary
               to sketch out the context in which corpus building has materialized. We first discuss
               the focus on parliamentary discourse, then move to the contrastive view underlying
               the project since its inception. We finally set forth the reasons why the TEI is a
               robust procedure for encoding parliamentary corpora. </p>
            <div xml:id="section2.1">
               <head>Why Parliamentary Debates?</head>
               <p>In political discourse, parliamentary debates have recently raised the interest of
                  linguists (<ref type="bibl" target="#burkhardtetal2000">Burkhardt and Pape
                     2000</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#burkhardt2003">Burkhardt 2003</ref>; <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#ihalainenetal2016">Ihalainen, Ilie, and Palonen
                  2016</ref>), especially because they are particularly valuable corpora for
                  contrastive studies (<ref type="bibl" target="#bayley2004">Bayley 2004</ref>; <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#ilie2010">Ilie 2010</ref>). Yet <quote source="#quote3">in
                     spite of the growing visibility of parliamentary institutions, the scholarly
                     interest for the study of parliamentary discourse has been rather low until
                     recently</quote> (<ref xml:id="quote3" type="bibl" target="#ilie2006">Ilie
                     2006, 188</ref>). In this context, parliamentary debates increasingly become an
                  object of linguistic annotation (see <ref type="bibl" target="#fiseretal2018"
                     >Fišer and Lenardič, 2018</ref> for an overview of CLARIN parliamentary corpora
                  on which the corpora addressed here are also listed). </p>
               <p> While we do not engage in a debate on whether parliamentary discourse is of
                  intrinsic research value, we believe that records of parliamentary interaction
                  yield valuable insights in linguistic analysis. First, in most Western countries,
                  parliamentary debates are publicly available in several complementary formats:
                  video, audio, and text. The plenary sessions are already transcribed by a team of
                  professional stenographers familiar with parliamentary procedures as well as with
                  the members of Parliament, thus enabling the researcher to focus on other levels
                  of transcription and annotation.</p>
               <p>The corpus used for the present study relies on the official transcripts of the
                  plenary debates. The differences between stenographic protocols and the
                  parliamentary debates, as well as the problems they raise, have been extensively
                  described for the three countries under investigation (see <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#slembrouck1992">Slembrouck 1992</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#mollin2007">Mollin 2007</ref> for the House of Commons; <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#gardey2005">Gardey 2005</ref> for the Assemblée nationale;
                     <ref type="bibl" target="#olschewski2000">Olschewski 2000</ref> for the German
                  Bundestag). Notwithstanding these valid reservations, official transcripts are
                     <quote source="#quote4">a valuable basis to start from</quote> (<ref
                     xml:id="quote4" type="bibl" target="#zimaetal2010">Zima, Brône, and Feyaerts
                     2010, 140</ref>) (see also <ref xml:id="quote5" type="bibl"
                     target="#cribbetal2018">Cribb and Rochford [2018, 13]</ref>, who speak of
                     <quote source="#quote5">a robust reporting procedure</quote>). Moreover, video
                  recordings are not a panacea since they are highly dependent on the choices made
                  by the cameraperson. In the case of unauthorized turns, verifications with the
                  video recordings are sometimes impossible since the camera focuses on the speaker
                  and very rarely on the co-interlocutors.</p>
               <p>Second, being at the interface between spoken and written data, parliamentary
                  discourse gives access to a wide range of discourse features (see <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#vukovic2012">Vuković [2012]</ref> for a comparison of pre-prepared and
                  spontaneous parliamentary discourse at the House of Commons). Even if official
                  proceedings/transcripts do not adequately capture the interactional nature of the
                  events such as pauses and hesitations (see <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#cribbetal2018">Cribb and Rochford [2018]</ref> for an example based on
                  the House of Commons), we adopted a TEI structure based on spoken data rather than
                  drama-oriented data in order to allow for further projects that would take into
                  consideration the interactional nature of plenary sessions. Finally, parliamentary
                  debates display a wide range of speakers over a large time span, thus inviting for
                  both diachronic and synchronic sociolinguistic case studies in terms of
                  (expressed) gender, status, or political affiliation (see <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#burnettetal2019">Burnett and Bonami [2019]</ref> for the Assemblée
                  nationale).</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section2.2">
               <head>Why a New Annotated Corpus of Parliamentary Debates?</head>
               <p>As sketched above, corpus studies based on parliamentary interaction have become
                  numerous in the last decade. Against this background, what can a new annotated
                  corpus of parliamentary data contribute? Why not work with already available
                  parliamentary corpora? While reference corpora such as the Hansard corpus, which
                  consists of British Parliament speeches between 1803 and 2005 (1.6 billion words,
                  7.5 million speeches), would offer statistically robust results with
                  corpus-assisted techniques, they do not give access to the whole co-text<note>We
                     define co-text as the elements surrounding an occurrence, as opposed to the
                     broader context that may be linked to discourse (see <ref type="bibl"
                        target="#widdowson2004">Widdowson 2004, 59</ref>). </note> because of
                  property rights. Moreover, no equivalent corpora for the German Bundestag and the
                  French Assemblée nationale were available when the project started
                  (2015–2016).</p>
               <p>It should be noted, however, that several projects involving parliamentary data
                  have been launched in the meantime. The <title level="m">GermaParl</title> R data
                  package, a corpus that includes <quote source="#quote6">all plenary protocols that
                     were published by the German Bundestag between February 1996 and December
                     2016</quote> (<ref xml:id="quote6" type="bibl" target="#blatteetal2018">Blätte
                     and Blessing 2018, 810</ref>), has been developed (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#blatte2017a">Blätte 2017a</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#blatte2017b">Blätte 2017b</ref>). Apart from the fact that the period
                  covered by the corpus is by no means comparable to the British House of Commons,
                  it raises problems in terms of transcription that will be addressed below.
                  Furthermore, as the authors acknowledge, <quote source="#quote7"
                        ><supplied>a</supplied> thematically specialized corpus <gap/> may offer
                     significantly more detailed metadata and annotation</quote> (<ref
                     xml:id="quote7" type="bibl" target="#blatteetal2018">Blätte and Blessing 2018,
                     810</ref>). A provisory version of other annotated French parliamentary debates
                  was also created (<ref type="bibl" target="#diwersyetal2018">Diwersy, Frontini,
                     and Luxardo 2018</ref>) after the first release of the corpus in November 2016
                  (see <ref type="crossref" target="#section6">sec. 6</ref> for more detail on the
                  platform that hosts the corpora). </p>
               <p>Parla-CLARIN,<note><bibl xml:id="erjavecetal2021"><author>Tomaž Erjavec</author>
                        and <author>Andrej Pančur</author>, <title level="m">Parla-CLARIN: A TEI
                           Schema for Corpora of Parliamentary Proceedings</title>, v. 0.2, accessed
                           <date>February 8, 2021</date>, <ptr
                           target="https://clarin-eric.github.io/parla-clarin"/>.</bibl></note> a
                  comprehensive project aiming <q>to develop a TEI customisation for annotating
                     parliamentary debates</q> by <q>storing and interchanging linguistically
                     annotated corpora of parliamentary data to be used in scholarly
                        research</q>,<note><bibl xml:id="erjavec2021"><author>Tomaž Erjavec</author>
                        and <author>Andrej Pančur</author>, <title level="m">Parla-CLARIN GitHub
                           repository</title>, accessed <date>February 8, 2021</date>, <ptr
                           target="https://github.com/clarin-eric/parla-clarin/"/></bibl>.</note>
                  was launched in 2018, two years after the open-access release of the corpora.
                  Similarly, ParlaMint: Towards Comparable Parliamentary Corpora,<note>Accessed
                     February 8, 2021, <ptr
                        target="https://www.clarin.eu/content/parlamint-towards-comparable-parliamentary-corpora"
                     />. </note> a project funded by CLARIN, <quote source="#quote8">is a
                     multilingual set of comparable corpora containing parliamentary debates mostly
                     starting at the end of 2015 and extending to mid-2020</quote> (<ref
                     xml:id="quote8" type="bibl" target="#erjavecetal2020">Erjavec et al. 2020,
                     Description</ref>). ParlaMint was not, however, available when Naomi Truan
                  started her PhD (2015), as it was launched in July 2020. While these projects
                  offer important and valuable sources of comparison, the annotation scheme
                  described in this paper was conceived before they were launched. </p>
               <p> Most of the projects presented above differ significantly from the small-scale
                  contrastive project which is the focus of this paper, however, as they involve
                  teams and infrastructures, while the TEI annotation presented here has been
                  implemented by one person only (the first author). The annotation scheme used for
                  the analysis (<ref type="bibl" target="#truan2018">Truan 2018</ref>, <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#truan2021">2021</ref>) not only invites extension and
                  possibly revision, but also offers a point of entry for further (doctoral)
                  projects working on small specialized corpora, thus showing what can be annotated
                  for specific research purposes and with limited means. Moreover, small-scale
                  annotation schemes offer other advantages: for example, the possibility of
                  encoding the variable majority/opposition, which had not been implemented
                  otherwise prior to the annotation scheme presented here (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#truan2019">Truan 2019, 45</ref>), as it needs to be done manually. </p>
               <p>The variety of sources and formats is a strong point in favor of a common
                  annotation framework. All the texts have been retrieved from the official websites
                  of the respective parliaments:</p>
               <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item><ptr target="http://hansard.parliament.uk/"/> for the House of Commons; </item>
                  <item><ptr target="http://pdok.bundestag.de/"/> for the German Bundestag; </item>
                  <item><ptr target="http://archives.assemblee-nationale.fr/"/> for the Assemblée
                        nationale.<note> All files are from the <term>Compte rendu intégral</term>
                        (and not from the <term>Compte rendu analytique</term> when it
                        exists).</note>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p> Both the British House of Commons and the French Assemblée nationale display the
                  parliamentary proceedings in HTML, which allows for a quick, easy, and accurate
                  retrieval of the content. The German corpus, on the other hand, is based on PDF
                  files. PDF files are noticeably less adequate for further encoding and tagging. In
                  this case, the files have sometimes suffered from inadequate word breaks, thus
                  necessitating minor corrections.</p>
               <p> We carried out the process of encoding in TEI by combining manual and automatic
                  processing workflows, with the idea of keeping both the content and the metadata
                  of the sources. In particular, we used the GROBID software suite,<note>GROBID is a
                     machine-learning library, with a particular focus on technical and scientific
                     publications, for extracting, parsing, and re-structuring raw documents such as
                     PDFs into structured TEI-encoded documents. For a detailed description, see
                        <ref type="bibl" target="#romaryetal2015">Romary and Lopez
                     (2015)</ref>.</note> which provides a relatively efficient transformation
                  process from PDFs to a decent TEI format, although not fully compliant with the
                  target encoding scheme. Attention was given to unifying the final format across
                  the three languages and parliamentary settings so that the same phenomena and
                  features would be encoded exactly in the same way for each sub-corpus.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section2.3">
               <head>Small Monolingual Corpora as the Basis for a Cross-Linguistic
                  Perspective</head>
               <p>The rationale behind the constitution of <quote source="#quote9">small monolingual
                     corpora</quote><note>The German corpus is the largest, with 417,095 tokens. The
                     British corpus contains 188,913 tokens, the French one 137,620. </note> (<ref
                     xml:id="quote9" type="bibl" target="#koester2010">Koester 2010</ref>) is to
                  allow for the interaction between statistical measures and a close-reading
                  analysis that is sensitive to the sociopolitical context in which parliamentary
                  interaction takes place. In order to ensure that external variables that may shape
                  parliamentary talk are assessed appropriately, the research project that builds
                  the basis for the annotation scheme focused on a limited range of national debates
                  concerning a major European Council meeting (see <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#truan2021">Truan 2021, chap. 4</ref>).</p>
               <p>Despite their high degree of conventionality, parliamentary debates involve a wide
                  range of different activities (or subgenres) such as ministerial statements,
                  speeches, debates, oral/written questions, and Question Time (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#ilie2006">Ilie 2006, 191</ref>). In order to capture a wide array of
                  speakers and to ensure thematic continuity, Naomi Truan selected one plenary
                  debate per year held between 1998 and 2015 in the British, German, and French
                  national parliaments, respectively, about a major European Council meeting (either
                  before or after the meeting or on the same day). As <ref xml:id="quote10"
                     type="bibl" target="#aueletal2014">Auel and Raunio (2014, 17)</ref> stress,
                     <quote source="#quote10"><supplied>p</supplied>roblematic for the comparative
                     analysis is that identifying EU debates is rather difficult in some
                     parliaments.</quote> While the Bundestag and the Assemblée nationale list what
                  they consider to be EU debates on their websites for the current and previous
                  legislative periods, the House of Commons does not provide such information on its
                  website. Search engines do not enable further distinction between the EU being
                  only mentioned in a debate on, say, agriculture on a national level, and the EU
                  being the specific topic covered during the plenary session. For these reasons,
                  and because European affairs are not the focus of this work but only a common
                  variable to ensure the comparability of the data, it has been assumed that the
                  European Council meetings offer a baseline against which to collect the national
                  plenary debates.</p>
               <p> To increase the reliability of the comparison, the genre of parliamentary debate
                  has therefore been considered a constant variable, together with the focus on
                  European Council meetings. The main purpose was to avoid contrastive analyses
                  based on the languages but disregarding the specificities of a particular culture
                  or institution. Following <ref xml:id="quote11" type="bibl"
                     target="#krzeszowski1989">Krzeszowski (1989, 61)</ref>, we recognize that
                     <quote source="#quote11"><supplied>t</supplied>ext-bound CS
                        <supplied>contrastive studies</supplied> are
                     <term>corpus-restricted</term></quote> since no systematic generalizations
                  outside the original data are made. Bearing in mind that institutional settings
                  are accordingly more stabilized, routinized and conventionalized than everyday
                  interactions, it can be posited that genres function as an intermediary level of
                  representativeness prior to analysis or as a first step toward the comparison of
                  discourse communities that should be the basis of expectations of a contrastive
                  discourse analysis (see <ref type="bibl" target="#munchow2010">von Münchow
                     2010</ref>).</p>
               <p>While the annotation scheme described in this paper presents typical features of
                  parliamentary interaction, it also represents a first step toward integrating
                  contrastive perspectives while developing an annotation framework. The advantage
                  of the comparison pertains to its heuristic value: by reflecting on similarities
                  and differences during the annotation process, we come closer to an architecture
                  that is valid and applicable to a large variety of linguistic data and metadata
                  (see also <ref type="bibl" target="#truan2019">Truan 2019</ref> for methodological
                  reflections on contrastive discourse analysis).</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="section3">
            <head>Preventing the Built-in Obsolescence of the Corpus</head>
            <p>In this section, we outline the principles guiding the documentation of the corpus
               and show how the choices we made are intended to serve general purposes. We argue
               that annotating corpora cross-linguistically calls for a very flexible annotation
               framework that allows for multiple, expansible, and evolving annotations that may
               change over the course of time—a principle that is deeply rooted in the TEI. In order
               for this paper to be received outside the TEI community as well, we first briefly
               present the TEI Guidelines and show why they are deemed to be appropriate for
               parliamentary debates. We then link this general framework to what we call a
               sustainable corpus. </p>
            <div xml:id="section3.1">
               <head>The TEI Annotation Scheme</head>
               <p>The Text Encoding Initiative (see <ref type="bibl" target="#romary2008">Romary
                     2008</ref>) has become, since its inception in 1987, the reference technical
                  standard for the representation of textual content in the humanities. Based upon
                  the W3C XML recommendation, it covers a wide range of genres and provides users
                  with a vocabulary of nearly six hundred XML elements. At the core of the TEI
                  Guidelines resides the principle that any TEI-based project should define its own
                  subset (or <term>customization</term>) where the elements which are deemed useful
                  for the representational task at hand are selected, documented, and possibly
                  amended.</p>
               <p>In the context of small specialized corpora, TEI annotation can be used to store
                  the <quote source="#quote12">detailed information about the speakers or
                     writers</quote> (<ref xml:id="quote12" type="bibl" target="#koester2010"
                     >Koester 2010, 72</ref>). Linked with <quote source="#quote13">the goals of the
                     interactions or texts and the setting in which they were produced as part of
                     the corpus database means that linguistic practices can easily be linked to
                     specific contextual variables</quote> (<ref xml:id="quote13" type="bibl"
                     target="#koester2010">Koester 2010, 72</ref>). TEI XML annotation enables
                  researchers to fruitfully visualize the articulation between text and context—that
                  is, between the plenary session and the metadata associated with it.
                  Interpretative data is situated within the corpus using dedicated TEI elements. As
                  we will detail in <ref type="crossref" target="#section6">section 6</ref>, the
                  corpus is available under a CC BY 4.0 license, which enables anyone to correct or
                  extend the metadata if necessary.</p>
               <p>Based on this general understanding, we have conceived the annotation framework
                  with this contrastive research question in mind: the subset we have devised
                  consists of elements that are deemed equally valid for British, French, and German
                  parliamentary debates. We argue that the cross-linguistic view enables us to take
                  into account national specificities while <quote source="#quote14"
                        >emphasiz<supplied>ing</supplied> what is common to every kind of
                     document</quote>, as <ref xml:id="quote14" type="bibl" target="#burnard2014"
                     >Burnard (2014, <title level="a">The TEI and XML</title>)</ref> highlights for
                  TEI. In this sense, and despite the fact that the political context changes over
                  time between France, Germany, and the United Kingdom, TEI gives access to a common
                  technical, practical, and methodological framework between the three subcorpora
                  and the three languages. </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section3.2">
               <head>A Sustainable Corpus</head>
               <p>In designing the TEI-based encoding scheme of our corpus, we intended for it to be
                  easy for other scholars to take it up to carry out various types of research, and
                  also to allow its possible extension (in terms of coverage) or enrichment (e.g.,
                  with additional annotated features). Although we would avoid the term
                     <term>reference corpus</term>, which is more applicable to large-scale
                  endeavors to build up a representative sample for a language (see, e.g., <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#kupietzetal2010">Kupietz et al. 2010</ref>), we strove to
                  create a sustainable corpus that may be combined in time and space with other
                  endeavors to describe language resources in a variety of contexts and for a
                  variety of genres. Within this framework, we saw adopting a sampling strategy
                  focused on our research question not as a restriction in the constitution of the
                  corpus, but rather as a route to a better grasp of the parameters for the
                  linguistic analysis and thus for the encoding.</p>
               <p> With this perspective in mind, we chose the TEI Guidelines as a basis for the
                  encoding scheme because of the lack of consistency across the various corpora of
                  parliamentary debates available online in their native source representations. As
                  reflected in the corpus overview page compiled by the CLARIN
                        infrastructure,<note><title level="a">Parliamentary Corpora</title>,
                     accessed <date>February 8, 2021</date>, <ptr
                        target="https://www.clarin.eu/resource-families/parliamentary-corpora"
                     />.</note> existing corpora have been designed mainly on the basis of
                  proprietary formats ranging from flat plain-text representations (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#kapociuteetal2017">Kapočiūtė-Dzikienė, Šarkutė, and Utka 2017</ref>;
                     <ref type="bibl" target="#frantzi2018">Frantzi 2018</ref>) to ad-hoc XML
                  vocabularies (<ref type="bibl" target="#prazaketal2012">Pražák and Šmídl
                     2012</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#hansen2018">Hansen 2018</ref>; <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#vitalietal2007">Vitali and Zeni 2007</ref>), with even
                  some attempts to define a specific metadata schema for parliamentary debates (<ref
                     type="bibl" target="#gartner2013">Gartner 2013</ref>)—a practice that can be
                  seen as opposite to the underlying assumptions of the TEI community that strives
                  towards finding consensus to cover similar use cases<note>As another illustration
                     of this, we can mention what the TEI Lex-0 has aimed to achieve in the domain
                     of interoperable lexical data and for which it was awarded the Rahtz Prize for
                     TEI Ingenuity in 2020 (see <bibl><author>Eliza Papaki</author>, <title
                           level="a">DARIAH Working Group on Lexical Resources Wins Innovation
                           Prize</title>, <date>November 20, 2020</date></bibl>, <ptr
                        target="https://www.dariah.eu/2020/11/20/dariah-working-group-on-lexical-resources-wins-innovation-prize/"
                     />).</note> rather than <term>ad hoc</term> solutions. Besides, even for those
                  corpora conforming to the TEI Guidelines, there are some strong discrepancies in
                  the actual TEI encoding styles: whereas some (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#research2018">Research Group of Computational Linguistics, University
                     of Tartu 2018</ref>) have used a simple paragraph segmentation for the encoding
                  of turns and associated features, others (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#blatteetal2018">Blätte and Blessing 2018</ref>) have considered
                  parliamentary debates as a possible instance of drama, with a third group of
                  researchers (<ref type="bibl" target="#pancuretal2018">Pančur, Šorn, and Erjavec
                     2018</ref>) who based their work upon the Transcription of Speech module of the
                  TEI Guidelines.</p>
               <p>The (internal) debate within the TEI community as to which module can optimally
                  deal with parliamentary corpora, Drama or Transcription of Speech, relates to a
                  more essential question: how should parliamentary debates be considered as a
                  scholarly source? Three arguments plead, in our view, for an annotation as
                  transcription of speech rather than drama. First, when designing the annotation
                  scheme, we were quickly set on identifying parliamentary debates as the tangible
                  record of an observable interaction rather than a performance that could be
                  derived from a preexisting script. Indeed, even if MPs may be reading from notes
                  when participating in a parliamentary debate, <foreign xml:lang="fr">seul le
                     prononcé fait foi</foreign>, that is, the transcription only records what is
                  actually said.</p>
               <p> Second, even if one could claim—following the theatrical metaphor—that MPs play a
                  role, specifically depending on their relation to the government (majority,
                  opposition) or their specific positioning on certain political issues, we also
                  observe speakers as concrete entities to which we can associate, as we shall see,
                  concrete personal and sociolinguistic markers in the context of a given political
                  speech. Finally, parliamentary debates display a wide range of phenomena
                  pertaining to spoken (multimodal) interactions such as overlaps, interruptions,
                  background noises, or applause, which may all be deemed to bear an interactional,
                  if not political, meaning and thus cannot equate with blocking as indications
                  pertaining to the staging of actors in order to facilitate the performance.
                  Furthermore, MPs often depart from the script (at the British House of Commons,
                  they are not allowed to read a text aloud). While the resemblance between
                  parliamentary debates and theater is attested (<ref type="bibl" target="#ilie2003"
                     >Ilie 2003</ref>), there is always room for improvisation, unplanned reactions,
                  interventions, or comments in parliament. It is true that some of these
                  characteristics may not be transcribed by the official stenographers (see below
                  for a discussion), yet they remain available. </p>
               <p>Third, although some parliamentary records appear to be strongly edited and may be
                  seen as very close to written prose or drama in style or structure, we think it
                  would go against a general effort toward interoperability to adopt, for a subset
                  of the general corpus of parliamentary records, an encoding strategy that would be
                  different from what is needed for more fine-grained transcriptions. As a matter of
                  fact, the tagset for the transcription of spoken language of the TEI Guidelines
                  does not imply that all details from the source must be encoded and one can
                  implement, with a very small subset of the corresponding elements, exactly what
                  could be achieved when adopting an encoding strategy based upon the tagset
                  intended for drama.</p>
               <p> For these three main reasons, we have adopted a TEI annotation scheme distinct
                  from drama.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="section4">
            <head>Enabling Sociolinguistic Explorations: The TEI Header</head>
            <p>The criteria for documenting the corpus are directly derived from the model sketched
               out in the first two sections. In this section, we account for two levels of analysis
               underlying the annotation scheme: first, the TEI header (<gi>teiHeader</gi> element),
               which stores information related to <quote source="#quote15">the metadata associated
                  with the digital document itself, analogous to the title page of a printed
                  book</quote> (<ref xml:id="quote15" type="bibl" target="#burnard2014">Burnard
                  2014, <title level="a">The TEI Header</title></ref>); second, the transcriptions
               of speech within the <gi>text</gi> element itself (for instance, the distribution of
               turns). </p>
            <div xml:id="section4.1">
               <head>Political Speakers: The TEI Element <gi>person</gi>
               </head>
               <p> In this part, we describe the metadata attached to the TEI element
                     <gi>person</gi> corresponding to each speaker. In this corpus, the TEI header
                  contains, among others, the metadata (or variables) associated with the
                  environment of the parliamentary debate (organization, place, and date encoded in
                     <gi>settingDesc</gi>: see <ref type="crossref" target="#example3">example
                     3</ref>) and with the speakers (name, sex, political party, political
                  affiliation, and position encoded in <gi>particDesc</gi>: see <ref type="crossref"
                     target="#example1">example 1</ref>).<note>For a comprehensive mapping of all
                     the TEI tags used in this work and how they have been applied to parliamentary
                     debates specifically, see <ref type="bibl" target="#truan2016a">Truan
                        2016a</ref>, <ref type="bibl" target="#truan2016b">2016b</ref>, and <ref
                        type="bibl" target="#truan2016c">2016c</ref>. </note>
               </p>
               <p> An important decision was to encode speakers’ related information in the header
                  of each document and to associate such descriptions with a group of features
                  relevant for the linguistic analysis of parliamentary discourse. In compliance
                  with the TEI Guidelines, and more specifically its Language Corpora module (<ref
                     type="bibl" target="#tei2022">TEI Consortium 2022, chap. 15</ref><note>Accessed
                     June 6, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CC.html"
                     /></note>), such information is situated in the profile description section
                     (<gi>profileDesc</gi>) of the TEI header within the element
                     (<gi>particDesc</gi>) dedicated to the cataloging of participants in a spoken
                  discourse. Our choice was essentially motivated by the need to find an adequate
                  compromise between two possible strategies:</p>
               <list rend="ordered">
                  <item> on the one hand, localizing speaker-related information at the utterance
                     level, at the risk of being insufficiently generic, introducing redundancy, and
                     above all introducing contradictory information throughout the document, when
                     annotation is not carried out consistently; </item>
                  <item> on the other hand, grouping all speakers’ related information within a
                     global prosopographic document (i.e., an independent digital thesaurus of
                     persons) where each MP would have been identified once and for all, thus
                     preventing a finer-grained analysis accounting for the variation of, for
                     instance, political roles over time and across parliamentary
                        debates.<note>There is a trade-off here as to how much speaker-related
                        information should be localized with the parliamentary debate as opposed to
                        grouped in a prosopographic document. We expect our encoding to reflect the
                        need to make each plenary debate an autonomous object not requiring constant
                        back-and-forth access to an external authority document.</note>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p> Crucially, providing the speaker’s description at the (local) level of each
                  parliamentary debate or TEI document (i) does not prevent us from setting up an
                  external, more comprehensive prosopographic document where all biographic
                  indications (and somehow independent from specific political contexts) may be
                  maintained (ii). Referring from the corpus documentation to such a prosopographic
                  document by means of the <att>corresp</att> attribute on the <gi>person</gi>
                  element is technically simple. </p>
               <p> Our documentation strategy has been determined by our fundamental decision within
                  our corpus to fragment parliamentary debates into document units corresponding to
                  plenary sessions, with the additional advantage of optimizing the maintenance of
                  the corresponding information within our corpus at large (e.g., allowing other
                  researchers to easily complement the corpus with additional sessions, as
                  independent TEI documents), as well as facilitating cross-session analysis. Hence,
                  each TEI XML document corresponds to one plenary debate as a communicative unit,
                  that is, a given spatiotemporal unit bound to a specific situation in which a
                  group of given participants discusses a given topic (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#kerbrat1990">Kerbrat-Orecchioni 1990, 216</ref>), thus making the text
                  the proper linguistic object under investigation.<note>But note that one session
                     can last more than one day, i.e., can be split.</note>
               </p>
               <p> We have chosen to identify the speakers in each debate in the corresponding
                  header and <emph>not</emph> in each utterance (or prior to each utterance) for
                  three main reasons: </p>
               <list rend="ordered">
                  <item> it makes the TEI document more readable at first glance since the metadata
                     associated with each speaker is not mixed—and thus potentially hard to
                     retrieve—all together in the text (see the ode to simplicity in the next
                     section); </item>
                  <item> it ensures the consistency of the parameters applied to each speaker since
                     the list of the speakers attending a specific plenary debate is given at the
                     beginning; </item>
                  <item> it permits the development and extension of the metadata associated with
                     each speaker if necessary by changing the TEI header only once, and not every
                     time a speaker produces a new turn. </item>
               </list>
               <p>In this context, the documentation of speakers in the header plays a double role
                  for the management of our transcription document:</p>
               <list rend="ordered">
                  <item> first, it ensures unique identification of the speakers<note>Speakers are
                        mostly, but not only, MPs. For instance, in France, members of the
                        government who are not members of the parliament can be invited to make a
                        speech. </note> across their various interventions within a plenary debate; </item>
                  <item> second, it provides various descriptive features which are both stable for
                     the corresponding debate and relevant for the purpose of the study of
                     parliamentary discourse at large. </item>
               </list>
               <figure xml:id="example1">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <teiHeader>
                        <profileDesc> ... <particDesc>
                              <listPerson type="parliamentarians"> ... <person
                                    xml:id="ROBERTSON-ANGUS">
                                    <persName>Angus Robertson</persName>
                                    <sex>male</sex>
                                    <occupation>MP</occupation>
                                    <affiliation>Scottish National Party</affiliation>
                                    <trait type="party">
                                       <desc>Independent</desc>
                                    </trait>
                                    <floruit>opposition</floruit>
                                    <nationality>UK</nationality>
                                    <residence>Moray</residence>
                                 </person> ... </listPerson>
                           </particDesc>
                        </profileDesc>
                     </teiHeader>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Example of a speaker’s description entry in the TEI header of
                     a session document</head>
               </figure>
               <p> Usually, the <gi>id</gi> of a speaker corresponds to the last name. When speakers
                  share their last names with another speaker of the corpus, as is the case here,
                  the first names are added. Another option could have been to add the date of birth
                  for each speaker. </p>
               <p> The first group of features attached to the description of an MP within a plenary
                  debate corresponds to stable—or very rarely varying—characteristics pertaining to
                  the identification of the speakers according to long-term properties such as name
                     (<gi>persName</gi>), sex (<gi>sex</gi>
                  <note>Although the TEI documentation reports on a <att>value</att> attribute to
                     normalize the corresponding content of the <gi>sex</gi> element, it does not
                     provide a real standardized set of values as reference (<ref type="bibl"
                        target="#tei2022">TEI Consortium 2022, Appendix C: Elements, <gi>sex</gi>,
                           <ptr
                           target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-sex.html"
                        /></ref>). We thus discarded this attribute in our encoding, but we used
                     normalized values within the corpus (male/female/none). </note>), and
                  nationality (<gi>nationality</gi>). The content of <gi>sex</gi> allows for simple
                  comparisons such as length of speeches by gender (see <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#truan2021">Truan 2021, chap. 4</ref>).</p>
               <p> The second group of features is more specific to each plenary debate and
                  corresponds to the political characteristics of the speakers: their political
                  affiliation (<gi>affiliation</gi>), their relation to current government
                     (<gi>floruit</gi>,<note> Although the description of the <gi>floruit</gi>
                     element in the TEI Guidelines may suggest that <gi>floruit</gi> should remain
                     limited to the description of a temporal time span, we consider it acceptable
                     to extend this description to the nature of the activity of the person in the
                     given time span, especially when this activity may change over time, as is the
                     case for the variable majority/opposition in the political sphere. </note> with
                  values <val>majority</val>and <val>opposition</val>), and the district that
                  elected them (<gi>residence</gi>).</p>
               <p> This approach allowed us to look into the corpus through variables that have not,
                  as far as we know, been consistently integrated into the corpus-based and
                  corpus-driven analysis of parliamentary discourse so far. We are able to gain
                  insights into the relationship between opposition and majority in terms of person
                  reference that otherwise would have remained hidden. For instance, referring to
                     <term xml:lang="fr">certains</term> (<term>some</term>), for a member of the
                  UMP (Conservatives in France), is likely to denote the Communists at the Assemblée
                  nationale (see <ref type="bibl" target="#truan2021">Truan 2021, chap. 7</ref>).
                  Building categories of discourse participants is closely intertwined with the
                  speaker’s construal of who is included and who is excluded. Such a finding could
                  only be attained through the exploration of the correlation between linguistic
                  forms and manually encoded variables in the form of TEI constructs.</p>
               <p> The annotation framework was geared toward the coding of external variables (or
                  metadata) which had only rarely been taken into account until the first release of
                  the corpus in November 2016, such as the variable majority/opposition or grouping
                  together parliamentary groups such as PDS/Die Linke that are coded as
                     <soCalled>Far Left</soCalled> (see the use of <gi>trait</gi> in <ptr
                     type="crossref" target="#example1"/>) (for some observations on the variable
                  majority/opposition in a Norwegian corpus, see <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#lapponietal2016">Lapponi and Søyland 2016</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#lapponietal2018">Lapponi et al. 2018</ref>). </p>
               <p> Although we have not encountered this situation in our corpus, it should be
                  pointed out that even in the last group of features, a change can happen within a
                  given debate, when for instance an MP changes sides. Such a scenario occurred with
                  the creation of The Independent Group (TIG) in February 2019. In such cases, the
                  flexibility of the TEI toolkit would allow for a meaningful representation through
                  the use of temporal attributes as exemplified in <ptr type="crossref"
                     target="#example2"/>.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example2">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <person xml:id="SOUBRY">
                        <persName>Anna Mary Soubry</persName> ... <affiliation notAfter="2019-02-20"
                           >Tories</affiliation>
                        <affiliation notBefore="2019-02-20">The Independent Group</affiliation> ...
                     </person>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Exemplifying a change in political party within a plenary
                     debate</head>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section4.2">
               <head>The Speech Event: The TEI Element <gi>settingDesc</gi>
               </head>
               <p>As shown previously, each parliamentary debate constitutes a specific speech event
                  taking place at one time and one place. The speech event constitutes a macro frame
                  in which speakers, who alternatively become hearers as well, produce several
                  turns. The contextual description of the speech event must thus contain the basic
                  features that enable a user of the corpus to situate each utterance within a
                  precise geo-temporal environment, but also to understand the broader political
                  context.</p>
               <p>The TEI Guidelines provide a suitable way to do so within the TEI header by using
                  the <gi>setting</gi> element within a <gi>settingDesc</gi> element, whose usage we
                  have adapted to match our purposes. As illustrated in the example below, we have
                  described the following features attached to a parliamentary debate:</p>
               <list rend="ordered">
                  <item>the name of the organization (<gi>orgName</gi>
                     <note> It might have been preferable to actually indicate the organization
                           (<tag type="start">org type="parliament"</tag>) rather than just the
                        name, but the corresponding element is currently not allowed in
                           <gi>setting</gi>.</note>) where the debate is taking place, namely the
                     corresponding national parliament (for this corpus: House of Commons, Deutscher
                     Bundestag, and Assemblée Nationale);</item>
                  <item>the actual date of the debate (<tag type="start">date
                        type="parliamentaryDebateDate"</tag>) both as recorded in the original
                     transcript and normalized according to the ISO standard 8601 (yyyy-mm-dd); </item>
                  <item>the name of the head of government in place (<gi>persName</gi>, <note>A
                        further development of general guidelines for such encodings should lead to
                        agreement on a <att>type</att> for such elements (e.g.,
                           <att>type</att>=<val>governmentHead</val>)</note> so that the debate can
                     be easily understood in relation to a wider political context. We adopted a
                     complementary numbering marker (e. g., Blair I, Blair II, Blair III, etc.) to
                     signal successive governments with the same leader; </item>
                  <item> the actual legislative session (<gi>name</gi>
                     <note>Here also we could think of adding a <att>type</att> to the corresponding
                           <gi>name</gi> element within a larger standardization context, and
                        possibly link this with a reference document of legislature events.</note>)
                     within which the debate is taking place. </item>
               </list>
               <p>In addition to these generic political parameters, we added two specific
                  descriptors intended to provide information about the European debate per se. In
                  doing this, we pursued our general encoding strategy, and reused existing elements
                  from the TEI Guidelines while slightly adapting their semantics as TEI components.
                  For the description of the main topic(s) of the European Council meeting about
                  which the national parliament is debating, we used the <gi>activity</gi> element.
                  For the description of the place where the European Council meeting took place, we
                  used the <gi>locale</gi> element. Both choices could probably be the most
                  problematic ones if we were to carry out a wider dialogue with the scientific
                  community on the standardization process and the encoding of parliamentary
                  debates.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example3">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <settingDesc>
                        <setting>
                           <orgName type="parliament">Assemblée Nationale</orgName>
                           <date type="parliamentarySessionDate" when="2008-12-10">10 December
                              2008</date>
                           <activity>Treaty of Lisbon, General questions</activity>
                           <locale>Brussels</locale>
                           <persName>Sarkozy</persName>
                           <name>XIIIe législature</name>
                        </setting>
                     </settingDesc>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Example of a session’s description entry in the TEI header of
                     a session document</head>
               </figure>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="section5">
            <head>Encoding the Content</head>
            <p> In this section, we present the decisions pertaining to the turn level <ptr
                  type="crossref" target="#section5.1"/> as well as the intra-turn level <ptr
                  type="crossref" target="#section5.2"/>. Importantly, we do not address other
               levels of annotation such as word-level annotation that could have been marked up in
               TEI as well. Indeed, for the purpose of this project, the results are based on
               automatic part-of-speech tagging. The open-source software TXM<note>Accessed February
                  5, 2021, <ptr target="http://textometrie.ens-lyon.fr/?lang=en"/>.</note> (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#heidenetal2010">Heiden, Magué, and Pincemin 2010</ref>) used
               in this project indeed proceeds to language-specific part-of-speech tagging when a
               corpus is imported.</p>
            <div xml:id="section5.1">
               <head>The Representation of Spoken Political Discourse: The Turn Level</head>
               <div xml:id="section5.1.1">
                  <head>Utterances/Turns</head>
                  <p>The element <gi>u</gi> (utterance) in the TEI Guidelines potentially covers any
                     kind of linguistic segmentation in a transcription of a spoken sequence as long
                     as this segment may be attributed to a single speaker. For the purpose of
                     encoding parliamentary debates, we decided to adopt a terser interpretation of
                     this element and considered that it should represent a <term>turn</term> in the
                     standard linguistic terminology. Turns are a superficial unit pertaining <quote
                        source="#quote16">to the surface structure of conversation</quote> (<ref
                        xml:id="quote16" type="bibl" target="#kerbrat2004">Kerbrat-Orecchioni 2004,
                        8</ref>) since they solely indicate a change of speaker. We made this
                     decision to account for the essentially monological nature of parliamentary
                     interaction so that a specific speaker’s turn can be easily identified and
                     distinguished from the preceding and following turns of other MPs.</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u who="#ROBERTSON-ANGUS">On the
                        question of European enlargement and immigration […] </u></egXML>

               </div>
               <div xml:id="section5.1.2">
                  <head> Interruptions </head>
                  <p><ref xml:id="quote17" type="bibl" target="#diwersyetal2018">Diwersy, Frontini,
                        and Luxardo (2018)</ref> observe that the descriptor <quote
                        source="#quote17">speech type (debate, interruption, vote explanation,
                        etc.)</quote>, which we do not use in our corpus annotation, proves to be
                        <quote source="#quote17">particularly important when it comes to
                        differentiate effects of register variation ranging from highly formulaic to
                        less formal speech (as in the case of e. g. interruptions).</quote> The main
                     reason for not annotating this level of analysis is, once again, to be found in
                     the contrastive perspective we adopt. Whereas interruptions are thoroughly
                     transcribed in the official recordings of the Bundestag and the Assemblée
                     nationale, enabling new research questions on the special kind of dialogue
                     emerging during these interactions, unexpected or unauthorized turns at the
                     British parliament are only indicated as <term>interruptions</term> with no
                     further information provided on the nature, source, or content of the
                     disruption, as in the following example:</p>


                  <cit>
                     <quote source="#blockquote"><p>Mr. David Cameron (Tories)
                              <supplied>majority</supplied>: There is a case for saying that the
                           institutions that Europe put in place after the second world war and I
                           would include NATO as well as the European Union have played a role in
                           making sure that we settle our problems around conference tables rather
                           than on the fields of Flanders. To that extent, yes, I think that it is
                           right.</p>
                        <p><emph>
                              <hi rend="bold">Interruption</hi>
                           </emph></p><p>Someone says, <q>Why not go?</q></p></quote>
                     <ref xml:id="blockquote" type="bibl" target="#truan2016c">UK
                           2012.10.22<note>The source of the utterance (or metadata) is to be found
                           at the end of the excerpt in round brackets: ISO 3166 country code (DE
                           for Germany, FR for France, UK for the United Kingdom), year.month.day of
                           the debate.</note></ref>
                  </cit>


                  <p>Although the co-text sometimes gives insights on what kind of
                        <term>interruption</term> occurred (and although the video recordings are
                     available online), it is clear that transcription practices (to name only one
                     factor) have a considerable impact on a contrastive research overall. For
                     statistical purposes, it appeared more suitable to encode changes of speakers
                     without discriminating between unauthorized and authorized interventions, which
                     enables us to retrieve automatically all the utterances of a given speaker.
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="section5.2">
               <head>Segments and Quotes: The Intra-turn Level</head>
               <p> Finally, we had to resort to the very generic <gi>note</gi> element to mark up
                  additional commentaries present in the transcripts of the debates and usually
                  added by the parliamentary clerks:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><note>Official Report, 15 January
                     2014, Vol. 573, c. 11MC.</note></egXML>

               <p> For the purpose of our corpus, we have not fully used the richness of the
                  Transcriptions of Speech module of the TEI Guidelines, as described by <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#schmidt2011">Schmidt (2011)</ref>. This is due to both the
                  specific scope of the linguistic study that we were pursuing and the actual
                  informational simplicity of the available sources. Still, the choice we made of
                  using this module offers the possibility of a variety of potential enrichments,
                  either by ourselves, or indeed by anyone who would want to further complement the
                  corpus. The possibility to align with precision, but means of a timeline, the
                  various turns, sub-segments or any kind of incident, offers the potential to have
                  a better insight in the nature of the interactions carried out in parliamentary
                  contexts, from a prosodic or gestural point of view for instance.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="section6">
            <head>Documenting and archiving the data</head>
            <p>The Text Encoding Initiative has been, right from the onset, the basis for a strong
               open science vision, where interoperability would be at the service of sharing and
               reusing digital content encoded according to the TEI Guidelines (for an overview, see
                  <ref type="bibl" target="#romary2020">Romary 2020</ref>). For this reason we
               provide here an overview of our efforts to make the corpus FAIR (<quote
                  source="#quote18">Findable, Accessible, Identifiable, and Reusable</quote>; <ref
                  xml:id="quote18" type="bibl" target="#wilkinsonetal2016">Wilkinson et al.
                  2016</ref>).</p>
            <p>As already alluded to, the corpus has been designed with the idea that it could be
               easily reused and complemented by others. It thus was in accord with our principles
               to adopt a completely open distribution setting by releasing it on the Ortolang
               platform (<ptr target="https://www.ortolang.fr/"/>). Ortolang combines a number of
               important technical features:</p>
            <list rend="ordered">
               <item> specialization in linguistic data with the ability to attach several
                  linguistic descriptors (language, genre, source type, etc.) to the corpus itself; </item>
               <item> provision of unique identifiers to the resources; </item>
               <item> long-term archiving for all uploaded resources; </item>
               <item> version management, which allows the publication of corrections and
                  improvements to the corpus while keeping the same underlying digital identity; </item>
               <item> precise identification of the various contributors to a resource; </item>
               <item> linking of resources with open licences—in our case a Creative Commons CC BY
                  licence requiring proper attribution to the authors (CC BY 4.0) in
                     <gi>publicationStmt</gi>; </item>
               <item> finally, the ability to add an XSLT stylesheet to the corpus to provide a
                  default search and presentation environment (in HTML). </item>
            </list>
            <p>Beyond the technical setting, we conclude with dissemination issues that, to our
               view, are an essential part of the annotation project. First, we considered that
               beyond seeing the corpus as reusable (linguistic) content, presenting the annotation
               framework as an ongoing process could also play a role as a methodological point of
               comparison for other comparable endeavors. As a consequence, we decided to distribute
               all the source documents rather than limiting access through, for example, a query
               interface, as is the case for the EuroParl corpus. Second, although there are often
               fears of being plundered when data is disseminated at too early a stage in a research
               process, the author who compiled the corpus as part of her dissertation project took
               the decision to have the data online even before the actual doctoral publication was
                  available.<note>One of the points of contention could be that the dissemination
                  through Ortolang is not fully open-source, as it would be through such a platform
                  as GitHub. We see GitHub, which is a private platform and thus does not fulfill
                  all our criteria of a sustainable environment, as a possible front end for the
                  further development of such a corpus as ours, while keeping an environment such as
                  Ortolang as the final publication setting. </note>
            </p>
            <p> The three corpora are available online at the following addresses:</p>
            <list rend="bulleted">
               <item><ptr target="hdl.handle.net/11403/uk-parl"/> for the British corpus; </item>
               <item><ptr target="hdl.handle.net/11403/fr-parl"/> for the French corpus; </item>
               <item><ptr target="hdl.handle.net/11403/de-parl"/> for the German corpus. </item>
            </list>
            <p> These links are dynamic persistent identifiers that always reference the latest
               published version of the subcorpora; thus no specific date of access of the given
               sources is provided. Online access to the corpus (or the three subcorpora) was opened
               in November 2016.</p>
            <p>Since the open-access release of the corpora in November 2016, the corpora (including
               their documentation) have been downloaded (partly or as a whole) 113 times for the
               British corpus, 49 times for the German corpus, and 418 times for the French corpus,
               respectively as of 17 May 2022. The corpora are listed on the CLARIN
                     website.<note><title level="a">Parliamentary Corpora</title>, accessed
                     <date>February 8, 2021</date>, <ptr
                     target="https://www.clarin.eu/resource-families/parliamentary-corpora"
                  />.</note> Moreover, they have been discussed in several other annotation projects
               (see, for instance, <ref type="bibl" target="#blatteetal2018">Blätte 2018</ref> for
               German or <ref type="bibl" target="#diwersyetal2018">Diwersy, Frontini, and Luxardo
                  2018</ref> for French) and used as a comparison corpus for other research projects
               (see, for instance, <ref type="bibl" target="#stefanowitsch2019">Stefanowitsch
                  2019</ref>, <ref type="bibl" target="#zinnetal2021">Zinn and Müller 2021</ref>,
                  <ref type="bibl" target="#piquer2022">Piquer Martinez 2022</ref>). These examples
               show that an early open-access release (November 2016) of the annotated corpora
               together with their documentation, long before the dissertation project was submitted
               (October 2018), is beneficial to the community.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="section7">
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p> This paper has suggested an integrative and comprehensive approach to the linguistic
               annotation of parliamentary discourse that takes into account national specificities
               and is specifically geared to proposing an annotation scheme that is both highly
               standardized and adaptable. The method is based on the TEI framework. We have argued
               that the linguistic features of parliamentary interaction call for an annotation
               scheme distinct from the ways theatrical plays have been accounted for within the TEI
               community. We have also pleaded for an easily reproducible cross-linguistic
               annotation framework. Specifically, we have shown that including metadata such as
                  <term>political affiliation</term> or the distinction between majority and
               opposition is crucial to allowing for the comparison between several parliamentary
               systems. </p>
            <p>We understand this paper as a first step toward the annotation of parliamentary
               corpora on a larger scale. We recognize that the small size of the corpora (from
               approximately 137,000 tokens for the French corpus to 417,000 for the German corpus)
               allowed for fine-grained annotation that may be more difficult to implement on a
               larger scale. Accordingly, the application of this annotation scheme to a bigger
               corpus needs to be systematized. On the other hand, it would also be possible to
               further complement the detailed annotation scheme, for instance by providing
               timestamps and the hyperlinks to the videos, as suggested by <ref xml:id="quote19"
                  type="bibl" target="#cribbetal2018">Cribb and Rochford (2018, 13)</ref>, <quote
                  source="#quote19">so that a user at a particular point in the report can link
                  through to the audio recording effortlessly and accurately</quote>. A more precise
               linkage between the videos and the transcripts could also enable insightful
               annotation in terms of kinesics—a dimension which, arguably, would adequately
               complete a close-reading discourse-analytic endeavor.</p>
            <p>These further extensions and exploitations of the annotated corpora are at the core
               of our understanding of annotation as a process rather than a finished product (see
               also <ref type="bibl" target="#bucholtz2000">Bucholtz 2000</ref>) for a similarly
               reasoned argument in terms of <q>the politics of transcription</q>). In doing science
               in the digital age it is essential to make decisions explicit, transparent, and
               replicable. The annotation scheme developed in this project is only a first step.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <!-- the bibliography for the article, organized as a series of <bibl> elements inside <listBibl> -->
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="aueletal2014"><author>Auel, Katrin</author>, and <author>Tapio
                     Raunio</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">Debating the State of the
                     Union? Comparing Parliamentary Debates on EU Issues in Finland, France, Germany
                     and the United Kingdom.</title>
                  <title level="j">Journal of Legislative Studies</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">(1)</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                  >13–28</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bayley2004"><editor>Bayley, Paul</editor>, ed. <date>2004</date>.
                     <title level="m">Cross-Cultural Perspectives on Parliamentary
                  Discourse</title>. <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>: <publisher>John
                     Benjamins</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="blatte2017a"><author>Blätte, Andreas</author>. <date>2017a</date>.
                     <title level="m">GermaParl: Corpus of Plenary Protocols of the German
                     Bundestag</title>. <publisher>R data package</publisher>, <biblScope>v.
                     1.0.4</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="http://polmine.sowi.uni-due.de/packages/src/contrib/GermaParl_1.0.4.tar.gz"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="blatte2017b"><author>Blätte, Andreas</author>. <date>2017b</date>.
                     <title level="m">GermaParl: Linguistically Annotated and Indexed Corpus of
                     Plenary Protocols of the German Bundestag</title>. <publisher>CWB
                     corpus</publisher>
                  <biblScope>v. 1.0.4</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.3735141</idno>,
                     <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3735141"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="blatteetal2018"><author>Blätte, Andreas</author>, and <author>Andre
                     Blessing</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">The GermaParl Corpus of
                     Parliamentary Protocols</title>. <title level="j">Proceedings of the Eleventh
                     International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC
                     2018)</title>, edited by <editor>Nicoletta Calzolari</editor>, <editor>Khalid
                     Choukri</editor>, <editor>Christopher Cieri</editor>, <editor>Thierry
                     Declerck</editor>, <editor>Sara Goggi</editor>, <editor>Koiti Hasida</editor>,
                     <editor>Hitoshi Isahara</editor>, et al., <biblScope unit="page"
                     >810–16</biblScope>. N.p.: <publisher>European Language Resources
                     Association</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2018/summaries/1024.html"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bucholtz2000"><author>Bucholtz, Mary</author>. <date>2000</date>.
                     <title level="a">The Politics of Transcription</title>. <title level="j"
                     >Journal of Pragmatics</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>):
                     <biblScope unit="page">1439–65</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.1016/S0378-2166(99)00094-6</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="burkhardt2003"><author>Burkhardt, Armin</author>. <date>2003</date>.
                     <title level="m">Das Parlament und seine Sprache: Studien zu Theorie und
                     Geschichte parlamentarischer Kommunikation</title>.
                     <pubPlace>Tübingen</pubPlace>: <publisher>Max Niemeyer</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="burkhardtetal2000"><editor>Burkhardt, Armin</editor>, and
                     <editor>Kornelia Pape</editor>, eds. <date>2000</date>. <title level="m"
                     >Sprache des deutschen Parlamentarismus: Studien zu 150 Jahren
                     parlamentarischer Kommunikation</title>. <pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Springer</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="burnard2014"><author>Burnard, Lou</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title
                     level="m">What Is the Text Encoding Initiative? How to Add Intelligent Markup
                     to Digital Resources</title>. <title level="s">Encyclopédie numérique</title>.
                     <pubPlace>Marseille</pubPlace>: <publisher>OpenEdition Press</publisher>. <idno
                     type="DOI">doi:10.4000/books.oep.426</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="burnettetal2019"><author>Burnett, Heather</author>, and <author>Olivier
                     Bonami</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title level="a">Linguistic Prescription,
                     Ideological Structure, and the Actuation of Linguistic Changes: Grammatical
                     Gender in French Parliamentary Debates</title>. <title level="j">Language in
                     Society</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
                     <biblScope unit="page">65–93</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.1017/S0047404518001161</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="cribbetal2018"><author>Cribb, V. Michael</author>, and <author>Shivani
                     Rochford</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">The Transcription and
                     Representation of Spoken Political Discourse in the UK House of
                  Commons</title>. <title level="j">International Journal of English
                     Linguistics</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
                     <biblScope unit="page">1–14</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.5539/ijel.v8n2p1</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="diwersyetal2018"><author>Diwersy, Sascha</author>, <author>Francesca
                     Frontini</author>, and <author>Giancarlo Luxardo</author>. <date>2018</date>.
                     <title level="a">The Parliamentary Debates as a Resource for the Textometric
                     Study of the French Political Discourse</title>. In <title level="m"
                     >Proceedings of the LREC2018 Workshop ParlaCLARIN: Creating and Using
                     Parliamentary Corpora</title>, edited by <editor>Darja Fišer</editor>,
                     <editor>Maria Eskevich</editor>, and <editor>Franciska de Jong</editor>,
                     <biblScope unit="page">73–77</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>European Language Resources Association</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="http://lrec-conf.org/workshops/lrec2018/W2/summaries/22_W2.html"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="erjavecetal2020"><author>Erjavec, Tomaž</author>, <author>Vladislava
                     Grigorova</author>, <author>Nikola Ljubešić</author>, <author>Maciej
                     Ogrodniczuk</author>, <author>Petya Osenova</author>, <author>Andrej
                     Pančur</author>, <author>Michał Rudolf</author>, and <author>Kiril
                     Simov</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="m">Multilingual Comparable
                     Corpora of Parliamentary Debates ParlaMint</title> 1.0. <date>October 15,
                     2020</date>. <publisher>CLARIN ERIC</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://hdl.handle.net/11356/1345"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="fiseretal2018"><author>Fišer, Darja</author>, and <author>Jakob
                     Lenardič</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">CLARIN Corpora for
                     Parliamentary Discourse Research</title>. In <title level="m">Proceedings of
                     the LREC2018 Workshop ParlaCLARIN: Creating and Using Parliamentary
                     Corpora</title>, edited by <editor>Darja Fišer</editor>, <editor>Maria
                     Eskevich</editor>, and <editor>Franciska de Jong</editor>, <biblScope
                     unit="page">2–7</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>European
                     Language Resources Association</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="http://lrec-conf.org/workshops/lrec2018/W2/summaries/14_W2.html"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="frantzi2018"><author>Frantzi, Katerina T</author>. <date>2018</date>.
                     <title level="a">Tour de CLARIN: Clarin:el Presents the Hellenic Parliament
                     Sittings and Hellenic Parliamentary Corpus H-ParCo</title>. Blog post, edited
                  by <editor>Maria Gavriilidou</editor>. <date>July 30</date>. <ptr
                     target="https://www.clarin.eu/blog/tour-de-clarin-clarinel-presents-hellenic-parliament-sittings-and-hellenic-parliamentary-corpus"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="gardey2005"><author>Gardey, Delphine</author>. <date>2005</date>.
                     <title level="a">Turning Public Discourse into an Authentic Artifact: Shorthand
                     Transcription in the French National Assembly</title>. In <title level="m"
                     >Making Things Public: Atmospheres of Democracy</title>, edited by
                     <editor>Bruno Latour</editor> and <editor>Peter Weibel</editor>, <biblScope
                     unit="page">836–43</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://archive-ouverte.unige.ch/unige:76415"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="gartner2013"><author>Gartner, Richard</author>. <date>2013</date>.
                     <title level="a">Parliamentary Metadata Language: An XML Approach to Integrated
                     Metadata for Legislative Proceedings</title>. <title level="j">Journal of
                     Library Metadata</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
                     <biblScope unit="page">17–35</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.1080/19386389.2013.778728</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="hansen2018"><author>Hansen, Dorte Haltrup</author>. <date>2018</date>.
                     <title level="m">The Danish Parliament Corpus 2009–2017, v1</title>.
                  CLARIN-DK-UCPH Centre Repository. <pubPlace>Copenhagen</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Centre for Language Technology, NorS, University of
                     Copenhagen</publisher>; <publisher>The Danish Parliament</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="http://hdl.handle.net/20.500.12115/8"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="heidenetal2010"><author>Heiden, Serge</author>. <date>2010</date>.
                     <title level="a">The TXM Platform: Building Open-Source Textual Analysis
                     Software Compatible with the TEI Encoding Scheme</title>. In <title level="m"
                     >Proceedings of the 24th Pacific Asia Conference on Language, Information and
                     Computation</title>, edited by <editor>Ryo Otoguro</editor>, <editor>Kiyoshi
                     Ishikawa</editor>, <editor>Hiroshi Umemoto</editor>, <editor>Kei
                     Yoshimoto</editor>, and <editor>Yasunari Harada</editor>, <biblScope
                     unit="page">389–98</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Waseda, Japan</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Institute for Digital Enhancement of Cognitive Development, Waseda
                     University</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-00549764/document"/>; <ptr
                     target="https://aclanthology.org/Y10-1044/"/>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ideetal2017"><editor>Ide, Nancy</editor>, and <editor>James
                     Pustejovsky</editor>, eds. <date>2017</date>. <title level="m">Handbook of
                     Linguistic Annotation</title>. <pubPlace>Dordrecht</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Springer</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ihalainenetal2016"><editor>Ihalainen, Pasi</editor>, <editor>Cornelia
                     Ilie</editor>, and <editor>Kari Palonen</editor>, eds. <date>2016</date>.
                     <title level="m">Parliament and Parliamentarism: A Comparative History of a
                     European Concept</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Berghahn</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ilie2003"><author>Ilie, Cornelia</author>. <date>2003</date>. <title
                     level="a">Histrionic and Agonistic Features of Parliamentary Discourse</title>.
                     <title level="j">Studies in Communication Sciences</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
                     <biblScope unit="page">25–53</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ilie2006"><author>Ilie, Cornelia</author>. <date>2006</date>. <title
                     level="a">Parliamentary Discourses</title>. In <title level="m">Encyclopedia of
                     Language &amp; Linguistics</title>, edited by <editor>Keith Brown</editor>,
                     <edition>2nd ed</edition>., <biblScope unit="page">188–96</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Elsevier</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ilie2010"><editor>Ilie, Cornelia</editor>, ed. <date>2010</date>.
                     <title level="m">European Parliaments under Scrutiny: Discourse Strategies and
                     Interaction Practices</title>. <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>: <publisher>John
                     Benjamins</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="kapociuteetal2017"><author>Kapočiūtė-Dzikienė, Jurgita</author>,
                     <author>Ligita Šarkutė</author>, and <author>Andrius Utka</author>.
                     <date>2017</date>. <title level="m">Lithuanian Parliament Corpus for Authorship
                     Attribution. CLARIN-LT Digital Library in the Republic of Lithuania</title>.
                     [<pubPlace>Kaunas, Lithuania</pubPlace>]: <publisher>Vytautas Magnus
                     University</publisher>. <ptr target="http://hdl.handle.net/20.500.11821/17"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="kerbrat1990"><author>Kerbrat-Orecchioni, Catherine</author>.
                     <date>1990</date>. <title level="m">Les interactions verbales</title>.
                     <biblScope unit="volume">Tome 1</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Armand Colin</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="kerbrat2004">
                  <author>Kerbrat-Orecchioni, Catherine</author>. <date>2004</date>. <title
                     level="a">Introducing Polylogue</title>. <title level="j">Journal of
                     Pragmatics</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
                     <biblScope unit="page">1–24</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.1016/S0378-2166(03)00034-1</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="koester2010"><author>Koester, Almut</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title
                     level="a">Building Small Specialised Corpora</title>. In <title level="m">The
                     Routledge Handbook of Corpus Linguistics</title>, edited by <editor>Anne
                     O’Keeffe</editor> and <editor>Michael McCarthy</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >66–79</biblScope>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Routledge</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="krzeszowski1989"><author>Krzeszowski, Tomasz P.</author>
                  <date>1989</date>. <title level="a">Towards a Typology of Contrastive
                     Studies</title>. In <title level="m">Contrastive Pragmatics</title>, edited by
                     <editor>Wieslaw Oleksy</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">55–72</biblScope>.
                     <title level="s">Pragmatics &amp; Beyond New Series 3</title>.
                     <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>: <publisher>John Benjamins</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="kupietzetal2010"><author>Kupietz, Marc</author>, <author>Cyril
                     Belica</author>, <author>Holger Keibel</author>, and <author>Andreas
                     Witt</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title level="a">The German Reference Corpus
                     DeReKo: A Primordial Sample for Linguistic Research</title>. In <title
                     level="m">Proceedings of the Seventh International Conference on Language
                     Resources and Evaluation (LREC’10)</title>, edited by <editor>Nicoletta
                     Calzolari</editor>, <editor>Khalid Choukri</editor>, <editor>Bente
                     Maegaard</editor>, <editor>Joseph Mariani</editor>, <editor>Jan Odijk</editor>,
                     <editor>Stelios Piperidis</editor>, <editor>Mike Rosner</editor>, and
                     <editor>Daniel Tapias</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">1848–54</biblScope>.
                  N.p.: <publisher>European Language Resources Association (ELRA)</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://aclanthology.org/L10-1285/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="lapponietal2016"><author>Lapponi, Emanuele</author>, and <author>Martin
                     G. Søyland</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="m">Talk of Norway. Common
                     Language Resources and Technology Infrastructure Norway (CLARINO) Bergen
                     Repository</title>. [<pubPlace>Oslo</pubPlace>]: <publisher>University of
                     Oslo</publisher>. <ptr target="http://hdl.handle.net/11509/123"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="lapponietal2018"><author>Lapponi, Emanuele</author>, <author>Martin G.
                     Søyland</author>, <author>Erik Velldal</author>, and <author>Stephan
                     Oepen</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">The Talk of Norway: A
                     Richly Annotated Corpus of the Norwegian Parliament, 1998–2016</title>. <title
                     level="j">Language Resources and Evaluation</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
                     <biblScope unit="page">873–93</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.1007/s10579-018-9411-5</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="leech2013"><author>Leech, Geoffrey</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
                     level="a">Introducing Corpus Annotation</title>. In <title level="m">Corpus
                     Annotation</title>, edited by <editor>Roger Garside</editor>, <editor>Geoffrey
                     N. Leech</editor>, and <editor>Tony McEnery</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >1–18</biblScope>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Routledge</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="mollin2007"><author>Mollin, Sandra</author>. <date>2007</date>. <title
                     level="a">The Hansard Hazard: Gauging the Accuracy of British Parliamentary
                     Transcripts</title>. <title level="j">Corpora</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
                     <biblScope unit="page">187–210</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.3366/cor.2007.2.2.187</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="munchow2010"><author>Münchow, Patricia von</author>. <date>2010</date>.
                     <title level="a">Langue, discours, culture: quelle articulation? (1ère
                     partie)</title>. In <title level="a">Visions du monde et spécificité des
                     discours</title>, ed. <editor>Mioara Codleanu</editor> and <editor>Sandina
                     Iulia Vasile</editor>, special issue, <title level="j">Signes, discours et
                     sociétés: Revue semestrielle en sciences humaines et sociales dédiée à
                     l’analyse des Discours</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="http://revue-signes.gsu.edu.tr/article/-LXz7yiZKgVO69fy49uT"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="olschewski2000"><author>Olschewski, Andreas</author>.
                  <date>2000</date>. <title level="a">Die Verschriftung von Parlamentsdebatten durch
                     die stenographischen Dienste in Geschichte und Gegenwart</title>. In <title
                     level="m">Sprache des deutschen Parlamentarismus. Studien zu 150 Jahren
                     parlamentarischer Kommunikation</title>, edited by <editor>Armin
                     Burkhardt</editor> and <editor>Kornelia Pape</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >336–53</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Springer</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pancuretal2018"><author>Pančur, Andrej</author>, <author>Mojca
                     Šorn</author>, and <author>Tomaž Erjavec</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title
                     level="a">SlovParl 2.0: The Collection of Slovene Parliamentary Debates from
                     the Period of Secession</title>. In <title level="m">Proceedings of the
                     LREC2018 Workshop ParlaCLARIN: Creating and Using Parliamentary
                  Corpora</title>, edited by <editor>Darja Fišer</editor>, <editor>Maria
                     Eskevich</editor>, and <editor>Franciska de Jong</editor>, <biblScope
                     unit="page">8–14</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>European
                     Language Resources Association</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="http://lrec-conf.org/workshops/lrec2018/W2/summaries/4_W2.html"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="piquer2022"><author>Piquer Martinez, Jose</author>. <date>2022</date>.
                     <title level="m">Corpus of Political Speeches: Policy responses to the Great
                     Recession in the United Kingdom and Spain (2008–2014)</title> [Dataset].
                     <publisher>Department of Politics And International Studies</publisher>. <idno
                     type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.17863/CAM.79047</idno>. <ptr
                     target="https://www.repository.cam.ac.uk/handle/1810/332648"/>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="prazaketal2012"><author>Pražák, Aleš</author> and <author>Luboš
                     Šmídl</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="m">Czech Parliament
                     Meetings</title>, LINDAT/CLARIAH-CZ digital library at the Institute of Formal
                  and Applied Linguistics (ÚFAL), Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Charles
                  University. [<pubPlace>Pilsen, Czech Republic</pubPlace>]: <publisher>University
                     of West Bohemia, Department of Cybernetics</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="http://hdl.handle.net/11858/00-097C-0000-0005-CF9C-4"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="research2018"><author>Research Group of Computational Linguistics,
                     University of Tartu</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="m">Reference
                     Corpus of Estonian: Transcripts of Riigikogu (Estonian Parliament)</title>.
                  Last modified <date>December 21, 2018</date>. <ptr
                     target="https://www.cl.ut.ee/korpused/segakorpus/riigikogu/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="risager2014"><author>Risager, Karen</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title
                     level="a">The language-culture nexus in transnational perspective</title>. In
                     <title level="m">The Routledge Handbook of Language and Culture</title>, edited
                  by <editor>Farzad Sharifian</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">87–99</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Routledge</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="romary2008">
                  <author>Romary, Laurent</author>. <date>2008</date>. <title level="a">Questions
                     &amp; Answers for TEI Newcomers</title>. <title level="j">Jahrbuch für
                     Computerphilologie</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">69–90</biblScope>.
                     <ptr target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00348372"/>; <ptr
                     target="http://computerphilologie.digital-humanities.de/jahrbuch/jb10-content.html"
                  />; <ptr target="http://computerphilologie.de/jg08/romary.pdf"/>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="romaryetal2015">
                  <author>Romary, Laurent</author>, and <author>Patrice Lopez</author>.
                     <date>2015</date>. <title level="a">GROBID - Information Extraction from
                     Scientific Publications</title>. <title level="j">ERCIM News</title>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">100 (January)</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01673305/document"/>; <ptr
                     target="https://ercim-news.ercim.eu/en100/r-i/grobid-information-extraction-from-scientific-publications"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="romary2020"><author>Romary, Laurent</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title
                     level="a">TEI Guidelines: Born to be Open</title>. <title level="s">ACDH-CH
                     (Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage) Lecture
                     6.1</title>, <date>June 10, 2020</date>, <pubPlace>Vienna, Austria</pubPlace>.
                     <ptr target="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-02864525"/>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="schmidt2011">
                  <author>Schmidt, Thomas</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title level="a">A TEI-Based
                     Approach to Standardising Spoken Language Transcription</title>. <title
                     level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/142"/>; <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.4000/jtei.142</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="slembrouck1992"><author>Slembrouck, Stef</author>. <date>1992</date>.
                     <title level="a">The Parliamentary Hansard <soCalled>Verbatim</soCalled>
                     Report: The Written Construction of Spoken Discourse</title>. <title level="j"
                     >Language and Literature</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
                     <biblScope unit="page">101–19</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.1177/096394709200100202</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="stefanowitsch2019"><author>Stefanowitsch, Anatol</author>.
                     <date>2019</date>. <title level="a">Delivering a Brexit Deal to the British
                     People: Theresa May as a Reluctant Populist.</title>
                  <title level="j">Zeitschrift für Anglistik und Amerikanistik</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
                     <biblScope unit="page">231–63</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="https://doi.org/10.1515/zaa-2019-0022"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tei2022"><author>TEI Consortium</author>. <date>2022</date>. <title
                     level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                     Interchange</title>. Version 4.4.0. Last updated <date>April 29 2022</date>.
                     <ptr target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="truan2016a"><author>Truan, Naomi</author>. <date>2016a</date>. <title
                     level="m">Parliamentary Debates on Europe at the Assemblée nationale
                     (2002–2012)</title> [Corpus]. <publisher>ORTOLANG (Open Resources and TOols for
                     LANGuage)</publisher>. <ptr target="hdl.handle.net/11403/fr-parl"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="truan2016b"><author>Truan, Naomi</author>. <date>2016b</date>. <title
                     level="m">Parliamentary Debates on Europe at the Deutscher Bundestag
                     (1998–2015)</title> [Corpus]. <publisher>ORTOLANG (Open Resources and TOols for
                     LANGuage)</publisher>. <ptr target="hdl.handle.net/11403/de-parl"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="truan2016c"><author>Truan, Naomi</author>. <date>2016c</date>. <title
                     level="m">Parliamentary Debates on Europe at the House of Commons
                     (1998–2015)</title> [Corpus]. <publisher>ORTOLANG (Open Resources and TOols for
                     LANGuage)</publisher>. <ptr target="hdl.handle.net/11403/uk-parl"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="truan2018"><author>Truan, Naomi</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title
                     level="u"><q>Who Are You Talking About?</q>. The Pragmatics of Third-Person
                     Referring Expressions: A Contrastive Corpus-Based Study of British, German, and
                     French Parliamentary Debates</title>. PhD diss., <pubPlace>Sorbonne Université
                     and Freie Universität Berlin</pubPlace>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="truan2019"><author>Truan, Naomi</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title
                     level="a">Möglichkeiten und Herausforderungen einer pragmatisch orientierten
                     kontrastiven Diskursanalyse: Ein Vorschlag am Beispiel deutscher, französischer
                     und britischer Parlamentsdebatten</title>. <title level="j">Diskurse –
                     digital</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
                     <biblScope unit="page">29–50</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="truan2021"><author>Truan, Naomi</author>. <date>2021</date>. <title
                     level="m">The Politics of Person Reference: Third-person Forms in English,
                     German, and French</title>. <title level="s">Pragmatics &amp; Beyond New Series
                     320</title>. <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>: <publisher>John
                     Benjamins</publisher>. <idno type="DOI">doi:10.1075/pbns.320</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="vitalietal2007"><author>Vitali, Fabio</author>, and <author>Flavio
                     Zeni</author>. <date>2007</date>. <title level="a">Towards a
                     Country-Independent Data Format: The Akoma Ntoso Experience</title>. In <title
                     level="m">Proceedings of the V Legislative XML Workshop</title>, edited by
                     <editor>Carlo Biagioli</editor>, <editor>Enrico Francesconi</editor>, and
                     <editor>Giovanni Sartor</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">67–86</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>Florence</pubPlace>: <publisher>European Press Academic
                     Publishing</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="vukovic2012"><author>Vuković, Milica</author>. <date>2012</date>.
                     <title level="a">Positioning in Pre-prepared and Spontaneous Parliamentary
                     Discourse: Choice of Person in the Parliament of Montenegro</title>. <title
                     level="j">Discourse &amp; Society</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
                     <biblScope unit="page">184–202</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.1177/0957926511431507</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="widdowson2004">
                  <author>Widdowson, H. G.</author>
                  <date>2004</date>. <title level="m">Text, Context, Pretext: Critical Issues in
                     Discourse Analysis</title>. <title level="s">Language in Society</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Malden, MA</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Blackwell</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="wilkinsonetal2016"><author>Wilkinson, Mark D.</author>, <author>Michel
                     Dumontier</author>, <author>IJsbrand Jan Aalbersberg</author>,
                     <author>Gabrielle Appleton</author>, <author>Myles Axton</author>, <author>Arie
                     Baak</author>, <author>Niklas Blomberg</author>, et al. <date>2016</date>.
                     <title level="a">The FAIR Guiding Principles for Scientific Data Management and
                     Stewardship</title>. <title level="j">Scientific Data</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>, article no. <idno>160018</idno>. <idno
                     type="DOI">10.1038/sdata.2016.18</idno>, <ptr
                     target="https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="zimaetal2010"><author>Zima, Elisabeth</author>, <author>Geert
                     Brône</author>, and <author>Kurt Feyaerts</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title
                     level="a">Patterns of Interaction in Austrian Parliamentary Debates: On the
                     Pragmasemantics of Unauthorized Interruptive Comments</title>. In <title
                     level="m">European Parliaments under Scrutiny: Discourse Strategies and
                     Interaction Practices</title>, edited by <editor>Cornelia Ilie</editor>,
                     <biblScope unit="page">135–64</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>John Benjamins</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="zinnetal2021"><author>Zinn, Jens O.</author>, and <author>Marcus
                     Müller</author>. <date>2021</date>. <title level="a">Understanding discourse
                     and language of risk</title>. <title level="j">Journal of Risk
                  Research</title>. <biblScope unit="page">1–14</biblScope>. <ref
                     target="https://doi.org/10/gnwxbv"><idno type="DOI"
                        >https://doi.org/10/gnwxbv</idno></ref>. </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
