<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!-- $Id: jtei-cc-ra-iglesias-192-source.xml 1020 2021-03-25 20:38:03Z pietro.liuzzo $ --><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Code of Maya Kings and Queens: Encoding and Markup of Maya Hieroglyphic
               Writing</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Martin</forename> 
                  <surname> de la Iglesia</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Martin de la Iglesia is the <roleName>digital humanities team member</roleName> on the project
                  <title level="a">Annotated digital edition of Philipp Hainhofer’s (1578–1647) travel and
                  collection accounts</title> at <orgName>Herzog August Bibliothek Wolfenbüttel</orgName>.</affiliation>
               <email>iglesia@hab.de</email>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name> 
                  <forename>Franziska</forename> 
                  <surname>Diehr</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Franziska Diehr is an <roleName>information scientist</roleName> specializing in knowledge
                  representation, currently working as an IT researcher at <orgName>Freie Universität Berlin</orgName>.</affiliation>
               <email>f.diehr@fu-berlin.de</email>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name> 
                  <forename>Uwe</forename> 
                  <surname>Sikora</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  Uwe Sikora works for several <roleName>digital humanities</roleName> projects at the <orgName>Göttingen State
                  and University Library</orgName> with a focus on metadata modeling.</affiliation>
               <email>sikora@sub.uni-goettingen.de</email>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name> 
                  <forename>Sven</forename> 
                  <surname>Gronemeyer</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Sven Gronemeyer is an<roleName> honorary associate</roleName> at <orgName>La Trobe University Melbourne</orgName>
                  specializing in Maya writing and linguistics. </affiliation>
               <email>S.Gronemeyer@latrobe.edu.au</email>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Maximilian</forename> 
                  <surname>Behnert-Brodhun</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Maximilian Behnert-Brodhun is <roleName>developer</roleName> at the <orgName>Göttingen State and University
                  Library</orgName> with focuses on linked open data, databases, and search functionalities.</affiliation>
               <email>behnert-brodhun@sub.uni-goettingen.de</email>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name> 
                  <forename>Christian</forename> 
                  <surname>Prager</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  Christian Prager is a<roleName> Maya epigrapher</roleName> and coordinates the project <title level="a">Text Database
                  and Dictionary of Classic Mayan</title> at the <orgName>University of Bonn</orgName>. </affiliation>
               <email>cprager@uni-bonn.de</email>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name> 
                  <forename>Nikolai</forename> 
                  <surname>Grube</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Nikolai Grube is the <roleName>director of the project</roleName> <title level="a">Text Database and Dictionary of
                  Classic Mayan</title> and professor in the <orgName>Department of the Anthropology of the
                  Americas, University of Bonn</orgName>.</affiliation>
               <email>ngrube@uni-bonn.de</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>01/04/2021</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence> 
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor role="guest">Georg Vogeler</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="14">Selected Papers from the 2019 TEI Conference</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Maya writing</term>
               <term>hieroglyphic writing</term> 
               <term>digital epigraphy</term> 
               <term>Maya culture</term>
               <term>Mesoamerica</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2021-03-17">Pietro Liuzzo encoded version of the file returned from authors after copyediting</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract"><p>Maya hieroglyphic script (300 BCE–1500 CE) is a semi-deciphered logographic and
            syllabic autochthonous writing system from the Americas and is one of the most
            significant writing traditions of the ancient world. Because of its incomplete
            state of decipherment, complexity and variation in graphematics, and partially
            lost lexicon, transliterations cannot be used within the encoding. The project
            Text Database and Dictionary of Classic Mayan approaches this challenge with an
            encoding strategy relying on stand-off markup, which is enriched with additional
            information sources. Using different formats (RDF, XML) and standards (CIDOC CRM,
            TEI P5), the inscriptions are encoded in a multilevel corpus: (1) a
            <code>tei_all</code>-compliant schema defining values and rules for the
            encoding of the text’s topological and structural features, (2) a <title level="a">Sign Catalogue</title>
            for the classification of Maya hieroglyphs, and (3) the tool ALMAH (Annotator for
            the Linguistic analysis of MAya Hieroglyphs) for linguistic analyses. In this
            paper, we focus on the TEI schema and highlight our strategy for encoding
            hieroglyphs without using linguistic transliterations and transcriptions.</p></div>
      </front>
      <body>
      
            <div xml:id="textdb">
               <head>Text Database and Dictionary of Classic Mayan</head>
               <p>In 2014, the project Text Database and Dictionary of Classic Mayan was established
                  at the University of Bonn by the North Rhine–Westphalian Academy of Sciences,
                  Humanities and Arts and the Union of the German Academies of Sciences and
                  Humanities to research the written language of the pre-Columbian Maya. The project
                  intends to use digital methods and technologies to compile the epigraphic contents
                  and object histories of all known hieroglyphic texts. The aim is to create a
                  dictionary of Classic Mayan, a language whose script has not yet been completely
                  deciphered. For this purpose, we will compile a machine-readable corpus of all
                  known Maya texts, which are written on about ten thousand text carriers and four
                  codices made of bark paper. To create a holistic environment that provides a solid
                  information base for the dictionary, we have also developed additional resources
                  and tools: a documentation of the text carriers, a classification of the Maya
                  signs, and a tool for linguistic annotation and analysis, as well as supplementary
                  archival materials and a bibliography. The dictionary will be a highly
                  concentrated extract of all these information sources. However, the
                  machine-readable corpus is the central part of the virtual environment: it is
                  enriched by the other information resources using stand-off markup and
                  data-linking mechanisms.</p>
               <p>In the first two sections of the paper, we present the complex writing system of
                  Classic Maya culture. Then we present and discuss our TEI encoding strategy for
                  the corpus. Toward the end, we look at the data-linking mechanisms connecting
                  other information sources to the corpus. We conclude by discussing our approach to
                  an ontological corpus.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="introCMW">
               <head>Introducing Classic Maya Writing</head>
               <p>The subject of our work is the written language of the Classic Maya culture on the
                  Yucatán Peninsula, whose cultural area extended over the territory of the
                  present-day states of Guatemala, Belize, and parts of Honduras and Mexico. Maya
                  writing has been used for more than fifteen hundred years and can be found, for
                  example, on freestanding monuments (stelae, altars), architectural elements
                  (lintels, doorjambs), portable objects (ceramics, shells), and natural features
                  such as caves or rocks (<ref type="bibl" target="#grube1994">Grube 1994</ref>). The writing system comprises about two
                  thousand figurative graphs exhibiting signs for words and syllables. It has
                  survived on more than ten thousand inscription carriers from more than five
                  hundred archaeological sites dating between 300 BCE and 1500 CE. The graphs of
                  this glottographic writing system include representations of figurative objects
                  from the natural environment, material culture, human and animal body parts, heads
                  of humans and animals or portraits of supernatural beings, and abstract ideas. The
                  high language of the hieroglyphs is called Classic Mayan and has been preserved in
                  greater parts in the colonial and modern Ch’olan and Yucatecan languages (<ref type="bibl" target="#wichmann2006">Wichmann
                  2006</ref>). A large number of texts display calendar dates for the precise dating of
                  events and thus also provide unique data on the history of writing and language.
                  Classic Mayan can therefore be reconstructed very accurately and compared with the
                  findings of historical linguistics. All inscriptions originate from the vicinity
                  of the palaces of the divine kings who ruled over independent city-states. The
                  inscriptions contain biographical information and provide written evidence for
                  inter- and intradynastic connections of the ruling families. Public monuments
                  depict and describe actions such as war or royal visits, and they exhibit
                  information about ceremonies and religious rituals in the context of accessions to
                  the throne, ancestor worship, calendar anniversaries, inaugurations, processions,
                  and other occasions of royal daily lives (<ref type="bibl" target="#martin2008">Martin and Grube 2008</ref>).</p>
               <p>Typologically, Maya writing is a morpho-syllabic writing system with two basic
                  sign functions: syllabograms and morphograms. Of the latter, logograms that denote
                  concrete words are the most common. Syllabic signs represent vowels and open
                  syllables of the form CV (consonant and vowel). These permitted the syllabic
                  spelling of lexical and grammatical morphemes. In addition, they were also used as
                  pre- or postfixed phonetic complements for logograms. Thus, it was possible to
                  write words entirely with syllabic signs or using only logograms. Usually,
                  logograms and syllabic signs were combined, providing logo-syllabic pronunciation
                  of words (<ptr target="#fig1" type="crossref"/>). A high level of calligraphic complexity was further achieved
                  through allographic spellings and allomorphic representation of signs. This
                  phenomenon allowed scribes to compose texts that were aesthetically sophisticated
                  without necessarily repeating graphs. There were at least two or more different
                  allographs for frequently used syllables (<ptr target="#fig2" type="crossref"/>), a situation which explains the
                  extremely high number of syllabic signs (about three hundred) within the total
                  inventory of approximately two thousand graphemes in the Maya script (Grube
                  1994).</p>
               
               <figure xml:id="fig1">
                  <graphic url="images/fig1.gif"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Different sign classes and their combination in writing words. The word
                     <mentioned>bahlam</mentioned> in italics represents the phonemic transcription stressing the length of
                     the first vowel. Bold words represent the graphematic transliteration. Drawings by
                     Sven Gronemeyer.</head>
               </figure>
               
               <figure xml:id="fig2">
                  <graphic url="images/fig2.gif"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Different allographs to write the syllable /u/. Drawings by Christian
                     Prager.</head>
               </figure>
               
               <p>The signs were combined with each other to build roughly quadratic blocks. One
                  such hieroglyphic block usually corresponds to the concept of a word among the
                  pre-Hispanic Maya. In most cases, these blocks were paired in double columns that
                  were read from left to right and from top to bottom. Sentences were formed by the
                  combination of hieroglyphic blocks indicating various parts of speech. Multiple
                  sentences were combined to produce complex texts, whose syntax and textual
                  structure are comparable to those of modern Mayan languages. The individual
                  elements in the hieroglyphic block are traditionally subdivided into main and
                  small graphs, with the main graphs being spatially larger and approximately square
                  in shape, and the small elements attached to the periphery of the main characters
                  oriented along the axis of the main graph. Within the block, the individual graphs
                  were not only arranged side by side or on top of each other. They could also be
                  conflated into one single outline, similar to a ligature. In addition, two or more
                  graphs could also be partially or completely overlapped or inserted into each
                  other (<ptr target="#fig3" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="fig3">
                  <graphic url="images/fig3.png"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Different graphotactic methods to combine graphs in a hieroglyphic
                     block. Drawings by Christian Prager.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>The altered shape of the individual graph within the block itself did not
                  influence the spelling and meaning of the hieroglyph. The morphology of the graphs
                  and their arrangement in a block is one of the main challenges for epigraphy in
                  those cases where either all or individual signs are not deciphered or only
                  tentatively deciphered and thus elude linguistic verification. The documentation
                  of the original spelling—the actual graph variation and the intrablock arrangement
                  using TEI XML—is therefore essential for the epigraphic work with hieroglyphic
                  writing systems, since a simple and linear transliteration of a text no longer
                  shows the original spelling or the placement of the glyphs within the block
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#prager2018">Prager and Gronemeyer 2018, 145</ref>).</p>
               <p>While these above-mentioned graphemic and graphotactic strategies only concern the
                  graphic realization of words in written Mayan, the principle of
                  underrepresentation of specific word endings also has an impact on the
                  pronunciation of hieroglyphs in modern epigraphy. The omission of signs further
                  enabled the scribes to vary individual words and texts (<ref type="bibl" target="#zender1999">Zender 1999, 130–142</ref>).
                  This scribal practice also has a high impact on the lexicography of Classic Mayan.
                  By means of the above-mentioned graphemic and graphotactic strategies, Maya
                  scribes were able to create a broad variety of texts with the avoidance of graphic
                  repetitions. They were skilled calligraphers, sought a maximum of visual splendor
                  and designed texts and pictorial works as individual pieces of art. On the other
                  hand textual and pictorial contents are rather formulaic.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="alloGraph">
               <head>Encoding Allography and Graphotactics</head>
               <p>Regular transliterations in TEI encoding would not be able to represent the
                  graphemic variability of Maya writing even if all signs had been fully deciphered.
                  Instead, we encode a proper description of each hieroglyphic block: the actual
                  graphic variant and the spatial relation of each graph to another. A digital Sign
                  Catalogue modeled in RDF provides the backbone of the TEI encoding. Each sign is
                  indexed using a unique number, each type of graphic variation using a two-letter
                  suffix (<ref type="bibl" target="#prager2018">Prager and Gronemeyer 2018</ref>). The URI of each graph is referenced in the
                  TEI. Furthermore, such digital approaches to epigraphy can help overcome some
                  shortcomings of predigital epigraphy, such as dealing with ambiguity.</p>
               <p>The encoding in TEI can be divided into a formal, descriptive part (the text
                  layout and design) and a textual part (the content and the glyphic spellings). In
                  addition to the TEI encoding itself, we needed to create an environment that
                  supports the entire workflow through which different materials such as texts,
                  photographs, drawings, artifact information, historical facts, and established
                  research results are made available. In this virtual environment, a TEI-encoded
                  corpus is enriched by other information resources which are themselves heavily
                  annotated with metadata. The following sections present the key features of the
                  encoding and enrichment strategy employed.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="elemStruct">
               <head>Textual Elements and Structure</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig4">
                  <graphic url="images/fig4.png"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Textual phenomena of Maya writing and how they are represented with TEI
                     elements and attributes. Monument of unknown provenance, Bonampak area. Drawing by
                     Linda Schele © David Schele (SD-6000). Photo courtesy Ancient Americas at LACMA
                     (<ptr target="http://ancientamericas.org/collection/aa010566"/>).</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  A Maya text consists of three units:
                  fields, blocks, and glyphs (<ptr target="#fig4" type="crossref"/>). Text fields are encoded using the element
                  <gi>tei:div</gi> (text division) with a defined <att>type</att> (<val>textfield</val>). Strictly
                  speaking, the <att>type</att>attributes would not be necessary, but they facilitate the
                  human interpretation of generic TEI elements as representations of specific
                  linguistic units. The same principle is used for encoding glyph blocks, for which
                  the element <gi>tei:ab</gi> (anonymous block) is used. For encoding single glyphs, the
                  element <gi>tei:g</gi> (character or glyph) is used with the attributes <att>ref</att>and <att>n</att>
                  The attribute <att>n</att> is used to indicate the catalogue number of the sign with its
                  graph variant according to the classification used by the project’s Sign
                  Catalogue. Instead of pointing to a <gi>tei:glyph</gi>, <att>ref</att> points to the URI in the
                  Sign Catalogue where the corresponding glyph is described. This mechanism is
                  explained in more detail below.</p>
               <figure xml:id="fig5">
                  <graphic url="images/fig5.png"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Partial example focusing solely on the structure of a hieroglyphic text. Monument of
                     unknown provenance, Bonampak area. Drawing by Linda Schele © David Schele (SD-6000).
                     Photo courtesy Ancient Americas at LACMA
                     (<ptr target="http://ancientamericas.org/collection/aa010566"/>).</head>
               </figure>
               <p>The textual elements are being brought into a logical structure by nesting the
                  elements (<ptr target="#fig5" type="crossref"/>): <gi>tei:div</gi> for the text field is the parent element to the
                  <gi>tei:ab</gi> elements of all the glyph blocks contained in that text field, in this
                  example from A1 to D4, and the glyph block contains all glyphs belonging to that
                  block (D1G1 to D1G3). Every element is provided with an <att>xml:id</att> attribute for
                  referencing purposes. In order to identify glyphs that form a group within a
                  block, a fourth element, <gi>tei:seg</gi> (arbitrary segment), is used. This is needed
                  to represent the positioning of the glyphs (<ref type="crossref" target="#glyphPosition">see section 5</ref>).</p>
               <p>Note how the usage of TEI elements differs slightly from approaches with similar
                  aims, such as Comic Book Markup Language (CBML). CBML is designed for the encoding
                  of a <quote source="#quoteref1">class of documents that tightly integrate pictorial images and text. Comic
                  books are just one such type of complex graphic document; other examples include
                  illuminated manuscripts; seventeenth-century alchemical manuscripts, with
                  hand-drawn figures and graphic symbols; artists’ books; artists’ sketchbooks;
                  illustrated poems like those of William Blake; letterpress productions like those
                  of the Kelmscott Press; illustrated children’s books; newspaper and magazine
                  advertisements; and even Web pages and other born-digital media</quote> 
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#walsh2012" xml:id="quoteref1">Walsh 2012</ref>). One
                  can easily imagine that Maya texts fit within this scope as well. The main
                  encoding difference is the introduction of new specific elements under the CBML
                  namespace, most notably <gi>cbml:panel</gi>. According to Walsh (<ref type="bibl" target="#walsh2012" xml:id="quoteref2">2012</ref>),
                  <quote source="#quoteref2"><gi>cbml:panel</gi> is a modification of TEI’s <gi>div</gi> element, which represents a
                  generic subdivision of the text in the TEI model.</quote> The <gi>cbml:panel</gi> element and
                  other custom elements in the CBML namespace are used alongside generic TEI
                  elements such as <gi>tei:div</gi> and <gi>tei:sound</gi>; together they constitute the
                  markup of comic book pages or entire comic book issues. In contrast, all of the
                  XML elements used in the Maya encoding scheme presented here are taken from the
                  TEI namespace. No custom elements or attributes are introduced. Instead,
                  information specific to Maya texts is encoded in the values of attributes such as
                  <att>type</att> (see above) or <att>rend</att> (see below). While these attribute values are
                  controlled by project-specific taxonomies,<note>All project ODDs can be accessed in the project’s
                  Gitolite repository, <ptr target="https://projects.gwdg.de/projects/documentations/repository"/>.</note> this
                  approach has the disadvantage that this information is not easily made
                  machine-readable and interchangeable. The advantage, on the other hand, is that
                  the markup as a whole validates to <code>tei_all</code> and may thus be processed and
                  interpreted by generic tools.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="glyphPosition">
               <head>Glyph Positioning in Glyph Block</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig6">
                  <graphic url="images/fig6.png"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Partial example showing the encoding of the relative positions of glyphs
                     in a glyph block using <att>rend</att> with predefined values. Furthermore, <att>corresp</att> indicates the position of each glyph or glyph group in relation to its
                     corresponding glyph or glyph group. Monument of unknown provenance, Bonampak area.
                     Drawing by Linda Schele © David Schele (SD-6000). Photo courtesy Ancient Americas
                     at LACMA (<ptr target="http://ancientamericas.org/collection/aa010566"/>).</head>
               </figure>
               <p>As explained above, the arrangement of glyphs within a block does not indicate a
                  reading order. When encoding the glyphs in the TEI document, only their
                  arrangement is made explicit. The correct reading order is established later by
                  the linguistic analysis. For this reason, it would be misleading to describe the
                  relative positions of glyphs using the <att>next</att> and <att>prev</att> attributes. This is
                  especially true when keeping in mind that Maya writing is not yet fully deciphered
                  and there may be multiple possible reading orders. The advantage of keeping the
                  encoding of arrangement and reading separate is that in the process of analyzing a
                  text, one can still be improved without having to change the other. Therefore,
                  instead of <att>next</att> and <att>prev</att> the <att>rend</att> attribute is used with predefined values.
                  This attribute, combined with the <att>corresp</att> attribute, can indicate a glyph’s
                  position in relation to neighboring glyphs, logically creating a statement like
                  <q>The current glyph is arranged in a specific manner (<att>rend</att> with respect to
                  another glyph (<att>corresp</att>.</q> The order in which the XML elements are encoded in the
                  document, such as which <gi>tei:g</gi> element appears first inside <gi>tei:seg</gi>, is
                  purely arbitrary and is not meant to imply any reading or writing order.</p>
               <p>As the example in <ptr target="#fig6" type="crossref"/> shows, the <gi>tei:seg</gi> element is used to describe the
                  positions more accurately. The first glyph, D1G1, is positioned on the left-hand
                  side of (<val>left_beside</val>) the corresponding segment, D1S1, which contains two glyphs
                  that are stacked over each other, their positions indicated by <val>above</val> and
                  <val>beneath</val>.</p>
               <figure xml:id="fig7">
                  <graphic url="images/fig7.png"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend">
                     Predefined values for <att>rend</att> describing glyph positions in Maya writing. 
                     In transliteration practice, operators like <q>.</q>, <q>:</q>, and <q>+</q> 
                     are used to describe positions.<note>In the field of Maya epigraphy, different conventions
                        coexist to present graphotactic relations of signs. The most established system is
                        by Thompson (<ref type="bibl" target="#thompson1962">1962</ref>). In our project we build on Thompson but add certain operators
                        to allow a more detailed description of sign relations.</note>
                     In contrast to that, using TEI encoding is much more precise because each glyph is described on its own. 
                     Drawings by Christian Prager.
                  </head>
               </figure>
               <p>There are other positioning options, of which we shall mention only a few here:
                  for instance, glyphs can be <soCalled>conflated</soCalled>, that is, merged so that they share a
                  mutual outline. As in the example on the right of the upper right side in <ptr target="#fig7" type="crossref"/>, 
                  the hand-shaped glyph is used as an outline for the head-variant glyph. Glyphs
                  can also be <soCalled>infixed</soCalled> by being completely enclosed by another glyph. In the
                  example on the left of the upper right side in <ptr target="#fig7" type="crossref"/>, the hand-shaped glyph is
                  enclosed by the head-variant glyph.</p>
               <p>In a way, these scribal phenomena are reminiscent of medieval European handwriting
                  which, when encoded in TEI, requires special attention to be paid to special
                  characters, abbreviation marks, punctuation, diacritical marks, and scribal sigla.
                  Some of these medieval scribal phenomena may also be encoded using custom <att>rend</att> 
                  values (<ref type="bibl" target="#fredell2013">Fredell, Borchers, and Ilgen 2013</ref>). The main difference between medieval
                  European and Maya texts, however, is that the former are still based on a standard
                  Latin alphabet and use XML tags only to supplement a linear succession of Unicode
                  characters, whereas Maya glyphs cannot, to date, be sufficiently represented by
                  Unicode characters.<note>There are some ideas about how to represent Maya
                     hieroglyphic writing in Unicode (see <ref type="bibl" target="#gayol2018">Pallán Gayol 2018</ref>). We argue that to provide
                  a concise character set for its representation in Unicode, there first has to be
                  an identified set of glyphs and their variants. At the moment all inventories of
                  Mayan glyphs are incomplete, imprecise, or inconclusive. Because of that, we
                  established the digital Sign Catalogue to overcome the shortcomings of previous
                  catalogs (see <ref type="crossref" target="#teiBeyond1">section 7</ref>). If at some point in the future a
                  Unicode character set of Maya glyphs is available, we could easily refer to it by
                  using our digital Sign Catalogue. Each graph would be enriched with its
                  corresponding Unicode character.</note>
                  
               </p>
               <p>To represent Maya glyphs in a block-like structure, the Ideographic Description
                  Sequences (IDS) as presented by Unicode seem promising. The IDS are used to
                  describe characters that are not present in the Unicode standard. Twelve special
                  characters (ranging from U+2FF0 to U+2FFB) are used as operators, prefixing other
                  characters to indicate their arrangement (<ref type="bibl" target="#unicode2010">Unicode Consortium 2010</ref>). However, many
                  Maya glyph blocks, like the one in figure 8, cannot be fully encoded using the IDS
                  because only some of the glyph positions in this block are covered by the IDS
                  characters. Our approach can deal with a variety of different arrangements and
                  therefore overcomes the insufficiency of IDS for describing Maya glyph block
                  arrangement.</p>
               <figure xml:id="fig8">
                  <graphic url="images/fig8.png"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Example of encoding conflation and interference in Maya 
                     hieroglyphic signs in the context of the term <foreign>ch’ahoom anaab</foreign> 
                     (<q>sacrificer and artist</q>) found on Sculptured Stone 5 from Bonampak. Drawings by Christian Prager.</head>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="readingDirection">
               <head>Reading Direction and Text Arrangement</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig9">
                  <graphic url="images/fig9.png"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend"> To encode the reading directions of text fields, a <att>style</att> attribute is
                  used with project-specific values in a <gi>tei:div</gi> element in <gi>tei:body</gi>.
                  Drawing by Alexandre Safronov. Courtesy Wayeb Drawing Archive.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>As mentioned above, the correct reading order of a glyph block is established by
                  linguistic analysis, but we can also identify a reading direction on the level of
                  a text field. To describe the writing mode, <soCalled>vendor-specific</soCalled> CSS definitions are
                  used within the <att>style</att> attribute in the <gi>tei:div</gi> element. In the example
                  pictured, text field 1 is written left-to-right, text field 2 right-to-left, and
                  text field 6 top-to-bottom.</p>
               <p>At first glance, these <att>style</att> values seem similar to some of the standard values
                  of the CSS <code>writing-mode</code> property, namely <code>horizontal-tb</code>, <code>vertical-rl</code>, and maybe
                  also <code>vertical-lr</code> (<ref type="bibl" target="#w3c2019">W3C 2019</ref>). However, on closer inspection, it turns out that
                  their semantics are slightly different. Consider, for instance, text field 6 from
                  the example above. Whereas in reading glyphs in a horizontal band, the order would
                  be from left to right (texts spelled from right to left are rare), text field 6
                  consists of glyphs stacked one upon the other in a single vertical line, intended
                  to be read from top to bottom. Standard CSS forces us to choose between
                  <code>vertical-rl</code> and <code>vertical-lr</code>, meaning that any following vertical lines would
                  be placed on the left or right, respectively, of the line in question. This makes
                  no sense in the context of Mayan inscriptions, as there are never two or more
                  consecutive vertical lines. In Maya inscriptions hieroglyphs are usually arranged
                  in parallel columns, which are to be read two columns at a time, beginning with
                  the uppermost glyph in the left-hand column, and then from left to right and top
                  to bottom. Then the next two columns are read in the same order, and so on. Thus,
                  to define any reading direction for sequences of vertical lines would be
                  misleading here. Furthermore, one would have to additionally specify the
                  orientation of the glyphs: without the <val>text-orientation</val> property, CSS assumes
                  that <quote source="#quoteref3"><supplied>t</supplied>ypographic character units from vertical scripts are typeset with their
                  intrinsic orientation</quote> (<ref type="bibl" target="#w3c2019" xml:id="quoteref3">W3C 2019</ref>). 
                  <soCalled>Vertical scripts</soCalled> include Chinese, Japanese,
                  and Korean. For Maya hieroglyphic writing, however, there is no universally
                  accepted specification that defines whether or not it counts among those vertical
                  scripts, which makes it necessary to explicitly indicate the character orientation
                  as <code>text-orientation:upright</code>. Otherwise one might think that the glyphs would be
                  rotated 90° clockwise (as are characters from so-called <soCalled>horizontal-only</soCalled> scripts,
                  such as Latin, when typeset as <val>vertical-rl</val>). Therefore, in place of cumbersome
                  and ultimately inappropriate standard CSS expressions such as
                  <code>writing-mode:vertical-lr; text-orientation:upright</code>, the vendor-specific property
                  <code>-idiom-writing-mode:tb</code> is a more concise way of expressing the same rendering
                  while at the same time being a more meaningful classification of a Mayan writing
                  mode.</p>
               <figure xml:id="fig10">
                  <graphic url="images/fig10.png"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Capturing the arrangement of the text by relating <gi>tei:surface</gi> and
                     <gi>tei:zone</gi> in <gi>tei:sourceDoc</gi> with the corresponding <gi>tei:div</gi> in
                     <gi>tei:body</gi>. Copan, Stela J. Drawing by Linda Schele © David Schele (SD-1014).
                     Photo courtesy Ancient Americas at LACMA
                     (<ptr target="http://ancientamericas.org/collection/aa010014"/>).</head>
               </figure>
               <p>When arranging text on a carrier, Maya scribes were very creative. <ptr target="#fig10" type="crossref"/> shows
                  Stela J from the archaeological site of Copán, Honduras. This stela has a very
                  elaborate design: the sections of the text are braided like ribbons. The text
                  arrangement is described within the <gi>tei:sourceDoc</gi> element using the elements
                  <gi>tei:surface</gi> and <gi>tei:zone</gi>. With the <att>rotate</att> attribute, we can indicate
                  the relative orientation of <gi>tei:zone</gi>. This one is rotated 45° clockwise from
                  its upright orientation. To relate the <gi>tei:zone</gi> elements to the logical text
                  structure described in the <gi>tei:body</gi>, we use <att>xml:id</att> attributes.</p>
               <figure xml:id="fig11">
                  <graphic url="images/fig11.png"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Using stand-off markup to connect image annotations stored in a separate XML file
                     containing SVG objects to the TEI document. Copan, Stela J. Drawing by Linda
                     Schele © David Schele (SD-1014). Photo courtesy Ancient Americas at LACMA
                     (<ptr target="http://ancientamericas.org/collection/aa010014"/>).</head>
               </figure>
               <p>How can the positions of these text sections on the stela be indicated? Despite
                  some recent improvements to the TEI Guidelines in the transcr (Representation of
                  Primary Sources) module, the XML language Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) is still
                  an attractive alternative to TEI because of its flexibility and expressiveness in
                  the description of geometric shapes. The measurements (i.e., the values of the SVG
                  <att>points</att> attributes) give an idea of the relative size and position of each text
                  section. Actually, however, the numbers refer to pixel coordinates on a specific
                  digital image of the stela. By linking the SVG data to the image file, the text
                  section positions can be indicated as shapes in an overlay displayed on top of the
                  image (<ptr target="#fig11" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <p>In practice, we use the virtual research environment TextGrid Lab
                  (<ptr target="https://textgrid.de/www.textgrid.de"/>) to create these data. TextGrid Lab comes
                  with a tool called Text Image Link Editor that enables the user to mark areas on a
                  picture and stores that positioning information in a separate XML file—the TEI/SVG
                  hybrid document pictured above. This allows us not only to relate a certain text
                  passage encoded in the <gi>tei:body</gi> to the source text represented by the
                  <gi>tei:sourceDoc</gi>, but also to enrich it with actual positions on the image. This
                  means that it is possible to indicate the appearance of every single glyph block
                  or glyph.</p>
               <p>By using stand-off markup,<note>When it comes to stand-off annotation, we do not make
                  use of the new <gi>tei:standoff</gi> container element (see <ref type="bibl" target="#tei2020">TEI Consortium 2020,
                  Appendix C: Elements</ref>, <gi>standoff</gi>, 
                  <ptr target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-standOff.html"/>) 
                  because when starting our project back in 2014
                  there simply was no such element at hand, so we needed some creativity to utilize
                  what TEI then had to offer. For us, the considerations of Bański (<ref type="bibl" target="#banski2010">2010</ref>) and
                  chapter 16.9 of the TEI P5 Guidelines (<ref type="bibl" target="#tei2020">TEI Consortium 2020</ref>, 
                  <title level="a">Stand-off Markup</title>,
                  <ptr target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SA.html#SASO"/>) were
                  fruitful starting points to develop a custom solution fitting our needs. Starting
                  with version 4.0.0 of the Guidelines, <gi>tei:standoff</gi> is a decent option for
                  including further information in the textual encoding that is not directly
                  represented in the source itself, such as contextual information. Nevertheless, we
                  decided to stick to our custom solution: first, because we already use not only
                  TEI but also non-TEI stand-off markup, and second, because there is no need to
                  change a perfectly running system.</note> we create a richly and
                  deeply annotated text; by using the Text Image Link Editor, we refer to the
                  appearance of the source text. By referencing the glyph in the Sign Catalogue, we
                  also refer to the graph variants that are used.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="teiBeyond1">
               <head>TEI… and Beyond: Sign Catalogue</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig12">
                  <graphic url="images/fig12.png"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Hieroglyphs in the TEI-encoded corpus referring to the Sign Catalogue, where the
                     glyph is assigned to a transliteration value that is used for linguistic
                     analysis.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Within the TEI document we encode the glyphs with the referring URI of the
                  <gi>idiom:Graph</gi> recorded in our Sign Catalogue using a <att>ref</att> attribute. The term
                     <hi rend="italic">graph</hi><note>The use of the term <soCalled>graph</soCalled> for the abstract, typified
                  form of a realized character is still under discussion within the project. Since
                  in linguistic discourse a realized character is commonly referred to as a <soCalled>graph</soCalled>,
                  the abstract form represents a kind of prototype of the graph. We are still
                  debating how such a type assignment can be understood as an intermediate step
                  between the realized graph and the grapheme. For example, the typed form could be
                  considered as a meta-graph or proto-graph, in contrast to the realized graph and
                  the grapheme.</note>
                   denotes an abstract, typed form of an individually realized sign. The graph
                  of /ja/ in the variation <soCalled>bipartite right</soCalled> (<mentioned>br</mentioned>) recorded in the catalog
                  represents a type which prototypically represents all individual writing variants
                  and thus all actual occurrences for /ja/ (<ptr target="#fig12" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <p>The Sign Catalogue is modeled as an ontology and stores information about the
                  classification of Maya signs and graphs in RDF (<ref type="bibl" target="#diehr2018">Diehr et al. 2018</ref>).<note>For 
                     documentation, see <title level="a">Ontology of the Sign Catalogue
                  for Classic Mayan</title>, accessed January 18, 2021, <ptr target="https://classicmayan.org/documentations/catalogue.html"/>.</note> The class <gi>idiom:Graph</gi> describes characteristics
                  of the Maya glyphs belonging to the realm of graphematics, like the type of
                  variation a <soCalled>graph</soCalled> can have. Every <gi>idiom:Graph</gi> is
                  connected to an <gi>idiom:Sign</gi>. One <gi>idiom:Sign</gi> can have more than one
                  <gi>idiom:Graph</gi>, but an <gi>idiom:Graph</gi> is only ever connected to one
                  <gi>idiom:Sign</gi>. As Maya signs can have both a <soCalled>logographic
                     reading</soCalled> and a <soCalled>syllabic reading</soCalled>, we have to
                  distinguish those first, before finally assigning a <hi rend="italic">transliteration value</hi> to the <gi>idiom:Sign</gi>. As the script of Classic
                  Mayan is not yet fully deciphered, there are multiple hypotheses for the readings
                  of various signs. Therefore a sign can be assigned multiple transliteration
                     values. The Sign Catalogue also provides a mechanism for
                  dealing with contradictory reading proposals (<ref type="bibl" target="#diehr2019">Diehr, Gronemeyer, Wagner, et al.
                     2019</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#diehr2019b">Diehr, Gronemeyer, Prager, et al. 2019</ref>).</p>
               <p>The TEI corpus and the Sign Catalogue provide information about the text as a
                  linguistic and epigraphic subject. To bring that information together, the TEI
                  document and the Sign Catalogue need to be processed further. To generate a
                  transliterated text that can be analyzed, we add another component to the virtual
                  research environment of the project: ALMAH, a tool for linguistic analysis of
                  Classic Mayan, which has also been developed in course of the project (<ref target="#grube2018" type="bibl">Grube et
                  al. 2018, 5–7</ref>). ALMAH will provide mechanisms for multivariant text analysis,
                  based on the TEI corpus and the linguistic information stored in the Sign
                  Catalogue. The text structure will be extracted from the TEI document, and the
                  (multiple) transliteration values are to be assigned from the Sign Catalogue. The
                  assembled text will inherit linguistic, epigraphic, and structural text
                  information. By using referencing mechanisms and stand-off markup strategies, the
                  text will always be traceable to the original writing.<note>ALMAH is still under development and will be the
                  subject of a future publication.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="teiBeyond2">
               <head>TEI… and Beyond: Artifact Documentation</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig13">
                  <graphic url="images/fig13.png"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend"> The text carrier referenced in the TEI document is further described by an
                     ontology that provides a rich schema for an extensive documentation of the
                     artifact. Drawing by Christian Prager.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>We provide a rich documentation of the text carrier. In the <gi>tei:teiHeader</gi>, we
                  refer to the artifact that is documented by using the Artefact Ontology of the
                  project (<ptr target="#fig13" type="crossref"/>). The ontology describes not only text carrier characteristics
                  such as material and technique, but also the finding context of the object and
                  information regarding its scholarly documentation (e.g., measurements,
                     designations).<note>For documentation of the Artefact Ontology, see <title level="a">Idiom
                  Schema</title>, accessed January 18, 2021, <ptr target="https://classicmayan.org/documentations/idiomschema.html"/>.</note> This Artefact Ontology consists of
                  components from pre-existing vocabularies such as CIDOC CRM and Dublin Core Terms,
                  as well as custom components in the idiom namespace. The information described by
                  the Artefact Ontology is stored as RDF data. See <ref type="crossref" target="#linkedCorpus">section 10, <title level="a">The Linked
                     Corpus</title></ref> below for details about the different
                  components of our virtual environment.</p>
               <p>It should be noted that this approach deliberately differs from ways of encoding
                  text carrier information directly in TEI, as, for instance, discussed by Nelson
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#brent2017">2017</ref>). The encoding of artifact-related data in TEI has been further facilitated
                  by the recent introduction of <gi>tei:object</gi> and related elements in the TEI P5
                  Guidelines (see <ref type="bibl" target="#tei2020">TEI Consortium 2020, 13.3.5</ref>: 
                  <title level="a">Objects</title>, <ptr target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ND.html#NDOBJ"/>). However,
                  the TEI-based encoding of information about objects is best suited for contexts in
                  which the object information itself exists as text that is part of the document(s)
                  to be encoded, as in the example of the historical inventories from Nelson’s
                  aforementioned article. In the case of the Text Database and Dictionary of Classic
                  Mayan, in contrast, the texts (which are encoded in TEI) and the text carrier
                  information (RDF) are derived from separate sources and thus do not benefit from
                  homogeneous encoding. Additional details are given by Grube et al. (<ref type="bibl" target="#grube2016">2016</ref>) and
                  Prager et al. (<ref type="bibl" target="#prager2018b">2018</ref>).</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="encodingHelper">
               <head>Encoding Helper: <title level="a">Classic Mayan TEI Generator</title></head>
               <p>Encoding the texts according to our schema may prove time-consuming: assessing
                  identifiers for elements, searching the URI of each graph in the Sign Catalogue as
                  well as the URI of the text carrier(s), correctly encoding the glyph positions,
                  and so on. In order to establish a basic structure of the TEI document including
                  <gi>tei:header</gi>, <gi>tei:sourceDoc</gi>, and <gi>tei:body</gi> (containing the glyph
                  blocks and glyphs), we developed a parser called Classic Mayan 
                  TEI Generator <note>For the parser, see <title level="a">ClassicMayanTEIGenerator</title>,
                  accessed January 18, 2021, <ptr target="https://projects.gwdg.de/projects/teigenerator"/>.</note> that transforms an alphanumeric transliteration
                  (i.e., sign number plus variant suffix; see <ptr target="#fig8" type="crossref"/>) alongside some metadata (e.g.,
                  editor of the document, information on the project) into a TEI document. The
                  description of graphotactics and the relation of graphs to each other is realized
                  by project-specific operators (see <ptr target="#fig7" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <p>The Classic Mayan TEI Generator is specifically not designed as a fully
                  functioning GUI for editing purposes. Once the parser has created a TEI document,
                  it cannot be used to edit the document any further. In particular, encodings like
                  editorial notes on lost and/or reconstructed glyphs are still made within the TEI
                  code itself. While these cannot be generated from a transliteration, we believe
                  that through working within the TEI XML structure, the editors get a better
                  understanding of what and how they encode. Combining automatic and manual
                  procedures ensures a high quality of encoding.</p>
               <p>The parser functions as a helper for providing the editors with a basic document
                  structure, already containing all identifiers, and a text structure. Even with its
                  reduced functionality, the parser is a welcome help for the editors since there
                  are about ten thousand texts to encode.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="linkedCorpus">
               <head>The Linked Corpus</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig14">
                  <graphic url="images/fig14.jpg"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend">The virtual research environment of the project uses multiple
                     information sources. With the TEI document as the central part, a kind of linked
                     corpus is assembled.</head>
               </figure>
               
               <p>In this paper we have laid out our strategy for encoding the hieroglyphic texts of
                  Classic Mayan. The complexity of the writing system presents researchers with
                  manifold obstacles and challenges. By using stand-off markup and other mechanisms
                  to link data, a corpus is established that joins different information resources
                  together in a virtual environment (<ptr target="#fig14" type="crossref"/>). The TEI document forms the central
                  part of this linked structure: the TEI encoding is used to describe the formal
                  structure of the text, its appearance, and its layout. The encoding is enriched by
                  multiple other resources to support specific functions and workflows for
                  annotation, documentation, and analysis: a Sign Catalogue for the classification
                  of signs and graphs as well as their variants; an ontology for the documentation
                  of the text carriers; the tool ALMAH for linguistic annotation and analysis; a
                  project bibliography (using Zotero); and documentation and organization of
                  archival material (which is managed by the DARIAH-DE service ConedaKOR). Bringing
                  all those information sources together provides a holistic research environment
                  for analyzing and deciphering the script of Classic Mayan.</p>
               <p>The data thus generated will be successively made available on the future project
                  portal <ptr target="https://www.classicmayan.org/"/>.
                  Furthermore, the corpus data will also be made freely accessible in the TextGrid
                  repository. All schemata created in the project (ODD, OWL) can be viewed in the
                  public area of our Git repository and can be used under a CC BY 4.0 license: <ptr target="https://projects.gwdg.de/projects/documentations/repository"/>.</p>
               <p>Ontology-based, linked open data in a virtual research environment will for the
                  first time provide a single point of reference in Maya studies. A corpus-based
                  dictionary not only facilitates the research on pending questions of historical
                  linguistics and enables a better adjustment of theories with epigraphic data. As
                  the meaning of a word is affected by its context, the database can also support
                  efforts to identify metaphors or stylistic devices, or to reconstruct a vocabulary
                  that was culturally lost. The encoding as applied by our project can also be
                  modified to describe the graphotactics of other nonlinear scripts or for other
                  (partially) undeciphered scripts, such as the rongorongo script of Rapa Nui
                  (Easter Island). It can also be used to represent (undeciphered) scripts for which
                  no Unicode block has yet been defined or approved.</p>
            </div>
         
      </body>
     <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="banski2010"><author>Bański, Piotr</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title level="a">Why TEI Stand-off Annotation Doesn’t Quite Work: And Why You
                  Might Want to Use It Nevertheless.</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings of Balisage:
                     The Markup Conference 2010</title>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol.
                  5. doi:<idno type="doi">10.4242/BalisageVol5.Banski01</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="diehr2018"><author>Diehr, Franziska</author>, <author>Sven Gronemeyer</author>, 
                  <author>Christian Prager</author>, <author>Elisabeth Wagner</author>, <author>Katja
                  Diederichs</author>, <author>Nikolai Grube</author>, and <author>Maximilian Brodhun</author>. <date>2018</date>. 
                  <title level="a">Organising the Unknown:
                  A Concept for the Sign Classification of Not Yet (Fully) Deciphered Writing
                  Systems Exemplified by a Digital Sign Catalogue for Maya Hieroglyphs.</title>
                  In <title level="m">Digital Humanities 2018 Puentes-Bridges: Book of Abstracts</title>,
                  <biblScope  unit="page">181–84</biblScope>. [<pubPlace>Mexico City</pubPlace>:] <publisher>Red de Humanidades Digitales</publisher>.
                  <ptr target="https://dh2018.adho.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/dh2018_abstracts.pdf"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="diehr2019"><author>Diehr, Franziska</author>, <author>Sven Gronemeyer</author>, 
                  <author>Elisabeth Wagner</author>, <author>Christian Prager</author>, <author>Katja
                  Diederichs</author>, <author>Uwe Sikora</author>, <author>Maximilian Brodhun</author>, 
                  and <author>Nikolai Grube</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title level="a">Modelling
                  Vagueness – A Criteria-Based System for the Qualitative Assessment of Reading
                  Proposals for the Deciphering of Classic Mayan Hieroglyphs.</title> In 
                  <title level="m">Proceedings of the Workshop on Computational Methods in the Humanities
                     2018</title>, edited by <editor>Michael Piotrowski</editor>, 
                  2314:<biblScope unit="page">33–44</biblScope>. Workshop Proceedings.
                  <pubPlace>Lausanne</pubPlace>: <publisher>CEUR</publisher>. 
                  <ptr target="https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:0074-2314-0"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="diehr2019b"><author>Diehr, Franziska</author>, 
                  <author>Sven Gronemeyer</author>, <author>Christian Prager</author>, 
                  <author>Elisabeth Wagner</author>, <author>Katja
                  Diederichs</author>, <author>Maximilian Brodhun</author>, 
                  <author>Uwe Sikora</author>, and <author>Nikolai Grube</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title level="a">Modellierung
                  von Entzifferungshypothesen in einem digitalen Zeichenkatalog für die
                  Maya-Schrift.</title> In <title level="m">Die Modellierung des Zweifels – Schlüsselideen
                     und -konzepte zur graphbasierten Modellierung von Unsicherheiten</title> (special
                  issue 4 of <title level="j">Zeitschrift für digitale
                     Geisteswissenschaften</title>), edited by <editor>Andreas Kuczera</editor>,
                  <editor>Thorsten Wübbena</editor>, and <editor>Thomas Kollatz</editor>. doi:<idno type="DOI">10.17175/sb004_002</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="fredell2013"><author>Fredell, Joel</author>, <author>Charles Borchers IV</author>, 
                  and <author>Terri Ilgen</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a">TEI P5 and Special
                  Characters Outside Unicode.</title> <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding
                     Initiative</title> 4. <ptr target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/727"/>;
                  doi:<idno type="DOI">10.4000/jtei.727</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="grube1994"><author>Grube, Nikolai</author>. <date>1994</date>. 
                  <title level="a">Mittelamerikanische Schriften.</title> 
                  In <title level="m">Schrift und Schriftlichkeit: Ein interdisziplinäres Handbuch internationaler
                  Forschung = Writing and Its Use: An Interdisciplinary Handbook of International
                  Research</title>, edited by <editor>Hartmut Günther</editor> and <editor>Otto Ludwig</editor>, 
                  1:<biblScope unit="page">405–15</biblScope>. Handbücher
                  zur Sprach- und Kommunikationswissenschaft 10. <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>: <publisher>Walter de Gruyter</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="grube2016"><author>Grube, Nikolai</author>, <author>Christian M. Prager</author>, 
                  <author>Katja Diederichs</author>, <author>Sven Gronemeyer</author>, <author>Elisabeth
                  Wagner</author>, <author>Maximilian Brodhun</author>, and <author>Franziska Diehr</author>. <date>2016</date>. 
                  <title level="a">Annual Report for 2015.</title>
                  <title level="j">Textdatenbank und Wörterbuch des Klassischen Maya</title>,
                  Project Report no. 3, edited by <editor>Arbeitsstelle der Nordrhein-Westfälischen Akademie
                  der Wissenschaften und der Künste an der Rheinischen
                  Friedrich-Wilhelms-Universität Bonn</editor>. doi:<idno type="DOI">10.20376/IDIOM-23665556.16.pr003.en</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="grube2018"><author>Grube, Nikolai</author>, 
                  <author>Christian Prager</author>, <author>Katja Diederichs</author>, <author>Sven Gronemeyer</author>, <author>Antje Grothe</author>,
                 <author>Céline Tamignaux</author>, <author>Elisabeth Wagner</author>,
                  <author>Maximilian Brodhun</author>, and <author>Franziska Diehr</author>. <date>2018</date>. 
                  <title level="a">Annual Report for 2017.</title> <title level="j">Textdatenbank und Wörterbuch des Klassischen Maya</title>, Project
                  Report no. 5, edited by <editor>Arbeitsstelle der Nordrhein-Westfälischen Akademie der
                  Wissenschaften und der Künste an der Rheinischen Friedrich-Wilhelms-Universität
                  Bonn</editor>. doi:<idno type="DOI">10.20376/IDIOM-23665556.18.pr005.en</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="martin2008"><author>Martin, Simon</author>, and <author>Nikolai Grube</author>. <date>2008</date>. 
                  <title level="m">Chronicle of the Maya
                  Kings and Queens: Deciphering the Dynasties of the Ancient Maya</title>. 2nd ed.
                  <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Thames &amp; Hudson</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="brent2017"><author>Nelson, Brent</author>. <date>2017</date>. 
                  <title level="a">Curating Object-Oriented Collections Using the TEI.</title> <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> 9.
                  <ptr target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1680"/>; doi:<idno type="DOI">10.4000/jtei.1680</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="gayol2018"><author>Pallán Gayol, Carlos</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">L2/18–038.
                  A Preliminary Proposal for Encoding Mayan
                  Hieroglyphic Text in Unicode</title>. Version 2, January 22.
                  <ptr target="https://www.unicode.org/L2/L2018/18038-mayan.pdf"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="prager2018"><author>Prager, Christian M.</author>, and <author>Sven Gronemeyer</author>. 
                  <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">Neue Ergebnisse in der
                  Erforschung der Graphemik und Graphetik des Klassischen Maya.</title> In <title level="m">Ägyptologische <q>Binsen</q>-Weisheiten III: Formen und Funktionen von
                     Zeichenliste und Paläographie</title>, edited by <editor>Svenja A. Gülden</editor>, <editor>Kyra V. J. van
                  der Moezel</editor>, and <editor>Ursula Verhoeven-van Elsbergen</editor>, 
                  <biblScope unit="page">135–81</biblScope>. Akademie der
                  Wissenschaften und der Literatur, Abhandlungen der Geistes- und Sozialwissenschaftlichen
                  Klasse 15. <pubPlace>Stuttgart</pubPlace>: <publisher>Franz Steiner Verlag</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="prager2018b"><author>Prager, Christian M.</author>, <author>Nikolai Grube</author>, 
                  <author>Maximilian Brodhun</author>, <author>Katja Diederichs</author>,
                  <author>Franziska Diehr</author>, <author>Sven Gronemeyer</author>, and <author>Elisabeth Wagner</author>. 
                  <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">The Digital
                  Exploration of Maya Hieroglyphic Writing and Language.</title> In <title level="m">Crossing Experiences in Digital Epigraphy: From Practice to Discipline</title>,
                  edited by <editor>Annamaria De Santis</editor> and <editor>Irene Rossi</editor>, 
                  <biblScope unit="page">65–83</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>: <publisher>De Gruyter</publisher>.
                  doi:<idno type="DOI">10.1515/9783110607208</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tei2020"><author>TEI Consortium</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                  Interchange.</title> Version 4.1.0. Last updated August 19. N.p.: TEI Consortium.
                  <ptr target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="thompson1962"><author>Thompson, J. Eric S.</author> <date>1962</date>. 
                  <title level="m">A Catalog of Maya Hieroglyphs</title>.
                  The Civilization of the American Indian Series 62. <pubPlace>Norman</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Oklahoma
                  Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="unicode2010"><author>Unicode Consortium</author>. <date>2010</date>. 
                  <title level="m">The Unicode Standard. Version 6.0.</title> Edited by <editor> Julie D.
                  Allen</editor> et al. <pubPlace>Mountain View, CA</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Unicode Consortium</publisher>.
                  <ptr target="http://www.unicode.org/versions/Unicode6.0.0/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="w3c2019"><author>W3C</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title level="a">CSS Writing Modes Level 3. W3C Recommendation</title>, December 10.
                  <ptr target="https://www.w3.org/TR/css-writing-modes-3/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="walsh2012"><author>Walsh, John A.</author> <date>2012</date>. 
                  <title level="a">Comic Book Markup Language: An Introduction and Rationale.</title>
                  <title level="j">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 6, no. 1.
                  <ptr target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/6/1/000117/000117.html"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="wichmann2006"><author>Wichmann, Søren</author>. <date>2006</date>. 
                  <title level="a">Mayan Historical Linguistics and Epigraphy: A New
                  Synthesis.</title> <title level="j">Annual Review of Anthropology</title> 35: <biblScope unit="page">279–94</biblScope>.
                  doi:<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev.anthro.35.081705.123257</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="zender1999"><author>Zender, Marc Uwe</author>. <date>1999</date>. 
                  <title level="m">Diacritical Marks and Underspelling in the Classic Maya
                  Script: Implications for Decipherment.</title> Master’s thesis, <pubPlace>University of Calgary</pubPlace>.
                  doi:<idno type="DOI">10.11575/PRISM/19313</idno>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
     </back>
  </text>
</TEI>