<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-cc-ra-okada-200-source.xml 1184 2023-03-02 20:46:55Z ron $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main"><term>Rubi</term> as a Text</title>
        <title type="sub">A Note on the Ruby Gloss Encoding</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Kazuhiro</forename>
            <surname>Okada</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Kazuhiro Okada, PhD, is a <roleName>lecturer</roleName> at
              <orgName>Hokkai-Gakuen University</orgName>, Hokkaido, Japan. Formerly, he was a
              <roleName>specially appointed assistant professor</roleName> at the <orgName>National
              Institute of Japanese Literature</orgName>, where he was responsible for the
            development of a project for digitized Japanese historical texts.</affiliation>
          <email>oo.kzhr@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Satoru</forename>
            <surname>Nakamura</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Satoru Nakamura, PhD, is an <roleName>assistant professor</roleName> at the
            Historiographical Institute of <orgName>the University of Tokyo</orgName>. His research
            centers on the development and utilization of digital archives, particularly for
            academic research. He played a central role in the digitization and publication of the
            technical documents left by Yuzuru Hiraga, who was president of Tokyo Imperial
            University and a vice-admiral in the shipbuilding division of the Imperial Japanese
            Navy. Nakamura is currently engaged in developing digital archives for the University of
            Tokyo Library.</affiliation>
          <email>nakamura.satoru@mail.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Kiyonori</forename>
            <surname>Nagasaki</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Kiyonori Nagasaki, PhD, is a <roleName>senior fellow</roleName> at the
              <orgName>International Institute for Digital Humanities</orgName> in Tokyo. His main
            research interest is in the development of a digital environment for Buddhist studies.
            He is also investigating the significance of digital methodology in the humanities in
            Japan. Recent publications include <title level="a">Contexts of Digital Humanities in
              Japan</title>, in <title level="m">Digital Humanities and Scholarly Research Trends in
              the Asia-Pacific</title>
            <!-- [RvdB] no bibliographic entry -->(2019, 71–90); and <title level="m">Migrating
              Cultural Materials to the Digital Environment</title> (in Japanese), Jusonbo,
            2019.</affiliation>
          <email>nagasaki@dhii.jp</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>14/02/2023</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Georg Vogeler</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="14">Selected Papers from the 2019 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals
          in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish
          full-text articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>ruby</term>
          <term>Japanese text encoding</term>
          <term>parallel textual structure</term>
          <term>cultural accommodation</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change/>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>This article describes a proposal for elements of ruby glossing that was incorporated
          into the <ref target="#TEIC2021" type="bibl">TEI Guidelines release 4.2.0</ref>, which was
          codenamed <soCalled>Ruby</soCalled>. The Japanese writing system is one of the most
          complex writing systems in the world, mixing three scripts. The system can also be
          described as complex in terms of text linearity: the ruby gloss, originally developed from
          vernacular glosses to Classical Chinese texts, is now a device for presenting a parallel
          text alongside the main text. <term>Ruby</term>, or <term>rubi</term>, or
            <term>furigana</term>, can be used to give clues about phonation as well as to present
          another reading of the text, which sometimes can be an essential part of the text. Such a
          textual structure requires another layer of semantics besides the existing set of
          vocabulary, such as <gi>seg</gi>, <gi>note</gi> (or <gi>add</gi>) and <gi>span</gi>. Ruby
          glosses can also be double-sided. This note discusses the encoding of examples attested in
          real texts using proposed elements (<gi>ruby</gi>, <gi>rb</gi>, and <gi>rt</gi>), and also
          considers Taiwanese <term>bopomofo</term>, a related gloss form.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="acknowledgements">
        <p>This paper has been developed from a paper presented at the 2019 TEI Conference. The
          authors wish to express their gratitude to Nobutake Kamiya, Naoki Kokaze, So Miyagawa, and
          Wang Yifan for their input in completion of the paper and the related proposal to the TEI
          Technical Council. Kazuhiro Okada wishes to express his gratitude for support from the
          Introduction of TEI to Japanese Pre-modern Texts project at the National Institute of
          Japanese Literature; Satoru Nakamura was supported by JSPS KAKENHI Grant Number
          JP19K20626; Kiyonori Nagasaki was supported by JSPS KAKENHI Grant Numbers JP19H00516 and
          JP19H00526. The authors are sincerely grateful for the concepts established by W3C (<ref
            target="#W3c2001" type="bibl">2001</ref>; <ref target="#W3c2013" type="bibl">2013</ref>;
            <ref target="#W3c2014" type="bibl">2014</ref>) and the clear guide developed by Ishida
            (<ref target="#Ishida2016" type="bibl">2016</ref>).</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="div_intro">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>Glossing is a custom found in most medieval manuscript cultures. In those cultures,
          phrases or words written in classical languages are explained by marginalia, interlinear
          glosses, and the like, normally in a vernacular language. Whereas most of these traditions
          have been abandoned and have not been incorporated into modern writing systems, glosses in
          the Japanese writing system have continuously evolved over the centuries, and are still
          used today. The Japanese gloss is now called <foreign>rubi ルビ</foreign>, a Japanese
          rendition of the movable body type size <soCalled>ruby</soCalled>. This paper describes
          the necessity of the ruby as an element set in the TEI Guidelines by explaining its
          characteristics. <note>
            <p>This paper was originally submitted to jTEI before submission of the proposal to the
              TEI-C Technical Council. In the course of editing, we have tried to reflect the
              outcome, but it is not the object of this paper to describe the underlying
              discussions. To prevent confusion with our proposed schema and the official schema, we
              decided to omit, or move to footnotes, part of the discussion related to the schema
              that we originally proposed. For details of the original schema and relevant
              discussion within the TEI community, see GitHub issues <ptr
                target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2054"/> and <ptr
                target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2109"/>. The authors wish to express
              sincere gratitude to the Technical Council, and especially Martin Holmes, who
              enthusiastically advocated for the proposal’s acceptance into the Guidelines and
              polished the details. Without him, the proposal would not have been committed so
              promptly. Holmes and Syd Baumann kindly tested, modified, and refined our proposal and
              edited the Guidelines based on our proposal. For details, see <ref
                target="https://github.com/martindholmes/rubyForTEI">the dedicated repository on
                GitHub</ref> (<ptr target="https://github.com/martindholmes/rubyForTEI"/>).</p>
          </note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="div_overview_of_ruby">
        <head>Overview of Ruby</head>
        <p>Other names for the ruby gloss include <foreign>furigana 振り仮名</foreign> and
            <foreign>bōkun 傍訓</foreign>. <term>Rubi</term> was a slang term used by printers in the
          early twentieth century, derived from the name of a size of movable type imported from
          England, and it is now a standard term. In Japanese linguistics literature in Japanese,
          the term <term>furigana</term> is preferred, as in Ōshima (<ref target="#Oshima1989"
            type="bibl">1989</ref>), Konno (<ref target="#Konno2009" type="bibl">2009</ref>), and
          Yada (<ref target="#Yada2018" type="bibl">2018</ref>). In this article, we consistently
          use the term <soCalled>ruby</soCalled>, following the convention adopted in markup
          languages.</p>
        <p>Whereas interlinear glosses are not found exclusively in the Japanese writing system, and
          similar phenomena can be observed in other East Asian material, the Japanese ruby is
          surely among the most complex glosses. A ruby basically functions as a phonetic gloss to
          an attached Chinese character, but it is not just a pronunciation aid; it can show
          multilayered reading or even encode the main voice of the text (see <ptr
            target="#div_historical" type="crossref"/> for a detailed discussion). Encoding
          multilayered ruby glosses within the existing TEI framework had been a challenge.</p>
        <p>A ruby gloss is visually aligned to some portion of text, but the relationship between a
          ruby and the text which it glosses and which it is embedded in can be flexible. This
          flexibility allows certain types of ruby to introduce nuanced or rather polyphonic
          expressions. First, the structure of polyphonic texts is, we believe, different from that
          of the interlinear glosses familiar from Western texts, normally tagged with <gi>add</gi>
          or <gi>note</gi>, whose purpose is usually to clarify the meaning of the text or to
          provide no more than a simple note, a common strategy used for encoding interlinear
          glosses (see <ref target="#Estill2016" type="bibl">Estill, 2016</ref>). Second, ruby
          glosses can be structurally multilayered: as demonstrated below, rubies can be doubled and
          even tripled, thus piling up multiple voices. This complexity, which has hindered existing
          ruby markup, may be seen as odd. But from another perspective, it is a unique
          characteristic of the ruby gloss. This article explores ways to conceptualize these
          phenomena within a manageable structure.</p>
        <p>Modeling a culturally specific phenomenon with TEI in order to introduce elements into a
          public standard, rather than creating a customized model, is also supported by the history
          of attempts to mark up ruby glosses. In fact, the Japanese community has faced difficulty
          with ruby markup in various projects: see Kawase, Ichimura, and Ogiso (<ref
            target="#KawaseIchimuraOgiso2013" type="bibl">2013</ref>), on their Japanese literature
          corpus building, and Cong and Takaku (<ref target="#CongTakaku2018" type="bibl"
          >2018</ref>), on Tang poems in secondary education textbooks in Japan. While the former
          encodes the glossed text with <gi>w</gi> and the ruby text with <att>ana</att>, the latter
          directly introduces a tagset from HTML. It indicates the difficulty of sharing methods of
          encoding interlinear glosses such as <gi>note</gi>, which are not explicitly included in
          the Guidelines. In this regard, encoding the ruby model directly within the TEI Guidelines
          not only provides a markup system natural to the text but accommodates other East Asian
          materials. This advance will also benefit similar glossing practices around the world.</p>
        <p>This paper is organized as follows: in <ptr target="#div_phenomena" type="crossref"/> we
          describe ruby examples from a historical perspective. The first half of <ptr
            target="#div_conceptualize" type="crossref"/> demonstrates encoded examples, and the
          last half deals with an efficient way of modeling the ruby examples discussed. <ptr
            target="#div_concl" type="crossref"/> discusses the proposal in light of other East
          Asian materials.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="div_phenomena">
        <head>Ruby Examples to Be Examined</head>
        <p>This section briefly explores the ruby examples to be considered. Before going deeper, we
          provide a glossary to assist the discussion: <list type="gloss">
            <label>glossed text (base text; <gi>rb</gi>)</label>
            <item>A part of text that is glossed. Usually in <term>kanji</term>, or Chinese
              characters, but not limited to them.</item>
            <label>ruby text (gloss; <gi>rt</gi>)</label>
            <item>A text that glosses the glossed text. In a plain text transcription, parenthesized
              text shows ruby text. Usually written in <term>hiragana</term> (or
                <term>katakana</term> for loanwords), but not exclusively (kanji,
                <term>romaji</term>, and also in Taiwan, bopomofo will appear).</item>
            <label>ruby gloss (ruby glossed text; <gi>ruby</gi>)</label>
            <item>A glossed text and its corresponding ruby text.</item>
            <label>right- (top-) or left- (bottom-)sided ruby</label>
            <item>A ruby gloss whose position relative to the glossed text is semantically
              meaningful. In Japanese, the default position is on the right side in a vertical text;
              in a horizontal text, the default position will be the top side. A ruby gloss placed
              on the other side implies a special case. A pair of ruby glosses that gloss a text
              from both right and left sides or top and bottom sides is called a <term>double-sided
                ruby</term>. In other writing systems the default position may differ. In the
              transcriptions in this paper, a ruby text in the default position precedes a text on
              the other side.</item>
            <label><term>kanji</term> (Chinese character)</label>
            <item>A script borrowed from the Chinese writing system for writing Japanese. Roughly
              speaking, it denotes either a word of Chinese origin, or the morphemic root of a
              Japanese native content word.</item>
            <label><term>kana</term></label>
            <item>Kana was developed from a phonological usage of kanji to write native words. It is
              also a cover term for hiragana and katakana (see below).</item>
            <label><term>hiragana</term></label>
            <item>Hiragana is a cursive development of kana. Among its uses in the contemporary
              Japanese writing system, it denotes the agglutinative part of the language, which
              cannot be fully specified with kanji. To illustrate the idea with English, given the
              word <mentioned>stronger</mentioned>, the root part, <mentioned>strong</mentioned>,
              would be written in kanji and the rest in hiragana. Hiragana is also preferred when
              use of kanji seems not to be suitable.</item>
            <label><term>katakana</term></label>
            <item>Katakana is developed from components or fragments of a phonological usage of
              kanji. It was a major component of the glossing system of Classical Chinese writing,
              and today katakana signals that the expression is special. It is usually used for
              modern words borrowed from Western languages and for words with colloquial
              nuances.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>A description of ruby gloss patterns and backgrounds now follows. An adequate history of
          the ruby gloss would require a book-length inquiry, but in this treatment we are going to
          concentrate on the history of its structure and related matters. For simplicity, we will
          first review modern Japanese ruby glosses. Then we will proceed to historical ones, and
          lastly to Taiwanese bopomofo examples.</p>
        <div xml:id="div_contemp">
          <head>Modern Japanese Ruby Glosses</head>
          <p>In modern Japanese texts, ruby glosses are used to gloss Chinese characters with kana
            syllabaries. The relationship between glossed and ruby texts have two general patterns
            that can be distinguished: either (A) the gloss is subject to the glossed text, or (B)
            the opposite. Ōshima (<ref target="#Oshima1989" type="bibl">1989</ref>) summarizes the
            possible ruby gloss patterns as follows: <cit>
              <quote source="#quote_Oshima1989_ref1">
                <list rend="simple">
                  <item><label>A-a.</label> Specifying phonation, pattern 1: to prevent confusion
                    with another word with the same orthography (such as <foreign>Ōgoto
                      大事[おおごと]</foreign> with <foreign>Daiji</foreign>, <foreign>Ani-san
                      兄[あに]さん</foreign> with <foreign>Nii-san</foreign>, or <foreign>Hinichi
                      日日[ひにち]</foreign> with <foreign>Hibi</foreign>).</item>
                  <item><label>A-b.</label> Specifying phonation, pattern 2: to supply an accented
                    reading (such as <foreign>Senso 戦争[せんそ]</foreign> with Standard Japanese
                      <foreign>Sensō</foreign> or <foreign>Chau 違[ちゃ]う</foreign> with
                      <foreign>Chigau</foreign>).</item>
                  <item><label>A-c.</label> Glossing a reading, pattern 1: to assist in the learning
                    of new words. Orthography and pronunciation of unfamiliar words are
                    presented.</item>
                  <item><label>A-d.</label> Glossing a reading, pattern 2: to explain unfamiliar
                    orthography. The reader would already know the word, but under a different
                    orthography.</item>
                  <item><label>B-e.</label> Specifying the meaning of the kana orthography. When the
                    orthography is irregular for the gloss, as in <foreign>rabirinsu
                      迷宮(ラビリンス)</foreign> for <foreign>meikyū</foreign>, <foreign>hito
                      女(ひと)</foreign> for <foreign>on’na</foreign>, and <foreign>hairu
                      侵(はい)る</foreign> for <foreign>okasu</foreign>.<note>
                      <p>This is a pattern playing with ambiguity. In the first example,
                          <foreign>ラビリンス</foreign>, a Japanese rendering of <q>labyrinth</q>, is
                        what the author wished to show as a text. It is foreign (or rather to say
                          <soCalled>exotic</soCalled>) to Japanese people, and the author decided to
                        gloss the word, choosing the Chinese-origin synonym <foreign>迷宮</foreign>
                          (<foreign>mígōng</foreign>). However, applying usual kana glosses here is
                        not preferred because the gloss employs Chinese characters rather than
                        standard Japanese orthography. At the same time, Chinese characters placed
                        in a gloss are not always legible. Thus, the placement in this example was
                        reversed: <foreign>迷宮</foreign> is on the text side, and
                          <foreign>ラビリンス</foreign> is on the gloss side. Another motivation is that,
                        following an older tradition, what is glossed should be Chinese characters.
                        Ōshima’s (<ref target="#Oshima1989" type="bibl">1989</ref>) viewpoint is on
                        the role of the glossing in question, so the
                          <soCalled>counterpart</soCalled> explanation is enough at the moment. An
                        English equivalent could be to mark the phrase <q>lol</q> with the gloss
                          <q>hearty laughter</q>, or <q xml:lang="la">vir</q> with the gloss <q>a
                          brave man</q>.</p>
                    </note></item>
                  <item><label>B-f.</label> Specifying the items referred to by the gloss.
                      <foreign>Achira 大陸(あちら)</foreign> for <foreign>Tairiku</foreign> and
                      <foreign>Ani-san 伊兵衛(あに)さん</foreign> for <foreign>Ibē san</foreign>.</item>
                </list>
                <figure xml:id="fig_oshima1989">
                  <graphic url="images/fig_oshima1989.png" width="963px" height="1338px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Original passage of Ōshima (<ref target="#Oshima1989"
                      type="bibl">1989</ref>).</head>
                </figure>
              </quote>
              <ref xml:id="quote_Oshima1989_ref1" target="#Oshima1989" type="bibl">Ōshima 1989,
                  72–73<note>Translation ours with slight modifications in numbering and
                  illustrations.</note></ref>
            </cit>
          </p>
          <p>Ōshima (<ref target="#Oshima1989" type="bibl">1989</ref>) adds other cases, for
            specifying the meaning of the Chinese character orthography (<foreign>tabū
              禁忌[タブー]</foreign> [<q>taboo</q>] for <foreign>kinki</foreign> [<q>taboo</q> or
              <q>contraindication</q>]), and the equal (or rather independent) relationship between
            the gloss and the glossed text (<foreign>Wocchingu 再発見[ウォッチング]</foreign>
              [<q>watching</q>] for <foreign>saihakken</foreign> [<q>rediscovery</q>]). We could add
            more patterns of glossing other language expressions. Here, what is important is that
            the uniform structure of the ruby gloss allows all of the above patterns. In addition,
            these patterns are not exclusive.</p>
          <p>Contemporary Japanese texts do not have ruby glosses unless they are needed. However,
            as seen in the above patterns, especially patterns A-b, B-e, and B-f, ruby glosses can
            be a device for rich expressions. Moreover, occasionally the text is glossed on both the
            right and left, or the top and bottom sides. The examples below illustrate the usual
            single- and double-sided ruby glosses.</p>
          <p>Note that single-sided ruby glosses have typographical complexities that are
            structurally straightforward. (As we will see later, HTML schemas have been concerned
            with typographical matters.) The examples below, <ptr
              target="#fig_kawakami1a #fig_kawakami1b #fig_kawakami2" type="crossref"/> (written top
            to bottom and right to left) show some typographical conventions when glossing words
            with complex orthography: <note>
              <p>Generally speaking, in the Japanese writing system, one kanji denotes a single
                morpheme or syllable. However, there are cases where two or more characters denote a
                single morpheme, which could be termed a complex-orthography word. There are a
                number of typographic considerations involved in the composition of ruby glossed
                text. However, this does not mean that they present logical complexities, which is
                the focus of the TEI proposal, and so differs from the W3C’s (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#W3c2012">2012</ref>) conception of the ruby glossed text.</p>
            </note>
            <list rend="bulleted">
              <item><q>真面目(ま/じ/め)</q> (from <ptr target="#fig_kawakami1a" type="crossref"/>)</item>
              <item><q>浴衣(ゆかた)</q> (from <ptr target="#fig_kawakami1b" type="crossref"/>)</item>
              <item><q>あんたの/鼾(いびき)</q> (from <ptr target="#fig_kawakami2" type="crossref"/>)</item>
            </list>
            <figure xml:id="fig_kawakami1a">
              <graphic url="images/fig_kawakami1a.png" width="178px" height="264px"/>
              <head type="legend"><bibl>Kawakami Hiromi. 1998. <title level="m">Yashi, Yashi
                    椰子・椰子</title>, p. 21, detail. Tokyo: Shinchosha.</bibl></head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="fig_kawakami1b">
              <graphic url="images/fig_kawakami1b.png" width="94px" height="307px"/>
              <head type="legend"><bibl>Kawakami Hiromi. 1998. <title level="m">Yashi,
                  Yashi</title>, p. 21, detail. Tokyo: Shinchosha.</bibl></head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="fig_kawakami2">
              <graphic url="images/fig_kawakami2-v2.png" width="335px" height="532px"/>
              <head type="legend"><bibl>Kawakami Hiromi. 1998. <title level="m">Yashi,
                  Yashi</title>, p. 29. Tokyo: Shinchosha.</bibl></head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>Unlike its appearance in the second (<ptr type="crossref" target="#fig_kawakami1b"/>),
            the ruby text (<q xml:lang="ja">いびき</q>) is not glossed to the word <q xml:lang="ja"
              >の</q>. This is because ruby glosses can be placed alongside a neighboring word if it
            would not be misleading, especially if the glossed text is in
            <!-- [RvdB] check consistency of kanji + kana -->kanji and the neighboring words are in
            kana. This is not a structural but a typographical matter; see W3C (<ref
              target="#W3c2012" type="bibl">2012, §3.3.5, figs. 121, 122</ref>) for further
            illustrations.</p>
          <p>Yet another example of a single-sided ruby gloss is of the pattern II-e (<ptr
              target="#fig_kindaichi" type="crossref"/>, written top to bottom and right to left).
            Here the translator rendered the name of an Ainu divinity,
              <foreign>kamuy’otopus</foreign>, in Japanese characters that were equivalent to the
            Chinese characters <q>神髪彦(カムイオトプシ)の</q>. We note that again the ruby text is allowed to
            continue alongside a character that is not being glossed. <figure xml:id="fig_kindaichi">
              <graphic url="images/fig_kindaichi.png" width="183px" height=" 321px"/>
              <head type="legend"><bibl>Kindaichi Kyosuke, editor and translator. 1936. <title
                    level="m">Ainu jojishi yūkara アイヌ叙事詩ユーカラ [Yukar: Ainu Epics]</title>, p. 219.
                  Tokyo: Iwanami Publishers.</bibl></head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>The next example is double-sided. In this example (<ptr target="#fig_yamakawa"
              type="crossref"/>), <q>大王(おおきみ)(だいおう)</q>, the preferred reading
              <foreign>ōkimi</foreign> is presented as the top ruby text and another reading,
              <foreign>daiō</foreign>, is presented parenthesized as a bottom-sided ruby. It should
            be noted that, as this is a textbook of Japanese history for Japanese junior high
            schools, it has numerous interlinear glosses, birth and death years for example.
            However, these glosses are not tied with a particular text, but just function as
            pointers, explanations, or something else. We consider them <emph>not</emph> to be ruby
            glosses, but general annotations that fall under the semantics of <gi>note</gi>. <figure
              xml:id="fig_yamakawa">
              <graphic url="images/fig_yoshikawa.png" width="558px" height="372px"/>
              <head type="legend"><bibl>Ishii Susumu, Gomi Fumihiko, Sasayama Haruo, and Takano
                  Toshihiko, editors. 2007. <title level="m">Shōsetsu nihonshi 詳説日本史 [Advanced
                    Japanese History]</title>, p. 21. Tokyo: Yamakawa Shoten.</bibl></head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>Lastly, although not yet confirmed by a real example, a double-sided ruby could overlap
            and not nest. In a blog entry discussing complex ruby structures and their encodings,
            Uchida cites a constructed example presented by a now-deleted tweet: <cit>
              <quote source="#quote_uchida_ref1">
                <p>まず、<ref target="http://twitter.com/koueihei/status/17330668872"
                    >@koueiheiさんによるルビの例</ref>。「労働者階級意識」といふ親文字列のうち、「労働者階級」に「プロレタリアート」といふルビ。同時に「階級意識」に「かいきゅういしき」といふルビ。これは入れ子方式ではマーク付けできない。</p>
                <p>もっとも、日本語でも英語でも「階級」と「意識」は2つの単語に分解できるんぢゃないか、したがって無理にcomplex
                  rubyで扱ふ必要な無いんぢゃないか、といふ指摘もあらう。</p>
              </quote>
              <ref xml:id="quote_uchida_ref1" target="#Uchida2010" type="bibl">Uchida 2010</ref>
            </cit> Twitter user <code>@koueihei</code> (who had deleted their account at the time of
            writing) offers a glossed text that reads <q>労働者階級意識</q> —a phrase that is difficult to
            translate. In this example, <code>@koueihei</code> has added two ruby glosses:
              <foreign>プロレタリアート</foreign> (<foreign>Proletariat</foreign>) to the (upper?/right?)
            side of <q>労働者階級</q>, and <q>かいきゅういしき</q> to the (bottom?/left?) side of <q>階級意識</q>
            (translation of <foreign>Klassenbewußtsein</foreign> or class consciousness). The
            double-sided ruby could be visualized as in either <ptr target="#fig_proletariat1"
              type="crossref"/> or <ptr target="#fig_proletariat2" type="crossref"/>. <figure
              xml:id="fig_proletariat1">
              <graphic url="images/fig_proletariat_consciousness.png" width="987px" height="255px"/>
              <head type="legend">A possible rendering of an example in Uchida (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#Uchida2010">2010</ref>), where the vertical bar shows morpheme
                boundaries. In this variant, the bottom-side ruby corresponds with word
                divisions.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="fig_proletariat2">
              <graphic url="images/fig_proletariat_consciousness_v2.png" width="987px"
                height="255px"/>
              <head type="legend">Another rendering of <ptr type="crossref" target="#fig_yamakawa"
                />. In this variant, the bottom-side ruby corresponds with morpheme
                divisions.</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>According to Uchida, word-to-morpheme alignment, as shown in <ptr
              target="#fig_proletariat1" type="crossref"/>, cannot be represented using nested
            structure. It is true, as Uchida also points out, that the glossed text consists of
            three morphemes, and that it does not need to encode both rubies as a single ruby gloss
            structure, as we can see from the glossing boundaries in <ptr target="#fig_proletariat2"
              type="crossref"/>. It is enough then to encode both rubies at the boundary of
              <q>階級</q> and <q>意識</q>, meaning that it is not necessarily an encoding problem.
            However, we can imagine a case where the left/bottom-side ruby was
              <foreign>Klassenbewußtsein</foreign>, and hence remains a problem for nested encoding.
            In any case, this example is surely one of the rarest structures among ruby glosses. But
            it is theoretically possible, and the possibility that examples will emerge warrants
            consideration of encoding strategies that can handle them.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="div_historical">
          <head>Historical Japanese Ruby Glosses</head>
          <p>Historical ruby glosses are not too distant from modern ruby glosses. Ruby is
            originally derived from interlinear glosses to Classical Chinese texts, or
              <foreign>Kanbun Kundoku (漢文訓読)</foreign>.<note>
              <p>Although the Japanese writing system adopts Chinese characters, the way it uses
                them cannot be summarized in a sentence. Roughly speaking, the major categories of
                Chinese characters in the Japanese writing system fall into Sino-Japanese and native
                strata. The Sino-Japanese stratum represents the adaptation of Chinese
                pronunciation, whereas the native stratum represents renditions of the Chinese
                language, in which a character generally represents a word or a syllable. The
                complexity of these reading strata also contributed to the development of
                interlinear glosses as a part of the writing system. <foreign>Ateji</foreign>, or
                  <quote source="#quote_Seeley1991_ref1">phonogram usage of Chinese
                  characters</quote> (<ref target="#Seeley1991" xml:id="quote_Seeley1991_ref1"
                  type="bibl">Seeley 1991, 188</ref>), is the most related to the need for ruby in
                Japanese texts. As <foreign>ateji</foreign> strips the character in question of its
                semantics, it can be ambiguous without the aid of a ruby gloss. For example,
                  <foreign>urayamashii</foreign>, or <q>to be jealous</q>, has been written in
                numerous ways: a more recent rendition prefers <q xml:lang="ja">羨しい</q>, compared
                with Chinese <foreign>xiànmù 羨慕</foreign>, or <q>to be jealous</q>, but older
                renditions employed <foreign>ateji</foreign> as in <foreign>裏山敷い</foreign>, where
                all three Chinese characters denote solely their phonetic value. Another device
                which deserves to be taken into account is <foreign>jukuji kun</foreign>, a native
                reading for a set of Chinese characters. As its name suggests, <foreign>jukuji
                  kun</foreign> provides a reading in cases where a sequence of the native reading
                for each character would not be adequate for a set of characters. For example, a
                rendition for the Chinese word <foreign>zuórì 昨日</foreign> is
                  <foreign>kinō</foreign> and not the Japanese equivalent <foreign>saki no
                  hi</foreign>. This also makes it difficult to read a text in a consistent way, and
                is helpfully shored up by a ruby gloss. The heavy use of the ruby gloss in the
                Japanese writing system emerged from such polyvalent Chinese character readings.</p>
            </note> A summary of the application of Japanese glosses to Classical Chinese texts can
            be found in Whitman (<ref target="#Whitman2011" type="bibl">2011</ref>) and Kosukegawa
              (<ref target="#Kosukegawa2014" type="bibl">2014</ref>). See Whitman (<ref
              target="#Whitman2011" type="bibl">2011</ref>) for a comparison with glosses in Latin
            manuscripts. Kosukegawa (<ref target="#Kosukegawa2014" type="bibl">2014</ref>)
            summarizes the Japanese glossing practice as follows: <cit>
              <quote source="#quote_Kosukegawa2014_ref1">
                <list rend="ordered">
                  <item>The source texts of <foreign>kundoku</foreign> glossing were in classical
                    Chinese.</item>
                  <item><gap/></item>
                  <item><foreign>Kundoku</foreign> involves the act of directly adding glosses to a
                    classical Chinese text.</item>
                  <item>The method of adding glosses has both similarities and differences in each
                    Sinoxenic language.<note>Any language that has a tradition of reading Chinese
                      characters is called Sinoxenic. Sinoxenic languages include Sino-Japanese,
                      Sino-Korean, and Sino-Vietnamese.</note></item>
                </list>
              </quote>
              <ref xml:id="quote_Kosukegawa2014_ref1" type="bibl" target="#Kosukegawa2014"
                >Kosukegawa 2014, 1</ref>
            </cit> The third point is particularly relevant to the ruby phenomenon. Here Kosukegawa
              (<ref target="#Kosukegawa2014" type="bibl">2014</ref>) translates the summarization of
            the Japanese glossing practice by Ishizuka (<ref xml:id="quote_Ishizuka2001_ref1"
              target="#Ishizuka2001" type="bibl">2001, 2</ref>) as <quote
              source="#quote_Ishizuka2001_ref1">adding of annotations or symbols to aid in the
              comprehension of a classical Chinese <supplied>text</supplied> while reading
              it.</quote> The purpose of glossing, not translating, is to preserve the original
            glossed text as it is. The purpose of Japanese ruby is practically the same: to leave
            the intended graphic expression in the glossed text while conveying the meaning.</p>
          <p>What distinguishes ruby glosses from glosses to the Classical Chinese text is that ruby
            glosses are applied to text in the same language. Yada (<ref target="#Yada2018"
              type="bibl">2018</ref>) identifies the earliest ruby gloss from late twentieth-century
            materials. Konno (<ref target="#Konno2009" type="bibl">2009, 93</ref>) demonstrates that
            B-e–type ruby glosses can be attested as early as the sixteenth century. Such glosses
            are as a rule not later additions but glosses by the authors themselves (see also <ref
              target="#Yada2018" type="bibl">Yada 2018, 803</ref>).</p>
          <p>Double-sided ruby glosses flourished between the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries,
            when the Tokugawa Shogunate ruled the nation. Murakami (<ref target="#Murakami2017"
              type="bibl">2017</ref>) claims that those double-sided ruby glosses emerged from the
            Sinological practices of Ogyū Sorai (1666–1728), who valued understanding texts through
            the living vernacular language rather than the vernacular-glossed Classical Japanese
            language. According to Murakami (<ref target="#Murakami2017" type="bibl">2017</ref>),
            while the right side of the ruby gloss generally shows the pronunciation, the left side
            of the ruby gloss is a vernacular explanation of the glossed text.<note>
              <p>We do not say much about the practice of glossing Classical Chinese texts. However,
                it should be noted that, prior to Sorai, nonstandard glosses had long been practiced
                in Chinese character dictionaries and in formal texts such as the <title level="m"
                  >Chronicle of Japan</title>, written in Classical Chinese, which Japanese readers
                have long preferred to read in its artificial archaic language (<ref
                  target="#Konno2009" type="bibl">Konno 2009, ch. 2</ref>). As for the Chinese
                character dictionaries, since a Chinese character can have a number of equivalents,
                more than ten glosses may appear, whereas they are not part of a running text. We do
                not see any rationale for treating them as a kind of ruby gloss, as in Konno (<ref
                  target="#Konno2009" type="bibl">2009</ref>). Glosses to Classical Chinese texts
                are in the semantic tradition of interlinear glosses.</p>
              <p>However, a modern rendition of a gloss of a Classical Chinese text can pose issues
                since it sometimes distinguishes agglutinative endings for a word root (or a stem)
                by the choice of two types of kana. See Cong and Takaku (<ref
                  target="#CongTakaku2018" type="bibl">2018</ref>) and Nagasaki, et al. (<ref
                  target="#NagasakiEtal2022" type="bibl">2022</ref>) for further discussion.</p>
            </note> Murakami’s (<ref target="#Murakami2017" type="bibl">2017</ref>) argument is
            important to account for the question as to why the complex glosses to Classical Chinese
            texts turn into the more modern double-sided rubies: the old glosses, sometimes
            successively accumulating, as a rule show independent interpretations and have nothing
            to do with position; in contrast, Sorai’s double-sided ruby glosses are systematically
            positioned. Sorai’s double-sided ruby glosses are intended to explain Classical Chinese
            texts in the vernacular Japanese language, and the same motivation lies behind
            double-sided rubies in Japanese texts.</p>
          <p>Explanatory vernacular glosses also developed during the days of the Tokugawa Shogunate.<note>
              <p>This practice was a fruit of the adaptation of Chinese vernacular-influenced
                literature, called <foreign>báihuà wénxué 白话文学</foreign>. The adopters wished to
                show traces of adaptation by rendering Chinese words as they were written, but at
                the same time, they wanted them to be read in Japanese discourse: they could imitate
                the old glossing method to show their intended reading while showing the Chinese
                words in Chinese characters. In this way, ruby glosses became important for reading
                the text.</p>
            </note> In a limited timeframe from the eighteenth to the nineteenth century,
            publications for the general public in which most Chinese characters were glossed
            appeared widely. Yanaike (<ref target="#Yanaike2009" type="bibl">2009</ref>) claims that
            such glosses, rather than the glossed text itself, were what people actually read. Such
            blanket use of glossing was demanded because of the Japanese population’s low literacy
            in Chinese characters, and was possible because of printing: almost all Japanese
            publications were produced using woodblock printing. Only in the last decade of the
            nineteenth century did movable type printing supersede woodblock printing. The ruby
            gloss became uneconomical in movable type printing, and the introduction of modern
            compulsory education reduced the need for the glosses.</p>
          <p>The example below is a page from an early modern text, <title level="m">Hanabusa
              sōshi</title> (<ptr target="#fig_hanabusa" type="crossref"/>). It is written top to
            bottom and right to left. Here, the line on the far left is to be transcribed: <cit>
              <quote source="#quote_hanabusa_ref1"
                >にむかひ梁(りやう)武帝(ぶてい)の仏(ぶつ)に淫(いん)して民膏(みんかう)(たみのあぶら)を費(ついや)し国の衰(おとろ)へとなり</quote>
              <bibl xml:id="quote_hanabusa_ref1">Tsuga Teishō. (1749). <title level="m">Hanabusa
                  sōshi 英草紙</title>. Vol. 1, f. 3r. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                >10.20730/200016727</idno>.</bibl>
            </cit>
            <figure xml:id="fig_hanabusa">
              <graphic url="images/fig_hanabusa.jpg" width="1008px" height="1366px"/>
              <head type="legend"><bibl>Tsuga Teishō. (1749). <title level="m">Hanabusa
                    sōshi</title>. Vol. 1, f. 3r. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                  >10.20730/200016727</idno>.</bibl></head>
              <head type="license">National Institute of Japanese Literature, Japan. CC BY-SA
                4.0.</head>
            </figure> In this example, a sequence of two characters <foreign>民膏</foreign>, or the
            wealth of the people, is doubly glossed, being Sino-Japanese reading in an old-fashioned
            spelling <q>minkō みんかう</q> (cf. Mandarin <foreign>mín gāo</foreign>): (1) on the right
            side, with the native word explanation <q>tami no abura たみのあぶら</q> and (2) on the left
            side. The left-side gloss, which literally means <q>the fat of the people</q>, is a
            rather literal rendition of the glossed characters, meaning that it explains the
            characters rather than the word.</p>
          <p>The next example is taken from a Japanese song, <title level="m">Igirisu
              dodoitsu</title> (<ptr target="#fig_igirisu" type="crossref"/>, written top to bottom
            and right to left). The first line has triple ruby glosses: <cit>
              <quote source="#quote_igirisu_ref1">まことリットル(りつとる)(少(すくな)き)</quote>
              <bibl xml:id="quote_igirisu_ref1">Bōan Koikoi Sanjin. Late 18c. <title level="m">Gengo
                  chūkai igirisu dodoitsu言語注解英語土渡逸</title>. Vol. 1, f. 1v. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                  >10.20730/200018433</idno>.</bibl>
            </cit>
            <figure xml:id="fig_igirisu">
              <graphic url="images/fig_igirisu.png" width="805px" height="1170px"/>
              <head type="legend"><bibl>Bōan Koikoi Sanjin. Late 18c. <title level="m">Gengo chūkai
                    igirisu dodoitsu</title>. Vol. 1, f. 1v. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                    >10.20730/200018433</idno>.</bibl></head>
              <head type="license">National Institute of Japanese Literature, Japan. CC BY-SA
                4.0.</head>
            </figure> In this example, the left-side gloss is itself glossed. The glossed text (1),
            in katakana script, is a rendition of <q>little.</q> An equivalent transcription in
            hiragana is given in the right-side ruby gloss (2), and a translation is given in the
            leftmost left-side ruby gloss (3). To the best of our knowledge, such complicated ruby
            glosses appear initially in the late eighteenth century and again briefly, around 1870.
            Although not unlikely in other eras, technically speaking a deeper gloss is possible. As
            TEI is intended for documenting rather than creating, we believe that a ruby schema
            should be capable of encoding historical examples as long as it does not complicate the
            schema itself.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="div_global">
          <head>Ruby-Like Interlinear Glosses in Other Writing Systems: An Example from Taiwanese
            Bopomofo</head>
          <p>There is another writing system, besides the Japanese system, that has ruby-like
            glosses: bopomofo, used in Taiwan. Bopomofo, or the <foreign>Zhùyīn Fúhào 注音符號</foreign>
            system, is a transcription system for Mandarin Chinese and other Chinese languages.
            Bopomofo was learned in order to gloss phonetically from Japanese kana, so we consider
            it one of the ruby gloss systems.</p>
          <p>Bopomofo has unique characteristics in ruby text positioning. It allows both top and
            right sides of the glossed text in horizontal writing, meaning that its default value
            for the ruby text position is not definable (<ref target="#MoE2000" type="bibl">Ministry
              of Education 2000</ref>; note that the right-hand position in horizontal writing is
            preferably called intercharacter position, a counterpart to the term <term>interlinear
              position</term>). The function of bopomofo, reflecting the monosyllabic nature of the
            Chinese language, is mostly to present the phonetic value of a glossed character.
            Metaphorical usage may technically arise, but it does not change the structure of
            bopomofo. <figure xml:id="fig_topbopomofo">
              <graphic url="images/fig_bopomofo.jpg" width="1547px" height="591px"/>
              <head type="legend">Horizontal right-sided (intercharacter) bopomofo example on the
                street</head>
              <head type="license">nesnad. 2016. <title level="a">File:Bopomofo on Taiwanese street
                  - with English - Nov 2016 2.jpg</title>. In <title level="m">Wikimedia
                  Commons</title>. <ptr
                  target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Bopomofo_on_Taiwanese_street_-_with_English_-_Nov_2016_2.jpg"
                /></head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>Similar examples can be obtained from schoolbooks used in mainland China, but not as
            frequently as in Taiwan. In Korea and Vietnam, similar vernacular reading aids were
            applied to words of Chinese origin written in Chinese characters before modern writing
            systems emerged. The TEI ruby gloss encoding schema will help to encode Korean and
            Vietnamese texts with such glosses.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="div_conceptualize">
        <head>Conceptualization of the Structure</head>
        <div xml:id="div_earlierschema-jp">
          <head>Earlier Proposed Schema and Encoding Models: Japanese Cases</head>
          <p>The ruby gloss has long been a problem for Japanese text encoding. Within the XML
            framework, Hara and Yasunaga (<ref target="#HaraYasunaga2002" type="bibl">2002</ref>)
            were among the first to address this problem. Their scope was, however, limited to the
            simple single-sided ruby. It is practically the same with Yamaguchi et al. (<ref
              target="#YamaguchiEtal2011" type="bibl">2011</ref>), whose goal was to build an XML
            vocabulary for Japanese linguistic corpora. They treated ruby text as an attribute for
            the ruby gloss element, which is useful only for the phonation gloss (types A-a,
            A-b).</p>
          <p>Such a simple structure works for most ruby glosses, but faces numerous problems.
            Taking an example from corpus building, if ruby text is going to be analyzed, how can it
            be described? It is impossible to tag an attribute value for a ruby text in XML. In
            fact, Murayama, Ogiso, and Nakamura (<ref target="#MurayamaOgisoNakamura2017"
              type="bibl">2017</ref>), building on the work of Yamaguchi et al. (<ref
              target="#YamaguchiEtal2011" type="bibl">2011</ref>), describe their difficulties in
            handling these values in their environment. In the same vein, a double-sided ruby can be
            described only as long as the ruby gloss element is allowed to nest, and the ruby text
            refers to the same glossed text. Kawase, Ichimura, and Ogiso (<ref
              target="#KawaseIchimuraOgiso2013" type="bibl">2013</ref>) attempted to introduce a TEI
            framework based on Yamaguchi et al. (<ref target="#YamaguchiEtal2011" type="bibl"
              >2011</ref>). They were aware of this problem, and introduced HTML’s ruby vocabulary
            while calling for a more sophisticated structural approach in TEI. Later, Murayama,
            Ogiso, and Nakamura (<ref target="#MurayamaOgisoNakamura2017" type="bibl">2017</ref>)
            addressed this issue by introducing a new nesting left-side ruby element to their own
            schema. Cong and Takaku (<ref target="#CongTakaku2018" type="bibl">2018</ref>) also
            introduce HTML’s ruby vocabulary to the TEI framework. However, HTML is not intended for
            documentation of the text, and this is a crucial limitation. Cong and Takaku (<ref
              target="#CongTakaku2018" type="bibl">2018</ref>) also marked up ruby texts character
            by character, rather than at the morphemic level, which would break up the logical
            relationship of ruby and glossed text.</p>
          <div xml:id="div_htmlschema">
            <head>HTML’s Ruby Schemas</head>
            <p>The history of ruby encoding in HTML is marked by pro- and anti-SGML (XML) positions
              on structure. A ruby encoding system was first proposed in the earliest draft of W3C
                (<ref target="#W3c2001" type="bibl">2001</ref>) (which eventually became a module of
              XHTML 1.1),<note><p>As acknowledged in W3C (<ref target="#W3c2001" type="bibl"
                    >2001</ref>), their work was inspired by Dürst (<ref target="#Duerst1997"
                    type="bibl">1997</ref>), in which ruby glosses were encoded as
                attributes.</p></note> in late 1998, and implemented in 1999 by Microsoft informally
              in their Internet Explorer 5. In its earliest form, W3C (<ref target="#W3c2001"
                type="bibl">2001</ref>) accommodates only single-sided ruby; however, the final form
              also covers double-sided ruby. The published form defines the envelope <gi
                scheme="ruby">ruby</gi> element, the container elements <gi scheme="ruby">rb</gi>,
                <gi scheme="ruby">rt</gi>, and respective <gi scheme="ruby">rbc</gi> and <gi
                scheme="ruby">rtc</gi> elements as the containers of <gi scheme="ruby">rb</gi>s and
                <gi scheme="ruby">rt</gi>s, with the compatibility-easing <gi scheme="ruby">rp</gi>
              element, whose role was to give parentheses to unsupported implementations. One thing
              to note is that the first draft, which was produced during the transition from HTML to
              XHTML, allowed the omission of the end tags of <gi scheme="ruby">rb</gi> and <gi
                scheme="ruby">rt</gi>, but reversed that in the final form. However, the Internet
              Explorer implementation was based on an earlier draft of this document, and they did
              not follow the later version. This gap between W3C and implementers, although not
              limited to this small corner, has continued to cause practical issues until now,
              although W3C abandoned their development of XHTML 2.0. Another thing worth mentioning
              is that, in this schema, <gi scheme="ruby">rb</gi> was allowed once per <gi
                scheme="ruby">ruby</gi> element, and not allowed under the <gi scheme="ruby"
                >rbc</gi> element (see W3C <ref target="#W3c2013" type="bibl">2013</ref> for a
              comparison between approaches in XHTML and HTML5); therefore, if an encoder wished to
              divide the ruby text character by character (as shown in the examples of <ptr
                target="#fig_kawakami1a #fig_kawakami1b #fig_kawakami2" type="crossref"/>), they
              needed to tag every unit of ruby-text correspondence, and ignore the semantic
              unit.</p>
            <p>As an extension to HTML5, W3C (<ref target="#W3c2014" type="bibl">2014</ref>) set out
              to create ruby encoding that met the requirements of W3C (<ref target="#W3c2012"
                type="bibl">2012</ref>) with the styling component covered by CSS3
                  modules.<note><p>As for the encoding model after HTML5, note well that before W3C
                    (<ref target="#W3c2013" type="bibl">2013</ref>) was published, HTML5 dropped <gi
                    scheme="ruby">rb</gi>, claiming that the base text element was unnecessary
                  because the children text nodes of <gi scheme="ruby">ruby</gi> necessarily were
                  the base text. See <ptr
                    target="https://www.w3.org/Bugs/Public/show_bug.cgi?id=10830"/> for details.
                  Thus, it is not clear why W3C (<ref target="#W3c2014" type="bibl">2014</ref>)
                  reintroduced the use of <gi scheme="ruby">rb</gi> and <gi scheme="ruby">rtc</gi>
                  elements. However, as they were declared optional, the difference may not be as
                  large as may appear. At any rate, current HTML standards have not fully
                  reintroduced these elements.</p></note> This extension addressed the gap noted in
              W3C (<ref target="#W3c2013" type="bibl">2013</ref>), which investigated the ways in
              which W3C (<ref target="#W3c2012" type="bibl">2012</ref>) was insufficient to meet
              ruby-related criteria. Based on JISC (<ref target="#Jisc2004" type="bibl">2004</ref>),
              W3C (<ref target="#W3c2012" type="bibl">2012</ref>) had tried to show the traditional
              typography standard that should be realized in modern browsers (<ref
                target="#Yabe2010" type="bibl">Yabe 2010</ref>). In contrast with fixed layout
              settings, where traditional typography has worked, it was not an easy task to
              accomplish this in content-flow layout; content-flow allows adjusting the layout to
              fit everything from smart-phone browsers to large monitors for desktop PCs. Ruby
              glosses present a number of challenges for content-flow layout; to name but two
              examples: How and at what distance from the glossed text should ruby text be rendered,
              given a limited allotted boundary? What if a line break occurs in the middle of the
              ruby gloss? Kawabata (<ref target="#Kawabata2014" type="bibl">2014</ref>) reviews
              difficulties in rendering ruby glosses properly in different versions of HTML.</p>
            <p>The encoding models that were adopted in HTML5 (and those inherited by WHATWG’s HTML
              Living Standards) have, in principle, a tabular structure and an interleaving
              structure. Each has its own strength and weakness, in terms of logical structure. The
              interleaving structure provides a simple parsing mechanism and conforms to desktop
              publishing implementations. Most actual HTML encoding tends to take this approach.
              However, since not a few Japanese words have two or more Chinese characters to be
              represented, it breaks up the logical word structure and hinders deeper encoding. In
              contrast, the tabular structure is more intuitive, but the repetition of the same <gi
                scheme="ruby">rb</gi> or <gi scheme="ruby">rt</gi> tags would cause ambiguity in
              encoding, especially when the numbers of <gi scheme="ruby">rb</gi> and <gi
                scheme="ruby">rt</gi> tags differ. As both <gi scheme="ruby">rb</gi> and <gi
                scheme="ruby">rt</gi> are content elements in their own right, they prioritize
              presentation functions at the expense of their original logical structure.</p>
            <p>The double-sided ruby, termed complex ruby in HTML schemas, is modeled using both a
              nested structure and a boxed structure. The nested structure gives a simpler and more
              flexible representation of the structure. The boxed structure creates a table layout
              within which details are filled in. One weakness of the nested model is that it cannot
              handle some overlapping cases, as discussed by Uchida (<ref target="#Uchida2010"
                type="bibl">2010</ref>). However, from the viewpoint of stand-off versus inline
              markup, this problem is rooted in a limitation of inline markup in XML. HTML5
              addresses this problem by allowing empty <gi scheme="ruby">rt</gi> elements (<ref
                target="#Ishida2016" type="bibl">Ishida 2016</ref>). In the context of the TEI
              Guidelines, blank elements can be replaced by linking elements.</p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="div_ourschema">
            <head>Our Proposed Schema and Encoding Model</head>
            <p>As we have seen, the HTML encoding schemas were designed principally to allow ruby to
              be rendered in browsers. But TEI is concerned principally with meaning, not rendering.
              Therefore, for the TEI schema, it was necessary to invent a new model for descriptive
              encoding. TEI has not only introduced a nested ruby gloss element, but also provided a
              stand-off mechanism for correspondence between spans of ruby and glossed texts.</p>
            <p>Our conception was, basically, that the schema should allow maximum flexibility
              through a simple model. In particular, while we allow nesting of the ruby gloss
              element (similar to the parallel segmentation method used in a critical apparatus), we
              also allow, if necessary, the double-end-point-attached method in order to accommodate
              the most complex examples, which require the use of <gi>anchor</gi>.<note><p>In the
                  original proposal, there was a limit of one <gi>rb</gi> and one <gi>rt</gi>
                  element per <gi>ruby</gi> element so as to force a nesting structure. However, it
                  was pointed out that Taiwanese bopomofo ruby sometimes uses bopomofo and pinyin
                  annotations simultaneously, and that they should not be treated as nested. To
                  address this, the constraint was not included in the Guidelines.</p></note> We do
              not find convincing reasons for maintaining multiple encoding strategies, and for the
              reasons discussed above, we avoid employing either the interleaving structure or the
              boxed structure.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="div_examples">
          <head>Encoding Examples</head>
          <p>The following examples show how our proposal addresses the examples discussed
            above.</p>
          <div xml:id="div_mod_ex">
            <head>Modern Japanese Ruby Glosses</head>
            <figure xml:id="code_majime">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                <p>
                  <ruby>
                    <rb><anchor xml:id="ma"/>真<anchor xml:id="ji"/>面<anchor xml:id="me"/>目</rb>
                    <rt><anchor target="#ma"/>ま<anchor target="#ji"/>じ<anchor target="#me"/>め</rt>
                  </ruby>
                </p>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">
                <q>真面目(ま/じ/め)</q>
              </head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="code_yukata">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                <p>
                  <ruby>
                    <rb>浴衣</rb>
                    <rt>ゆかた</rt>
                  </ruby>
                </p>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">
                <q>浴衣(ゆかた)</q>
              </head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="code_ibiki">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                <p>あんたの <ruby>
                    <rb>鼾</rb>
                    <rt>いびき</rt>
                  </ruby>
                </p>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">
                <q>あんたの鼾(いびき)</q>
              </head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="code_kamuiotopusi">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                <p>
                  <ruby>
                    <rb>神髪彦</rb>
                    <rt xml:lang="ain">カムイオトプシ</rt>
                  </ruby>の </p>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">
                <q>神髪彦(カムイオトプシ)の</q>
              </head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="code_okimi">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                <p>
                  <ruby>
                    <rb>
                      <ruby>
                        <rb>大王</rb>
                        <rt place="top">おおきみ</rt>
                      </ruby>
                    </rb>
                    <rt place="bottom">（だいおう）</rt>
                  </ruby>
                </p>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">
                <q>大王(おおきみ)([だいおう])</q>
              </head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="code_proletariat">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                <p>
                  <ruby>
                    <rb xml:id="rb1">労働者<anchor xml:id="rb1-1"/>階級<anchor xml:id="rb1-2"/>意識<anchor
                        xml:id="rb1-3"/></rb>
                    <rt from="#rb1" to="#rb1-2" place="left">プロレタリアート</rt>
                    <rt from="#rb1-1" to="#rb1-3" place="right">かいきゅういしき</rt>
                  </ruby>
                </p>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">
                <q>労働者階級意識</q>
              </head>
            </figure>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="div_hist_ex">
            <head>Historical Japanese Ruby Glosses</head>
            <figure xml:id="code_hanabusa">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                <p>にむかひ<ruby>
                    <rb>梁</rb>
                    <rt>りやう</rt>
                  </ruby><ruby>
                    <rb>武帝</rb>
                    <rt>ぶてい</rt>
                  </ruby>の<ruby>
                    <rb>仏</rb>
                    <rt>ぶつ</rt>
                  </ruby>に<ruby>
                    <rb>淫</rb>
                    <rt>いん</rt>
                  </ruby>して<ruby>
                    <rb><ruby>
                        <rb>民膏</rb>
                        <rt place="right" type="primary">みんかう</rt>
                      </ruby>
                    </rb>
                    <rt place="left" type="secondary">たみのあぶら</rt>
                  </ruby>を<ruby>
                    <rb>費</rb>
                    <rt>ついや</rt>
                  </ruby>し国の<ruby>
                    <rb>衰</rb>
                    <rt>おとろ</rt>
                  </ruby>へとなり </p>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">Example from <title level="m">Hanabusa soshi</title></head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="code_igirisu">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                <l>まこと<ruby>
                    <rb><ruby>
                        <rt place="right">りつとる</rt>
                        <rb>リットル</rb>
                      </ruby></rb>
                    <rt place="left"><ruby>
                        <rb>少</rb>
                        <rt place="right">すくな</rt>
                      </ruby>き</rt>
                  </ruby></l>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">Example from <title level="m">Igirisu dodoitsu</title></head>
            </figure>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="div_oth_ex">
            <head>Bopomofo</head>
            <figure xml:id="code_bopomofo">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                <tagsDecl>
                  <rendition selector="rt" scheme="css"> ruby-position: inter-character; /* making
                    use of editor’s draft CSS 3 module, CSS Ruby Annotation Layout Module Level 1 */
                  </rendition>
                </tagsDecl> … <p>
                  <ruby>
                    <rb>牆</rb>
                    <rt>ㄑㄧㄤˊ</rt>
                  </ruby><ruby>
                    <rb>面</rb>
                    <rt>ㄇㄧㄢˋ</rt>
                  </ruby><ruby>
                    <rb>請</rb>
                    <rt>ㄑㄧㄥˇ</rt>
                  </ruby><ruby>
                    <rb>勿</rb>
                    <rt>ㄨˋ</rt>
                  </ruby><ruby>
                    <rb>攀</rb>
                    <rt>ㄆㄢ</rt>
                  </ruby><ruby>
                    <rb>爬</rb>
                    <rt>ㄆㄚˊ</rt>
                  </ruby>，</p>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">Example of bopomofo</head>
            </figure>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="div_concep_remark">
          <head>Some Remarks on Encoding Strategy</head>
          <p>Some additional comments are worth making. First, in the case of double-sided ruby
            glosses encoding, if the order of priority is apparent, lower-priority glosses should be
            encoded in the shallower level and have a <att>type</att> for both <gi>rt</gi>s; their
            respective values should be something like <val>primary</val> and <val>secondary</val>
            in the working language of the encoding project (see <ptr target="#code_hanabusa"
              type="crossref"/>; in this case, the right-sided ruby gloss is encoded in a shallower
            position than the left-sided one).<note><p>In our original proposal, <att>type</att> was
                allowed for the <gi>ruby</gi> element and required when nested. However, it is not
                always apparent which side of a ruby gloss is primary. In addition, having a
                  <att>type</att> attribute on the <gi>rt</gi> element is considered more
                intuitive.</p></note> If the order is not apparent, encoders should treat them in a
            consistent manner. Second, in a writing system where the default value of the ruby text
            position cannot be fixed, documenting it in <gi>tagUsage</gi> and <gi>rendition</gi> may
            be helpful (see <ptr target="#code_bopomofo" type="crossref"/>). Third, the
            correspondence between layouts of the ruby and glossed texts should be made clear with
            the aid of the <gi>anchor</gi> element.<note>
              <p>Descriptions in the TEI Guidelines, <ref target="#TEIC2021" type="bibl">chapter
                  3.4.2</ref> differ somewhat in details. When encoders divide some glossed text
                with <gi>anchor</gi>, the Guidelines encourages the user to specify correspondence
                by dividing up their respective ruby glosses as well. The reason we maintain our
                original proposal here is because we want to allow analytic elements in <gi>rt</gi>.
                This may be a matter for further discussion. For the difference, see, for example,
                the transcription for <ptr target="#fig_kawakami1a" type="crossref"/>:</p>
              <figure xml:id="code_guideline-anchor" rend="inline">
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="inline" valid="true"><p
                    rend="inline">
                    <ruby>
                      <rb><anchor xml:id="ma"/>真<anchor xml:id="ji"/>面<anchor xml:id="me"/>目</rb>
                      <rt target="#ma">ま</rt><rt target="#ji">じ</rt><rt target="#me">め</rt>
                    </ruby>
                  </p>
                </egXML>
                <head type="legend"><q>真面目(ま/じ/め)</q></head>
              </figure>
            </note> In an HTML context, reflecting a perception that ruby text is glossed per
            character, encoders may wish to encode <ptr target="#code_majime" type="crossref"/> as
            follows (<ptr target="#code_majime2" type="crossref"/>): <figure xml:id="code_majime2">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true"><p>
                  <ruby>
                    <rb>真</rb><rt>ま</rt>
                    <rb>面</rb><rt>じ</rt>
                    <rb>目</rb><rt>め</rt>
                  </ruby>
                </p></egXML>
              <head type="legend">Not recommended encoding example of <q>真面目(ま/じ/め)</q></head>
            </figure> Such a structure is not prohibited, but it prevents users from further
            analyzing and encoding the ruby and the glossed text.</p>
          <p>The new schema permits the encoding of complex ruby glosses. Ruby glosses can be
            nested, and adjusted for unusual spanned alignment, making it possible to encode triple
            ruby glosses and the nonnested glosses. It has also a downside in that these most
            complex ruby glosses cannot be directly translated into HTML, the most widely used ruby
            gloss encoding schema. In addition, the default ruby position cannot be fixed. Thus,
            every encoding project should use <att>place</att> to specify a desired output.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="div_concl">
        <head>Conclusion</head>
        <p>Our goal has been to describe the rationale for introducing to the TEI Guidelines a
          schema that fully accommodates the rich structure of ruby. This richness, as presented in
          Ariga (<ref target="#Ariga1989" type="bibl">1989, 332</ref>), is seen in an 1874 essay by
          a Japanese author where the text is written in Classical Chinese but expected to be read
          with detailed accompanying glosses in Japanese. In the dialog a Chinese word <foreign>鄙吝
            bǐlìn</foreign> (in Sino-Japanese form, <foreign>birin</foreign>), or
            <mentioned>stingy</mentioned>, was transformed into Japanese slang <foreign>kechinbō
            ケチンボー</foreign> using an unusual ruby gloss to give a vivid tone to a formal narrative.
          (See also <ref target="#TakashiWilkersonWilkerson2000" type="bibl">Takashi Wilkerson and
            Wilkerson 2000</ref> on the playfulness of contemporary ruby.) Our proposal was to allow
          such a structure to be encoded in conformance with the Guidelines.</p>
        <p>Such inclusion of localized meaning not only takes a great step toward fully including a
          local textual tradition but also gives the TEI community a way to contribute to the global
          humanities by encouraging the inclusion of other underrepresented textual traditions. We
          hope this proposal encourages introducing other underrepresented local textual structures
          into the Guidelines.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Ariga1989"><author>Ariga, Chieko</author>. <date>1989</date>. <title
              level="a">The Playful Gloss: Rubi in Japanese Literature</title>. <title level="j"
              >Monumenta Nipponica</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">309–35</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
            >10.2307/2384611</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="CongTakaku2018"><author>Cong, Yan</author>, and <author>Masao
              Takaku</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">Tōshi sakuhin no honbun furu
              tekisuto ni taisuru TEI mākuappu shuhō no teian 唐詩作品の本文フルテキストに対するTEIマークアップ手法の提案 [A
              Proposal of TEI Markup for the Content of Tang Poems]</title>. <title level="j">Jōhō
              chishiki gakkai shi 情報知識学会誌 [Journal of Japan Society of Information and
              Knowledge]</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">174–85</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.2964/jsik_2018_017</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Duerst1997"><author>Dürst, Martin J.</author>
            <date>1997</date>. <title level="u">Ruby in the Hypertext Markup Language</title>.
            Internet draft. <ptr target="https://www.w3.org/International/draft-duerst-ruby-01"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Estill2016"><author>Estill, Laura</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title
              level="a">Encoding the Edge: Manuscript Marginalia and the TEI</title>. <title
              level="j">Digital Literary Studies</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>). <ptr
              target="https://journals.psu.edu/dls/article/view/59715"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="HaraYasunaga2002"><author>Hara, Shōichirō</author>, and <author>Yasunaga,
              Hisashi</author>. <date>2002</date>. <title level="a">Kokubungaku kenkyū shien no tame
              no SGML/XML dēta sisutemu: Kokubungaku dēta kyōyū no tame no hyōjunka
              国文学研究支援のためのSGML/XMLデータシステム: 国文学データ共有のための標準化 [SGML/XML Data System for Japanese
              Classical Literature: Standardization for Literacy Resource Sharing]</title>. <title
              level="j">Jōhō chishiki gakkai shi 情報知識学会誌 [Journal of Japan Society of Information
              and Knowledge]</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">17–35, 46</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.2964/jsik_KJ00001039453</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Ishida2016"><author>Ishida, Richard</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title
              level="a">Ruby Markup</title>. <title level="j">W3C Internationalization</title>. Last
            updated July 18, 2016. <ptr
              target="https://www.w3.org/International/articles/ruby/markup.en"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Ishizuka2001"><author>Ishizuka, Harumichi</author>. <date>2001</date>.
              <title level="a">Sōron 総論 [General Remarks]</title>. In <title level="m">Kuntengo
              jiten 訓点語辞典 [A Linguistic Dictionary of Kunten Materials]</title>, <biblScope
              unit="page">1–2</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Tokyodō</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Jisc2004"><orgName>JISC (Japan Industrial Standard Committee)</orgName>.
              <date>2004</date>. <title level="m">JIS X 4051: Nihongo bunsho no kumihan hōhō
              日本語文書の組版方法 [Formatting Rules for Japanese Documents]</title>.
              <placeName>Tokyo</placeName>: <publisher>Japanese Industrial Standards
              Committee</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Kawabata2014"><author>Kawabata, Taichi</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title
              level="a">HTML no rubi hyōjunka no genjō to kadai HTMLのルビ標準化の現状と課題 [Current Status and
              Issues in HTML’s Ruby Standardization]</title>. <title level="j">Journal of Japan
              Association for East Asian Text Processing</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">4–15</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="KawaseIchimuraOgiso2013"><author>Kawase, Akihiro</author>, <author>Taro
              Ichimura</author>, and <author>Tomonobu Ogiso</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
              level="a">TEI P5 ni motozuku kinsei kōgo shiryō no kōzōka to sono mondaiten TEI
              P5に基づく近世口語資料の構造化とその問題点 [Problems in TEI P5 Encoding on Colloquial Japanese Documents
              of the Early Modern Period]</title>. In <title level="m">Jinmonkon 2013 ronbunshū
              じんもんこん2013論文集 [Proceedings of the Computers and Humanities Symposium JinMonCom
              2013]</title>, <biblScope unit="page">7–12</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Jōhō shori gakkai</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://id.nii.ac.jp/1001/00096389/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Konno2009"><author>Konno, Shinji</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title
              level="m">Furigana no rekishi 振仮名の歴史</title>. Tokyo: Shueisha.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Kosukegawa2014"><author>Kosukegawa, Teiji</author>. <date>2014</date>.
              <title level="a">Explaining What Kundoku Is in the Premodern Sinosphere</title>. In
              <title level="m">Lecture vernaculaire de textes classiques chinois / Reading Chinese
              Classical texts in the Vernacular</title>, edited by <editor>John Whitman</editor> and
              <editor>Franck Cinato</editor>. <title level="s">Dossiers d’HEL</title> (electronic
            supplement to the journal Histoire Épistémologie Langage) <biblScope unit="issue"
              >7</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="http://shesl.org/index.php/dossier7-lecture-vernaculaire/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="MoE2000"><orgName>Ministry of Education</orgName>. <date>2000</date>. <title
              level="m">The Manual of the Phonetic Symbols of Mandarin Chinese</title>.
              <pubPlace>Taipei</pubPlace>: <publisher>Ministry of Education</publisher>. <ptr
              target="https://language.moe.gov.tw/001/Upload/files/site_content/M0001/juyin/index.html"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Murakami2017"><author>Murakami, Masataka</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title
              level="a">Kunyaku iwayuru hidari rubi o megutte 訓訳 いわゆる左ルビをめぐって [On
                <foreign>Kun’yaku</foreign> (Colloquial Japanese Glosses in
                <foreign>báihuà</foreign> Novels)]</title>. In <title level="m">Nihon kindaigo
              kenkyū 6</title>, edited by <editor>Modern Japanese Language Research
              Association</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">87–106</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>: <publisher>Hitsuji shobō</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="MurayamaOgisoNakamura2017"><author>Murayama, Miwako</author>,
              <author>Toshinobu Ogiso</author>, and <author>Takenori Nakamura</author>.
              <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">Keitairon jōhō no tajūka ni yoru sharebon kōpasu
              no shitsuteki kakuchō 形態論情報の多重化による洒落本コーパスの質的拡張 [Qualitative Expansion of the
                <foreign>Sharebon</foreign> Corpus using Multilayer Morphological
              Information]</title>. <title level="j">Jōhō shori gakkai kenkyū hōkoku 情報処理学会研究報告
              [IPSJ SIG Technical Report]</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">2017-CH-114</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue"
            >8</biblScope>): <biblScope unit="page">1–8</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="http://id.nii.ac.jp/1001/00178697/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="NagasakiEtal2022"><author>Nagasaki, Kiyonori</author>, <author>Satoru
              Nakamura</author>, <author>Makoto Tanaka</author>, <author>Masato Nishikawa</author>,
              <author>Ryūju Hayashi</author>, <author>Keijun Inoue</author>, and <author>Masahiro
              Shimoda</author>. <date>2022</date>. <title level="a">Kōzōka tekisuto dēta no katsuyō
              ni okeru genjō to kadai: TEI ni junkyo shita <title level="m">Jōdo Shinshū Seiten
                Zensho</title> zenbun kensaku shisutemu no kaihatsu o tsūjite
              構造化テキストデータの活用における現状と課題: TEIに準拠した『浄土真宗聖典全書』全文検索システムの開発を通じて [Current Status and Issues
              in Utilization of Structured Text Data: Development of a Full-Text Search System for
              TEI-Compliant Buddhist Scriptures]</title>. <title level="j">Jinmonkon 2022 ronbunshū
              じんもんこん2022論文集 [Proceedings of the Computers and Humanities Symposium JinMonCom
              2022]</title>
            <biblScope unit="page">73–78</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>: <publisher>Jōhō
              shori gakkai</publisher>. <ptr target="http://id.nii.ac.jp/1001/00223165/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Oshima1989"><author>Ōshima, Chūsei</author>. <date>1989</date>. <title
              level="a">Hyōki shutai no hyōki mokuteki kara mita kanji kana heiretsu hyōki: Iwayuru
              furigana tsuki hyōki keishiki o megutte 表記主体の表記目的から見た漢字仮名並列表記: いわゆる振り仮名付き表記形式をめぐって
              [Kanji-kana Paralleled Orthography with Emphasis on the Intention of the Agent of
              Writing: The So-Called Orthography with <foreign>Furigana</foreign>]</title>. <title
              level="j">Dōshisha Joshi Daigaku gakujutsu kenkyū nenpō 同志社女子大学学術研究年報 [Doshisha
              Women’s College of Liberal Arts Annual Reports of Studies]</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">440–54</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Seeley1991"><author>Seeley, Christopher</author>. <date>1991</date>. <title
              level="m">A History of Writing in Japan</title>. <pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Brill</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="TakashiWilkersonWilkerson2000"><author>Takashi Wilkerson, Kyoko</author>,
            and <author>Douglas Wilkerson</author>. <date>2000</date>. <title level="a">The Gloss as
              Poetics, Transcending the Didactic</title>. <title level="j">Visible Language</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">228–63</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="TEIC2021"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2021</date>. <title
              level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>.
              <edition>Version 4.2.0</edition>. Last updated on 25th February 2021, revision
            736c0acf0. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>: <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
              target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.2.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Uchida2010"><author>Uchida, Akira</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title
              level="a">Yahari HTML5 niwa complex ruby ga hitsuyō dewa naikaやはりHTML5にはcomplex
              rubyが必要ではないか [Isn’t HTML5 Still Necessary for Complex Ruby?]</title>, <title level="j"
              >Nihongo renshūchū 日本語練習虫 [A Bug in Training Japanese Language Skill]</title> (blog).
            July 4, 2010. <ptr target="http://uakira.hateblo.jp/entry/20100704"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Whitman2011"><author>Whitman, John</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title
              level="a">The Ubiquity of the Gloss.</title>
            <title level="j">SCRIPTA</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">95–121</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="W3c2001"><orgName>W3C</orgName>. <date>2001</date>. <title level="m">Ruby
              Annotation</title>. W3C Recommendation. May 31, 2001. <ptr
              target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2001/REC-ruby-20010531/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="W3c2012"><orgName>W3C</orgName>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="m"
              >Requirements for Japanese Text Layout</title>. W3C Working Group Note. April 3,
              2012.<ptr target=" https://www.w3.org/TR/2012/NOTE-jlreq-20120403/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="W3c2013"><orgName>W3C</orgName>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="m">Use
              Cases &amp; Exploratory Approaches for Ruby Markup</title>. W3C Working Group Note.
            October 8, 2013. <ptr target="https://www.w3.org/TR/ruby-use-cases/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="W3c2014"><orgName>W3C</orgName>. 2014. HTML Ruby Markup Extensions . W3C
            Working Group Note. February 4, 2014. <ptr
              target="https://www.w3.org/TR/html-ruby-extensions/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Yabe2010"><author>Yabe, Masafumi</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title
              level="m">Katsuji to arufabetto: Gijutsu kara mita nihongo hyōki no sugata 活字とアルファベット:
              技術から見た日本語表記の姿 [Movable Types and the Alphabet: The Japanese Writing System Seen
              Through Technologies]</title>. <pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>: <publisher>Hōsei daigaku
              shuppankyoku</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Yada2018"><author>Yada, Tsutomu</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title
              level="a">Furigana</title>. In <title level="m">Nihongogaku daijiten</title>, edited
            by <editor>The Society for Japanese Linguistics</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >802–3</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>: <publisher>Tokyodō</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="YamaguchiEtal2011"><author>Yamaguchi, Masaya</author>, <author>Tomokazu
              Takada</author>, <author>Masanori Kitamura</author>, <author>Yōko Mabuchi</author>,
              <author>Ōshima Hajime</author>, <author>Kobayashi Masayuki</author>, <author>Nishibe
              Michiru</author>, et al. <date>2011</date>. <title level="m"><q>Gendai nihongo kaki
                kotoba kinkō kōpasu</q> ni okeru denshika fōmatto ver. 2.2
              『現代日本語書き言葉均衡コーパス』における電子化フォーマット ver. 2.2 [Digitization and Encoding Rules for the
              Balanced Corpus of Contemporary Written Japanese]</title>. <pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>NINJAL</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="Yanaike2009"><author>Yanaike, Makoto</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title
              level="a"><q>Sō rubi</q> no jidai: Nihongo hyōki no jūkyū seiki 「総ルビ」の時代: 日本語表記の十九世紀
              [An Era of <foreign>Sō Rubi</foreign>: The Nineteenth Century in the History of the
              Japanese Writing System]</title>. <title level="j">Bungaku 文学 [Literature]</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">117–30</biblScope>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
