<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">In search of comity: TEI for distant reading</title>
            <author xml:id="LB42"><name><forename>Lou</forename>
                  <surname>Burnard</surname></name> is an <roleName>independent
                  consultant</roleName> in TEI XML. He was for many years associate director of
                  <affiliation>Oxford University Computing Services</affiliation>, and was one of
               the original editors of the TEI. <email>lou.burnard@gmail.com</email></author>
            <author xml:id="CS"><name><forename>Christof</forename>
                  <surname>Schöch</surname></name> is <roleName>professor</roleName> of digital
               humanities at <affiliation>Trier University</affiliation>, Germany, and co-director
               of the <affiliation>Trier Centre for Digital Humanities (TCDH)</affiliation>. He
               chairs the COST Action Distant Reading for European Literary History
                  (CA16204).<email>schoech@uni-trier.de</email></author>
            <author xml:id="CO"><name><forename>Carolin</forename>
                  <surname>Odebrecht</surname></name> is a <roleName>corpus linguist</roleName> at
                  <affiliation>Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</affiliation>. Her research fields
               include modeling, creating, and archiving of historical corpora and corpus metadata
               as well as repository software development. She is the lead for Working Group 1
               Scholarly Resources in CA16204.<email>carolin.odebrecht@hu-berlin.de</email></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>08/07/2021</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor role="guest">Georg Voegeler</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="14">Selected Papers from the 2019 TEI Conference</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the original source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for
               journals in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking
               to publish full-text articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>distant reading</term>
               <term>ELTeC</term>
               <term>ODD chaining</term>
               <term>corpus design</term>
               <term>the European novel</term>
               <term>literary studies</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2020-02-26" who="#CS">Some minor corrections.</change>
         <change when="2019-07-22" who="#CO">some corrections including references, some
            revision.</change>
         <change when="2019-07-22" who="#LB42">submitted</change>
         <change when="2019-07-15" who="#LB42">working through CO and CS comments</change>
         <change when="2019-07-08" who="#LB42">circulated first draft to CO and CS</change>
         <change when="2019-07-01" who="#LB42">started first draft</change>
         <change when="2019-04-24" who="#LB42">finalised abstract</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract">
            <p>Any expansion of the TEI beyond its traditional user base involves a recognition that
               there are many differing answers to the traditional question <q>What is text,
                  really?</q> We report on some work carried out in the context of the COST Action
               Distant Reading for European Literary History (CA16204), in particular on the
               TEI-conformant schemas developed for one of its principal deliverables: the European
               Literary Text Collection (ELTeC).</p>
            <p>The ELTeC will contain comparable corpora for each of at least a dozen European
               languages, each being a balanced sample of one hundred novels from the period 1840 to
               1920, together with metadata concerning their production and reception. We hope that
               it will become a reliable basis for comparative work in data-driven textual
               analytics.</p>
            <p>The focus of the ELTeC encoding scheme is not to represent texts in all their
               original complexity, nor to duplicate the work of scholarly editors. Instead, we aim
               to facilitate a richer and better-informed distant reading than a transcription of
               lexical content alone would permit. At the same time, where the TEI encourages
               diversity, we enforce consistency by permitting representation of only a specific and
               quite small set of textual features, both structural and analytical. These
               constraints are expressed by a master TEI ODD, from which we derive three different
               schemas by ODD chaining, each associated with appropriate documentation.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="intro">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Comity is a term from theology or political studies, where it is used to describe the
               formal recognition by different religions, nation-states, or cultures that other such
               entities have as much right to existence as themselves. In applied linguistics, the
               term has also been used by such writers as Widdowson (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#widdowson1990">1990</ref>) or Aston (<ref type="bibl" target="#aston1988"
                  >1988</ref>) seeking to demonstrate how the establishment of comity can facilitate
               successful intercultural communication, even in the absence of linguistic competence.<note>
                  <quote source="#quote1">Those participating in conversational encounters have to
                     have a care for the preservation of good relations by promoting the other’s
                     positive self-image, by avoiding offence, encouraging comity, and so on. The
                     negotiation of meaning is also a negotiation of social relations</quote> (<ref
                     xml:id="quote1" type="bibl" target="#widdowson1990">Widdowson 1990,
                  110</ref>).</note> We appropriate the term in this latter sense in order to
               reassert the interdisciplinary roots of the TEI.</p>
            <p>Recent histories of the TEI (e.g., <ref type="bibl" target="#gavin2017">Gavin
                  2017</ref>) have a tendency to underemphasize the multiplicity of disciplines
               gathered at its birth, preferring to focus on those disciplines which can be
               plausibly framed as prefiguring our current configuration of the <soCalled>digital
                  humanities</soCalled> (DH) in some way. Yet both the Poughkeepsie conference and
               the process of designing the Guidelines which followed were kick-started by input
               from corpus linguists and computer scientists just as much as from traditional
               philologically minded editors and source-driven historians. The TEI belongs to a
               multiplicity of research communities, dating as it does from a period when
               scholarship at large was beginning to wake up to the implications of the advent of
               massive amounts of digital text for their disciplines. The steering committee which
               oversaw its development and the TEI editors alike conscientiously attempted to ensure
               that the Guidelines should reflect a view of text which was generally shared and
               generic, rather than specific to any discipline or to any particular usage model.</p>
            <p>The TEI necessarily attempted to address the question <q>What is text, really?</q>
               first posed by DeRose and others in 1990 (<ref target="#derose1990" type="bibl"
                  >DeRose et al.
               1990</ref>;<!--               was in copyedited text, against bibliography DeRose et al. 2002-->see
                  also<ref type="bibl" target="#caton2013">Caton 2013</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#vanZundert2017">van Zundert and Andrews 2017</ref>). But in so doing it
               advanced the radical proposition that there may be such a thing as a single abstract
               model of textual components, which might usefully be considered independently of its
               expression in a particular source or output, or its use in any particular discipline.
               This suggestion was necessarily at odds with at least two prevailing orthodoxies: on
               the one hand, the view that a text is no less and no more than the physical documents
               which instantiate it, and can be adequately described and represented by its salient
               visual properties alone; on the other hand, the view that a text is solely a
               linguistic phenomenon, comprising a bag of words, the statistical properties of which
               are adequate to describe it. But the TEI tried very hard to prefer comity over
               conflict, not only in its organization, which brought together an extraordinarily
               heterogeneous group of experts, but also in its chief outputs: a set of encoding
               guidelines which, while supporting specialization, did not require any particular
               specialization to prevail.</p>
            <p>Old orthodoxies do not die easily, and many of the same arguments are still being
               played out in the somewhat different context of today’s DH theorizers. But in our
               present paper, we simply want to explore the extent to which the TEI’s model of text
               can be adapted to conform to the model of text characterizing such fields as
               stylometry, stylistics, textual analytics, or (to use the current term)
                  <soCalled>distant reading</soCalled>. We hope also to explore the claim that by so
               doing we may facilitate the enrichment of that model, and thus facilitate more
               sophisticated research into textual phenomena across different corpora. And we hope
               to demonstrate that this is best done by cultivating mutual respect for the widely
               differing scientific, cultural, and linguistic traditions characterizing this
               cross-European and cross-disciplinary project, that is, by acknowledging a comity of
               methods as well as languages.</p>
            <p>Our approach focuses on using the TEI predominantly as a format for exchange and as a
               starting point for further transformation, conversion, and enrichment processes that
               might result in different formats.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="cost">
            <head>The COST Action Distant Reading for European Literary History</head>
            <p>The context for this work is the EU-funded COST Action Distant Reading for European
               Literary History (CA 16204), a principal deliverable of which will be the European
               Literary Text Collection (ELTeC).<note>This project is a COST (European Cooperation
                  in Science and Technology)</note> This is a set of comparable corpora for each of
               at least a dozen European languages, each corpus being a balanced selection of one
               hundred novels from the period 1840 to 1920, together with metadata situating them in
               their contexts of production and of reception. It is hoped that the ELTeC will become
               a reliable basis for comparative work in cross-linguistic data-driven textual
               analytics, eventually providing an accessible benchmark for a particular written
               genre of considerable cultural importance across Europe during the period between
               1840 and 1920.</p>
            <p>Two significant decisions made early on in the planning of the COST Action underlie
               the work reported here. First, it was agreed that the ELTeC should be delivered in a
               TEI-encoded format, using a schema developed specifically for the project. Second,
               the design of that encoding scheme, in particular the textual features it makes
               explicit by means of markup, should be defined as far as possible by the needs of the
               distant reading research community rather than by any preexisting notions about the
               nature of literary texts, to the extent that the needs of that community could be
               determined. The target audience envisaged includes experts in computational
               stylistics, corpus linguistics, computational literary studies, and traditional
               literary studies as well as more general digital humanists, but is probably best
               characterized as having major enthusiasm and expertise in the application of
               statistical methods to literary and linguistic analysis, and only minor interest in
               the kinds of textual features on which most TEI projects have tended to focus. In
               various scenarios, however, these scholars do benefit from explicit markup of textual
               phenomena such as chapter boundaries, quotations, notes, front and back matter, or
               foreign words and phrases.<note>There is no authoritative single list of TEI
                  projects, though the TEI Consortium website has for many years offered a platform
                  for one: <title level="a">Projects Using the TEI,</title> accessed May 17, 2021,
                     <ptr target="https://tei-c.org/activities/projects/"/>. More recently, the
                  TEIhub project lists more than 12,500 <ptr type="software" xml:id="R1"
                     target="#GitHub"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R1">GitHub</rs>-hosted TEI
                  projects (last updated May 11, 2021, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R7"
                     target="#teipelican"/><rs type="soft.url" ref="#R7"><ptr
                        target="https://teihub.netlify.app/"/></rs>); an associated bot called <rs
                     type="soft.url" ref="#R7">TEI Pelican</rs> provides a daily twitter feed of new
                     <ptr type="software" xml:id="R2" target="#GitHub"/><rs type="soft.name"
                     ref="#R2">GitHub</rs> repositories containing a TEI header. We are unaware of
                  any systematic analysis of the application types indicated by these data sources,
                  but a glance gives the impression that traditional editorial and resource-building
                  projects predominate.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The work of the Action<note>Further information about the Action is available from
                  its website at <ptr target="https://www.distant-reading.net/"/>. For information
                  about the organization and decision processes see also the COST Vademecum, June
                  2019, <ptr
                     target="https://www.cost.eu/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/Vademecum-20062019-V7-.pdf"
                  />.</note> is carried out by four Working Groups: WG1 Scholarly Resources is
               responsible for the work described in this paper; WG2 Methods and Tools is concerned
               with text analytic techniques and tools; WG3 Literary Theory and History is concerned
               with applications and implications of those methods and for literary theory; WG4
               Dissemination is responsible for outreach and communication.</p>
            <p>The design and construction of the ELTeC is the responsibility of WG1, as noted
               above. Initially, this work was split into three distinct tasks: First, defining
               selection criteria (corpus design); second, developing basic encoding methods (both
               for data and for metadata); and third, defining a suitable workflow for preparation
               of the corpus. Working papers on each of these topics plus a fourth on theoretical
               issues of sampling and balance were prepared for discussion and approval by the
               members of WG1, and remain available from the Working Group’s website. <note>These
                  and other documents are available from the Action’s <ptr type="software"
                     xml:id="R3" target="#GitHub"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R3">GitHub</rs> page,
                  accessed May 17, 2021, <ptr target="https://distantreading.github.io/"/>.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="eltec">
            <head>The ELTeC Encoding Scheme(s)</head>
            <p>Distant reading methods cover a wide range of computational approaches to literary
               text analysis, such as authorship attribution, topic modeling, character network
               analysis, or stylistic analysis, but they are rarely concerned with editorial matters
               such as textual variation, the establishment of an authoritative text, or production
               of print or online versions of a text. Consequently, the ELTeC encoding scheme was
               deliberately not intended to represent source documents in all their original
               complexity of structure or appearance, but rather to make it as simple as possible to
               access the words of which the texts are composed in an informed and predictable way.
               The goal was neither to duplicate the work of scholarly editors nor to produce (yet
               another) digital edition of a specific source document. Rather, the encoding scheme
               was designed in such a way as to ensure that ELTeC texts could be processed by
               simple-minded (but XML-aware) systems primarily concerned with lexis and to make life
               easier for the developers of such systems.</p>
            <p>Next to the application scenarios for distant reading, the multilingual and European
               perspective of ELTeC poses further requirements for the encoding. The encoding system
               should be applicable to different languages as well as language- or context-specific
               publication traditions during the entire period and across Europe. We anticipated
               different realizations of text and chapter structure and differing paratextual
               organizations. Hence, our encoding schema concentrates on commonalities rather than
               the specifics of certain printing houses or traditions.</p>
            <p>A further important principle is that ELTeC markup should offer the encoder very
               little choice, and the software developer very few surprises: the number of tags
               available is greatly reduced, and their application is tightly constrained. It
               facilitates processing greatly if access to each part of the XML tree can be provided
               in a uniform and consistent way across multiple ELTeC corpora.</p>
            <p>By default, the TEI provides a very rich vocabulary, and many subtly different ways
               of doing more or less the same thing. TEI encoders have often taken full advantage of
               that to produce texts which vary enormously, both in the set of XML tags used and in
               the range of attribute values associated with them. It is tempting, but entirely
               mistaken, to assume that the TEI-conformant deliverables from project A will
               necessarily be marked up in the same way as the TEI-conformant deliverables from
               project B.<note>A large-scale project called MONK (Metadata Offer New Knowledge)
                  demonstrated some of the technical consequences of this for integrated searching
                  of TEI resources: see further the MONK web page, last updated August 13, 2014,
                     <ptr target="http://monk.library.illinois.edu/"/>.</note> On the contrary, all
               that <soCalled>TEI conformance</soCalled> really guarantees is that the intended
               semantics of the markup used by the two projects should be recoverable by reference
               to a published standard, and are not entirely ad hoc or sui generis. (This may not
               seem much of an advance, though it is: see further <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#burnard2019">Burnard 2019</ref>).</p>
            <p>Following this No Surprises principle, the simplest ELTeC schema (the <soCalled>level
                  zero</soCalled> schema) provides the bare minimum of tags needed to mark up the
               typical structure and content of a nineteenth-century novel. All preliminary matter
               other than the title page and any authorial preface or introduction is discarded; the
               remainder is marked as a <gi>div</gi> of <att>type</att>
               <val>titlepage</val> or <val>liminal</val>, within a <gi>front</gi> element. Within
               the <gi>body</gi> of a text, the <gi>div</gi> element is also used to make explicit
               its structural organization, with <att>type</att> attribute values <val>part</val>,
                  <val>chapter</val>, or <val>letter</val> only.<note>An exception is made for
                  epistolary novels which contain only the representation of a sequence of letters,
                  with no other significant content: these may be marked as <tag>div
                     type=&quot;letter&quot;</tag>.</note> For ELTeC purposes, a
                  <soCalled>chapter</soCalled> is considered to be the smallest subsection of a
               novel within which paragraphs of text appear directly. Further subdivisions within a
               chapter (often indicated conventionally by ellipses, dashes, stars, etc.) are marked
               using the <gi>milestone</gi> element; larger groupings of <gi>div</gi> elements are
               indicated by <gi>div</gi> elements, always of type <val>part</val>, whatever their
               hierarchical level. Headings, at whatever level, are always marked using the
                  <gi>head</gi> element when appearing at the start of a <gi>div</gi>, and the
                  <gi>trailer</gi> element when appearing at the end. Within the <gi>div</gi>
               element, only a very limited number of elements is permitted: specifically, in
               addition to those already mentioned, <gi>p</gi> or <gi>l</gi> (verse line). Within
               these elements we find either plain text, <gi>hi</gi> (highlighted), <gi>pb</gi>
               (page break), or <gi>milestone</gi> elements. After some debate, the Action’s
               Management Committee agreed that it would be practical to require only this tiny
               subset of the TEI for all ELTeC texts.</p>
            <p>The texts included in an ELTeC corpus may come from different kinds of sources. For
               some language collections, no digital texts of any kind exist: the encoder must start
               from page images, manually transcribe or put them through OCR, and introduce ELTeC
               markup from scratch. Such cases are, however, unusual. For most languages, existing
               digital texts are already available, but the encoder must research the format used
               and find a way of converting it to ELTeC’s TEI encoding schema. In some cases, a TEI
               version may already exist; in others, a Project Gutenberg or an eBook version; in yet
               others, the text may be stored in a database of some kind. Whichever is the case, if
               it is possible to retain distinctions which the ELTeC scheme permits, this is clearly
               desirable and feasible; perhaps less obviously, it is also necessary to remove
               distinctions made by the original format which the ELTeC scheme does not permit. This
               diversity of source material was one motivation for permitting multiple encoding
               levels in the ELTeC scheme: at level zero, only the bare minimum of markup defined
               above is permitted, while at level 1 a slightly richer (though still minimalist)
               encoding is defined. At level 2, additional tags are introduced to support linguistic
               processing of various kinds, as discussed further below. Down-conversion from a
               higher to a lower level is always automatically possible, but up-conversion from a
               lower to a higher level generally requires human intervention or additional
               processing.</p>
            <p>At level 1, the following additional distinctions may be made in an encoding:</p>
            <list>
               <item>the <gi>label</gi> element may be used for heading-like titles appearing in the
                  middle of a division;</item>
               <item>the <gi>quote</gi> element may be used to distinguish passages such as
                  quotations, epigraphs, stretches of verse, and letters which seem to
                     <soCalled>float</soCalled> within the running text;</item>
               <item>the <gi>corr</gi> element may be used to indicate a passage (typically a word
                  or phrase) which is clearly erroneous in the original and which has been
                  editorially corrected;</item>
               <item>the elements <gi>foreign</gi>, <gi>emph</gi>, or <gi>title</gi> are available
                  and should be used in preference to <gi>hi</gi> for passages rendered in a
                  different font or otherwise made visually salient in the source, where an encoder
                  can do so with confidence;</item>
               <item>the element <gi>gap</gi> may be used to indicate where some component of a
                  source (typically an illustration) has been left out of the encoding;</item>
               <item>the elements <gi>note</gi> and <gi>ref</gi> may be used to capture the location
                  and content of authorially supplied footnotes or endnotes; wherever they occur in
                  the source, notes must be collected together in a <tag>div
                     type=&quot;notes&quot;</tag> within a <gi>back</gi> element.</item>
            </list>
            <p>This list of elements may seem distressingly small. It lacks entirely some elements
               which every TEI introductory course regards as indispensable (no <gi>list</gi> or
                  <gi>item</gi>; no <gi>choice</gi> or <gi>abbr</gi>; no <gi>name</gi> or
                  <gi>date</gi>, etc.) and tolerates some practices bordering on tag abuse. For
               example, all the components of a title page are marked as <gi>p</gi> since no
               specialized elements (<gi>titlePage</gi>, <gi>docImprint</gi>, etc.) are available.
               In the absence of specialized but culture-specific features (for example, publisher
               name, imprint, and imprimatur), the encoding identifies only fundamental textual
               features common to every kind of text. Nevertheless, we believe that the set of
               concepts it supports overlaps well with the set of textual features which almost any
               existing digital transcription will seek to preserve in some form or another. This
               may explain both why the majority of the texts so far collected in the ELTeC have
               been encoded at level 1 rather than level 0, and also the speed with which the
               collection is growing.</p>
            <p>ELTeC level 1 is intended to facilitate a richer and better-informed distant reading
               of a text than a transcription of its lexical content alone would permit. ELTeC level
               2 is partly intended to provide a consistent and TEI-conformant way of representing
               the results of such readings, in particular those concerned with linguistic features.
               Its primary goal is to represent in a standard way additional layers of annotation of
               particular importance to distant reading applications such as stylometry or topic
               modeling. Enrichment of each lexical token to indicate its morpho-syntactic category
               (part of speech: POS) or its lemma and identification of tokens which refer to named
               entities are both well within the scope of existing text-processing techniques, and
               are also routinely used in distant reading applications. The challenge is that the
               input and the output formats typically used by such tools are rarely XML-based, and
               seem superficially to have a model of text quite different from that of the
                  <soCalled>ordered hierarchy of content objects</soCalled> in terms of which the
               TEI community traditionally operates. For many in the distant reading community (it
               seems), a text is little more than a sequence of tokens, mostly corresponding with
               orthographically defined words, though there is some variability in the principles
               underlying the process of tokenization, for example in the modeling of clitics or
               compound forms. Each token has a number of properties, which might include such
               attributes as its part of speech, its lemma, or its position in the sequence of
               tokens making up the document. Information such as its rendition or its status as
               part of a dialogue or narrative, which in a more faithful XML model would be
               represented as properties of some higher level construct, may also sometimes be
               modeled as a property of the token itself.</p>
            <p>If a community is defined by its tools, it would appear that the distant reading
               community has not fully embraced the notion of XML as anything other than a rather
               verbose archival format. However, communities are not defined solely by their tools:
               by seeking a way of reconciling these differing views of what text really is in a
               spirit of comity we hope to demonstrate that there are advantages both for the
               distant reader or stylometrician and for the literary analyst or textual editor.</p>
            <p>At ELTeC level2, all existing elements are retained and two new elements, <gi>s</gi>
               and <gi>w</gi>, are introduced to support segmentation of running text into
               sentence-like and word-like sequences respectively. Individual tokens are marked
               using the <gi>w</gi> element and decorated with one or more of the TEI-defined
               linguistic attributes <att>pos</att>
               <att>lemma</att> and <att>join</att> Both words and punctuation marks are considered
               to be <soCalled>tokens</soCalled> in this sense, although the TEI recommends
               distinguishing the two cases using <gi>w</gi> and <gi>pc</gi> respectively. On this
               occasion, we have preferred a reduction in the number of choices for the encoder to a
               strict adherence to TEI semantics. The <gi>s</gi> (segment) element is used to
               provide an end-to-end tessellating segmentation of the whole sequence of <gi>w</gi>
               elements, based on orthographic form. This provides a convenient extension of the
               existing text-body-div hierarchy within which tokens are located.</p>
            <p>The elements <gi>p</gi>, <gi>head</gi>, and <gi>l</gi> (which at levels 0 and 1
               contain only text) at level 2 can contain a sequence of <gi>s</gi> elements. Elements
                  <gi>gap</gi>, <gi>milestone</gi>, <gi>pb</gi>, and <gi>ref</gi> are also permitted
               within text content at any point, but these are disregarded when segmentation is
               carried out.<note>To facilitate this, any content within a <gi>ref</gi> element is
                  discarded at level 2.</note> Each <gi>s</gi> element can contain a sequence of
                  <gi>w</gi> elements, either directly or wrapped in one of the sub-paragraph
               elements <gi>corr</gi>, <gi>emph</gi>, <gi>foreign</gi>, <gi>hi</gi>, <gi>label</gi>,
                  <gi>title</gi>. To this list we add the element <gi>rs</gi> (referring string),
               provided by the TEI for the encoding of any form of entity name, such as a Named
               Entity Recognition procedure might produce.</p>
            <p>This approach implies that <gi>w</gi> elements may appear at two levels in the
               hierarchy, which may upset some software; it also implies that <gi>w</gi> elements
               must be properly contained within one of these sub-paragraph elements, without
               overlap. If either issue proves to be a major stumbling block, an alternative would
               be to remove the tags demarcating these sub-paragraph elements, indicating their
               semantics instead by additional attribute values on the <gi>w</gi> elements they
               contain.</p>
            <p>This TEI XML format is equally applicable to the production of training data for
               applications using machine learning techniques and to the outputs of such systems.
               However, since such machine learning applications typically operate on text content
               in a tabular format only, we envisage XSLT filters which transform (or generate) the
               XML markup discussed here from such tabular formats without loss of information. At
               the time of writing, however, Working Group 2 has yet to put this proposed
               architecture to the test.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="eltecmetadata">
            <head>ELTeC Metadata and Corpus Design</head>
            <p>Like every other TEI document, every ELTeC text has a TEI Header, though for the
               reasons already mentioned its organization and content are both constrained much more
               tightly than is common TEI praxis. The structure of an ELTeC Header is the same no
               matter what level of encoding applies to the text. It provides minimal bibliographic
               information about the encoded text and its source, sufficient to identify the text
               and its author, in a fixed and consistent format. It is assumed that if more detailed
               bibliographic information is required, for example about the author or work encoded,
               it is better obtained from standard authority files; to that end a VIAF (Virtual
               International Authority File) code may be associated with the title and author in the
               TEI header.</p>
            <p>As noted above, ELTeC texts may be derived from many sources, each of which should be
               documented correctly in the header’s <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element. After some debate,
               a common set of practices has been identified to distinguish (for example) ELTeC
               texts derived directly from a print source from those derived from a digital source,
               itself derived from a known print source, and to provide information about each
               source. In the following example, the source of the ELTeC version is a preexisting
               digital edition provided by Project Gutenberg, but the source description also
               provides information about the first print edition of the work concerned.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example1">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <bibl type="digitalSource">
                     <title>Project Gutenberg EBook A engomadeira de Almada Negreiros</title>
                     <ref target="http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/23879"/>
                  </bibl>
                  <bibl type="firstEdition">
                     <title>A engomadeira</title>
                     <author>José de Almada Negreiros</author>
                     <publisher>Typographia Monteiro &amp; Cardoso</publisher>
                     <date>1917</date>
                  </bibl>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">A preexisting digital edition provided by Project Gutenberg as
                  source of the ELTeC version</head>
            </figure>
            <p>In most cases, the ELTeC text will correspond with the first edition of a work in
               book form; but even where this is not the case, or where information about the
               precise source used is not available, minimal information about that first edition
               should also be provided in order to place the work in its original temporal
               context.</p>
            <p>As with other TEI-conformant documents, beside the mandatory file description, the
               TEI header of every ELTeC text contains a publication statement which specifies its
               licensing conditions (all texts included in the ELTeC corpora are in the public
               domain; the textual markup is provided with a Creative Commons Attribution [CC BY]
               licence); an encoding statement specifying the level of encoding used; and a revision
               description containing versioning information. The TEI header is also used to provide
               metadata describing the associated text in a standardized form; this is held in the
                  <gi>profileDesc</gi> element, which must specify the languages used by the text,
               may optionally include a <gi>textClass</gi> element containing any culture-specific
               keywords considered useful to describe the text, and must contain a <gi>textDesc</gi>
               element which documents the text’s status with respect to selection criteria
               discussed below.</p>
            <p>One of the knottier problems or (to be positive) more distinctive features of an
               ELTeC corpus is that it is not intended to be an ad hoc accidentally constructed
               collection but a designed corpus. Its composition is determined not by the
               happenstance of whatever we can get our hands on, but is instead defensible, at least
               in theory, as a principled and representative selection.</p>
            <p>The big question is, of course, representative of what.</p>
            <p>It would be nice to say that it represents the production of novels in a specific
               language during a specified historical period (1840–1920) throughout Europe. WG1 has
               working definitions for both novels and Europe which we do not discuss further here,
               though both are clearly problematic terms. It is hoped that the ELTeC will provide
               data for an empirical discussion of such terms, feeding into the work of WG3 on
               literary theory and terminology.</p>
            <p>But we cannot make that claim without any data about the population we are claiming
               to represent—which is hard to come by for many of the languages concerned. We know
               about the novels which we know about, which tend to be the ones that national
               libraries or equivalent cultural heritage institutions have chosen to preserve, which
               publishers over time have been able to sell, and which lecturers in literary studies
               have chosen to teach. More ephemeral titles may have been collected (for example, by
               a copyright library), but equally well may have been discarded or even suppressed as
               unworthy of inclusion in the national patrimony. Titles and authors alike can go in
               and out of fashion. But how can we express opinions about changes in the nature of
               the published novel if the sample on which we base those opinions is wildly different
               in composition from the actual population? If our data leads us to assert that novels
               in a given language are never written by women, or are never of fewer than one
               hundred thousand words, is this simply because no female authors happen to have been
               preserved, or because short novels were routinely discarded from the collection? Or,
               on the other hand, does this actually indicate something fundamental, a
               characteristic of the population we are investigating? This matters particularly for
               ELTeC, one of the goals of which is precisely to facilitate cross-language
               comparisons.</p>
            <p>This problem of representativeness is of course one which every corpus linguist has
               to face, and discussions of its implications are easy to find in the
                  literature.<note>Some notable examples include <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#biber1993">Biber 1993</ref>; <ref target="#ludeling2011" type="bibl"
                     >Lüdeling 2011</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#bode2018">Bode
                  2018</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Our approach is to sidestep the impossibility of representing an unknown (and
               sometimes unknowable) population by attempting instead to represent the range of
               possible variation in the values of a predefined set of variables (metadata), each
               corresponding with a more or less objective category of information available for all
               members of the population. To take a trivial example, every novel can be
               characterized as short, medium, or long; there is no possible fourth value for this
               category unless we revise our definition of length (elastic? unknown?
               instantaneous?). So, as a working hypothesis, we might say that a corpus in which
               roughly a third of the titles are short, a third are long, and a third are medium
               will represent the variation possible for this category. If we apply this principle
               uniformly across all our corpora, we can reliably investigate (for example)
               cross-language variation in some other observable phenomenon (say a fondness for
               syntactically complex sentences) with respect to length. But note that we have made
               absolutely no claim about whether novel length in the underlying population is also
               divided in this way.</p>
            <p>The decade in which a novel first appears in book form is a similarly objectively
               characteristic, which in principle we can determine for every member of the
               population. We can also classify every title according to the actual sex of their
               author(s) (with values such as female, male, mixed, unknown). And we can likewise
               classify a title in terms of its staying power or persistence by looking at the
               number of times it has been reprinted over a particular period. We suggest that texts
               which have been frequently reprinted over a long period may reasonably be considered
                  <soCalled>canonical</soCalled> in some sense of that vexed term. The goal of our
               corpus-balancing exercise is to ensure more or less equal time for each possible
               value for each of these four categories—size, decade, author sex, and reprint
               count.</p>
            <p>Ideally, each corpus should have similar figures not just for each value, but for
               each combination of values (text proportion within each corpus): so, for example,
               looking at the third of all titles which are characterized as
                  <soCalled>short</soCalled>, there should be roughly equal numbers for each decade
               of first appearance, roughly equal numbers by male and female authors, and so on.
               This may however be a counsel of perfection. It is already apparent that for some
               languages, it is very difficult to find any texts at all within some time periods, or
               by female authors. Similarly, our definitions of short (ten to fifty thousand words),
               medium (fifty to one hundred thousand words), and long (over one hundred thousand
               words), though objective and easy to validate, assumes that there will be enough
               novels of a given length in the underlying population for us to extract a balanced
               sample; but in some languages it may be that the distribution of lengths across the
               population is entirely different. We cannot tell whether (for example) the absence of
               any <soCalled>long</soCalled> novels at all in Czech, Serbian, or Norwegian is
               characteristic of those languages, or an artifact of the selection process. Another
               difficulty is that our corpus design deliberately seeks to include some forgotten or
               marginal works along with well-known canonical texts: this is relatively easy for
               traditions such as English, French, or German where copyright laws have led to the
               maintenance and documentation of large national collections, but less so for other
               less well-documented languages. The ELTeC Summary Page (produced April 9, 2021, <ptr
                  target="http://distantreading.github.io/ELTeC/"/>) gives figures for the current
               state of each ELTeC corpus, but of course does not provide data about the populations
               from which those corpora have been selected.<note>For a further discussion of corpus
                  composition in ELTeC, see <ref type="bibl" target="#Schöchetal2021">Schöch et al.
                     (forthcoming)</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To encode these balance criteria in the TEI header in as direct and accessible a
               manner as possible, we have chosen to repurpose the little-used <gi>textDesc</gi>
               element, originally provided by the TEI as a wrapper for a set of so-called
               situational parameters proposed by corpus linguists as a way of objectively
               characterizing linguistic production.<note>The <gi>textDesc</gi> element is discussed
                  in section 15.2.1 of the TEI Guidelines (<ref type="bibl" target="#tei2021">TEI
                     Consortium 2021</ref>, <title level="a">The Text Description</title>, <ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.2.2/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CC.html#CCAHTD"
                  />).</note> In our case, we replace the TEI’s suggested vocabulary for these
               parameters with a vocabulary representing our four criteria, expressed as new non-TEI
               elements in the ELTeC namespace. These elements (<gi>eltec:sex</gi>,
                  <gi>eltec:size</gi>, <gi>eltec:reprintCount</gi>, and <gi>eltec:timeSlot</gi>) are
               required by the ELTeC schemas and have an attribute <att>key</att> which supplies a
               coded value for the criterion concerned taken from a predefined closed list. So, for
               example, a long (over 100,000 words) novel by a female author first published between
               1881 and 1900 but only infrequently reprinted thereafter might have a text
               description like the following:</p>
            <figure xml:id="example2">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <textDesc xmlns:eltec="http://distant-reading.net/ns">
                     <eltec:authorGender key="F"/>
                     <eltec:reprintCount key="low"/>
                     <eltec:size key="long"/>
                     <eltec:timeSlot key="T3"/>
                  </textDesc>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">New non-TEI elements in the ELTeC namespace.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>When complete, this information can be used to select subcorpora from the corpus as a
               whole, thus permitting more delicate cross-linguistic comparisons: for example
               between the lexis of male and female writers, or between the stylistic features
               typically associated with long or short texts. During the construction phase, these
               coded values also make it easy to monitor the emerging composition of the corpus, for
               example to detect whether or not the ratio of male to female writers is consistent
               across different time periods, by means of a simple visualization like that in <ptr
                  target="#figure1" type="crossref"/>:</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure1">
               <graphic url="media/image1.png" height="340px" width="454px"/>
               <head type="legend">ELTeC-eng Balance</head>
            </figure>
            <p>The columns of this <soCalled>mosaic plot</soCalled> show the proportion of long,
               medium, and short novels, while the rows show the proportion of novels from each time
               slot, and the color shows the proportion of male/female authors. In this
               representation of the current state of the English corpus (one hundred texts) there
               are roughly as many female (blue) as male (pink) writers across the board, but there
               is a preponderance of long texts, as shown by the greater width of the first column.
               Moreover, by adding the numbers given within each row , we can quickly detect the
               preponderance of titles published in time slot 3.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure2">
               <graphic url="media/image3.png" height="340px" width="454px"/>
               <head type="legend">ELTeC-hun Balance</head>
            </figure>
            <p>For comparison, in <ptr target="#figure2" type="crossref"/> the same plot for the
               current state of the Hungarian corpus (one hundred texts) shows significantly fewer
               female writers, and a higher proportion of short texts.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="chaining">
            <head>Chaining ODDs</head>
            <p>The TEI ODD (One Document Does it all) system (<ref type="bibl" target="#rahtz2013"
                  >Rahtz and Burnard 2013</ref>) is widely used as a means of customizing TEI and
               documenting the customization in a standard way. When only a single ODD customization
               is used across a project, there is a natural tendency to produce broadly permissive
               schemas, to allow for the inevitable variation of requirements when materials of
               different kinds are to be processed in an integrated collection. But this prevents
               the encoder from taking full advantage of the ability of an XML schema to check that
               particular documents conform to predefined rules, unless they are willing greatly to
               increase the complexity of their workflow. A better approach, pioneered by the
               Deutsches Textarchiv (<ref type="bibl" target="#haaf2017">Haaf and Thomas
               2017</ref>), has been the use of a technique known as ODD chaining (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#burnard2016">Burnard 2016</ref>). Here, a project first defines a base
               ODD which selects all the TEI components considered to be useful anywhere and then
               uses it as the basis for smaller, more constraining, ODDs which select from the base
               only the components (or other rules) specific to a subset of the project’s
               documentary universe. For example, an archive may have identified a common set of
               metadata it wishes to document across all of its holdings but also have particular
               metadata requirements for print and manuscript sources respectively. Simply defining
               two different ODDs, one for print and one for manuscript, when many other components
               apply to either kind of source, opens the door to redundant duplication and the risk
               of inconsistency. The ODD-chaining approach requires the definition of a base ODD
               which contains the union of the components needed for these two different ODDs,
               constructed as an appropriate selection from the full range of TEI components. The
               ODDs for print and manuscript are then defined as further specializations or
               customizations of the base, ensuring thereby that the common components are used in a
               consistent manner, but preserving comity by allowing equal status to the two
               specialized schemas.</p>
            <p>In the ELTeC project, we begin by defining an ODD which selects from TEI all the
               components used by any ELTeC schema at any level. This ODD also contains
               documentation and specifies usage constraints applicable across every schema. This
               base ODD is then processed using the TEI standard odd2odd stylesheet to produce a
               stand-alone set of TEI specifications which we call eltec-library. Three different
               ODDs, eltec-0, eltec-1, and eltec-2, then derive specific schemas and documentation
               for each of the three ELTeC levels, using this library of specifications as a base
               rather than using the whole of the TEI. This enables us to customize the TEI across
               the whole project, while at the same time respecting three different views of the
               resulting encoding standard. As with other ODDs, we are then able to produce
               documentation and formal schemas which reflect exactly the scope of each encoding
               level.</p>
            <p>The ODD sources and their outputs are maintained on <ptr type="software" xml:id="R4"
                  target="#GitHub"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R4">GitHub</rs> and are also <ptr
                  target="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3546326"/>published on Zenodo (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#odebrecht2019">Odebrecht et al. 2019</ref>) along with the
               ELTeC corpora.<note>The <ptr type="software" xml:id="R5" target="#GitHub"/><rs
                     type="soft.name" ref="#R5">GitHub</rs> repository for the ELTeC collection
                  (last updated May 17, 2021) is found at <ptr
                     target="https://github.com/COST-ELTeC/"/>; the Zenodo community within which it
                  is being published (last updated April 11, 2021) lives at <ptr
                     target="https://zenodo.org/communities/eltec/"/>.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="stateofplay">
            <head>State of Play and Future Work</head>
            <p>The ELTeC is still very much a work in progress and hence we cannot report with any
               plausibility that our design goals have been achieved. An initial release of the
               collection was published on Zenodo in November 2019 (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#odebrecht2019">Odebrecht et al. 2019</ref>), with a first major 1.0
               release at the end of 2020. We expect several future releases before the end of the
               project, as more language collections reach the target of one hundred titles. As of
               this writing, seven collections (English, French, German, Hungarian, Polish,
               Portuguese, and Slovenian) have already achieved this goal, and a further five
               (Norwegian, Romanian, Serbian, Spanish, and Swedish) are over halfway there. Four
               more collections (Czech, Greek, Lithuanian, and Ukrainian) are currently under active
               development and are expected to become available during the coming year. As noted
               above, up-to-date information about the current state of all corpora is publicly
               visible at <ptr target="http://distantreading.github.io/ELTeC/"/>, which includes
               links to the individual <ptr type="software" xml:id="R6" target="#GitHub"/><rs
                  type="soft.name" ref="#R6">GitHub</rs> repositories for each corpus.</p>
            <p>As well as continuing to expand the collection, and continuing to fine-tune its
               composition, we hope to improve the consistency and reliability of the metadata
               associated with each text, as far as possible automatically. For example, we have
               developed two complementary methods of automatically counting the number of reprints
               for each title, one by screen-scraping from WorldCat, and the other by processing
               data from a Z39.50 server where available. These methods should provide more reliable
               data than have hitherto been available for the <soCalled>reprintCount</soCalled>
               criterion mentioned above.</p>
            <p>The main area of future work we anticipate is, however, in the testing of the
               proposed ELTeC level 2 encoding and an evaluation of its usefulness. At a technical
               level, this may necessitate some changes in the existing markup scheme, but of
               perhaps more interest is the extent to which its availability will exemplify the
               virtue of striving for comity among the many ways in which TEI XML markup can be
               applied.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <head>References</head>
               <bibl xml:id="aston1988"><author>Aston, Guy</author>. <date>1988</date>. <title
                     level="a">Learning Comity: An Approach to the Description and Pedagogy of
                     Interactional Speech</title>. <title level="j">Testi e discorsi: Strumenti
                     linguistici e letterari</title> 9. Bologna: CLUEB.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="biber1993"><author>Biber, Douglas</author>. <date>1993</date>. <title
                     level="a">Representativeness in Corpus Design</title>. <title level="j"
                     >Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 8 (4): <biblScope unit="page"
                     >243–57</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI">10.1093/llc/8.4.243</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bode2018"><author>Bode, Katherine</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title
                     level="m">A World of Fiction: Digital Collections and the Future of Literary
                     History</title>. Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan Press.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="burnard2016"><author>Burnard, Lou</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title
                     level="a">ODD Chaining for Beginners</title>. TEI Council Technical Working
                  Paper. TEI <ptr type="software" xml:id="GitHub" target="#GitHub"/><rs
                     type="soft.name" ref="#GitHub">GitHub</rs> IO Repository. Available at <ptr
                     target="http://teic.github.io/PDF/howtoChain.pdf"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="burnard2019"><author>Burnard, Lou</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title
                     level="a">What Is TEI Conformance, and Why Should You Care?</title>
                  <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> 12. <ptr
                     target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1777"/> doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.4000/jtei.1777</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="caton2013"><author>Caton, Paul</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
                     level="a">On the Term <term>Text</term> in Digital Humanities</title>. <title
                     level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 28 (2): <biblScope
                     unit="page">209–20</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                  >10.1093/llc/fqt001</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="derose1990"><author>DeRose, Steven J.</author>, <author>David G.
                     Durand</author>, <author>Elli Mylonas</author>, and <author>Allen H.
                     Renear</author>. <date>1990</date>. <title level="a">What Is Text,
                     Really?</title>
                  <title level="j">Journal of Computing in Higher Education</title> 1 (2):
                     <biblScope unit="page">3–26</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.1007/BF02941632</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="gavin2017"><author>Gavin, Michael</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title
                     level="a">How to Think about EEBO</title>. <title level="j">Textual
                     Cultures</title> 11 (1–2) (published online June 11, 2019). doi:<idno
                     type="DOI">10.14434/textual.v11i1-2.23570</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="haaf2017"><author>Haaf, Susanne</author>, and <author>Christian
                     Thomas</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">Enabling the Encoding of
                     Manuscripts within the DTABf: Extension and Modularization of the
                     Format</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding
                     Initiative</title> 10. <ptr target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1650"
                  /> doi:<idno type="DOI">10.4000/jtei.1650</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ludeling2011"><author>Lüdeling, Anke</author>. <date>2011</date>.
                     <title level="a">Corpora in Linguistics: Sampling and Annotation</title>. In
                     <title level="m">Going Digital. Evolutionary and Revolutionary Aspects of
                     Digitization,</title> edited by <editor>Karl Grandin</editor>, <biblScope
                     unit="page">220–43</biblScope>. Nobel Symposium 147. New York: Science History
                  Publications/USA.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="odebrecht2019"><author>Odebrecht, Carolin</author>, <author>Lou
                     Burnard</author>, <author>Borja Navarro Colorado</author>, <author>Maciej
                     Eder</author>, and <author>Christof Schöch</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title
                     level="a">The European Literary Text Collection ELTeC</title>. Poster, version
                  1, November 18. Zenodo. doi:<idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.3546326</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="rahtz2013"><author>Rahtz, Sebastian</author>, and <author>Lou
                     Burnard</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a">Reviewing the TEI ODD
                     System</title>. In <title level="m">DocEng 13: Proceedings of the 2013 ACM
                     Symposium on Document Engineering</title>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >193–96</biblScope>. New York: ACM. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.1145/2494266.2494321</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Schöchetal2021"><author>Schöch, Christof</author>, <author>Roxana
                     Patraș</author>, <author>Diana Santos</author>, and <author>Tomaž
                     Erjavec</author>. Forthcoming. <title level="a">Creating the European Literary
                     Text Collection (ELTeC): Challenges and Perspectives.</title>
                  <title level="m">Modern Languages Open</title>. <ptr
                     target="https://doi.org/Preprint"/>Preprint, May 7, 2021. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.5281/zenodo.4742419</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tei2021">TEI Consortium. <date>2021</date>.<title level="m">TEI P5:
                     Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange. Version 4.2.2.</title>
                  Last updated April 9. N.p.: TEI Consortium. <ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.2.2/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="vanZundert2017"><author>van Zundert, Joris J.</author>, and
                     <author>Tara L. Andrews</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">Qu’est-ce
                     qu’un texte numérique? A New Rationale for the Digital Representation of
                     Text</title>. <title level="j">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> 32
                  (supplement 2): <biblScope unit="page">ii78–88</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.1093/llc/fqx039</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="widdowson1990"><author>Widdowson, Henry G.</author>
                  <date>1990</date>. <title level="m">Aspects of Language Teaching</title>. Oxford:
                  Oxford University Press.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
