<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-cc-ra-mylonas-202-source.xml 1158 2023-01-31 08:46:51Z ron $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI.internal">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Archiving a TEI Project FAIRly</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Andrew</forename>
            <surname>Creamer</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Andrew Creamer is the <roleName>scientific data management
              librarian</roleName> in the <orgName>Brown University Library</orgName>. He assists
            faculty and student researchers with documenting their methods, describing their data,
            and providing the public and other researchers with long-term access to their research
            products via deposit in online repositories, including the Brown Digital Repository
            (BDR). Andrew also currently serves as an informationist for Brown’s Superfund Center
            Community Engagement Core on a NIEHS-funded project focused on making the Center’s
            research products more FAIR and enhancing their discovery, access, reuse, and citation.
              <lb/><ptr target="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5286"/></affiliation>
          <email>andrew_creamer@brown.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Gaia</forename>
            <surname>Lembi</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Gaia Lembi was a <roleName>visiting assistant professor</roleName> of Judaic
            Studies at <orgName>Brown University</orgName> and project manager for the Inscriptions
            of Israel/Palestine from 1995 to 2020. <lb/><ptr
              target="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8962"/></affiliation>
          <email>gaialembi@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Elli</forename>
            <surname>Mylonas</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Elli Mylonas works in the Center for Digital Scholarship in the
              <orgName>Brown University Library</orgName>. She is the technical manager of the
            Inscriptions of Israel/Palestine and is also part of the US Epigraphy project. Her
            experience with SGML, XML, and TEI is longstanding; she is currently a member of the
            EpiDoc maintenance group and has served several terms on the TEI Council. Mylonas was
            the managing editor of the Perseus Project when it first began, and has worked on many
            digital humanities and digital scholarship projects since then. Her background is in
            classics. <lb/><ptr target="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0215"/>
          </affiliation>
          <email>elli_mylonas@brown.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Michael</forename>
            <surname>Satlow</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Michael Satlow is <roleName>professor of Judaic studies and religious
              studies</roleName> at <orgName>Brown University</orgName>. He is the principal
            investigator of the Inscriptions of Israel/Palestine Project. He specializes in the
            history of Jews and Judaism in antiquity but also writes and teaches more broadly,
            including in digital humanities. Among other grants and fellowships, Satlow has been
            awarded a Humanities Open Book grant from the Mellon Foundation to digitize fifty
            volumes from the Brown Judaic Studies series and make them open access. <lb/><ptr
              target="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7692"/>
          </affiliation>
          <email>michael_satlow@brown.edu</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>08/12/2022</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Georg Vogeler</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="14">Selected Papers from the 2019 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals
          in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish
          full-text articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="head">font-weight:bold;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>FAIR</term>
          <term>digital epigraphy</term>
          <term>EpiDoc</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="RvdB" when="2022-12-11">Updated encoding to final Word file.</change>
      <change who="RvdB" when="2022-11-30">Initial encoding</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>The Inscriptions of Israel/Palestine project is an online corpus of over four thousand
          inscriptions from Israel and Palestine, written in Hebrew, Greek, Latin, and Aramaic,
          dating roughly from the Persian Period to the Arab Conquest. The source files with
          inscription text and metadata are encoded using EpiDoc, a TEI customization widely used by
          epigraphers. As the project prepared to deposit its XML files in an institutional
          repository, it transformed them into a locally developed robust archival format. This
          paper evaluates these decisions against the FAIR metrics, using IIP as a test case. This
          allows us to suggest improvements for our own archival encoding as well as to see where
          EpiDoc and TEI enhance FAIRness and where they could provide more support. Finally, we
          suggest some ways to use FAIR metrics that are more amenable to TEI documents and
          corpora.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="introduction">
        <head>Introduction to IIP, history and motivation, principles</head>
        <p>The Inscriptions of Israel/Palestine project (IIP) collects and transcribes inscriptions
          from Israel/Palestine, dating roughly from the Persian period through the Islamic
          conquest, and makes them discoverable and browsable on the web. There are about ten
          thousand relevant texts, written in Hebrew, Aramaic, Greek, and Latin, by Jews,
          Christians, Greeks, and Romans. Their number and variety provide a fascinating window into
          the ancient world. Despite their importance for historical and linguistic investigation,
          these inscriptions have been published for the most part individually or in small corpora;
          IIP provides an accessible platform for searching and analyzing them all together.</p>
        <p>Currently, the project contains over four thousand inscriptions, which are available as a
            <ref target="http://library.brown.edu/iip">searchable online corpus</ref>, via an <ref
            target="https://library.brown.edu/iip/about/api/">API</ref>, and in the <ref
            target="https://github.com/Brown-University-Library/iip-texts/tree/master/epidoc-files"
            >IIP GitHub repository</ref>.<note>IIP website and search interface:
                <bibl><author>Michael L. Satlow</author>, <title level="u">Inscriptions of
                Israel/Palestine</title>, 2002– , accessed July 3, 2022, <ptr
                target="http://library.brown.edu/iip"/>.</bibl> Brown Digital Repository API
            documentation with examples: accessed July 3, 2022, <ptr
              target="https://library.brown.edu/iip/about/api/"/>. IIP texts in GitHub: accessed
            July 3, 2022, <ptr
              target="https://github.com/Brown-University-Library/iip-texts/tree/master/epidoc-files"
            />.</note> The project team is continuing to add to the corpus, and at the same time
          developing new functionalities for the website and experimenting with interfaces for
          different audiences. The project is focusing its new developments on the inscription text
          and, in particular, using NLP for lemmatization and other lexical features.</p>
        <p>The epigraphic texts in IIP have been extensively marked up using the EpiDoc schema (<ref
            type="bibl" target="#elliott2021">Elliott et al. 2021</ref>). As with many other digital
          corpora, IIP simultaneously balances two criteria: inscriptions must be encoded so as to
          facilitate specific online presentations, interfaces, and interactivity, and must at the
          same time use data structures and descriptors that result in a sustainable epigraphic
          archive that will last across presentation formats and can be used for different purposes.
          Our digital corpus thus adds value, not just by allowing for accessibility but also by
          adding contextual and linguistic information and interoperability with similar digital
          projects that use EpiDoc and other structured formats.</p>
        <p>For example, IIP disambiguates geographic names and dates in the edition texts by linking
          to external authorities using linked open data (LOD) Uniform Resource Identifiers (URIs).
          Geographic locations refer to the Pleiades gazetteer (<ref type="bibl" target="#bagnall"
            >Bagnall et al. 2006–</ref>). Working with Pleiades was mutually beneficial: as we
          linked our material to the Gazetteer, we also contributed new places to it. IIP relies on
          Periodo (<ref type="bibl" target="#rabinowitz">Rabinowitz, Shaw, et al., n.d.</ref>) to
          enrich dating information, linking temporal information to existing periods. The
          incorporation of LOD references into IIP metadata provides functionality beyond
          disambiguation: IIP data can now be aggregated with any other data set that uses the same
          linked-data URIs to express time and location.</p>
        <p>Although the epigraphic community is working on developing ontologies and authority lists
          for metadata, these are not yet standardized. IIP adds links to the Getty Art &amp;
          Architecture Thesaurus (AAT) (<ref type="bibl" target="#getty">Getty Research Institute,
            n.d.</ref>) to object types, but implements project-level authority lists for genres and
          materials. This makes encoding much easier and less prone to error, as it provides
          encoders with values to choose from. The closed list of values also enables faceted
          searching and makes adding a new value a more considered decision.</p>
        <p>IIP is constantly in motion, with new inscriptions being added and others corrected. As
          such, the project team recently began to assess the strategy and workflow necessary for
          data preservation. IIP data is routinely made accessible on GitHub and from the project
          website, via an API, but still requires a more sustainable and secure solution. The first
          choice for preservation is a local one, using the <ref
            target="https://repository.library.brown.edu/">Brown Digital Repository</ref>
            (BDR).<note>Accessed July 3, 2022, <ptr target="https://repository.library.brown.edu/"
            />.</note> In order to store robust, reusable resources in the BDR, we developed an
          archival format for the inscriptions that ensured each file was self-documenting and did
          not refer to locally maintained external files. A major challenge was incorporating full
          bibliographical information, which is stored in Zotero. It was also necessary to add
          documentation about accessibility in the TEI Header and include essential metadata such as
          the principal investigator and contributors (with ORCID [Open Researcher and Contributor
          ID] persistent identifiers when available); rights statements; edition information;
          information on how to cite the inscription; and snapshots of internal authority lists for
          any references in the file.<note>The first edition of deposited files with archival
            headers, last updated June 2019, can be viewed at <ptr
              target="https://repository.library.brown.edu/studio/collections/id_904/"/>.</note>
          External LOD references linked via URIs remain in the files.</p>
        <p>As part of the archival process, a Digital Object Identifier (DOI) was minted using the
          DataCite Registration Agency (RA) for the Inscriptions of Israel/Palestine project, which
          resolves to the project home page. At the moment that is the only DOI; there is no
          separate DOI for IIP data or individual inscriptions. We discuss below how we might better
          use DOI identification.</p>
        <p>This paper evaluates the strategy and workflow for archiving a living and connected
          corpus. We begin with IIP as the test case, and, as it is encoded in these formats, can
          extend our results to the EpiDoc and TEI Guidelines and schemas. We have sought to adhere
          to the principles of FAIR, making our inscriptions <emph>findable</emph>,
            <emph>accessible</emph>, <emph>interoperable</emph>, and <emph>re-usable</emph>. We will
          document how the IIP project has attempted to adhere to these goals and the challenges
          that we still confront.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="FAIR">
        <head>FAIR Principles and FAIR Metrics</head>
        <p>The seed of the term <soCalled>FAIR</soCalled> was originally planted in 2014 during a
          workshop in Leiden, the Netherlands, in which the participants produced a set of guiding
          principles and practices for helping to ensure the long-term discovery, access, and reuse
          of metadata and data by machines and people (<ref type="bibl" target="#wilkinson2016"
            >Wilkinson et al. 2016, 3</ref>). Members of the FORCE11 community formed a working
          group to continue work on these principles and develop attribution practices that are both
            <quote source="#quoteref1">human understandable and machine-actionable</quote> (<ref
            xml:id="quoteref1" type="bibl" target="#dsg2014">Data Citation Synthesis Group
            2014</ref>). Wilkinson et al. (<ref type="bibl" target="#wilkinson2016">2016</ref>)
          published the FAIR Principles with the aim of ensuring that curators of digital
          objects—that is, <soCalled>(meta)data</soCalled> and their systems and practices for
          storing, formatting, describing, and dissemination—would be guided towards making them
            <soCalled>machine-actionable</soCalled>: <quote source="#quoteref2">enhancing the
            ability of machines to automatically find and use the data, in addition to supporting
            its reuse by individuals</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref2" type="bibl"
            target="#wilkinson2016">Wilkinson et al. 2016, 1</ref>).</p>
        <p>According to the FAIR Principles, to be <term>findable</term>, digital objects
            <soCalled>meta(data)</soCalled> should be assigned globally unique and persistent
          identifiers, be described with metadata that capture the aforementioned identifier, and be
          indexed in a searchable resource. <term>Accessibility</term> is framed around the
          retrievability of metadata via open protocols, allowing for authentication and
          authorization (with the proviso that metadata should in all cases be accessible even in
          cases when the object they describe no longer is). The principles comprising
            <term>interoperability</term> focus on the utilization of standard programming
          languages, controlled vocabularies, and authoritative references. Lastly,
            <term>reusability</term> of digital objects relies on the capture of provenance and
          rights information, with these metadata formatted to a community/domain standard,
          necessary to provide potential users with the ability to both research veracity and
          provide attribution.</p>
        <p>The European Union (EU) has been active in funding both infrastructure and initiatives
          that align with the FAIR Principles, as well as metrics for assessing their
          implementation. Notably, in 2016 the European Commission (EC) called for the establishment
          of what would become the European Open Science Cloud (EOSC). The following year the EC
          established its Expert Group on FAIR Data. In 2018 the group published its report <title
            level="a">Turning FAIR into Reality</title> (<ref type="bibl" target="#EC2018">European
            Commission, Directorate-General for Research and Innovation 2018</ref>), which laid out
          an action plan that included <soCalled>embedded and sustained metrics</soCalled>. That
          same year, the EU’s Research and Innovation program Horizon 2020 funded a project called
          FAIRsFAIR: Fostering FAIR Data Practices in Europe (<ref type="bibl" target="#fairsfair"
            >FAIRsFAIR, n.d.</ref>). The UK and EU partners collaborating on the project will
          develop standards for FAIRsFAIR certification of repositories that will inform the Rules
          of Participation (RoP) and regulatory compliance for participation in the EOSC, which the
          EOSC governance structure will use <quote source="#quoteref3">to establish whether
            components of the infrastructure function in a FAIR manner</quote> (<ref
            xml:id="quoteref3" type="bibl" target="#EC2016">European Commission, Directorate-General
            for Research and Innovation 2016</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#EC2018">2018</ref>).
          In the United States, the embrace of FAIR by federal funders of scientific research is
          notable, particularly its inclusion in the text of recent funding opportunities
          announcements from the Department of Energy (DOE) and within the most recent strategic
          plan of the National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (NIEHS), one of the
          National Institutes of Health (NIH).</p>
        <p>The EU, UK, and US examples above may give the false impression that FAIR did not have an
          impact on researchers in the humanities and social sciences. On the contrary, since their
          debut the FAIR Principles have provided different domains and communities interested in
          the curation, dissemination, and preservation of knowledge in the form of digital objects
          with a framework in which to situate their systems and practices, and to assess their
          projects through the lens of FAIR. This resulted in many of these projects drafting
            <soCalled>roadmaps</soCalled> intended to align their projects with meeting certain
          markers with the context of FAIR Principles. In addition, the invocation of FAIR as an
          adjective to represent a project’s inclusion of FAIRness among their goals has extended
          beyond the guidelines’ emphasis on machines to now equally describe researchers’ data
          handling practices. For example, in their proposal for a Cross-Linguistic Data Formats
          Initiative, Forkel et al. (<ref xml:id="quoteref4" type="bibl" target="#forkel2018">2018,
            2</ref>) describe the current data sharing and reuse practices of researchers in their
          field of linguistics as being <quote source="#quoteref4">far away from being
              <soCalled>FAIR</soCalled></quote>.</p>
        <p>The publication of the FAIR Principles provided a lens through which scholarly
          communities can view their domain-specific data stewardship practices as well as the
          stewardship of other types of digital objects such as software (<ref type="bibl"
            target="#lamprecht2020">Lamprecht et al. 2020</ref>). For example, Koster and
          Woutersen-Windhouwer use the FAIR Principles as the foundation for creating their <title
            level="a">FAIR Principles for Library, Archive and Museum (LAM) Collections</title>
            (<ref type="bibl" target="#koster2018">Koster and Woutersen-Windhouwer 2018</ref>). The
          authors translate the broad FAIR principles into ones that specify identifiers, standards,
          rights, and provenance practices recognized as best practices within LAM communities. They
          suggest a <soCalled>roadmap</soCalled> for LAMs to achieve the goal of
            <soCalled>FAIRness</soCalled>. While at that time they did not go as far as defining the
          metrics for assessing the degree of a collection’s FAIRness, their roadmap leaves open the
          possibility for this by recommending LAMs create working groups to study their
          collections’ alignment with the FAIR principles and develop a FAIR policy and
          implementation plan. Other scholarly communities similarly moved from using the Principles
          as guide to using them as a tool for assessing the FAIRness of their systems and practices
          for describing and disseminating digital objects in their field. For example, Calamai and
          Frontini (<ref type="bibl" target="#calamai2018">2018</ref>) relied on the FAIR Principles
          as a frame for assessing the strengths and weaknesses of the speech and oral archives and
          scholarly practices in their field. Lastly, there have also been movements to extend FAIR
          and develop complementary principles such as the CARE Principles for Indigenous Data
          Governance, whose hashtag is <code>#BeFAIRandCARE</code>. The CARE Principles ask stewards
          and data ecosystems to take into account <term>collective benefit</term>, <term>authority
            to control</term>, <term>responsibility</term>, and <term>ethics</term> in their
          governance of Indigenous data (<ref type="bibl" target="#gida">Global Indigenous Data
            Alliance, n.d.</ref>).</p>
        <p>The authors of the original 2016 FAIR Principles quickly became aware of these scholarly
          communities’ needs to translate the FAIR Principles into some type of metric to assess
          their projects, infrastructure, and practices and measure their progress towards achieving
          FAIRness: <cit>
            <quote source="#quoteref5">The Principles are aspirational, in that they do not strictly
              define how to achieve a state of <soCalled>FAIRness</soCalled>, but rather they
              describe a continuum of features, attributes, and behaviors that will move a digital
              resource closer to that goal. This ambiguity has led to a wide range of
              interpretations of FAIRness, with some resources even claiming to already <soCalled>be
                FAIR</soCalled>! The increasing number of such statements, the emergence of
              subjective and self-assessments of FAIRness, and the need of data and service
              providers, journals, funding agencies, and regulatory bodies to qualitatively or
              quantitatively evaluate such claims, led us to self-assemble and establish a FAIR
              Metrics group to pursue the goal of defining ways to measure FAIRness.</quote>
            <ref xml:id="quoteref5" type="bibl" target="#wilkinson2018">Wilkinson et al. 2018,
              1</ref>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p>After drafting its initial universal metrics, the FAIR Metrics working group quickly
          recognized that what is considered FAIR in one community may be quite different in another
          community (<ref type="bibl" target="#wilkinson2018">Wilkinson et al. 2018, 1</ref>). Thus,
          the working group accounted for this in allowing for a workflow for their universal
          metrics to be supplemented by domain- and community-specific metrics, including creating a
          template and GitHub repository for these communities to build upon and create their own
          metrics as well as the infrastructure for communities to contribute their metrics back to
          the open repository.</p>
        <p>The creation of metrics by the working group has generated an opportunity for individual
          projects to now measure their FAIRness against a core set of universal metrics. For
          example, van Erp et al. were among the first to publish their use of the metrics to assess
          three open-source data catalogs: CKAN, Dataverse, and Invenio (<ref type="bibl"
            target="#erp2018">van Erp et al. 2018</ref>). There is also now an opportunity for
          specific domains, such as the larger epigraphy community, to further develop and
          contribute back a set of community-specific FAIRness metrics.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="IIPFAIR">
        <head>IIP and FAIR Principles</head>
        <p>When IIP originally started to incorporate linked open data URIs and to settle upon a
          robust archival format, the IIP team was not yet aware of the FAIR principles or FAIR
          metrics. We would now like to apply the FAIR metrics to the IIP archival format, which is
          based on practices and requirements that are particular to the epigraphic and the
          EpiDoc/TEI community. In the process, we can lay the groundwork for using metadata that
          are in the <gi>teiHeader</gi> to express the FAIR principles in a measurable way.</p>
        <p>In 2016, when the Epigraphische Datenbank Heidelberg was threatened with having its
          funding withdrawn, Francisca Feraudi-Gruénais and Frank Grieshaber sent out a warning and
          call to action (<ref type="bibl" target="#feraudi2016">Feraudi-Gruénais and Grieshaber
            2016</ref>). This resulted in the formation of <ref target="https://epigraphy.info/"
            >Epigraphy.info</ref>,<note>Accessed July 31, 2019, <ptr
              target="https://epigraphy.info/"/>.</note> a community working to develop sustainable
          digital epigraphic practices in order to make sure that epigraphic research corpora are
          more broadly supported. Epigraphy.info recognizes the significance of the FAIR principles
          as a way to ensure the survival of these research corpora. The principles help by
          extending traditional editorial conventions, canonical reference systems, and vocabularies
          and making them more broadly applicable, as well as by allowing for extensibility and
          growth. Encouraged by their embrace of FAIR, and bolstered by our efforts to generate an
          archival format for the IIP inscriptions, we will evaluate IIP encoding practices against
          the FAIR metrics, and extend our results to EpiDoc and TEI documents more generally.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="measuringFAIR">
        <head>Measuring FAIRness in IIP and EpiDoc</head>
        <p>The template developed by Wilkinson et al. to document each FAIR metric is intended to be
          generally applicable across disciplines. Communities can work with the same template to
          describe the metrics in ways that are best applicable to their own data and practices. The
          template asks for the following nine pieces of information. Each field serves a different
          role: 1–2 and 9 identify, 3–5 provide rationale for measurement, and 6–8 describe how to
          measure each principle (<ref type="bibl" target="#wilkinson2018">Wilkinson et al. 2018,
            2</ref>). <list rend="ordered">
            <item>Metric identifier.</item>
            <item>Metric name identifier.</item>
            <item>To which principle does it apply?</item>
            <item>What is being measured?</item>
            <item>Why should we measure it?</item>
            <item>What must be provided?</item>
            <item>How do we measure it?</item>
            <item>What is a valid result?</item>
            <item>For which digital resource(s) is this relevant?</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>We will evaluate each metric to learn how well it measures FAIRness in IIP documents, and
          by extension, in EpiDoc and TEI. We assume at the outset that the IIP documents are valid
          with respect to the EpiDoc schema, adhere to the EpiDoc encoding guidelines, and use a
            <gi>teiHeader</gi> to encode metadata as recommended by the TEI Guidelines. The
          discussion below is based on these best practices and on the work we did to create
          archival versions of the working IIP documents; to apply the same metrics to other EpiDoc
          and TEI documents, they should also be valid according to the TEI schema and provide
          similar rich metadata. <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">Findable</hi>
        </p>
        <p>The first five metrics evaluate the findability of resources. They focus on metadata and
          identifiers. An important and unique characteristic of TEI and EpiDoc files that affects
          these metrics is that data and metadata are usually part of the same document, and often
          in the same file. This removes the need to relate metadata records to data files, but also
          means that metadata alone are less visible. <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">FM-F1A: Identifier uniqueness</hi>
          <lb/> [<ptr
            target="https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics/blob/master/Distributions/FM_F1A.pdf"/>] </p>
        <p>This metric measures whether a resource’s identifier is unique and described by a known
          identifier scheme. The IIP project partially meets this metric because it has a DOI that
          points to the project website and stands in for all the parts of the project. It would be
          more informative if there were an additional DOI either for the set of encoded archival
          source files, or for each individual document, as is the case for many scientific
          publications. The <ref target="https://isicily.org/">I.Sicily</ref> project,<note>Accessed
            September, 2022 <ptr target="https://isicily.org/"/>.</note> which is collecting the
          complete corpus of inscriptions from ancient Sicily, mints a Zenodo DOI for each
          inscription in the corpus. As IIP inscriptions each have an identifier in the form
            <code>\w{4}\d{4}\w?</code> that is unique within the project, DOI suffixes would ideally
          incorporate this information together with a reference to the IIP corpus.<note>The digital
            journal <title level="j">British Art Studies</title> (accessed July 3, 2022, <ptr
              target="http://britishartstudies.ac.uk/"/>) assigns DOIs to each page in an article,
            and generates them in a form that functions as a human-readable citation as well as a
            machine-readable identifier. An example is <bibl><author>Kelvin Chuah</author>, <title
                level="a">Instant Malaysia: Imagining a Nation at the Commonwealth
              Institute</title>, <title level="j">British Art Studies</title>, <biblScope
                unit="issue">no. 13</biblScope> (Sept. 2019): 4, <ptr
                target="https://doi.org/10.17658/issn.2058-5462/issue-14/kfein/p4"/></bibl>.</note>
          Using such an identifier scheme, an inscription could be referenced individually, outside
          the context of IIP, and at the same time be identifiable as belonging to the IIP corpus.
          The accuracy of a document-level DOI could also be checked against the IIP ID, which is
          encoded as an <gi>idno</gi> in the <gi>publicationStmt</gi>. Currently, the project-level
          DOI is referenced in the <gi>licence</gi> element of the document metadata.</p>
        <p>We recommend assigning a DOI to each document, and encoding it using a second
            <gi>idno</gi> with the attribute <att>type</att>=<val>DOI</val>.</p>
        <p>As the IIP documents are stored in an institutional repository, each file also has a
          persistent identifier (PID) provided by the repository in the form of a URI. The PID is
          not currently referenced in the IIP header metadata, but like the project ID, it can be
          encoded with <tag>idno type=&quot;BDR&quot;</tag>. Some projects have developed workflows
          that incorporate a repository-generated DOI back into the file, as the file is being
          deposited into a repository like Zenodo (<ref type="bibl" target="#prag2020">Prag
            2020</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#wagner">Wagner, n.d.</ref>). There may be other
          types of files beyond the epigraphic documents that should have unique identifiers: for
          example, local authority lists if they are external to the documents, or XSL scripts that
          can be used to process the files. <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">FM-F1B: Identifier persistence</hi>
          <lb/> [<ptr
            target="https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics/blob/master/Distributions/FM_F1B.pdf"/>] </p>
        <p>This metric addresses the universal problem of identifier persistence and how changing a
          URI might affect the findability of a resource. The FAIR metrics test for a policy that
          sets out how changes in identifier should be handled. If, as described above, there is a
          DOI for the data set as a whole or each of the individual documents in the corpus, then
          the DOI system itself provides the most secure form of persistence. <quote
            source="#quoteref6">The system provides a means to continue interoperability through
            exchange of meaningful information about identified entities through at minimum
            persistence of the DOI name and a description of the referent</quote> (<ref type="bibl"
            target="#paskin2009" xml:id="quoteref6">Paskin 2009, 1591</ref>). In the case of IIP,
          this information is available at <ptr
            target="https://search.datacite.org/works/10.26300/pz1d-st89"/>. <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">FM-F2: Machine-readability of metadata</hi>
          <lb/> [<ptr
            target="https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics/blob/master/Distributions/FM_F2.pdf"/>] </p>
        <p>This metric tests whether machine-readable metadata exist for the document in a format
          that will increase its findability. The metric is written assuming that the metadata
          record that is being tested is part of a metadata registry or can be discovered by a web
          search engine independently from the rest of the document. The FAIR principle for this
          metric is met by TEI (and therefore EpiDoc and IIP) documents, as they contain
          predictable, machine-readable metadata in the <gi>teiHeader</gi>. The namespace
          declaration identifies TEI as the data format. Within the TEI header, the
            <gi>fileDesc</gi> provides machine-actionable information about the digital object, the
            <gi>sourceDesc</gi> contains information about the object being encoded, the
            <gi>publicationStmt</gi> provides responsibility and licensing information, and the
            <gi>encodingDesc</gi> holds information about the project and its encoding
          practices.</p>
        <p>This metric exposes an important characteristic of TEI documents which is demonstrated by
          the IIP archival format. Document metadata is closely tied to document data, often in a
          single file. It is machine-readable, but not necessarily available to search engines and
          indexes. And there is no central TEI-aware registry which would allow it to be easily
          located or natively indexed. FAIR discussions tend to draw on data from the life sciences,
          where there are more metadata registries and where metadata is created and resides
          separately from research data. IIP inscriptions are available to view on the web, but
          their source XML is less easily findable.</p>
        <p>For TEI and EpiDoc, this metric could be better aligned with community practice if it
          were used to test for the existence of structured information in the <gi>teiHeader</gi>
          and for a namespace declaration. This information could also be exposed in a more general
          format in a registry or on the web. An EpiDoc-aware disciplinary registry can ingest TEI
          metadata directly and expose it to the web. The role and need for a discipline-specific
          registry will come up again in the following discussion. <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">FM-F3: Metadata clearly and explicitly include the identifier of the
            data they describe</hi>
          <lb/> [<ptr
            target="https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics/blob/master/Distributions/FM_F3.pdf"/>] </p>
        <p>IIP, following the EpiDoc and TEI Guidelines, encodes the project identifier for a
          document in the <gi>idno</gi> element in the <gi>teiHeader</gi>, which seems to fulfill
          this metric. The FAIR metrics specify that the identifier take the form of a
            GUID<note>Globally Unique Identifier or Universally Unique Identifier: see Leach,
            Mealling, and Salz (<ref type="bibl" target="#leach2005">2005</ref>).</note> so the
          unique string can be searched in a document or on the web, and can be used to pair data
          and metadata files. For epigraphic corpora which often have well-developed identifier
          schemes, it is more relevant to modify the metric and recommend that each document have an
          ID that is unique within the project and to encode it in the <gi>idno</gi> element with an
          appropriate <att>type</att> attribute. A more robust scheme that includes a project ID
          could be developed and documented by the larger community of digital epigraphy projects.
          It is interesting to note that the GUID, which is for all practical purposes unique,
          together with a web search engine, can play the same role as a registry. <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">FM-F4: (Meta)data are registered or indexed in a searchable
            resource</hi>
          <lb/> [<ptr
            target="https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics/blob/master/Distributions/FM_F4.pdf"/>] </p>
        <p>This metric tests whether it is possible to find a document on the web using a search
          engine. In order for this to work, a metadata record, or—in the case of IIP or other
          EpiDoc documents—the file that contains the data and metadata, must be indexed by a search
          engine. The IIP corpus fails this test even though the documents contain metadata and
          identifiable IDs, because they are always accessed via a web application or from the
          institutional repository and therefore neither their unique IDs nor the PIDs assigned by
          the repository are indexed by web search engines. One solution is to allow the source
          files to be crawled, especially if they have unique identifiers, or to deposit them in a
          repository that exposes permanent identifiers and other metadata. Identifiers would also
          be findable if projects were encouraged to include identifiers in their web applications
          so they could be crawled and indexed whether they are recognized as identifiers or not. To
          make IIP resources more findable, we will work with our institutional repository to expose
          more EpiDoc metadata and identifiers for indexing. <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">Accessibility</hi>
        </p>
        <p>The second set of metrics focuses on accessibility, testing for the use of open protocols
          and permissions. <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">FM-A1.1: The protocol is open, free, and universally
            implementable</hi>
          <lb/> [<ptr
            target="https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics/blob/master/Distributions/FM_A1.1.pdf"/>] <lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">FM-A1.2: The protocol allows for authentication and authorization
            where necessary</hi>
          <lb/> [<ptr
            target="https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics/blob/master/Distributions/FM_A1.2.pdf"
          />]</p>
        <p>The first two accessibility metrics can be treated together. IIP documents meet the first
          metric because they have no access restrictions and are accessible via HTTP, an open and
          well-documented protocol. Most epigraphic projects using EpiDoc provide their source data
          freely via HTTP. If a project’s documents are not openly available, the second metric
          tests to see if the procedure for getting access is documented and if it works. Even in
          the case of openly available TEI and EpiDoc documents, this information should be
          specified in the <gi>availability</gi> and <gi>licence</gi> elements in the
            <gi>publicationStmt</gi>. In order for this information to be available, however, the
          document’s metadata need to be exposed, or available in an index, catalog, or registry. <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">FM-A2: Metadata should be accessible even when the data are no
            longer available</hi>
          <lb/> [<ptr
            target="https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics/blob/master/Distributions/FM_A2.pdf"/>] </p>
        <p>This metric is one that most corpora encoded using EpiDoc and TEI cannot easily meet.
          Currently, they maintain very rich technical and descriptive metadata in the
            <gi>teiHeader</gi>, which is part of the document, but there is no default, independent
          location that holds only metadata. If a corpus or document has a DOI, which in the case of
          IIP points to the project website, the DOI registry contains minimal, but persistent,
          metadata about the resource. This may prove that the document existed at one time and
          provide a hint about the contents, but is not otherwise very informative. This metric
          might be recast to make it more applicable to accessibility and persistence for TEI
          documents. For example, if one source of an inscription becomes unavailable, the conjoined
          TEI/EpiDoc metadata and data could continue to live by deposit in multiple places
          (LOCKSS). <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">Interoperability</hi>
        </p>
        <p>The interoperability and reuse principles and associated metrics try to determine if,
          once retrieved, the data and metadata formats of a document are documented so they can be
          understood, and if the specifications on which they draw are themselves FAIR. Overall, IIP
          and other EpiDoc and TEI documents are fairly well positioned. The area that needs the
          most attention is not so much the encoded documents and corpora but rather the
          machine-verifiable FAIRness of the guidelines, schemas, and authorities on which they
          draw. <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">FM-I1: (Meta)data use a formal, accessible, shared, and broadly
            applicable language for knowledge representation</hi>
          <lb/> [<ptr
            target="https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics/blob/master/Distributions/FM_I1.pdf"/>] </p>
        <p>TEI and EpiDoc are XML schemas, so by extension, IIP files are expressed in XML. XML is
          an open standard, with a formal definition and an IANA (Internet Assigned Numbers
          Authority) media type. In addition, the TEI and EpiDoc schemas are written in ODD (One
          Document Does it all), a formal specification which is itself a TEI XML document that
          serves to link schema and documentation together (<ref type="bibl" target="#tei2020">TEI
            Consortium 2020</ref>). There are two ways to point to the ODD in a TEI file: in the
            <gi>encodingDesc</gi> or in the <tag type="pi">xml-model</tag> processing instruction.
          The former is preferable because its presence can be ascertained using an XPath
          expression. IIP, as an EpiDoc project, should refer to the EpiDoc ODD in header metadata,
          but it currently does not include this information. Also, because the project strives to
          validate against the current EpiDoc schema in its day-to-day work, no EpiDoc version
          number is specified. In order to fulfill this metric, the IIP archival format should
          include this information in the <gi>encodingDesc</gi>. <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">FM-I2: (Meta)data use vocabularies that follow the FAIR
            principles</hi>
          <lb/> [<ptr
            target="https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics/blob/master/Distributions/FM_I2.pdf"/>] <lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">FM-I3: (Meta)data include qualified references to other
            (meta)data</hi>
          <lb/> [<ptr
            target="https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics/blob/master/Distributions/FM_I3.pdf"/>] </p>
        <p>The second and third interoperability metrics test for the use of well-defined and
          documented vocabularies, linked in semantically informative ways. They also recommend that
          linked data should point as often as possible to authorities that are external to the
          document or project. The IIP project links to public, documented, and stable authorities
          wherever possible. Geographic locations are linked to the Pleiades geographical gazetteer
            (<ref type="bibl" target="#bagnall">Bagnall et al. 2006–</ref>), dates are linked to the
          PeriodO gazetteer of historical periods (<ref type="bibl" target="#rabinowitz">Rabinowitz,
            Shaw, et al., n.d.</ref>), and object types are disambiguated using links to the Getty
          Art and Architecture Thesaurus (<ref type="bibl" target="#getty">Getty Research Institute,
            n.d.</ref>). Overall, IIP fulfills the criteria for interoperable and external
          vocabularies. However, these links are not explicitly qualified as specified in FM-I3. For
          example, the relationships are not expressed in RDF (Resource Description Framework), and
          so can only implicitly represent an identity relationship. Future enhancements to IIP
          metadata should take this into account. We will also be guided by the ongoing discussions
          around incorporating RDFa into TEI data and metadata. A positive sign is that the project
          was able to use metadata present in the TEI header to generate RDF triples in order to
          incorporate IIP into the <ref target="https://pelagios.org/">Pelagios
            Network</ref>.<note>Pelagios network: accessed July 4, 2022, <ptr
              target="https://pelagios.org/"/>. IIP RDF data: Brown University Library GitHub
            repository, accessed July 4, 2022, <ptr
              target="https://github.com/Brown-University-Library/iip-texts/blob/master/pelagios/iip-pelagios.ttl"
            />.</note> Epigraphy.info has also published an official draft of <title level="u"
            >Modeling Epigraphy with an Ontology</title> which outlines how to use existing
          ontologies such as <ref target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/">CIDOC-CRM</ref>, <ref
            target="http://nomisma.org/">Nomisma</ref>, and <ref
            target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/crmtex/home-8">CRMtex</ref><note>CIDOC (International
            Committee for Documentation) Conceptual <ptr type="software" xml:id="Reference"
              target="#Reference"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#Reference">Reference</rs> Model,
            accessed July 4, 2022, <ptr target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/"/>; Nomisma (knowledge
            organization system for numismatics), accessed July 4, 2022, <ptr
              target="http://nomisma.org/"/>; CRMtex model for the study of ancient texts (an
            extension of CIDOC-CRM), accessed July 4, 2022, <ptr
              target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/crmtex/home-8"/>.</note> to describe inscribed
          objects (<ref type="bibl" target="#bodard2021">Bodard et al. 2021</ref>). <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">Reuse</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Projects and documents that are encoded in TEI are generally well set up for both
          interoperability and reuse, as these were two goals of the TEI from its very beginnings.
          The <gi>teiHeader</gi> allows for including a license and providing provenance information
          both for source material, in the <gi>sourceDesc</gi>, and for the electronic document, in
            <gi>fileDesc</gi>. The existence of these elements can be tested using XPath
          expressions. <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">FM-R1.1: (Meta)data are released with a clear and accessible data
            usage license</hi>
          <lb/> [<ptr
            target="https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics/blob/master/Distributions/FM_R1.1.pdf"/>] </p>
        <p>This test is fulfilled together with FM-A1.2, and can be tested by an XPath statement
          that resolves to the <gi>licence</gi> element in the <gi>publicationStmt</gi>. IIP
          documents use a CC BY-NC 4.0 license. <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">FM-R1.2: (Meta)data are associated with detailed provenance</hi>
          <lb/> [<ptr
            target="https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics/blob/master/Distributions/FM_R1.2.pdf"/>] </p>
        <p>In the IIP archival format, both data and metadata have detailed, machine-readable
          provenance information. Authorship or responsibility for the data is available in the
            <gi>publicationStmt</gi>; proper citation information is provided in the
            <gi>availability</gi> element in the <gi>publicationStmt</gi>; and information about how
          and why the data or document was produced is encoded in the <gi>projectDesc</gi> and the
            <gi>encodingDesc</gi>, all of which are prescribed by the EpiDoc and based on TEI. In
          addition, the <soCalled>how</soCalled> question is partially answered in XML by the
          reference in the namespace declaration and in TEI by the <gi>schemaRef</gi> element.
          Currently the TEI namespace declaration does not point to any further information about
          TEI. This metric would be even more adequately met if the link to the TEI namespace
          declaration also yielded pathways to viewing the TEI Guidelines and schema. <lb/><lb/>
          <hi rendition="#head">FM-R1.3: (Meta)data meet domain-relevant community standards</hi>
          <lb/> [<ptr
            target="https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics/blob/master/Distributions/FM_R1.3.pdf"/>] </p>
        <p>IIP meets this last metric in principle through its adoption of EpiDoc, which has been
          developed by the epigraphic community for digital epigraphic corpora. However, the FAIR
          metrics look for a form of machine-verifiable certification that a document or dataset
          meets some minimum requirements with respect to metadata and formats. This is not only not
          available in the TEI context, it has also been rejected as a concept, as there is no
          governing body which might provide the certification, and in fact the Guidelines are, as
          indicated in their name, not a standard. However, if the TEI consortium and its members
          recommend how to fulfill the FAIR principles by using the <gi>teiHeader</gi> as discussed
          for each metric above, and provide <ptr type="software" xml:id="XSLT" target="#XSLT"/><rs
            type="soft.name" ref="#XSLT">XSLT</rs> and Schematron files for validation, the output
          of that file could indicate compliance. As always, it is the responsibility of the encoder
          and project to make sure that the metadata are accurate and detailed.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="conclusion">
        <head>Conclusion and Future Work</head>
        <p>We have described the modifications necessary in order to generate a more sustainable,
          archival form of the IIP corpus, and then evaluated them against the FAIR metrics. More
          modifications to the IIP archival format are necessary, such as minting DOIs for each
          document and adding the BDR PIDs into the <gi>teiHeader</gi> metadata. We have shown that
          the TEI header can provide much of the information required by the FAIR principles in a
          predictable and machine-readable form. Specifically, the TEI Guidelines and schema
          indicate where and how to encode licensing information, metadata formats, documentation,
          and identifiers and their presence can be verified using <ptr type="software"
            xml:id="XSLT" target="#XSLT"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#XSLT">XSLT</rs>, XPath, and
          Schematron. Overall, the affordances of the TEI, best practices of the EpiDoc community,
          and IIP archival format decisions have resulted in a set of documents that measure up to
          the requirements of FAIR metrics. Furthermore, the best practices adopted by the IIP
          project over the course of its development incorporated many FAIR behaviors with little
          extra effort.</p>
        <p>However, some issues that are unique to TEI encoding, as well as future directions of
          FAIR, indicate areas where the TEI community could do more. Generally, these are formal
          components that have to do primarily with persistence of metadata external to the IIP
          document, identifiers, and documentation of formats and vocabularies. In this paper, we
          have raised these issues with respect to each individual metric. One way to make metadata
          findable in a discipline-agnostic way is to deposit it into known registries such as ICPSR
          or other FAIR repositories.<note>DataCite hosts a finder, developed in partnership with
            the American Geophysical Union, to locate repositories that are certified in the US as
              <soCalled>FAIR Enabling</soCalled> and in the EU as <soCalled>FAIRsFAIR</soCalled>:
            accessed July 4, 2022, <ptr target="https://repositoryfinder.datacite.org/"/>.</note>
          Using such registries could be regarded as reducing accessibility to the full TEI and
          EpiDoc metadata. Differences between the metadata schemas in these repositories and the
          TEI metadata mean that the registered metadata would be less complete than the TEI header
          itself. A discipline-specific approach would be to create new registries, or to recommend
          an existing registry or aggregator which could undertake to expose more of the relevant
          disciplinary metadata. The <ref target="https://www.eagle-network.eu/">EAGLE</ref> project
          attempted to do this for digital epigraphy,<note>EAGLE, The Europeana network of Ancient
            Greek and Latin Epigraphy, accessed July 4, 2022, <ptr
              target="https://www.eagle-network.eu/"/>.</note> but was not able to develop a
          sustainable financial model. Another registry-like effort is represented by the
          Trismegistos project (<ref type="bibl" target="#depauw2014">Depauw and Gheldof
          2014</ref>), which is aggregating documents, metadata, people, places, and bibliography
          from the ancient world and assigning identifiers to them. Trismegistos has adopted a
          subscription model to sustain its work. IDEA has created a <ref
            target="https://zenodo.org/communities/eagle-idea">Zenodo community</ref> for epigraphy
          that contains epigraphic corpora, among other resources.<note>International Digital
            Epigraphy Association on Zenodo, accessed July 4, 2022, <ptr
              target="https://zenodo.org/communities/eagle-idea"/>.</note></p>
        <p>Some discipline-specific issues are more thought-provoking. Like the LAM community, the
          text encoding and epigraphic communities are working with data that do not look like the
          life or physical sciences data for which FAIR was developed. TEI documents, unlike
          research data created in the sciences or even the social sciences, which may be
          observational or machine-generated, embody a more tightly bound mixture of data and
          metadata. In the TEI universe, linguistic corpora are perhaps the datasets most similar to
          those of the other sciences. They differ from literary and historical texts in their size,
          uniformity, and computability. Literary or historical texts mingle data and metadata, at
          least from the point of view of the scholar. Is a bibliography data or metadata? Is it
          different when encoded in the <gi>teiHeader</gi> than when it is in a <gi>back</gi>
          element? What about the physical description of a book or other text-bearing object? And
          what about the encoding itself, which is an interpretive, analytical overlay onto a more
          undifferentiated text (which itself inherently embodies an interpretation—in the case of
          epigraphy, even the letters of the text may represent an editorial intervention). FAIR
          metrics focus on metadata as a surrogate for a document or dataset. IIP documents
          incorporate metadata about format, encoding, and the data themselves in one
          self-documenting entity, which makes them more FAIR, in spirit, if not in letter. This
          interconnection complicates conformance to metrics that are concerned with extracting
          metadata and treating them as surrogates for the complete document.</p>
        <p>IIP followed the EpiDoc and TEI recommendations for encoding metadata about provenance
          and reuse, as well as metadata about the epigraphic object itself. Other epigraphic
          corpora may choose to handle some of these features differently, or not to include them at
          all. In order to make it easy for projects to make their documents and collections FAIR,
          there is a need for more prescriptive information than is currently in the TEI Guidelines,
          especially to ensure interoperability and reusability. This can most effectively be
          provided by disciplinary customizations like EpiDoc, which is used by a community with
          common requirements, and in situations where a group like Epigraphy.info can recommend
          external authorities, or document identifiers for epigraphic texts.</p>
        <p>Finally, in the process of evaluating IIP against the FAIR metrics, we realized that not
          all FAIR criteria are under the control of a project; some depend on external entities.
          IIP relies on XML as an ISO standard, on the FAIRness of TEI and external vocabularies, as
          well as on the best practices recommended by the EpiDoc Guidelines. In order for a project
          like IIP to meet the FAIR metrics, it is necessary to also evaluate EpiDoc and TEI against
          the same criteria. According to the intent of the FAIR Metrics, the community represented
          by epigaphy.info or EpiDoc users as a whole should redefine the criteria of the fourteen
          metrics to better suit digital epigraphic documents. And as the FAIR Metrics Working Group
          recognized, universal metrics are not equally applicable to all domains; they have to be
          supplemented by domain- and community-specific metrics. Future work can continue to test
          and develop metrics that work best for individual projects using EpiDoc and TEI encoding
          and disciplinary communities that make use of them. We also look to developments in the
          epigraphic community and the TEI Consortium with respect to FAIRness at a broader
          level.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="appendix">
        <head>Appendix: Summary of Metrics and Tests</head>
        <p>Here we list some possible machine-actionable tests for the FAIR Metrics discussed
          above.</p>
        <table xml:id="table1">
          <row role="label">
            <cell>Metric</cell>
            <cell>Test</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>FM-F1A: Identifier uniqueness</cell>
            <cell>Check for DOI:
                <lb/><code>/TEI/teiHeader/fileDesc/publicationStmt/idno[@type=&quot;DOI&quot;]</code></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>FM-F1B: Identifier persistence</cell>
            <cell>DOI registry information: <lb/><ptr
                target="https://search.datacite.org/works/10.26300/pz1d-st89"/>.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>FM-F2: Machine-readability of metadata</cell>
            <cell>Check for machine-readable metadata in the document: <lb/><ptr
                target="https://www.w3.org/XML/"/>
              <lb/><code>/TEI/teiHeader</code></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>FM-F3: Metadata clearly and explicitly include the identifier of the data they
              describe</cell>
            <cell>Test for existence of DOI (or other identifiers):
                <lb/><code>/TEI/teiHeader/fileDesc/publicationStmt/idno[@type=&quot;DOI&quot;]</code></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>FM-F4: (Meta)data are registered or indexed in a searchable resource</cell>
            <cell>Not currently testable</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>FM-A1.1: The protocol is open, free, and universally implementable</cell>
            <cell><code>/TEI/teiHeader/fileDesc/publicationStmt/availability</code></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>FM-A1.2: The protocol allows for authentication and authorization where
              necessary</cell>
            <cell><code>/TEI/teiHeader/fileDesc/publicationStmt/availability/licence</code></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>FM-A2: Metadata should be accessible even when the data are no longer
              available</cell>
            <cell>LOCKSS, DOI registry, disciplinary registry</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>FM-I1: (Meta)data use a formal, accessible, shared, and broadly applicable
              language for knowledge representation</cell>
            <cell><code>/TEI/teiHeader/encodingDesc/schemaRef</code></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>FM-I2: (Meta)data use vocabularies that follow the FAIR principles</cell>
            <cell>Relies on FAIRness of vocabularies used.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>FM-I3: (Meta)data include qualified references to other (meta)data</cell>
            <cell>Not met</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>FM-R1.1: (Meta)data are released with a clear and accessible data usage
              license</cell>
            <cell>IIP documents use a CC BY-NC 4.0 license:
                <lb/><code>/TEI/teiHeader/fileDesc/publicationStmt/availability/licence</code></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>FM-R1.2: (Meta)data are associated with detailed provenance</cell>
            <cell><code>/TEI/teiHeader/fileDesc/titleStmt</code>
              <lb/><tag type="pi">xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"</tag>
              <lb/><code>xmlns=&quot;http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0&quot;</code>
              <lb/><code>/TEI/teiHeader/encodingDesc/schemaRef</code></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>FM-R1.3: (Meta)data meet domain-relevant community standards</cell>
            <cell>Can conform to recommendation, but without formal certification.</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bagnall"><author>Bagnall, Roger</author>, <author>Richard J. A.
              Talbert</author>, <author>Sarah Bond</author>, <author>Jeffrey Becker</author>,
              <author>Tom Elliott</author>, <author>Sean Gillies</author>, <author>Lindsay
              Holman</author>, <author>Ryan Horne</author>, et al. <date>n.d.</date>
            <title level="u">Pleiades</title>. Chapel Hill, NC: Ancient World Mapping Center,
            University of North Carolina; London: Stoa Consortium; New York: Institute for the Study
            of the Ancient World, New York University. Accessed July 6, 2022, <ptr
              target="https://pleiades.stoa.org/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bodard2021"><author>Bodard, Gabriel</author>, <author>Hugh Cayless</author>,
              <author>Chiara Cenati</author>, <author>Alison Cooley</author>, <author>Tom
              Elliott</author>, <author>Silvia Evangelisti</author>, <author>Achille
              Felicetti</author>, et al. <date>2021</date>. <title level="u">Modeling Epigraphy with
              an Ontology</title>. Working paper, Ontology Working Group, Epigraphy.org, version
            0.1, March 26. doi:<idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.4639507</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="calamai2018"><author>Calamai, Silvia</author>, and <author>Francesca
              Frontini</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">FAIR Data Principles and Their
              Application to Speech and Oral Archives</title>. <title level="j">Journal of New Music
              Research</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">339–54</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.1080/09298215.2018.1473449</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dsg2014"><orgName>Data Citation Synthesis Group</orgName>.
            <date>2014</date>. <title level="u">Joint Declaration of Data Citation
              Principles</title>. Edited by <editor>Martone M.</editor>. San Diego CA: FORCE11.
              doi:<idno type="DOI">10.25490/a97f-egyk</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="depauw2014"><author>Depauw, Mark</author>, and <author>Tom Gheldof</author>.
              <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">Trismegistos: An Interdisciplinary Platform for
              Ancient World Texts and Related Information.</title> In <title level="m">Theory and
              Practice of Digital Libraries—TPDL 2013 Selected Workshops</title>, edited by
              <editor>Łukaz Bolikowski</editor>, <editor>Vittore Casarosa</editor>, <editor>Paula
              Goodale</editor>, <editor>Nikos Houssos</editor>, <editor>Paolo Manghi</editor>, and
              <editor>Jochen Schirrwagen</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">40–52</biblScope>.
            Communications in Computer and Information Science <biblScope unit="issue"
              >416</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Cham</pubPlace>: <publisher>Springer</publisher>.
              doi:<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-319-08425-1_5</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="elliott2021"><author>Elliott, Tom</author>, <author>Gabriel Bodard</author>,
              <author>Hugh Cayless</author>, et al. <date>2021</date>. <title level="u">EpiDoc:
              Epigraphic Documents in TEI XML</title>. <edition>Version 9.3</edition>, November
            2021. <ptr target="http://epidoc.stoa.org"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="erp2018"><author>Erp, Jarno A. A. van</author>, <author>Carolyn D.
              Langen</author>, <author>Anca Boon</author>, and <author>Kees van Bochove</author>.
              <date>2018</date>. <title level="u">Testing the FAIR Metrics on Data Catalogs</title>.
            Preprint, received and published September 4. PeerJ Preprints. doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.7287/peerj.preprints.27151v2</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="EC2016"><orgName>European Commission</orgName>, <orgName>Directorate-General
              for Research and Innovation</orgName>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="m">Realising
              the European Open Science Cloud: First Report and Recommendations of the Commission
              High Level Expert Group on the European Open Science Cloud.</title>
            <pubPlace>Luxembourg</pubPlace>: <publisher>Publications Office of the European
              Union</publisher>. doi:<idno type="DOI">10.2777/940154</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="EC2018"><orgName>European Commission</orgName>, <orgName>Directorate-General
              for Research and Innovation</orgName>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="m">Turning
              FAIR into Reality: Final Report and Action Plan from the European Commission Expert
              Group on FAIR Data.</title>
            <pubPlace>Luxembourg</pubPlace>: <publisher>Publications Office of the European
              Union</publisher>. doi:<idno type="DOI">10.2777/1524</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fairsfair"><title>FAIRsFAIR</title>. <date>n.d.</date>
            <title level="u">The Project</title>. Accessed June 8, 2020. <ptr
              target="https://www.fairsfair.eu/the-project"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="feraudi2016"><author>Feraudi-Gruénais, Francisca</author>, and <author>Frank
              Grieshaber</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">Digital Epigraphy am
              Scheideweg? / Digital Epigraphy at a Crossroads?</title> Nachnutzung und
            Nachnutzbarkeit der Forschung im Akademienprogramm Workshop der Nordrhein-Westfälischen
            Akademie der Wissenschaften und der Künste und der Union der deutschen Akademien der
            Wissenschaften AG <soCalled>eHumanities</soCalled>. Düsseldorf: N.p, 2016. doi:<idno
              type="DOI">10.11588/heidok.00022141</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="forkel2018"><author>Forkel, Robert</author>, <author>Johann-Mattis
              List</author>, <author>Simon J. Greenhill</author>, <author>Christoph
            Rzymski</author>, <author>Sebastian Bank</author>, <author>Michael Cysouw</author>,
              <author>Harald Hammarström</author>, <author>Martin Haspelmath</author>,
              <author>Gereon A. Kaiping</author>, and <author>Russell D. Gray</author>. 2018. <title
              level="a">Cross-Linguistic Data Formats, Advancing Data Sharing and Re-Use in
              Comparative Linguistics</title>. <title level="j">Scientific Data</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>, article 180205. doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.1038/sdata.2018.205</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="getty"><orgName>Getty Research Institute</orgName>. <date>n.d.</date>
            <title level="m">Art &amp; Architecture Thesaurus Online</title>. Accessed May 31, 2020.
              <ptr target="https://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/aat/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gida"><orgName>Global Indigenous Data Alliance</orgName>. <date>n.d.</date>
            <title level="u">CARE Principles for Indigenous Data Governance</title>. Accessed June
            9, 2020. <ptr target="https://www.gida-global.org/care"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="koster2018"><author>Koster, Lukas</author>, and <author>Saskia
              Woutersen-Windhouwer</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">FAIR Principles for
              Library, Archive and Museum Collections: A Proposal for Standards for Reusable
              Collections</title>. <title level="j">Code4Lib Journal</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">40</biblScope> (May). <ptr
              target="https://journal.code4lib.org/articles/13427"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lamprecht2020"><author>Lamprecht, Anna-Lena, Leyla Garcia</author>,
              <author>Mateusz Kuzak</author>, <author>Carlos Martinez</author>, <author>Ricardo
              Arcila</author>, <author>Eva Martin Del Pico</author>, <author>Victoria Dominguez Del
              Angel</author>, et al. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">Towards FAIR Principles for
              Research Software</title>. <title level="m">Data Science</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">37–59</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.3233/DS-190026</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="leach2005"><author>Leach, Paul J.</author>, <author>Michael
              Mealling</author>, and <author>Rich Salz</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title level="u"
              >A Universally Unique IDentifier (UUID) URN Namespace</title>. RFC 4122, Standards
            Track. N.p.: The Internet Society. <ptr target="https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4122.txt"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="paskin2009"><author>Paskin, Norman</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title
              level="a">Digital Object Identifier (DOI®) System</title>. In <title level="m"
              >Encyclopedia of Library and Information Sciences</title>, <edition>3rd ed.</edition>,
            edited by <editor>Marcia J. Bates</editor> and <editor>Mary Niles Maack</editor>,
              <biblScope unit="page">1586–92</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Boca Raton</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>CRC Press</publisher>. doi:<idno type="DOI">10.1081/E-ELIS3</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="prag2020"><author>Prag, Jonathan</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title
              level="a">Publication in a Digital World</title>. I.Sicily. December 23, 2020. <ptr
              target="https://isicily.org/2020/12/23/publication-in-a-digital-world/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rabinowitz"><author>Rabinowitz, Adam</author>, <author>Ryan Shaw</author>,
            et al. <date>n.d.</date>
            <title level="u">PeriodO: A Gazetteer of Periods for Linking and Visualizing
              Data.</title> Accessed May 31, 2020. <ptr target="http://perio.do/en/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tei2020"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2020</date>. <title
              level="a">Documentation Elements.</title> Chap. 22 in <title level="m">TEI P5:
              Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>. <edition>Version
              4.0.0</edition>. Last updated February 13. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>: <publisher>TEI
              Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
              target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.0.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="wagner"><author>Wagner, Andreas</author>. <date>n.d.</date>
            <title level="u">Tei2zenodo</title>. Accessed June 8, 2020. <ptr
              target="https://gitlab.gwdg.de/rg-mpg-de/tei2zenodo"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="wilkinson2016"><author>Wilkinson, Mark D.</author>, <author>Michel
              Dumontier</author>, <author>IJSbrand J. Aalbersberg</author>, <abbr>Gabrielle
              Appleton</abbr>, <abbr>Myles Axton</abbr>, <abbr>Arie Baak</abbr>, et al.
              <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">The FAIR Guiding Principles for scientific data
              management and stewardship</title>. <title level="j">Scientific Data</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>, article 160018. doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.1038/sdata.2016.18</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="wilkinson2018"><author>Wilkinson, Mark D.</author>, <author>Susanna-Assunta
              Sansone</author>, <author>Erik Schultes</author>, <author>Peter Doorn</author>,
              <author>Luiz Olavo Bonino da Silva Santos</author>, and <author>Michel
              Dumontier</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">A Design Framework and
              Exemplar Metrics for FAIRness</title>. <title level="j">Scientific Data</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>, article 180118. doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.1038/sdata.2018.118</idno>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
