<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-cc-pn-erjavec-195-source.xml 1140 2022-09-21 07:13:26Z ron $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Parla-CLARIN Recommendations for Encoding Corpora of Parliamentary
          Proceedings</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Tomaž</forename>
            <surname>Erjavec</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Tomaž Erjavec is a <roleName>senior researcher</roleName> at the Department
            of Knowledge Technologies, <orgName>Jožef Stefan Institute</orgName>, and at the Fran
            Ramovš Institute of the Slovenian Language at the <orgName>Scientific Research Centre of
              the Slovenian Academy of Sciences and Arts</orgName>. His work focuses on developing
            language resources, especially as regards their annotation and encoding, in the fields
            of language technologies and of digital humanities. He is the national coordinator of
            the Slovenian branch of the CLARIN research infrastructure for language resources and
            tools and a member of ISO/TC 37/SC 4 <soCalled>Language resource
            management</soCalled>.</affiliation>
          <email>tomaz.erjavec@ijs.si</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Andrej</forename>
            <surname>Pančur</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Andrej Pančur is a <roleName>research fellow</roleName> at the
              <orgName>Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>, a national coordination
            institution for the Slovenian branch of DARIAH. Since 2011 he has been working for the
            ICH’s infrastructure program Research Infrastructure of Slovene Historiography, where he
            is responsible for technological development, research data, digital editions, and
            bringing digital humanities techniques and methods into the Slovenian research area. In
            2018 he became the head of the research infrastructure.</affiliation>
          <email>andrej.pancur@inz.si</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>28/04/2022</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Georg Vogeler</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="14">Selected Papers from the 2019 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals
          in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish
          full-text articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>parliamentary corpora</term>
          <term>encoding recommendations</term>
          <term>TEI ODD</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="RvdB" when="2022-04-28">Initial encoding</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>Parliamentary proceedings are a rich source of data that can be used by scholars in
          various humanities and social sciences disciplines. Unlike the sources of most other
          language corpora, parliamentary proceedings are not subject to copyright or personal
          privacy protections, and are typically available online, thus making them ideal for
          compilation into corpora and for open distribution. For these reasons many countries have
          already produced corpora of parliamentary proceedings, but each typically in their own
          encoding, limiting their comparability and utilization in a multilingual setting. In this
          paper we propose an encoding schema which could serve as an interchange format for
          parliamentary corpora compiled for the purposes of scholarly investigations. The schema,
          called Parla-CLARIN, was developed within the CLARIN research infrastructure, and is
          written as a TEI ODD which includes a TEI customization and prose guidelines with examples
          of use. We discuss the coverage and choices made in designing the recommendations, and
          give an overview of the guidelines. We also discuss two other standard schemas for
          encoding parliamentary data, Akoma Ntoso and RDF, and their relation to Parla-CLARIN. We
          conclude by presenting corpora already encoded in Parla-CLARIN and discussing further
          work, especially the provision of a set of example documents and of transformation scripts
          that would make the proposed encoding more usable.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="acknowledgements">
        <p>The authors would like to thank the two anonymous reviewers for their helpful comments
          and suggestions, Jan Odijk for his leadership in proposing and organizing the Amersfoort
          CLARIN ParlaFormat Workshop, and the workshop participants for their constructive
          criticisms on the draft Parla-CLARIN proposal. The work presented here was supported by
          CLARIN ERIC through the CLARIN Type B ParlaFormat Workshop, through the CLARIN ParlaMint
          project, and by the CLARIN.SI Slovenian node of CLARIN and the DARIAH-SI Slovenian node of
          the DARIAH research infrastructure.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="introduction">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>The unique content, structure, and language of records of parliamentary debates make them
          an important object of study in a wide range of disciplines in the digital humanities and
          social sciences, such as political science (<ref type="bibl" target="#dijk10">Dijk
            2010</ref>), sociology (<ref type="bibl" target="#cheng15">Cheng 2015</ref>), history
            (<ref type="bibl" target="#pancur16">Pančur and Šorn 2016</ref>), discourse analysis
            (<ref type="bibl" target="#hirst14">Hirst et al. 2014</ref>), sociolinguistics (<ref
            type="bibl" target="#rheault16">Rheault et al. 2016</ref>), and multilinguality (<ref
            type="bibl" target="#bayley04">Bayley 2004</ref>). With parliaments in Europe playing an
          increasingly decisive role in their constituents’ lives and because of their rapidly
          changing relations with the public, mass media, executive branches, and international
          organizations, further empirical research and development of integrative analytical tools
          are necessary in order to achieve a better understanding of parliamentary discourse as
          well as its wider societal impact, in particular with studies that represent diverse parts
          of society (women, minorities, and marginalized groups) and cross-cultural studies (<ref
            type="bibl" target="#hughes15">Hughes et al. 2015</ref>).</p>
        <p>The most distinguishing characteristic of records of parliamentary debates is that they
          are essentially transcriptions of spoken language produced in controlled and regulated
          circumstances and are rich in valuable (sociodemographic) metadata. They are also easily
          available under various Freedom of Information Acts set in place to enable informed
          participation by the public and to improve effective functioning of democratic systems,
          making the datasets even more valuable for researchers with heterogeneous backgrounds. For
          these reasons, and because parliamentary proceedings are often available online, many
          researchers have already compiled corpora of parliamentary proceedings.<note>For an
            overview, see Fišer and Lenardič (<ref type="bibl" target="#fiser18">2018</ref>).</note>
          However, these corpora are encoded using a variety of different annotation schemes,
          limiting their interchange and reuse.</p>
        <p>In order to overcome this problem, the CLARIN Research Infrastructure for Language
          Resources and Technologies organized the ParlaFormat Workshop (May 23–24, 2019,
                Amersfoort)<note><bibl><author>Jan Odijk</author>, <title level="u">CLARIN
                ParlaFormat workshop</title> (blog post), CLARIN, May 29, <date>2019</date>, <ptr
                target="https://www.clarin.eu/blog/clarin-parlaformat-workshop"/>.</bibl></note> at
          which the idea and draft of a TEI-based common annotation scheme for encoding corpora of
          parliamentary proceedings was introduced. The participants presented their own experiences
          with encoding parliamentary corpora and gave their comments on the proposal. On this basis
          we developed the Parla-CLARIN recommendations for encoding parliamentary corpora which we
          present in this paper. These recommendations aim to provide community-based reference TEI
          customizations for a specific application, following similar prior initiatives, from <ref
            target="https://sourceforge.net/projects/epidoc/">EpiDoc</ref><note><bibl><author>Tom
                Elliott</author>, <author>Gabriel Bodard</author>, <author>Hugh Cayless</author>, et
              al., <title level="m">EpiDoc: Epigraphic Documents in TEI XML</title>, <edition>v.
                9.3</edition> (November 2021), <ptr
                target="https://sourceforge.net/projects/epidoc/"/>.</bibl></note> for epigraphic
          documents to <ref target="https://github.com/DARIAH-ERIC/lexicalresources">TEI
                Lex-0</ref><note><bibl><orgName>DARIAH-ERIC Working Group</orgName>
              <title level="m">Lexical Resources</title>, TEI Lex-0 <edition>v. 0.9.0</edition>
              (September 26, 2021), <ptr target="https://github.com/DARIAH-ERIC/lexicalresources"
              />.</bibl></note> for dictionaries.</p>
        <p>In the process of the developing the recommendations, we also produced the second version
          of the siParl corpus (<ref type="bibl" target="#pancur20">Pančur and Erjavec 2020</ref>;
            <ref type="bibl" target="#pancur20b">Pančur et al. 2020</ref>), a carefully encoded and
          linguistically annotated collection of parliamentary debates from the Assembly of the
          Republic of Slovenia from 1990 to 2018, with over 1 million speeches and 200 million
          words. This was the first substantial corpus to be fully Parla-CLARIN encoded, where we
          had the good fortune that the first version of siParl was the basis for an extended
          tutorial on how corpora can be used to investigate language use and communication
          practices in the context of political discourse (<ref type="bibl" target="#fiser20">Fišer
            and Pahor de Maiti 2020</ref>). The work on this tutorial revealed various shortcomings
          of the first version, which were addressed in the encoding and structure of siParl 2.0 and
          also informed the development of the Parla-CLARIN recommendations.</p>
        <p><ptr type="crossref" target="#overview"/> gives an overview of the Parla-CLARIN proposal,
            <ptr type="crossref" target="#relatedwork"/> presents related work, and <ptr
            type="crossref" target="#conclusions"/> gives conclusions and directions for further
          work.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="overview">
        <head>Overview of the Parla-CLARIN Proposal</head>
        <p>The Parla-CLARIN recommendations are implemented as a customization of the TEI Guidelines
          that allows a wide range of corpora of parliamentary proceedings to be encoded and makes
          explicit prose recommendations on the manner of encoding various phenomena. In particular,
          the recommendations attempt to take into account the following aspects of parliamentary
          corpora: <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>Structure: legislative periods, sessions, topics, speeches, transcription
              variants</item>
            <item>Metadata: mandates, titles, parliamentary bodies, locations, dates and
              times</item>
            <item>Speakers: date of birth, sex, education, party membership, links to external
              resources</item>
            <item>Political parties: name(s), history, relations</item>
            <item>Speeches: speaker, text, transcriber comments, verbal and nonverbal
              interruptions</item>
            <item>Linguistic annotation: part-of-speech (PoS) tagging, named entity annotation,
              syntax, etc.</item>
            <item>Multimedia: audio and video, facsimile of original transcript</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <div xml:id="schema">
          <head>The Parla-CLARIN Schema</head>
          <p>Parla-CLARIN is written as a TEI ODD document, consisting of the prose guidelines and
            the schema specification, on the basis of which it is possible, using the standard TEI
            XSLT stylesheets, to derive an XML schema expressed either as a RelaxNG schema, a DTD,
            or a W3C schema, which is then used for formal validations of a Parla-CLARIN
            parliamentary corpus.</p>
          <p>While the proposal tries to cater for many encoding needs, it is possible that new
            users will have to use TEI elements or attributes that are not discussed in the prose
            guidelines. Since the recommendations are still under development, the formal schema
            specification has been left rather unconstrained, so it can accommodate encoding
            practices that have not yet been foreseen. The downside of this approach is that the
            schema allows constructs that are at odds with those proposed in the prose of the
            recommendations. Currently the prose should therefore be taken as the definitive way of
            encoding the phenomena under discussion: that is, even if a corpus validates against the
            schema, it might still not be encoded according to the recommendations.</p>
          <p>The Parla-CLARIN schema uses the following TEI modules: <list rend="bulleted">
              <item>the obligatory <ident>tei</ident>, <ident>header</ident>, <ident>core</ident>,
                and <ident>textstructure</ident> modules defining the elements used in any
                TEI-encoded text;</item>
              <item>the <ident>corpus</ident> module to encode the root <gi>teiCorpus</gi> element
                and the details of various metadata of the corpus;</item>
              <item>the <ident>spoken</ident> module for encoding speech corpora, so that speeches
                are encoded as utterance elements;</item>
              <item>the <ident>figures</ident> module, which, among other things, defines the
                elements for encoding tables, as these can also appear in parliamentary
                proceedings;</item>
              <item>the <ident>namesdates</ident> module, which defines a wealth of elements and
                attributes to describe people and organizations;</item>
              <item>the <ident>transcr</ident> module, which is used for transcription of primary
                sources, such as manuscripts, and is useful for encoding historical parliamentary
                corpora where the facsimile is of interest;</item>
              <item>the <ident>linking</ident> module, which defines useful attributes for linking
                elements of the corpus;</item>
              <item>the <ident>analysis</ident> and <ident>iso-fs</ident> modules, the former for
                encoding linguistic analyses of the transcriptions and the latter for defining
                formal pieces of data, such as decomposing morphosyntactic descriptions into their
                features;</item>
              <item>the <ident>gaiji</ident> module for encoding special characters that are
                especially likely to appear in historical parliamentary proceedings.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>The crucial choice above was to use the <ident>spoken</ident> module for encoding
            speech corpora, so that parliamentary debates are encoded, essentially, as a speech
              corpus.<note>Similarly to Truan (<ref type="bibl" target="#truan16"
              >2016</ref>).</note> The competing options would be to encode them either using the
            default text structure elements (<gi>div</gi> and <gi>p</gi> or <gi>ab</gi>), or to use
            the <ident>drama</ident> module, that is, treating the debates as a play. The first
            option gives TEI elements that are too generic, which could encode the semantics of
            various structures only with many type attributes, while the second, maybe surprisingly,
            maps quite well onto the structure of parliamentary debates and is, in fact, used as the
            base encoding of siParl. However, the semantics of the elements made for performance
            texts are nevertheless rather far from the reality of parliamentary debates, and often
            require mixed content, which is best avoided if the text is also to be linguistically
            annotated. Importantly, the <ident>speech</ident> module also supports encoding the
            alignment of the utterances (or other contained elements) with the speech or video
            signal. That the choice of this module is the correct one is also supported by the
            overview of the encodings of other parliamentary corpora (see <ptr type="crossref"
              target="#relatedwork"/>), where the majority use TEI <ident>speech</ident>.</p>
          <p>Unlike some other TEI customizations, such as the one for encoding Computer-Mediated
            Communication proposed by the TEI CMC SIG,<note>Computer-Mediated Communication Special
              Interest Group, TEI Consortium, accessed January 13, 2022, <ptr
                target="https://tei-c.org/activities/sig/cmc/"/>.</note> the Parla-CLARIN schema
            does not introduce new elements, but rather uses existing TEI ones. The advantages of
            this approach are that the documentation is already directly available and that standard
            TEI-aware tools can be used to process the elements. On the downside, the elements used
            might not have as specific semantics as would be desired in the context of parliamentary
            corpora, and their content models can be too complex or too general. For the modules
            used, however, the schema does disallow certain elements that we assume that would never
            be used in the context of parliamentary corpora, and the schema also introduces
            recommended values for certain attributes, such as for the <code>div/@type</code>
            attribute.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="guidelines">
          <head>The Parla-CLARIN Guidelines</head>
          <p>The Parla-CLARIN guidelines—that is, the prose recommendations—are, to an extent, based
            on <title level="u"><ref target="http://purl.org/TEI/teiinlibraries">Best Practices for
                TEI in Libraries</ref></title> (<ref type="bibl" target="#hawkins18">Hawkins et al.,
              2018</ref>) in that they also give general recommendations for such matters as
            encoding relating to characters and filenames and how to document the encoding process
            and languages used. After such introductory considerations, the guidelines comprise the
            following chapters: <list rend="bulleted">
              <item><emph>overall document structure</emph>, which explains how the corpus should be
                structured, what the text divisions look like and how they should be typed, and how
                to encode document variants, which are meant for cases where both versions of
                parliamentary proceedings are to be encoded—that is, the original,
                  <soCalled>raw</soCalled> transcription and the edited,
                  <soCalled>redacted</soCalled> transcription;</item>
              <item><emph>corpus metadata</emph>, which can contain significant and valuable
                information about the proceedings, with descriptions and examples given on how to
                encode information about the speakers and parties, and the relationships between the
                speakers and parties;</item>
              <item><emph>transcriptions</emph>, where the encoding of the utterances (speeches) and
                commentary (notes by the transcribers) is explained, including specifics such as the
                encoding of interrupted utterances, verbal and nonverbal incidents, and how to
                encode voting results;</item>
              <item><emph>linguistic annotation</emph>, which details the encoding of linguistic
                features added to the utterances and is further divided into word-level annotation
                (e.g., part-of-speech tagging), segmental annotation (e.g., named entities), and
                linking annotation (e.g., dependency syntax);</item>
              <item><emph>multimedia</emph>, explaining how to align speech or video recordings, as
                well as facsimiles, to the transcription.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Finally, the guidelines also contain a chapter on conversions to or from other formats.
            This chapter, and especially the accompanying code, should be significantly extended, as
            having good conversion procedures is crucial to ensure the viability of the proposal.
            Currently, only one conversion procedure has been developed, namely that of converting
            parliamentary debates encoded in Akoma Ntoso to Parla-CLARIN, a topic that we discuss
            further in <ptr type="crossref" target="#relatedwork"/>.</p>
          <p>In the Parla-CLARIN guidelines, every mention of an element is linked to its
            definition, where examples of use are also given, and the text also makes frequent
            reference to the text of the TEI Guidelines. However, the TEI Guidelines give generic
            examples and explanations, which can be at odds with particular recommendations that are
            made for Parla-CLARIN, so the ones from the TEI Guidelines should in this context be
            taken with a grain of salt.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="presentation">
          <head>Presentation of Parla-CLARIN</head>
          <p>Like the TEI Guidelines, the Parla-CLARIN recommendations are available on <ref
              target="https://github.com/clarin-eric/parla-clarin/">GitHub</ref>, as a
              project<note>Tomaž Erjavec and Andrej Pančur, Parla-CLARIN project GitHub site, last
              updated March 17, 2021, <ptr target="https://github.com/clarin-eric/parla-clarin/"
              />.</note> of the CLARIN ERIC collection. The project contains a folder for the schema
            (i.e., the Parla-CLARIN ODD document and XML schemas derived from it), a folder for the
            programs that convert the ODD into the XML schemas and to the HTML of the prose and
            schema definitions, and a folder for examples, which contains an artificial but fully
            worked out example of a Parla-CLARIN document and subfolders with various example
            resources, where each should contain: <list rend="ordered">
              <item>a sample of a corpus in its source encoding;</item>
              <item>XSLT script to convert it into Parla-CLARIN; and</item>
              <item>the output of the conversion.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Currently, the folder contains examples of Akoma Ntoso encodings and two Slovene
            corpora of parliamentary proceedings: SlovParl (<ref type="bibl" target="#pancur17"
              >Pančur, Šorn, and Erjavec 2017</ref>) and siParl version 1.0 (<ref type="bibl"
              target="#pancur19">Pančur et al. 2019</ref>).</p>
          <p>Furthermore, the project contains a document folder with the HTML of the
            recommendations, which can be read online via the <ref
              target="https://clarin-eric.github.io/parla-clarin/">github.io</ref> pages.<note>Tomaž
              Erjavec and Andrej Pančur, Parla-CLARIN: A TEI Schema for Corpora of Parliamentary
              Proceedings, v. 0.2 (December 8, 2020), <ptr
                target="https://clarin-eric.github.io/parla-clarin/"/>.</note> Finally, the project
            has a wiki, which gives the technical details on how to validate a corpus against the
            Parla-CLARIN XML schema, how to add example documents to the project, and how to change
            the ODD in case it turns out to be insufficient for the modeling needs of a particular
            corpus.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="relatedwork">
        <head>Related Work</head>
        <p>Before embarking on designing the Parla-CLARIN recommendations, we studied which other
          formats are used for encoding parliamentary corpora to gauge whether TEI-based
          recommendations would make sense. First, as shown in <ptr type="crossref" target="#table1"
          />, and as evidenced by the overview of parliamentary corpora by Fišer and Lenardič (<ref
            type="bibl" target="#fiser18">2018</ref>)<note>See also <title level="u">Parliamentary
              Corpora</title>, CLARIN Language Resources: Resource Families, accessed January 13,
            2022, <ptr target="https://www.clarin.eu/resource-families/parliamentary-corpora"
            />.</note> and a survey of those presented by the participants of the ParlaFormat
            Workshop,<note>See Tomaž Erjavec and Andrej Pančur, <title level="u">Response to the
              Presentations</title>, slide 3, presented at ParlaFormat Workshop, Amersfoort, May 24,
            2019, <ptr
              target="https://www.clarin.eu/sites/default/files/erjavec-pancur-teiparla_2019_response_.pdf"
            />.</note> we found that the majority of such corpora already use TEI in some guise or
          another when we counted <soCalled>TEI-inspired</soCalled> encodings, which, even though
          they use their own schemas, use elements with names and semantics similar to the ones used
          by TEI.</p>
        <table xml:id="table1">
          <head>Overview of encodings of selected parliamentary corpora</head>
          <row role="label">
            <cell>Corpus name</cell>
            <cell>Format</cell>
            <cell>Reference</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Polish Parliamentary Corpus</cell>
            <cell>TEI speech</cell>
            <cell>(<ref type="bibl" target="#ogrodniczuk18">Ogrodniczuk 2018</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                target="#ogrodniczuk20">Ogrodniczuk and Nitoń 2020</ref>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>ParlaMeter-sl and ParlaMeter-hr</cell>
            <cell>TEI speech</cell>
            <cell>(<ref type="bibl" target="#ljubesic18">Ljubešić et al. 2018</ref>; <ref
                type="bibl" target="#dobranic19">Dobranić, Ljubešić, and Erjavec 2019</ref>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Debates on Europe at the Bundestag</cell>
            <cell>TEI speech</cell>
            <cell>(<ref type="bibl" target="#truan16">Truan 2016</ref>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>TAPS-fr</cell>
            <cell>TEI speech</cell>
            <cell>(<ref type="bibl" target="#diwersy20">Diwersy and Luxardo 2020</ref>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>ParlAT</cell>
            <cell>TEI-inspired</cell>
            <cell>(<ref type="bibl" target="#wissik18">Wissik and Pirker 2018</ref>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>DutchParl</cell>
            <cell>TEI-inspired</cell>
            <cell>(<ref type="bibl" target="#marx10">Marx and Schuth 2010</ref>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>GermaParl</cell>
            <cell>TEI-inspired</cell>
            <cell>(<ref type="bibl" target="#blatte18">Blätte and Blessing 2018</ref>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>German Political Speeches</cell>
            <cell>TEI-inspired</cell>
            <cell>(<ref type="bibl" target="#barbaresi18">Barbaresi 2018</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                target="#barbaresi19">2019</ref>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Danish Parliament Corpus</cell>
            <cell>custom XML</cell>
            <cell>(<ref type="bibl" target="#hansen18">Hansen 2018</ref>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Czech Parliamentary Meetings</cell>
            <cell>TRS XML</cell>
            <cell>(<ref type="bibl" target="#prazak12">Pražák and Šmídl 2012</ref>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Corpus of the Saeima</cell>
            <cell>RDF, CoNLL-U</cell>
            <cell>(<ref type="bibl" target="#dargis18">Darģis et al. 2018</ref>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>The Debates of the European Parliament</cell>
            <cell>RDF</cell>
            <cell>(<ref type="bibl" target="#aggelen17">Aggelen et al. 2017</ref>)<note>This corpus
                was compiled as part of the CLARIN Traveling Campus <soCalled>Talk of
                  Europe</soCalled>, which encoded the proceedings of the European Parliament as
                linked open data: see <ptr target="http://www.talkofeurope.eu/"/>.</note>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Swedish Parliamentary Data</cell>
            <cell>Prolog</cell>
            <cell>(<ref type="bibl" target="#eide19">Eide 2019</ref>)</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <p>This was, of course, encouraging, as the barriers to converting from such encodings into
          Parla-CLARIN are much lower than those to converting from completely unrelated encoding
          systems. Nevertheless, there are two other formats that each also have a significant
          following and are contenders for being or becoming a standard format for parliamentary
          corpora.</p>
        <div xml:id="akomantoso">
          <head>Akoma Ntoso</head>
          <p><ref target="http://www.akomantoso.org/">Akoma Ntoso</ref><note>Accessed January 13,
              2022, <ptr target="http://www.akomantoso.org/"/>; see also the slides by Monica
              Palmirani, <title level="u">Akoma Ntoso for Parliamentary Documents</title>, presented
              at the 2019 Parla-CLARIN workshop: <ptr
                target="https://www.clarin.eu/sites/default/files/palmirani-akn-clarin-parl2019.pdf"
              />.</note> was explicitly developed as an XML format for encoding legislative and
            judiciary documents, including parliamentary proceedings, is an OASIS standard, and has
            already been used to encode various legal documents in a number of countries. Akoma
            Ntoso defines an XML schema (called AKN) for modeling legal documents, uses FRBR
            (Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records) concepts, and has a built-in
            relationship to ontologies. While these are all good reasons for AKN to be the
            interchange format for parliamentary corpora, there are, we feel, nevertheless a number
            of reasons why TEI-based recommendations are preferable.</p>
          <p>First, corpus compilers and users are typically unfamiliar with AKN but—as shown in
              <ptr type="crossref" target="#table1"/>—relatively familiar with TEI. It should also
            be noted that for most corpus compilers, parliamentary corpora will be only one type of
            corpus they will be compiling, so it is somewhat unrealistic for them to learn AKN and
            develop conversion scripts from it for just one type of corpus; on the other hand, TEI
            can be used for practically any type of corpus.</p>
          <p>Second, AKN makes no provisions for storing speaker metadata, which is instead accessed
            from external data sources, using an AKN-specific referencing system; on the other hand,
            TEI has a number of elements for recording details about persons. For reasons of
            completeness, uniform and easier processing, and experimental replicability it is better
            to include such data directly in the corpus.</p>
          <p>Third, AKN has no built-in support for linguistic annotation (apart from named
            entities). And while it would be possible to add elements for such annotation via a
            different namespace to AKN, AKN has no provisions for extending its schema, while TEI
            already has such elements available. As Parla-CLARIN is focused on corpora of
            parliamentary proceedings, and it is difficult to imagine a corpus without any
            linguistic annotation, TEI seems a better choice.</p>
          <p>Nevertheless, AKN is an important schema for modeling parliamentary proceedings,
            especially as the primary encoding standard used by various legislative bodies, so some
            of AKN’s solutions were used in developing the Parla-CLARIN proposal, in particular the
            typology of divisions of a document. Also developed was a partial, but non-trivial,
            conversion from AKN to Parla-CLARIN, which covers several AKN example documents. As
            mentioned in <ptr type="crossref" target="#presentation"/>, the example documents and
            conversion script can be found in the <ident>Examples</ident> folder of the Parla-CLARIN
            Git repository. The <ident>akn2tei.xsl</ident> script attempts to preserve the IDs of
            the source AKN document, converts the AKN addressee, role, and questions and answers to
            Parla-CLARIN, and maps FRBR data (which distinguishes a <soCalled>work</soCalled> from
            its <soCalled>expression</soCalled> and its expression from its
              <soCalled>manifestation</soCalled>) to the appropriate TEI elements and attributes.
            For the FRBR mapping, we used the already mentioned recommendations of Best Practices
            for TEI in Libraries (<ref type="bibl" target="#hawkins18">Hawkins et al. 2018</ref>),
            in particular those in section 4.1.5, <title level="a"><ref
                target="https://tei-c.org/extra/teiinlibraries/4.0.0/bptl-driver.html#frbr">The TEI
                Header and FRBR</ref></title>,<note><ptr
                target="https://tei-c.org/extra/teiinlibraries/4.0.0/bptl-driver.html#frbr"
              />.</note> which recommends that FRBR information is encoded in a
              <gi>listRelation</gi> element within <gi>sourceDesc</gi>. Unlike the original AKN
            identification element, <gi>listRelation</gi> contains a simple list of relation
            elements, so these must also specify the relation between the particular piece of data
            and the fact that it belongs to the FRBR <soCalled>work</soCalled>,
              <soCalled>expression</soCalled>, or <soCalled>manifestation</soCalled>. These and
            other formalized relations are taken from the formal vocabularies of W3C (for RDF and
            OWL) and (via purl.org) of Dublin Core and vocab.org.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="rdf">
          <head>RDF</head>
          <p>The Resource Description Framework (<ref target="https://www.w3.org/RDF/"
              >RDF</ref><note>Last updated February 25, 2014, <ptr target="https://www.w3.org/RDF/"
              />.</note>) is a W3C specification and a standard model for computer-processable data
            interchange on the web. It is also the base format for modeling information in the
            context of Linked Open Data (LOD), an influential model for linking data on the web.
            While most LOD datasets do not focus on language data, there does exist the <ref
              target="http://linguistic-lod.org/llod-cloud">Linguistic Linked Open Data Cloud</ref>
              (LLOD<note>Open Linguistics Working Group, <title level="u">The Linguistic Linked Open
                Data Cloud Diagram</title> (draft), accessed January 13, 2022, <ptr
                target="http://linguistic-lod.org/llod-cloud"/>.</note>) initiative, which is
            explicitly aimed at language resources and is active, for example, in the scope of the
            COST Action <ref target="https://nexuslinguarum.eu/">NexusLinguarum</ref>,
              <soCalled>European network for Web-centred linguistic data
              science</soCalled>.<note>Nexus Linguarum website, accessed January 13, 2022, <ptr
                target="https://nexuslinguarum.eu/"/>; see also <title level="u"
              >Description</title>, CA18209 – European Network for Web-centred Linguistic Data
              Science (Brussels: COST: European Cooperation in Science &amp; Technology), accessed
              January 13, 2022, <ptr target="https://www.cost.eu/actions/CA18209/"/>.</note> RDF/LOD
            has also been used for modeling parliamentary debates, in particular the Debates of the
            European Parliament as Open Data (<ref type="bibl" target="#aggelen17">Aggelen et al.
              2017</ref>).</p>
          <p>Again, the question is, why not use RDF to encode parliamentary corpora, rather than
            developing a TEI-based solution? Partially it is the community addressed by
            Parla-CLARIN: while LOD is targeted at computer scientists and assumes a
            machine-processable and -linked World Wide Web, TEI addresses mostly researchers from
            the digital humanities and models internally complete resources, while XML is also more
            popular than RDF in the NLP community. In practical terms, RDF data are
            machine-processable but hardly human-readable, and highly connected to external data
            sources; TEI documents, in contrast, are relatively self-explanatory, especially after
            some exposure to the TEI Guidelines, can be edited in any XML editor, and are mostly
            self-contained. Furthermore, while LLOD is indeed focused on language data, it has so
            far been used mostly to encode lexical resources, and its treatment of corpora has so
            far been concerned only with encoding linguistic annotations (<ref type="bibl"
              target="#declerck20">Declerck et al. 2020</ref>). Detailed encodings of particular
            types of language resources are thus still lacking, and the same can be said for RDF
            attempts at encoding parliamentary debates, which model only rather shallow aspects of
            such data.</p>
          <p>Our position is that RDF could be a useful downstream encoding for exploiting such
            corpora, and it would be a worthwhile exercise to develop a TEI-to-RDF conversion. Some
            prior work does exist on this topic (<ref type="bibl" target="#chiarcos19">Chiarcos and
              Ionov 2019</ref>) and the best way seems to be to use RDFa attributes
            <att>about</att>, <att>property</att>, and <att>resource</att> on TEI elements.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="conclusions">
        <head>Conclusions</head>
        <p>In this paper we have given an overview and presented the motivation and justification
          for developing a proposal for a standard interchange encoding scheme for corpora of
          parliamentary proceedings meant for scholarly investigations. This scheme is currently a
          straightforward customization of the TEI Guidelines, with the majority of the effort
          having gone into the writing of the prose guidelines of the Parla-CLARIN recommendations
          and into developing the conversion from Akoma Ntoso to Parla-CLARIN. We have not included
          examples of the encoding, as these are readily available on the GitHub documentation page
          of the project, and large Parla-CLARIN encoded corpora are openly available.</p>
        <p>Apart from the siParl 2.0 corpus mentioned above (<ptr type="crossref"
            target="#introduction #overview"/>), the recommendations have already been used to
          encode the Czech (<ref type="bibl" target="#hladka20">Hladka, Kopp, and Straňák
          2020</ref>) and Icelandic (<ref type="bibl" target="#steingrimsson20">Steingrímsson,
            Barkarson, and Örnólfsson 2020</ref>) parliamentary corpora. Furthermore, the ParlaMint
            project<note>See <bibl><author>Maciej Ogrodniczuk</author> and <author>Petya
                Osenova</author>, <title level="u">ParlaMint: Towards Comparable Parliamentary
                Corpora</title>, accessed January 13, 2022, <ptr
                target="https://www.clarin.eu/content/parlamint"/>.</bibl></note> has so far
          compiled four comparable Parla-CLARIN encoded parliamentary corpora (Bulgarian, Croatian,
          Polish, and Slovenian) containing sessions from 2015 to 2020 with about 20 million words
          each (<ref type="bibl" target="#erjavec20">Erjavec et al. 2020</ref>). In all four cases,
          the corpora are based on previously compiled corpora (<ref type="bibl" target="#osenova12"
            >Osenova and Simov 2012</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#dobranic19">Dobranić, Ljubešić,
            and Erjavec 2019</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#ogrodniczuk20">Ogrodniczuk and Nitoń
            2020</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#pancur20b">Pančur et al. 2020</ref>) but reduced
          to include only sessions from 2015 on, extended with the latest sessions, recoded in
          Parla-CLARIN, and linguistically annotated for <ref
            target="https://universaldependencies.org/">Universal Dependencies</ref><note>Accessed
            January 13, 2022, <ptr target="https://universaldependencies.org/"/>.</note> and named
          entities with state-of-the-art tools.</p>
        <p>As we wanted to have corpora that are not only interchangeable but interoperable as well,
          we created a bespoke ParlaMint XML schema directly in RelaxNG – the schema is compatible
          with Parla-CLARIN as it validates a subset of documents that would be validated against
          Parla-CLARIN. We produced common scripts that can convert any of the four corpora to plain
          text, to CoNLL-U format as used by the Universal Dependencies project, and to vertical
          format as used by the <ref target="http://cwb.sourceforge.net/">CWB</ref><note>The IMS
            Open Corpus Workbench (CWB), last modified March 30, 2021, <ptr
              target="http://cwb.sourceforge.net/"/>.</note> and <ref
            target="http://www.sketchengine.eu/">Sketch Engine</ref><note>Accessed January 13, 2022,
              <ptr target="http://www.sketchengine.eu/"/>.</note> (<ref type="bibl"
            target="#kilgarriff14">Kilgarriff et al. 2014</ref>) concordancers, as well as to
          extract complete speech metadata into TSV files.</p>
        <p>In order for Parla-CLARIN to achieve its goal of becoming a widely recognized encoding
          format for corpora of parliamentary proceedings, significant work remains to be done. On
          the basis of the lessons learned in creating ParlaMint, we plan to revise the prose
          recommendations and to write a more prescriptive TEI ODD that will allow, as much as
          possible, only elements, attributes, and content models that are in line with the
          recommendations. Furthermore, we plan to change the examples given in the schema
          specification from the default ones in the TEI Guidelines to ones taken or adapted from
          the collected parliamentary corpora.</p>
        <p>Second, as we have already done for ParlaMint, we plan to add to the GitHub Parla-CLARIN
          project more down-conversion scripts with which we would increase the usability of the
          Parla-CLARIN corpora. As mentioned, work also needs to be done to develop a conversion to
          RDF.</p>
        <p>Last, but not least, one of the great benefits of Git is the ability to support
          collaborative work, be it through posting issues, or through using pull requests to
          incorporate changes. While the community has not so far made use of these options, we hope
          that Parla-CLARIN will eventually become a collaborative effort of those interested in
          compiling parliamentary corpora.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="aggelen17"><author>Aggelen, Astrid van</author>, <author>Laura
              Hollink</author>, <author>Max Kemman</author>, <author>Martijn Kleppe</author>, and
              <author>Henri Beunders</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">The Debates of
              the European Parliament as Linked Open Data.</title>
            <title level="j">Semantic Web – Interoperability, Usability, Applicability.</title> Vol.
              <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>, No. <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>.
              <publisher>IOS Press</publisher>. Revised version submitted January 21, 2016. Preprint
            available at <ptr target="http://www.semantic-web-journal.net/system/files/swj1300.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="barbaresi18"><author>Barbaresi, Adrien</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title
              level="a">A Corpus of German Political Speeches from the 21st Century.</title> In
              <title level="m">Proceedings of the Eleventh International Conference on Language
              Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2018)</title>, edited by <editor>Nicoletta
              Calzolari</editor>, <editor>Khalid Choukri</editor>, <editor>Christopher
              Cieri</editor>, <editor>Thierry Declerck</editor>, <editor>Sara Goggi</editor>,
              <editor>Koiti Hasida</editor>, <editor>Hitoshi Isahara</editor>, et al., <biblScope
              unit="page">792–97</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>European
              Language Resources Association (ELRA)</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2018/summaries/324.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="barbaresi19"><author>Barbaresi, Adrien</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title
              level="m">German Political Speeches Corpus and Visualization</title>. <edition>4th
              release</edition>, June 17, 2019. <ptr target="https://politische-reden.eu/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bayley04"><author>Bayley, Paul</author>. <date>2004</date>. <title level="a"
              >Introduction: The Whys and Wherefores of Analyzing Parliamentary Discourse.</title>
            In <title level="m">Cross-Cultural Perspectives on Parliamentary Discourse</title>,
            edited by <editor>Paul Bayley</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">1–44</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>: <publisher>John Benjamins
            Publishing</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="blatte18"><author>Blätte, Andreas</author>, and <author>Andre
              Blessing</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">The GermaParl Corpus of
              Parliamentary Protocols.</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings of the Eleventh
              International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2018)</title>,
            edited by <editor>Nicoletta Calzolari</editor>, <editor>Khalid Choukri</editor>,
              <editor>Christopher Cieri</editor>, <editor>Thierry Declerck</editor>, <editor>Sara
              Goggi</editor>, <editor>Koiti Hasida</editor>, <editor>Hitoshi Isahara</editor>, et
            al., <biblScope unit="page">810–16</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>European Language Resources Association (ELRA)</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2018/summaries/1024.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cheng15"><author>Cheng, Jennifer E</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title
              level="a">Islamophobia, Muslimophobia or Racism? Parliamentary Discourses on Islam and
              Muslims in Debates on the Minaret Ban in Switzerland.</title>
            <title level="j">Discourse &amp; Society</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">562–86</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.1177/0957926515581157</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="chiarcos19"><author>Chiarcos, Christian</author>, and <author>Max
              Ionov</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title level="u">Linking the TEI: Approaches,
              Limitations, Use Cases.</title> Paper presented at Digital Humanities Conference,
            Utrecht, July 9–12, 2019. <ptr
              target="https://dev.clariah.nl/files/dh2019/boa/0910.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dargis18"><author>Darģis, Roberts</author>, <author>Ilze Auziņa</author>,
              <author>Uldis Bojārs</author>, <author>Pēteris Paikens</author>, and <author>Artūrs
              Znotiņš</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">Annotation of the Corpus of the
              Saeima with Multilingual Standards.</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings of the
              LREC2018 Workshop ParlaCLARIN: Creating and Using Parliamentary Corpora</title>,
            edited by <editor>Darja Fišer</editor>, <editor>Maria Eskevich</editor>, and
              <editor>Franciska de Jong</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">39–42</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>European Language Resources
              Association</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://lrec-conf.org/workshops/lrec2018/W2/summaries/21_W2.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="declerck20"><author>Declerck, Thierry</author>, <author>John
            McCrae</author>, <author>Matthias Hartung</author>, <author>Jorge Gracia</author>,
              <author>Christian Chiarcos</author>, <author>Elena Montiel</author>, <author>Philipp
              Cimiano</author>, et al. <date>2020</date>. <title level="m">Recent Developments for
              the Linguistic Linked Open Data Infrastructure</title>. Geneva: Zenodo. doi:<idno
              type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.3934626</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dijk10"><author>Dijk, Teun A. van</author>
            <date>2010</date>. <title level="a">Political Identities in Parliamentary
              Debates.</title> In <title level="m">European Parliaments under Scrutiny: Discourse
              Strategies and Interaction Practices</title>, edited by <editor>Cornelia
            Ilie</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">29–56</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="diwersy20"><author>Diwersy, Sascha</author>, and <author>Giancarlo
              Luxardo</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">Querying a Large Annotated
              Corpus of Parliamentary Debates.</title>
            <title level="m">Proceedings of the LREC 2020 Workshop on Creating, Using and Linking of
              Parliamentary Corpora with Other Types of Political Discourse (ParlaCLARIN
            II)</title>, edited by <editor>Darja Fišer</editor>, <editor>Maria Eskevich</editor>,
            and <editor>Franciska de Jong</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">75–79</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>European Language Resources Association
              (ELRA)</publisher>. <ptr
              target="https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/2020.parlaclarin-1.13"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dobranic19"><author>Dobranić, Filip</author>, <author>Nikola
              Ljubešić</author>, and <author>Tomaž Erjavec</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title
              level="m">Croatian Parliamentary Corpus ParlaMeter-hr 1.0</title>. Slovenian language
            resource repository CLARIN.SI. <pubPlace>Ljubljana</pubPlace>: <publisher>Jožef Stefan
              Institute</publisher>. <ptr target="http://hdl.handle.net/11356/1209"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="eide19"><author>Eide, Stian Rødven</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title
              level="a">The Swedish PoliGraph: A Semantic Graph for Argument Mining of Swedish
              Parliamentary Data.</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings of the 6th Workshop on
              Argument Mining</title>, edited by <editor>Benno Stein</editor> and <editor>Henning
              Wachsmuth</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">52–57</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Florence</pubPlace>: <publisher>Association for Computational
              Linguistics</publisher>. <ptr target="https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/W19-4506"/>;
              doi:<idno type="DOI">10.18653/v1/W19-4506</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="erjavec20"><author>Erjavec, Tomaž</author>, <author>Vladislava
              Grigorova</author>, <author>Nikola Ljubešić</author>, <author>Maciej
              Ogrodniczuk</author>, <author>Petya Osenova</author>, <author>Andrej Pančur</author>,
              <author>Michał Rudolf</author>, and <author>Kiril Simov</author>. <date>2020</date>.
              <title level="m">Multilingual Comparable Corpora of Parliamentary Debates ParlaMint
              1.0.</title> Slovenian language resource repository CLARIN.SI. CLARIN ERIC. <ptr
              target="https://hdl.handle.net/11356/1345"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fiser18"><author>Fišer, Darja</author>, and <author>Jakob Lenardič</author>.
              <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">CLARIN Corpora for Parliamentary Discourse
              Research.</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings of the LREC2018 Workshop
              ParlaCLARIN: Creating and Using Parliamentary Corpora</title>, edited by <editor>Darja
              Fišer</editor>, <editor>Maria Eskevich</editor>, and <editor>Franciska de
              Jong</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">2–7</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>European Language Resources Association</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://lrec-conf.org/workshops/lrec2018/W2/summaries/14_W2.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fiser20"><author>Fišer, Darja</author>, and <author>Kristina Pahor de
              Maiti</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">Voices of the Parliament.</title>
            <title level="j">Modern Languages Open</title>, 2020 issue <biblScope unit="issue"
              >1</biblScope>: article 46. doi:<idno type="DOI">10.3828/mlo.v0i0.295</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hansen18"><author>Hansen, Dorte Haltrup</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title
              level="m">The Danish Parliament Corpus 2009–2017, v1</title>. CLARIN-DK-UCPH Centre
            Repository. <pubPlace>Copenhagen</pubPlace>: Centre for Language Technology, NorS,
              <publisher>University of Copenhagen</publisher>; <publisher>The Danish
              Parliament</publisher>. <ptr target="http://hdl.handle.net/20.500.12115/8"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hawkins18"><editor>Hawkins, Kevin</editor>, <editor>Michelle
            Dalmau</editor>, <editor>Elli Mylonas</editor>, and <editor>Syd Bauman</editor>, eds.
              <date>2018</date>. <title level="u">Best Practices for TEI in Libraries: A Guide for
              Mass Digitization, Automated Workflows, and Promotion of Interoperability with XML
              Using the TEI</title>. <edition>Version 4.0.0</edition>. Last updated September 10,
            2018. <ptr target="http://purl.org/TEI/teiinlibraries"/>; <ptr
              target="https://tei-c.org/extra/teiinlibraries/4.0.0/bptl-driver.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hirst14"><author>Hirst, Graeme</author>, <author>Vanessa Wei Feng</author>,
              <author>Christopher Cochrane</author>, and <author>Nona Naderi</author>.
              <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">Argumentation, Ideology, and Issue Framing in
              Parliamentary Discourse.</title> In <title level="m">ArgNLP 2014: Proceedings of the
              Workshop on Frontiers and Connections between Argumentation Theory and Natural
              Language Processing</title>, edited by <editor>Elena Cabrio</editor>, <editor>Serena
              Villata</editor>, and <editor>Adam Wyner</editor>. <ptr
              target="https://dblp.org/rec/conf/argnlp/2014"/>; <ptr
              target="http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-1341/paper6.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hladka20"><author>Hladka, Barbora</author>, <author>Matyáš Kopp</author>,
            and <author>Pavel Straňák</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">Compiling Czech
              Parliamentary Stenographic Protocols into a Corpus.</title> In <title level="m"
              >Proceedings of the LREC 2020 Workshop on Creating, Using and Linking of Parliamentary
              Corpora with Other Types of Political Discourse (ParlaCLARIN II)</title>, edited by
              <editor>Darja Fišer</editor>, <editor>Maria Eskevich</editor>, and <editor>Franciska
              de Jong</editor>, pp. <biblScope unit="page">18–22</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>European Language Resources
              Association</publisher>. <ptr
              target="https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/2020.parlaclarin-1.4"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hughes15"><author>Hughes, Lorna M.</author>, <author>Paul S. Ell</author>,
              <author>Gareth A. G. Knight</author>, and <author>Milena Dobreva</author>.
              <date>2015</date>. <title level="a">Assessing and Measuring Impact of a Digital
              Collection in the Humanities: An Analysis of the SPHERE (Stormont Parliamentary
              Hansards: Embedded in Research and Education) Project.</title>
            <title level="j">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">183–98</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.1093/llc/fqt054</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kilgarriff14"><author>Kilgarriff, Adam</author>, <author>Vít Baisa</author>,
              <author>Jan Bušta</author>, <author>Miloš Jakubíček</author>, <author>Vojtěch
              Kovář</author>, <author>Jan Michelfeit</author>, <author>Pavel Rychlý</author>, and
              <author>Vít Suchomel</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">The Sketch Engine:
              Ten Years On.</title>
            <title level="j">Lexicography: Journal of ASIALEX</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">7–36</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.1007/s40607-014-0009-9</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ljubesic18"><author>Ljubešić, Nikola</author>, <author>Darja Fišer</author>,
              <author>Tomaž Erjavec</author>, and <author>Filip Dobranić</author>.
            <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">The Parlameter Corpus of Contemporary Slovene
              Parliamentary Proceedings.</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings of the Conference
              on Language Technologies &amp; Digital Humanities</title>, edited by <editor>Darja
              Fišer</editor> and <editor>Andrej Pančur</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >162–67</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Ljubljana, Slovenia</pubPlace>: <publisher>Ljubljana
              University Press</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://nl.ijs.si/jtdh18/proceedings-en.html"/>; <ptr
              target="http://www.sdjt.si/wp/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/JTDH-2018_Ljubesic-et-al_The-Parlameter-corpus-of-contemporary-Slovene-parliamentary-proceedings.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="marx10"><author>Marx, Maarten</author>, and <author>Anne Schuth</author>.
              <date>2010</date>. <title level="a">DutchParl: The Parliamentary Documents in
              Dutch.</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings of the Seventh International Conference
              on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC’10)</title>, edited by <editor>Nicoletta
              Calzolari</editor>, <editor>Khalid Choukri</editor>, <editor>Bente Maegaard</editor>,
              <editor>Joseph Mariani</editor>, <editor>Jan Odijk</editor>, <editor>Stelios
              Piperidis</editor>, <editor>Mike Rosner</editor>, and <editor>Daniel Tapias</editor>,
              <biblScope unit="page">3670–77</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Valletta, Malta</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>European Language Resource Association (ELRA)</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2010/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ogrodniczuk18"><author>Ogrodniczuk, Maciej</author>. <date>2018</date>.
              <title level="a">Polish Parliamentary Corpus.</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings
              of the LREC2018 Workshop ParlaCLARIN: Creating and Using Parliamentary
            Corpora</title>, edited by <editor>Darja Fišer</editor>, <editor>Maria
            Eskevich</editor>, and <editor>Franciska de Jong</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >15–19</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>European Language Resources
              Association</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://lrec-conf.org/workshops/lrec2018/W2/summaries/11_W2.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ogrodniczuk20"><author>Ogrodniczuk, Maciej</author>, and <author>Bartłomiej
              Nitoń</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">New Developments in the Polish
              Parliamentary Corpus.</title>
            <title level="m">Proceedings of the LREC 2020 Workshop on Creating, Using and Linking of
              Parliamentary Corpora with Other Types of Political Discourse (ParlaCLARIN
            II)</title>, edited by <editor>Darja Fišer</editor>, <editor>Maria Eskevich</editor>,
            and <editor>Franciska de Jong</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">1–4</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>European Language Resources Association
              (ELRA)</publisher>. <ptr
              target="https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/2020.parlaclarin-1.1"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="osenova12"><author>Osenova, Petya</author>, and <author>Kiril
            Simov</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">The Political Speech Corpus of
              Bulgarian.</title>
            <title level="m">Proceedings of the Eighth International Conference on Language
              Resources and Evaluation (LREC’12)</title>, edited by <editor>Nicoletta
              Calzolari</editor>, <editor>Khalid Choukri</editor>, <editor>Thierry
            Declerck</editor>, <editor>Mehmet Uğur Doğan</editor>, <editor>Bente Maegaard</editor>,
              <editor>Joseph Mariani</editor>, <editor>Asuncion Moreno</editor>, et al., <biblScope
              unit="page">1744–47</biblScope>. <publisher>European Language Resources Association
              (ELRA)</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2012/pdf/956_Paper.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pancur20"><author>Pančur, Andrej</author>, and <author>Tomaž
              Erjavec</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">The siParl Corpus of Slovenian
              Parliamentary Proceedings.</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings of the LREC 2020
              Workshop on Creating, Using and Linking of Parliamentary Corpora with Other Types of
              Political Discourse (ParlaCLARIN II)</title>, edited by <editor>Darja Fišer</editor>,
              <editor>Maria Eskevich</editor>, and <editor>Franciska de Jong</editor>, <biblScope
              unit="page">28–34</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>European
              Language Resources Association (ELRA)</publisher>. <ptr
              target="https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/2020.parlaclarin-1.6"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pancur20b"><author>Pančur, Andrej</author>, <author>Tomaž Erjavec</author>,
              <author>Mihael Ojsteršek</author>, <author>Mojca Šorn</author>, and <author>Neja Blaj
              Hribar</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="m">Slovenian Parliamentary Corpus
              (1990–2018) siParl 2.0</title>. Slovenian language resource repository CLARIN.SI.
            Institute of Contemporary History. <ptr target="http://hdl.handle.net/11356/1300"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pancur19"><author>Pančur, Andrej</author>, <author>Tomaž Erjavec</author>,
              <author>Mihael Ojsteršek</author>, <author>Mojca Šorn</author> and <author>Neja Blaj
              Hribar</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title level="m">Slovenian parliamentary corpus
              siParl 1.0 (1990–2018)</title>, Slovenian language resource repository CLARIN.SI.
            Institute of Contemporary History. <ptr target="http://hdl.handle.net/11356/1236"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pancur16"><author>Pančur, Andrej</author>, and <author>Mojca Šorn</author>.
            2016. <title level="a">Smart Big Data: Use of Slovenian Parliamentary Papers in Digital
              History.</title>
            <title level="j">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino / Contributions to Contemporary
              History</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">130–46</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="https://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/193"/>; doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.51663/pnz.56.3.09</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pancur17"><author>Pančur, Andrej</author>, <abbr>Mojca Šorn</abbr> and
              <abbr>Tomaž Erjavec</abbr>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="m">Slovenian
              parliamentary corpus SlovParl 2.0</title>, Slovenian language resource repository
            CLARIN.SI. Institute of Contemporary History. <ptr
              target="http://hdl.handle.net/11356/1167"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="prazak12"><author>Pražák, Aleš</author>, and <author>Luboš Šmídl</author>.
              <date>2012</date>. <title level="m">Czech Parliament Meetings</title>.
            LINDAT/CLARIAH-CZ Digital Library at the Institute of Formal and Applied Linguistics
            (ÚFAL), Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Charles University. <ptr
              target="http://hdl.handle.net/11858/00-097C-0000-0005-CF9C-4"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rheault16"><author>Rheault, Ludovic</author>, <author>Kaspar
            Beelen</author>, <author>Christopher Cochrane</author>, and <author>Graeme
              Hirst</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">Measuring Emotion in Parliamentary
              Debates with Automated Textual Analysis.</title>
            <title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>):
            e0168843. <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0168843"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="steingrimsson20"><author>Steingrímsson, Steinþór</author>, <author>Starkaður
              Barkarson</author>, and <author>Gunnar Thor Örnólfsson</author>. <date>2020</date>.
              <title level="a">IGC-Parl: Icelandic Corpus of Parliamentary Proceedings.</title> In
              <title level="m">Proceedings of the LREC 2020 Workshop on Creating, Using and Linking
              of Parliamentary Corpora with Other Types of Political Discourse (ParlaCLARIN
              II)</title>, edited by <editor>Darja Fišer</editor>, <editor>Maria Eskevich</editor>,
            and <editor>Franciska de Jong</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">11–17</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>European Language Resources
              Association</publisher>. <ptr
              target="https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/2020.parlaclarin-1.3"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="truan16"><author>Truan, Naomi</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="m"
              >Parliamentary Debates on Europe at the Deutscher Bundestag (1998–2015)</title>
            [Corpus]. ORTOLANG (Open Resources and TOols for LANGuage). <ptr
              target="https://hdl.handle.net/11403/de-parl"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="wissik18"><author>Wissik, Tanja</author>, and <author>Hannes
            Pirker</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">ParlAT Beta Corpus of Austrian
              Parliamentary Records.</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings of the LREC2018
              Workshop ParlaCLARIN: Creating and Using Parliamentary Corpora</title>, edited by
              <editor>Darja Fišer</editor>, <editor>Maria Eskevich</editor>, and <editor>Franciska
              de Jong</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">20–23</biblScope>.
            <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>European Language Resources Association
              (ELRA)</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://lrec-conf.org/workshops/lrec2018/W2/summaries/2_W2.html"/>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
