<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-barabuccietal-196-source.xml 1114 2022-05-12 07:21:36Z tiago.sousa-garcia $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI.internal">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Signs of the Times: Medieval Punctuation, Diplomatic Encoding and
               Rendition</title>
            <!-- author information in separate <author> elements per author -->
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Elisa</forename>
                  <surname>Cugliana</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Dr. Elisa Cugliana is currently working at the <orgName>Cologne Center
                     for eHumanities (University of Cologne, Germany)</orgName>, where she is
                  involved in the Text+ consortium of the <orgName>German National Research Data
                     Infrastructure (NFDI)</orgName>. She completed her PhD in Germanic philology
                  and digital editing in February 2022 with a joint dissertation project between
                     <orgName>Ca’ Foscari University of Venice</orgName> and the <orgName>University
                     of Cologne</orgName>. For her PhD, she edited a medieval German version of
                  Marco Polo’s travel account, concentrating in particular on a computational
                  approach to the normalisation of the texts. Among her research interests are
                  indeed (computational) scholarly editing, Germanic philology and medieval
                  textuality (with a focus on the so-called <soCalled>sortes</soCalled> texts), as
                  well as diachronic linguistics and the Cimbrian language of Northern
                  Italy.</affiliation>
               <email>elisa.cugliana@unive.it</email>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Gioele</forename>
                  <surname>Barabucci</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Gioele Barabucci is an <roleName>associate professor in Computer
                     Science</roleName> at the <orgName>Department of Design of the Norwegian
                     University of Science and Technology (NTNU)</orgName>. He received his PhD in
                  Computer Science from the University of Bologna and later went on to pursue his
                  research interests in the digital humanities as a Marie Curie Experienced
                  Researcher and as a research fellow at the Cologne Center for eHumanities. His
                  main research topics are the design of knowledge and the evolution of information.
                  Concretely, this means studying comparison algorithms, devising versioning
                  systems, and formalizing document models, as well as researching ontologies, legal
                  documents, and multilingual systems.</affiliation>
               <email>gioele.barabucci@ntnu.no</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>11/01/2022</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor role="guest">Georg Vogeler</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="14">Selected Papers from the 2019 TEI Conference</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for
               journals in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking
               to publish full-text articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>normalization</term>
               <term>punctuation</term>
               <term>automated workflow</term>
               <term>pipelines</term>
               <term>computable edition</term>
               <term>formalization of editorial rules</term>
               <term>reproducibility</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="TSG" when="2022-05-20">Further author corrections</change>
         <change who="TSG" when="2022-05-11">Author corrections</change>
         <change who="TSG" when="2022-01-11">Initial encoding</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p>Digitally managing punctuation in the editions of medieval manuscripts is one of
               those issues that initially looks like a minor detail, but later reveals itself as a
               tangled web of problems spanning from computer science (how to represent punctuation
               signs?) to philology (what types of signs exist?) through epistemology (is the
               processing of punctuation a mere technical transformation or a valuable part of the
               scholarship?). The aim of this paper is to address the theoretical aspects of these
               questions and their practical implications, providing a couple of solutions fitting
               the paradigms and the technologies of the TEI.</p>
            <p>This paper describes how we dealt with the encoding and transformation of the
               punctuation in the Early New High German edition of Marco Polo’s travel account.
               Technically, we implemented a set of general rules (as XSLT templates) plus various
               exceptions (as descriptive instructions in XML attributes), and applied them in an
               automated fashion (using XProc pipelines). In addition to this, we discuss the
               philological foundation of this method and, contextually, we address the topic of the
               transformation of a single original source into different transcriptions: from a
               highly diplomatic edition to an interpretative one, going through a spectrum of
               intermediate levels of normalization. We also reflect on the separation between
               transcription and analysis, as well as on the role of the editor when the edition is
               the output of a semi-automated process.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <!-- text divisions, each with an @xml:id and <head> -->
         <div xml:id="introduction">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Since its inception, the critical edition of the Early New High German (ENHG) Marco
                  Polo<note>A philological introduction to the project can be found in <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#cugliana2019">Cugliana (2019)</ref>.</note> (version
                  DI<note>Originally <hi rend="italic">DI</hi> stood for <term>Deutsche
                     Inkunabel</term>, but nowadays it just denotes the Early New High German
                  version of Marco Polo’s work, preserved in five witnesses.</note> of the <title
                  level="m">Devisement dou Monde</title>) has been planned as an edition with
               multiple layers. For each witness the editor would manually edit a master TEI file
               and, from that file, three edition levels would be generated, each at a different
               level of closeness to the source: a purely diplomatic edition (where aspects like
               colors, letter sizes, glyph variance, and layout are preserved), a fully
               interpretative edition (presenting a more modernized text), and a semidiplomatic
               edition (with a text which still maintains relevant features from the source, but
               which is already more readable and fluent, also thanks to a minimal system of
               punctuation).</p>
            <p>These issues quickly arose while editing:</p>
            <list rend="ordered">
               <item>the master TEI file became too big and its structure too complex, thus too hard
                  to navigate and maintain, even when using advanced XML editors such as Oxygen
                  XML;</item>
               <item>normalizing punctuation revealed itself as a complex task that required
                  profound changes to the structure of the edited text.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The first issue, the overgrowth of the master TEI file, is due to the need to
               transcribe and encode three variants of each word of the witness (one for each level
               of edition). Not only is this process extremely time-consuming, but it also requires
               the addition of a lot of markup (e.g., <gi scheme="TEI">choice</gi> elements) that
               stiffens the text hierarchy and makes it cumbersome to encode complex linguistic
               phenomena or critical annotations that span multiple words.</p>
            <p>The second issue, the complexity of normalizing punctuation, emerged from the
               combination of two factors:</p>
            <list rend="ordered">
               <item>it was not possible to find an underlying system governing the use of
                  punctuation in the source;</item>
               <item>using the standard approach to normalization in TEI (using <gi scheme="TEI"
                     >choice</gi> with, e.g., <att>orig</att> and <att>reg</att>) turned out to be
                  impracticable for two main reasons: the verbosity of the encoding and the lack of
                  correspondences between the medieval and the modern systems (<att>orig</att> would
                  very often be empty), both complicated by the presence of three levels of edition
                  (diplomatic, semidiplomatic, and interpretative).</item>
            </list>
            <p>To address these issues, we devised and implemented a novel approach that made it
               possible for a single scholar to edit each witness in three different levels of
               edition in the allotted time span of eighteen months, while keeping the master TEI
               file lean in its structure and readable even by scholars who are not well versed in
               XML technologies.</p>
            <p>The key innovation of this approach is the encoding of many textual phenomena (and of
               how these phenomena should be handled) as formal, machine-readable rules, separate
               from the edited text. An automated workflow is then used to process the master file
               according to the rules and to produce each of the three levels of edition, depending
               on which set of rules has been selected. In contrast with other similar systems,
               there is a clear distinction between rules and exceptions in our approach. This is
               particularly important in the ENHG Marco Polo edition because the language it is
               written in has never been standardized and thus the system of rules has been
               organically derived during the editorial work (as described in detail in section
               2).</p>
            <p>This paper provides an overview of our approach (section 3) and shows how our
               approach addresses both issues. In particular we show how normalizing punctuation
               represents a dramatic step beyond the more classical normalization of words. The
               current implementation of our approach, based on XProc and XSLT, is also presented in
               section 3.</p>
            <p>Moving to an editorial workflow with such a level of automation requires a
               reevaluation of the role of the editor, from wordsmith to formalizer of rules (and
               exceptions). In section 4 we discuss how our approach fits the recent
                  <soCalled>edition-as-a-program</soCalled> paradigm and which changes in
               perspective a widespread adoption of this methodology could entail for future
               critical editors.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="background">
            <head>Background and issues</head>
            <div xml:id="marcopolo">
               <head>Marco Polo and ENHG</head>
               <p>The <title level="m">Devisement dou Monde</title> is a travel narrative written by
                  Rustichello da Pisa and Marco Polo, most probably in 1298, while they were both in
                  prison, in Genoa. It narrates Marco Polo’s travels to and within the Eastern
                  World: the traveler was a Venetian who, following his father and uncle on a
                  business trip to Asia, ended up spending almost twenty-five years in the East, at
                  the court of Kublai Khan. The account of his journey is preserved in more than 140
                  manuscripts which were produced over two centuries. The original version composed
                  by the two prison companions is unfortunately lost. The text was translated into
                  German twice during the Middle Ages. While one of these translations (version VG3)
                  was already edited by <ref type="bibl" target="#tscharner1935">Tscharner
                     (1935)</ref>, version DI is being edited for the first time in our project,
                  which serves as the backdrop for the present study.</p>
               <p>Under the name ENHG Marco Polo we refer to an edition project including the three
                  main witnesses of version DI of the <title level="m">Devisement dou Monde</title>,
                  all written in Early New High German: a manuscript (München, BSB Cgm 696), an
                  incunabulum (München, BSB-Ink P-671), and a short fragment (München, BSB Cgm 252).
                  These three witnesses are considered the most important from a stemmatic point of
                  view (<ref type="bibl" target="#cugliana2019">Cugliana 2019</ref>) and all date
                  back to the second half of the fifteenth century.</p>
               <p>The output of the ENHG Marco Polo project is not a critical edition which aims at
                  presenting a reconstructed text, but rather a collection of editions, in which
                  each witness is edited separately: for each witness, three different editions will
                  be produced, one for each of three targeted levels of rendition: diplomatic,
                  semidiplomatic, and interpretative. Because each witness is treated as a separate
                  entity, no critical apparatus in the traditional sense will be produced, and in
                  its stead, the edited texts will be accompanied by a set of
                     commentaries.<note>These commentaries are not a critical apparatus in the
                     traditional sense (see <ref type="bibl" target="#maceetal2015">Macé and Roelli
                        2015, s.v. Apparatus</ref>) as no critical text was established for this
                     edition: the reasons for this choice depend on the history of the transmission
                     of the text and are illustrated in <ref type="bibl" target="#cugliana2019"
                        >Cugliana (2019)</ref>.</note> The commentaries will, in part, be shared by
                  all editions (for example, the commentaries on the named entities, which are
                  central to Marco Polo research), and, in part, be edition-specific (for example,
                  the edition of the incunabulum will contain a commentary on the style of the
                  writing typical of the first printed texts, while the edition of the fragment will
                  contain a description of the conservative traits of the language it is written
                     in<note>The conservative traits of the language in which these works are
                     written have already been noted by <ref type="bibl" target="#benedetto1928"
                        >Benedetto (1928)</ref>, one of the most important scholars in the
                     field.</note>).</p>
               <p>Our use of the term <term>edition</term> matches that of the Italian school of
                  textual scholarship,<note>See for instance <ref type="bibl" target="#buzzoni2016"
                        >Buzzoni (2016)</ref>, and the bibliography cited there, for an introduction
                     to the Italian school of thought, and the works by other philologists such as
                     Gianfranco Contini, Alfredo Stussi, Domenico de Robertis, Giorgio Pasquali,
                     Raul Mordenti, and Paolo Trovato, to mention a few.</note> according to which
                  the term edition refers to a specific rendition of the text (diplomatic,
                  interpretative, etc.). This use of the word <term>edition</term> also conforms to
                  the definition of scholarly edition provided by <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#sahle2016">Sahle (2016, 23)</ref>, although the scholar uses this term
                  to include all parts of an edition project: the act of rendering the text in, say,
                  an interpretative way, is <foreign xml:lang="de">erschließend</foreign>
                  (revealing, opening up to the text) in its nature, as some specific aspects of the
                  text are presented in such a way that the reader is granted more informed access
                  to them.</p>
               <p>The edition will be published online using a specifically tailored version of EVT
                  (Edition Visualization Technology<note><quote source="#quote1">A light-weight,
                        open source tool specifically designed to create digital editions from
                        XML-encoded texts</quote> (<ref type="bibl" target="#delturco2013"
                        xml:id="quote1">Rosselli Del Turco et al. 2013</ref>).</note>) and will
                  present, on the one hand, each witness in its continuum from facsimile to multiple
                  levels of normalization and, on the other hand, the three main witnesses in
                  synopsis. From each module of the edition and from each of the texts composing the
                  editorial project it will be possible to access a twofold commentary: specific
                  notes referring to the named entities and the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                     >realia</foreign> appearing in the text, and philological notes referring
                  either to all of the three witnesses or to one witness in particular.</p>
               <p>The language in which the three witnesses are written is Early New High German.
                  ENHG represents quite a problematic phase of the German language, beginning with
                  the definition of its time span. As a matter of fact, there have been different
                  proposals for a definition of its periodization (see, for instance, <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#grimm1822">Grimm 1822</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#scherer1878">Scherer 1878</ref>, and <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#wells1990">Wells 1990</ref>), but what is relevant here is that the
                  ENHG phase covers a long time span, going through Gutenberg’s media revolution,
                  which had a huge impact on the written German language (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#bosco2003">Bosco Coletsos 2003, 187–91</ref>). This stage of the
                  German language is extremely diverse, which has quite a few consequences for the
                  scholarly editor approaching the texts written or printed during the period.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="normalization">
               <head>Normalization</head>
               <p><quote source="#quote2">Normalisation takes place when the orthography (or other
                     aspects of the language) of a text is changed in order to make it correspond to
                     a certain standard</quote> (<ref type="bibl" target="#maceetal2015"
                     xml:id="quote2">Macé and Roelli 2015, s.v. <ptr
                        target="https://wiki.helsinki.fi/display/stemmatology/Normalisation"
                  /></ref>).</p>
               <p>The need for normalization in scholarly editions arises from the fact that
                  premodern texts present a high degree of variation when it comes to orthography
                  and punctuation.<note>On the variation characterizing premodern texts see <ref
                        type="bibl" target="#contini2014">Contini (2014✝, 45)</ref> and <ref
                        type="bibl" target="#pierazzo2016">Pierazzo (2016, 41)</ref>. As for
                     punctuation, the following manuals are used as a reference in the present
                     project: <ref type="bibl" target="#parkes1992">Parkes (1992)</ref>, <ref
                        type="bibl" target="#mortara2008">Garavelli (2008)</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                        target="#rinas2017">Rinas (2017)</ref>, and <ref type="bibl"
                        target="#kirchhoff2017">Kirchhoff (2017)</ref>.</note> This clashes with the
                  desire of many scholarly editors to produce readable texts where orthographic,
                  morphological, and dialectal variance have been regularized and eroded. This
                  desire has had different motivations in the history of editorial practice. When
                  philology was still considered an ancillary discipline, the role of the editors
                  was to prepare the texts for historians and literary scholars, who were mainly
                  interested in the contents. Diacritics, for instance, and other linguistic
                  peculiarities were considered on a par with <foreign xml:lang="de">ein verdammtes
                     Unkraut</foreign> (<q>a damned weed</q>) in a tidy flower garden, as Julius
                  Weizsäcker wrote in 1867.<note>As quoted in <ref type="bibl" target="#sahle2013"
                        >Sahle (2013, 1:71)</ref></note>
               </p>
               <p>With Karl Lachmann,<note>For a systematization of Lachmann’s method, see <ref
                        type="bibl" target="#maas1950">Maas (1950)</ref>.</note> normalization
                  became a necessity for philologists themselves: needing to summarize a whole
                  textual tradition in an apparatus at the bottom of the page, it was no longer
                  feasible to take into account all variants and punctuation. Collation, in
                  particular, implies normalization: the establishment of a traditional stemma is
                  based on Leitfehler (<q>guiding errors</q>), not on equivalent variants.<note>But
                     things are different in digital stemmatology: see in this respect <ref
                        type="bibl" target="#andrews2020">Andrews (2020)</ref>.</note> The formal
                  appearance of the reconstructed text (for example, the dialectal variety chosen
                  for the text) would then be given the shape considered to be closest to the
                  language of the author.<note>After a long discussion on the importance of formal
                     variance and on the overlapping between form and content, <ref type="bibl"
                        target="#contini2014" xml:id="quote3">Contini (2014✝, 50)</ref> gives
                     concrete indications on how formal variance should be dealt with in a critical
                     edition: <quote source="#quote3">a parità di condizioni, si adotta
                        costantemente la forma di un testimone, scelto (ma per di solito
                        apoditticamente) per ragioni o di antichità o di congruenza regionale o di
                        sorvegliata organicità.<gap/> Non ci si sottrae all’impressione che la forma
                        passi in seconda linea innanzi alla sostanza</quote> (<quote
                        source="#quote3">all things being equal, one constantly adopts the form of
                        one witness, chosen (but usually apodictically) for reasons either of
                        antiquity, or regional consistency, or surveilled organicity.<gap/> One does
                        not escape the impression that the form is in the second place with respect
                        to the substance</quote>) (our translation).</note> Generally, however, it
                  is commonly assumed that editors of medieval texts are free to decide when, how,
                  and how much their texts should be normalized.<note><quote source="#quote4">The
                        extent of normalisation, as well as the rules followed by the editors,
                        depends on their judgement and the methods they adopt.</quote> (<ref
                        type="bibl" target="#buzzoni2020" xml:id="quote4">Buzzoni 2020,
                     140</ref>)</note>
               </p>
               <p>For many languages the exact procedures used to normalize a text have been
                  established <foreign xml:lang="la">a posteriori</foreign> by historical linguists.
                  For instance, normalized Middle High German was first established by Karl Lachmann
                  (see <ref type="bibl" target="#maas1950">Maas 1950</ref>) and then accepted by the
                  scholarly community.</p>
               <p>However, no such normalization standards currently exist for ENHG. As <ref
                     xml:id="quote5" type="bibl" target="#ebertetal1993">Ebert et al. (1993,
                     7)</ref> write: <quote source="#quote5">Until the sixteenth century and for
                     many aspects also later, there is no variety of Early New High German that
                     <gap/> had a generally accepted and undisputable prestige over all the others
                     and which can, on the basis of such sociolinguistic fact, be considered as a
                     reference variety for synchronic writing and speaking or for diachronic
                     use.</quote><note><quote source="#quote5">Es gibt bis ins 16. Jahrhundert und
                        unter vielen Aspekten selbst darüber hinaus keine Varietät des
                        Frühneuhochdeutschen, die <gap/> ein zeitgenössisch allgemein anerkanntes,
                        unbestreitbar über alle anderen Varietäten hinausragendes Prestige gehabt
                        hätte und der man aufgrund eines solchen sprachsoziologischen Faktums die
                        Funktion einer Leitvariante für synchrones Schreiben und Sprechen und für
                        die Diachronie zuschreiben könnte</quote> [our translation]. This horizontal
                     variation is in fact <foreign xml:lang="de">eines der markantesten Kennzeichen
                        des Frühneuhochdeutschen</foreign> (one of the most distinctive features of
                     Early New High German).</note>
               </p>
               <p>A survey of existing editions of ENHG texts shows that, while internal coherence
                  in normalization practices is desired and documented, not only are normalization
                  standards missing, they are also not actively sought after. Focusing on the
                  Ingelheimer Haderbücher project (<ref type="bibl" target="#marzietalnd">Marzi and
                     Sprenger n.d.</ref>), for instance: although the editors were extremely
                  accurate in outlining their principles for textual transcription, they did not
                  provide any specific bibliographical reference in support of their decisions on
                  how the texts were transcribed and normalized. In fact, they only tangentially
                  address this concern by writing that <quote source="#quote6">for the orthography
                     of the single letters and the creation of the transcriptions we mostly welcomed
                     and observed the suggestions of Germanists, linguists, and
                     paleographers</quote>.<note><quote source="#quote6">Bei der Schreibung der
                        einzelnen Buchstaben wurden vor allem Hinweise von Germanisten,
                        Sprachforschern und Paläographen aufgenommen und bei der Erstellung der
                        Transkription berücksichtigt</quote> [our translation] (<ref xml:id="quote6"
                        type="bibl" target="#marzietalnd">Marzi and Sprenger (n.d.), <title
                           level="a">Richtlinien: Transkription und Register</title>, accessed
                        September 17, 2021</ref>, <ptr
                        target="https://www.haderbuecher.de/projekt/editionsrichtlinien/"/>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>An interesting case is the <title level="m">Frühneuhochdeutsches
                     Wörterbuch</title> (<ref type="bibl" target="#worterbuch">FWB</ref>), a
                  dictionary of ENHG, started in the 1980s and expected to be completed in
                        2027.<note><ptr target="https://fwb-online.de/"/>.</note> The editors of the
                  FWB did propose a set of rules, a necessary precondition for such a large-scale
                  project. The principle at the basis of the orthography chosen for the lemmata in
                  the dictionary is a phonological one: after having established an ideal
                  phonological system of ENHG, the corresponding graphemes were chosen. The editors
                  themselves, however, state very clearly that such a systematization represents
                  only an ideal (in their words <foreign xml:lang="de">ausgezeichnet</foreign>)
                     language.<note>In their words, the lemmata appear in <q>einer ausgezeichneten
                        Wortbildungsform in ausgezeichneter Lautung und ausgezeichneter Graphie.
                        Diese Form muß alle Vorkommensformen in einem bestimmten Sinne
                        repräsentieren.</q>
                     <ptr
                        target="https://fwb-online.de/einleitung/positionen-des-woerterbuchartikels-i-das-lemma"
                     />.</note> We are not using the FWB as a reference for our normalization,
                  first, because this ideal language is very distant from the actual language and
                  orthography we find in our witnesses, and, second, because the dictionary is still
                  not complete (many letters are completely missing, and many are incomplete: only
                  six letters of the alphabet are fully represented).</p>
               <div xml:id="normalisationchoices">
                  <head>Normalization Choices Are Editorial Choices</head>
                  <p>For a scholar editing a medieval text, <soCalled>to normalize</soCalled> means
                     making a series of editorial decisions.<note>For a guide on how to normalize
                        medieval texts, see <ref type="bibl" target="#stussi1988">Stussi (1988,
                           161)</ref>, and for a concrete example of normalization, see <ref
                           type="bibl" target="#renzietal2009">Renzi and Andreose (2009,
                           272–82)</ref>.</note> Some examples of the kinds of decisions that need
                     to be made are:</p>
                  <list rend="bulleted">
                     <item>how to substitute modern equivalents for original textual features (e.g.,
                        if and when to substitute the modern <term>s</term> for the <term>long s
                           [ſ]</term>);</item>
                     <item>how to change certain signs to others (e.g., when to turn a
                           <term>virgula</term> into a comma, when to turn it into a full stop, and
                        when to eliminate it completely);</item>
                     <item>when to omit features that are today considered unnecessary (such as
                        decorations);</item>
                     <item>when to add new features that were not yet fully developed in medieval
                        times (like capitalization rules or spaces between different words or
                        sections of text).</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>To an external observer, the act of normalizing a text can be seen as a sort of
                     correction being imparted on the text. Scholars, in this respect, have often
                     distinguished between <soCalled>normalization</soCalled> and
                        <soCalled>correction</soCalled>, between mechanical and less mechanical
                     interventions: the former, normalization, being seen as an almost objective
                     process, while the latter, correction, often considered as a subjective act
                     that involves the editor’s <term>iudicium</term>.<note>See, for example, the
                        difference between substantial and formal variants and between operations
                           <foreign xml:lang="la">ope codicum</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="la"
                           >ope ingenii</foreign> (<ref type="bibl" target="#stussi1988">Stussi
                           1988</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#renzietal2009">Renzi and Andreose
                           2009</ref>).</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>In our view there is no strict dichotomy between normalization and correction,
                     but rather a continuum. No normalization is entirely objective, no correction
                     is entirely subjective. For example, one can argue that substituting
                        <term>u</term> for <term>v</term> and vice versa is quite unproblematic and
                     rather objective because it follows an established rule of the art in a certain
                     school of philology. However, in our opinion, choosing which set of rules to
                     follow is also a subjective choice of the scholar that cannot, and should not,
                     be seen as independent of their work. In addition, we argue that even in the
                     simplest cases the philologist runs the risk of concealing linguistic features
                     of great importance, taking them for scribal negligence.</p>
                  <p>In our opinion no intervention pertaining to the normalization process can be
                     considered objective or mechanical. The lack of a clear line of distinction
                     suggests that as much information as feasibly possible should be preserved
                     during the preparation of a scholarly edition.</p>
                  <p>Preserving information has, however, a cost: the editor must put in the effort
                     to record every single correction, even the most minute. The method we present
                     in <ref type="crossref" target="#ourapproach">section 3</ref> aims to make it
                     possible to preserve a vast amount of information with little effort on the
                     part of the editor.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="normalizationtei">
                  <head>Normalization in TEI</head>
                  <p>In TEI most of these normalization actions are represented using <gi
                        scheme="TEI">choice</gi> elements. For example, the expansion of
                        <term>ᵽ</term> into <term>per</term> would be encoded as</p>
                  <figure xml:id="example1">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                        <w>
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>ᵽ</abbr>
                              <expan>per</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </w>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Expansion of an abbreviation with <gi scheme="TEI"
                           >choice</gi></head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>It is also possible to use <gi scheme="TEI">choice</gi> to encode more than one
                     normalization form for the same word, for example, using the ad-hoc elements
                     described by the Menota handbook:<note><ref type="bibl" target="#haugen2019"
                           >Haraldur Bernharðsson and Odd Einar Haugen, <title level="a">Levels of
                              text representation</title>, ch. 4 in Haugen 2019,
                           https://www.menota.org/HB3_ch4.xml</ref>.</note>
                  </p>
                  <figure xml:id="example2">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
                        xmlns:me="http://www.menota.org/ns/1.0" valid="true">
                        <w>
                           <choice>
                              <me:facs>waꝛn</me:facs>
                              <me:dipl>warn</me:dipl>
                              <me:norm>waren</me:norm>
                           </choice>
                        </w>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Normalisation in the Menota project</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>There are many TEI elements that are routinely used in combination with <gi
                        scheme="TEI">choice</gi> to express different kinds of normalization
                     intents: for instance, <gi scheme="TEI">abbr</gi>, <gi scheme="TEI">expan</gi>,
                        <gi scheme="TEI">sic</gi>, <gi scheme="TEI">corr</gi>, <gi scheme="TEI"
                        >orig</gi>, <gi scheme="TEI">reg</gi>, <gi scheme="TEI">supplied</gi>, and,
                     for punctuation, <gi scheme="TEI">pc</gi>.</p>
                  <p>The use of <gi scheme="TEI">choice</gi> has two main drawbacks: first, it
                     causes a twentyfold expansion in character count (a five-letter word with two
                     normalizations requires more than one hundred characters to be encoded), and,
                     second, it forces what would be a single <gi scheme="TEI">w</gi> element to
                     grow into an eight-tag, two-level-deep markup structure. When each word in a
                     manuscript needs such a treatment (as is the case in medieval texts), these two
                     drawbacks quickly lead to the creation of a TEI file that is hard to navigate
                     and to maintain.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="punctuation">
               <head>Punctuation</head>
               <p>Punctuation is one of the many aspects of a text that undergoes normalization
                  during the creation of a scholarly edition. In most cases normalizing punctuation
                  is considered a secondary task and very quickly brushed off in the introductions
                  of many editions.<note>An example of the traditional way to address punctuation is
                     the edition of <title level="m">Erek</title> by <ref xml:id="quote7"
                        type="bibl" target="#hammeretal2017">Hammer, Millet, and Reuvekamb-Felber
                        (2017)</ref> which is based on manuscript A. The authors state that <quote
                        source="#quote7">in order to account for the dominance of A in the context
                        of the textual transmission <gap/>, we put this text in the focus of our
                        edition and we represent it in the form (except for the interventions noted
                        below) in which it came to us</quote> (our translation) (p. XXXV). In the
                     introduction to the edition, only six lines are devoted to punctuation: there,
                     it is stated that <quote source="#quote7"><supplied>w</supplied>e insert
                        punctuation according to modern rules and to our understanding of the text.
                        Generously at the end of the verse, much more careful inside the
                        verse</quote> (our translation) (p. XXXVIII). The original reads <quote
                        source="#quote7"><supplied>i</supplied>nterpunktion setzen wir nach modernen
                        Regeln und entsprechend unserem Verständnis des Textes. Am Verseende
                        großzügig, im Versinneren deutlich vorsichtiger.</quote> This is no
                     criticism of the edition itself, which is extremely valuable, but a
                     matter-of-fact observation capturing the common way of dealing with punctuation
                     in state-of-the-art editions.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In our opinion, the normalization of punctuation is a critical step in the
                  creation of any nondiplomatic edition. Punctuation is not only a reading aid: it
                  delivers meaning, suggests interpretations, creates structures, and changes the
                  importance of words. It is the responsibility of the editor of a non-diplomatic
                  edition to translate ancient punctuation systems into something that a modern
                  reader can fully understand.</p>
               <p>From an operational point of view, the normalization of punctuation marks is
                  profoundly different from the normalization of words, although the two are often
                  treated in the same way.</p>
               <p>The normalization of words is usually quite simple and has only minimal impact on
                  the markup structure (when done without preserving information, as described in
                  the previous section). In the most common case, some letters in a word are
                  changed, requiring the replacement of that word. The more convoluted cases require
                  splitting or merging words, but those still have, at most, a linear effect on the
                  markup structure (for example, turning <tag type="start">w</tag>aberes<tag
                     type="end">w</tag> into <tag type="start">w</tag>aber<tag type="end"
                     >w</tag><tag type="start">w</tag>es<tag type="end">w</tag>
                  <note>From München, BSB Cgm 696, f. 145r.</note>).</p>
               <p>In contrast, the normalization of punctuation is often more complex, leads to
                  modifications in the hierarchical structure of the markup, and even has a ripple
                  effect on the surrounding text. For example, normalizing the middle dot in <q><tag
                        type="start">s</tag><gap/> geben ‧ von stund er gesund wirt <gap/><tag
                        type="end">s</tag></q> into a full stop will not only change the markup
                  structure, but also require the capitalization of the following word, now the
                  first word of the following sentence: <q><tag type="start">s</tag><gap/>
                        geben.<tag type="end">s</tag><tag type="start">s</tag>Von stund er gesund
                     wirt <gap/><tag type="end">s</tag></q>.<note>From München, BSB Cgm 696, f.
                     265r.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The additional complexity of normalizing punctuation is especially prominent when
                  dealing with medieval texts. As a matter of fact, punctuation in the Middle Ages
                  responded to needs that were completely different from what we are used to in
                  modern times, and different rules were applied based on many factors: the <foreign
                     xml:lang="la">scriptorium</foreign> where the manuscripts were produced, the
                  scribe, the language, the destination of the text, and the local customs.</p>
               <p>This is the case in medieval German, where punctuation was usually not driven by
                  syntactic principles, but instead often had a rhetoric function: it was meant as
                  an aid to those reading the text aloud (<ref type="bibl" target="#digilio2008"
                     >Digilio 2008, 373</ref>). For instance, an important element in the clause
                  could be put between two commas to signal that it was to be read louder; today
                  this would have the opposite result. Take for example, <q>Mary, his sister, is a
                     doctor</q>: if we were to follow some medieval punctuation conventions, like
                  the ones often found in the witnesses represented in the ENHG Marco Polo, <q>his
                     sister</q> would be the focus of the sentence, while according to the modern
                  use of commas, the same phrase would be of secondary importance. An example of
                  this is the following sentence, from the rubric of chapter 3 in München, BSB Cgm
                  696: <q>die zwen prüder <gap/> darnach chomen, zu dem groſſen hern, der gancȝen
                     tartarey</q>.<note><q>The two brothers <gap/> then come, to the great lord, of
                        whole Tatarstan</q>.</note> Despite being the pragmatic focus of the
                  sentence, <q>zu dem groſſen hern</q> is here between commas: the commas clearly
                  emphasize the phrase in question. Moreover, modern punctuation imposed on medieval
                  texts can obscure important linguistic phenomena: in the case of the ENHG Marco
                  Polo, this concerns structures such as the connecting relative and the syntactic
                  parameter of the null subject.</p>
               <p>Unfortunately, things are even more complex than that; the sentence we have just
                  analyzed proceeds as follows: <q>die zwen prüder <gap/> darnach chomen, zu dem
                     groſſen hern, der gancȝen tartarey, gnant ẟ groſe cham, kayſer ʋon Chatay</q>:
                  the second part of the sentence, which translates <q>called the Great Kaan,
                     emperor of Chatay</q>, would seem to reflect instead a more modern use of
                  commas.</p>
               <p>The underlying truth is that the systems regulating punctuation in medieval texts
                  are not yet fully understood. This is true for the German Middle Ages in general,
                  as Digilio (<ref type="bibl" target="#digilio2008">2008, 373</ref>) observes, and
                  for ENHG in particular. In this respect, <ref xml:id="quote8" type="bibl"
                     target="#ebertetal1993">Ebert et al. (1993, 29)</ref> write that <quote
                     source="#quote8">how far it is possible to describe rules and how much
                     rulelessness reigns here, remains to be determined.</quote><note><quote
                        source="#quote8">Inwieweit hier Regeln beschreibbar sind und inwieweit hier
                        Regellosigkeit herrscht, bleibt noch festzustellen.</quote></note> The very
                  meaning of the signs is often ambiguous: <term>punctus</term> and
                     <term>virgula</term>, the two signs that appear in the witnesses at the basis
                  of the edition,are, particularly in the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries, <quote
                     source="#quote9">polyfunctional</quote> (<ref xml:id="quote9" type="bibl"
                     target="#ebertetal1993">Ebert et al. 1993, 29</ref>).</p>
               <p>This lack of systematic rules and the high degree of ambiguity makes it hard to
                  understand which set of rules was being used in the first place and, in turn,
                  almost impossible to transpose in a fully mechanical way the punctuation system
                  used by a manuscript into one of the many currently used. Contini supports our
                  observations when he writes that <quote source="#quote10">the frictions due to the
                     change of system are particularly visible in the case of punctuation
                        <supplied>that in old texts mixes semantic and melodic functions</supplied>,
                     so that it is only rarely possible to insert or omit one and the same sign in
                     the same place</quote> (<ref xml:id="quote10" type="bibl" target="#contini2014"
                     >Contini 2014†, 23</ref>). Instead of a translation from one system into
                  another (which is the definition of normalization adopted by Contini), in the case
                  of punctuation one would have to substitute the system <foreign xml:lang="la">in
                     toto</foreign>.</p>
               <p>We are not the first to notice that normalizing punctuation differs profoundly
                  from normalizing words. In 2014, for instance, Elena Pierazzo wrote in a
                  discussion on the TEI mailing list on the subject of normalization of
                     punctuation:<note>Elena Pierazzo, <bibl xml:id="maillist"><title level="u">Re:
                           Original and editorial punctuation</title>, TEI-L, May 23, 2014, <ptr
                           target="https://listserv.brown.edu/cgi-bin/wa?A2=TEI-L;4b7897d6.1405"/>;
                           <ptr
                           target="http://tei-l.970651.n3.nabble.com/Original-and-editorial-punctuation-td4025791.html#a4025812"
                        /></bibl>.</note>
               </p>
               <cit>
                  <quote source="#maillist"><p>The point is that punctuation is not like spelling
                        and orthography. <supplied>F</supplied>or the latter, you have words and
                        sequences of characters that evolve from one accepted format to another
                        accepted format.<gap/></p>
                     <p>However, punctuation does not work like this: you cannot trace the evolution
                        of a medieval or early modern comma into, say, a semicolon, because they are
                        completely different systems that are practically unrelated to each
                        other.<gap/>So when editing a medieval/early modern text, <hi rend="bold">if
                           providing a modern punctuation is a requirement of the project, then
                           first you strip the text from all the punctuation and then you add
                           completely new one.</hi> (emphasis added)</p></quote>
               </cit>
               <div xml:id="possibleapproaches">
                  <head>Possible Approaches</head>
                  <p>Among the different attempts on the part of scholarly editors to address this
                     issue, we can identify three main tendencies:</p>
                  <list rend="ordered">
                     <item>the complete removal of the original punctuation system, replacing it
                        with a modern one;</item>
                     <item>the decision to maintain punctuation exactly as it was in the source
                        document;</item>
                     <item>an endeavor to normalize punctuation, while remaining as close as
                        possible to the source.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>An example of the first approach, removal and replacement of the original
                     punctuation, is found in <title level="m">Corpus Rhythmorum Musicum</title>
                        (<ref type="bibl" target="#stella2020">Stella 2020</ref>),<note><ptr
                           target="http://www.corimu.unisi.it/public/frontend"/>.</note> a
                     multimodal edition containing the earliest medieval Latin songs, together with
                     their musical rendition. Figure 1 shows an excerpt from the edition alongside
                     one of the witnesses:</p>
                  <figure xml:id="figure1">
                     <graphic url="img/figure1.png" height="186px" width="525px"/>
                     <head type="legend">Left: Manuscript of the song <title level="a">A solis ortu
                           usque ad occidua</title>.<note><ptr
                              target="http://www.corimu.unisi.it/public/manoscritti/manoscritto/idms/7"
                           /> Verona, Biblioteca Capitolare, XC (85).</note> Right: Edition of the
                        song from the <title level="m">Corpus Rhythmorum Musicum</title>.<note>
                           <ptr
                              target="http://www.corimu.unisi.it/public/previewedizione/testo/idschede/1"
                           />.</note> The medieval punctuation present in the original manuscript
                        has been removed <term>in toto</term> and replaced by modern punctuation in
                        the edited text.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>An example of the second method, the faithful preservation of the original
                     punctuation in the edited text, can be found in the <title level="m"
                        >Parzival-Projekt</title> (<ref type="bibl" target="#stolzetal2020">Stolz
                        2020</ref>),<note><ptr
                           target="http://www.parzival.unibe.ch/cod857/Daten/materialien.html"
                        />.</note> depicted in <ref type="crossref" target="#figure2">figure
                     2</ref>. Here the transcription of the witness perfectly matches the original
                     punctuation: the medieval dot is encoded using a modern full point, fully
                     comparable from the point of view of its visual rendering.</p>
                  <figure xml:id="figure2">
                     <graphic url="img/figure2.png" height="82px" width="453px"/>
                     <head type="legend">Extract St. Gallen, Stiftsbibliothek, Cod. 857 (f. 10a,
                        verses 18.30–19.03) from the edition of MS D in the <title level="m"
                           >Parzival-Projekt</title>. The edited text maintains the original
                        punctuation.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>An example of the third strategy, normalizing punctuation while trying to keep
                     it close to the original, is the <title level="m">Digital Vercelli Book</title>
                     by Roberto Rosselli Del Turco (<ref type="bibl" target="#delturcond"
                     >n.d.</ref>). The Vercelli Book has two editions: a diplomatic and an
                     interpretative one. While the diplomatic edition preserves the original
                     punctuation, the interpretative edition presents a simplification of the
                     original punctuation. This simplification replaces most archaic signs with full
                     stops, but still respects most of the features of the original punctuation, in
                     particular its position. This often leads to unnatural-looking edited texts,
                     such as that shown in <ref type="crossref" target="#figure3">figure 3</ref>. In
                     this example, the dot preceding the string <q>achine</q> is maintained in its
                     original position, but the two words composing the string <q>ac</q> and
                        <q>hine</q> are separated. Having a full stop still adjacent to the first
                     letter of a word, though, is quite unfamiliar for modern readers, who might
                     have difficulties parsing the text.</p>
                  <figure xml:id="figure3">
                     <graphic url="img/figure3.png" height="36px" width="453px"/>
                     <head type="legend">Extract from the <title level="m">Digital Vercelli
                           Book</title>. Some punctuation is simplified <soCalled>in
                           place</soCalled>, leading to unfortunate hard-to-read artifacts that do
                        not match current punctuation conventions (e.g., <q>.ac hine</q>).</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>If, on the one hand, we appreciate the attempt to normalize the original
                     punctuation, on the other hand, this approach does not seem to improve the
                     readability of the text, as one would expect from an interpretative edition.
                     Moreover, it does not seem to help much in the analysis of the original
                     punctuation either. However, it could represent one step in a potential
                     spectrum of normalizations, a first step in reducing the complexity present in
                     the original source.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="punctuationENHG">
                  <head>Punctuation in the ENHG Marco Polo</head>
                  <p>In our project, punctuation will be handled in three different ways, one for
                     each level of faithfulness: diplomatic, semidiplomatic, and interpretative.</p>
                  <p>At the diplomatic level punctuation will be fully preserved. Each punctuation
                     mark will be encoded in its original position and using the nearest Unicode
                     code point. Extracting precise information about the punctuation marks from the
                     facsimile and encoding it in the TEI files will also have the positive side
                     effect of unlocking important analyses in the fields of stylometry and
                     phylogenetics (<ref type="bibl" target="#darmonetall2020">Darmon et al.
                        2020</ref>).</p>
                  <p>At the semidiplomatic level a reduced system of punctuation consisting of two
                     signs, a middle dot (·) and a <term>virgula</term> (|), will be introduced.
                     Similar systems are often used in the late Middle Ages (<ref type="bibl"
                        target="#parkes1992">Parkes 1992, 46</ref>) and are often adopted in ENHG
                     texts of the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries (<ref type="bibl"
                        target="#hartwegetal2005">Hartweg and Wegera 2005, 131</ref>). This reduced
                     system based on unfamiliar signs will allow a smooth presentation of the text’s
                     structure, and, at the same time, reduce the intervention of the editor on the
                     interpretation of the textual content. A similar approach was used by <ref
                        type="bibl" target="#mitchelletal1998">Mitchell and Robinson (1998)</ref>,
                     as discussed in <ref type="crossref" target="#multipleeditions">the next
                        section</ref>. In addition, in our case, the insertion of this minimal
                     system of punctuation follows the motto <quote source="#quote11">no punctuation
                        where the sense is clear without any</quote> (<ref xml:id="quote11"
                        type="bibl" target="#mitchelletal1998">Mitchell and Robinson 1998,
                     313</ref>).</p>
                  <p>At the interpretative level the punctuation will be completely modernized,
                     allowing the general public to easily read the text.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="multipleeditions">
               <head>Multiple Editions</head>
               <p>Notwithstanding the issues outlined in the previous section, the project behind
                  the ENHG Marco Polo edition strives to match and surpass the state of the art for
                  digital editions.</p>
               <p>One particular aim of the ENHG Marco Polo is to be able to programmatically
                  produce multiple editions, each with different notes and normalized texts, from a
                  single master TEI file. In practice, this means:</p>
               <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>The witnesses will be encoded using TEI-compliant XML markup.</item>
                  <item>The scholar will work by directly editing the TEI XML master file.</item>
                  <item>For each witness, there will be a single master file containing all related
                     information and critical annotations (including the references for the editor’s
                     notes).</item>
                  <item>The same text will be edited in multiple levels of closeness to the source:
                     diplomatic (with special characters to show allographic variance, colors,
                     abbreviations, errors etc.), semi-diplomatic (with expanded abbreviations, but
                     still maintaining some relevant graphematic distinctions, a reduced punctuation
                     system, and the correction of trivial mistakes), and interpretative (with the
                     correction of all mistakes and the modernization of graphemes, punctuation, and
                     other textual features). Given that the project is based on three main
                     witnesses, this means producing a total of nine different editions.</item>
                  <item>Multiple editions will be generated automatically from the master TEI file,
                     with no manual intervention on the resulting files.</item>
                  <item>The generated editions files will conform to the TEI subset understood by
                     EVT.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Some of these desiderata clash with each other. For instance, the desire to
                  directly edit the XML file makes it hard and error-prone to keep in a single
                  master file all the information needed to generate the three editions. It would
                  have been hardly possible to respect the desired level of explicitness in the
                  normalisation process due to the complexities emerging from the high level of
                  granularity of the transcriptions combined with the goal of producing multiple
                  levels of normalisation.</p>
               <div xml:id="predigitalapproaches">
                  <head>Predigital Approaches</head>
                  <p>In predigital times, presenting the same text at different levels of rendition
                     would of course mean a lot of work. The philologist, after completing the
                     diplomatic transcription, would start all over again and proceed with another
                     transcription and repeat the process for each level of normalization they
                     wished to produce. Not only is this a very long and demanding workflow, but it
                     also poses a number of problems: first of all, if an uncertain passage of the
                     text gets clarified later on in the editing process, the changes need to be
                     made on all the different editions separately. Moreover, inconsistencies can
                     emerge between different edition levels, as they are created independently from
                     each other.</p>
                  <p>An interesting example, in this respect, is that of <ref type="bibl"
                        target="#mitchelletal1998">Mitchell and Robinson (1998)</ref>: in their
                     edition of <title level="m">Beowulf</title>, they decided to use modern
                     punctuation. The text, in fact, needed to be accessible to a wide audience. At
                     the same time, however, they expressed their reservations on the issue: modern
                     punctuation would not suit Old English poetry and it would force the editors to
                     make decisions in order to resolve ambiguities which cannot be resolved. Given
                     these considerations, extensively explained in section IIIB of their edition,
                     they wanted to offer a way out, or at least an alternative. They proposed a
                     different system of punctuation, which inspired our intermediate level of
                     normalization. However, they limited themselves to offering a mere taste of
                     their solution in the appendix to the edition (pp. 313–18). In the appendix
                     they edited verses 1–114 again, using a different punctuation system and
                     inviting the reader to go back to the beginning of the full edition, where the
                     first three folios of the manuscripts are reproduced in a black and white
                     facsimile (pp. 44–48). Such an approach has many limitations: it is highly
                     impractical, both from the point of view of the reader, who is forced to go
                     back and forth from the beginning to the end of the book and who, in the end,
                     only gets a small portion of the <soCalled>best</soCalled> version of the text,
                     and from the point of view of the scholar, who cannot realize their ideas to
                     the fullest, as that would probably cost too much time and space.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="digitalapproaches">
                  <head>Digital Approaches</head>
                  <p>One of the main advantages of digital transcriptions of manuscripts is that
                     they can be reprocessed and transformed quite easily, at least in theory. This
                     lends itself to the idea of having a single container that includes both a
                     diplomatic transcription and hints on how to normalize certain pieces of
                     texts.</p>
                  <p>For example, it is quite common for philologists who prepare their editions
                     using TEI to make use of elements such as <gi scheme="TEI">choice</gi>, <gi
                        scheme="TEI">orig</gi>, and <gi scheme="TEI">reg</gi> to indicate how to
                     normalize certain words, or <gi scheme="TEI">sic</gi> and <gi scheme="TEI"
                        >corr</gi> to encode corrections. A software tool will then process these
                     hints and, for example, allow the reader to choose between a version that has
                     been created on the fly by selecting the text marked with <gi scheme="TEI"
                        >orig</gi>/<gi scheme="TEI">sic</gi> and another version created by
                     selecting the text in the<gi scheme="TEI">reg</gi>/<gi scheme="TEI">corr</gi>
                     elements.</p>
                  <p>A digital edition exemplifying this approach is the aforementioned <title
                        level="m">Digital Vercelli Book</title>, by <ref type="bibl"
                        target="#delturcond">Roberto Rosselli Del Turco (n.d.)</ref>: here two
                     levels of edition are offered, a diplomatic and a more interpretative one. The
                     user can compare the two editions visualizing them synoptically in the EVT
                     software used for the edition.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="ourapproach">
            <head>Our Approach</head>
            <p>To address the challenges and the desiderata of the ENHG Marco Polo edition (single
               master file, directly editable, multiple output editions), we developed and
               implemented a novel approach where normalization is dealt with using formal rules,
               explicit exceptions, and automated pipelines to generate ephemeral edition files.
               This approach is inspired by similar initiatives in the fields of collation (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#barabuccietal2017a">Barabucci and Fischer 2017</ref>; <ref
                  type="bibl" target="#vanzundert2019">van Zundert 2019</ref>), textual edition
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#barabuccietal2017b">Barabucci, Spadini, and Turska,
                  2017</ref>), legal analysis (<ref type="bibl" target="#barabuccietal2011"
                  >Barabucci et al. 2011</ref>), and curation of research data (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#barabucci2018">Barabucci 2018</ref>).</p>
            <p>This methodology is characterized by the following key aspects:</p>
            <list rend="bulleted">
               <item>the master TEI file contains the transcriptions;</item>
               <item>general rules are encoded using a formal language, with a scheme such as <q>if
                     CONDITION then TRANSFORMATION</q>;</item>
               <item>rules are stored outside the master TEI file;</item>
               <item>rules are applied to structures, not just to pieces of text;</item>
               <item>the few exceptions (such as manual corrections or cases where a rule should not
                  be applied) are encoded in the master TEI file;</item>
               <item>the edition files, despite being the main concrete output of the editorial
                  project, are ephemeral and never modified directly.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The implementation consists of a series of XSLT transformations, each representing
               and implementing a single rule, coordinated by three different XProc pipelines, one
               for each level of edition. The source code is available at <ptr
                  target="https://marcopolo.cceh.uni-koeln.de/"/>.</p>
            <p>This methodology contrasts with the established editorial practice of mingling
               transcription, normalization, and critical amendments. Instead of just performing the
               desired normalization steps while transcribing and keeping track of them in an
               introduction to the edition, here the rules are separate artifacts, related to, but
               independent from, the edited text. In fact, as a fortunate byproduct of this
               methodology, the ENHG Marco Polo produced a set of rules for the normalization of
               words and punctuation in Early New High German. The scholarly community now has the
               opportunity to evaluate, discuss, critique, modify, and, if desired, adopt this set
               of rules independently from the edited text.</p>
            <p>Another important distinction is the epistemological status of the generated edition
               files. The three edition files are the main scholarly output of the editorial
               project, but they are also ephemeral files that can be thrown away and reproduced in
               their exact form at any time. This is possible because all the knowledge needed to
               create the edition files (both the scholarly and the technical knowledge) is stored
               either in the master TEI file or in one of the pipelines. No manual
                  <soCalled>drive-by</soCalled> modification is performed at any time. With this
               framework in place, it even becomes possible to reconstruct the chain of reasoning
               and transformations that lead to a certain result in a specific part of the edition
               file, giving critical editing the same kind of transparency and mechanical
               reproducibility common to other sciences.</p>
            <div xml:id="rules">
               <head>Rules</head>
               <p>Rules are the way in which the scholar formalizes the normalization process. The
                  kind of rule used in the project is of the form <q>if CONDITION then
                     TRANSFORMATION</q>. Examples of rules implemented in ENHG Marco Polo edition
                  are:</p>
               <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>orthographic corrections after changes in punctuation (e.g., if a
                        <term>virgula</term> has been normalized into a full stop, then the first
                     letter of the following word must be capitalized);</item>
                  <item>methods to join words split at the ends of lines (e.g., if a token is at the
                     end of a line and ends with one of the characters used to denote a joining,
                     then merge this token with the following token).</item>
                  <item>replacement rules for archaic letters (e.g., replace a long s (ſ) with a
                     lowercase s);</item>
                  <item>expansion rules for abbreviations (e.g., replace all occurrences of
                        <q>vñ</q> with <q>vnd</q>).</item>
               </list>
               <p>The first two examples demonstrate why one should not think of these rules as
                  simple textual substitutions. As described in previous sections, there is a deep
                  connection between punctuation and the structure of the text. Changing punctuation
                  can, and often does, change the structure of the text. At the same time, it is
                  essential to represent such structures in a machine-readable way. For example,
                  without a proper representation of the concept of <term>sentence</term> it would
                  not be possible to write rules such as <q>if a word appears at the beginning of a
                        <term>sentence</term><gap/></q> What follows is that there is a continual
                  interaction between the rules and the structure of the edited text. Rules, and in
                  particular punctuation rules, often modify the structure of the text. A technical
                  system that does not allow for this interaction to happen is not able to deal in
                  properly with normalization in general and punctuation in particular.</p>
               <p>Each rule is implemented as a small and self-contained XSLT transformation. At the
                  time of writing, the ENHG Marco Polo project comprises about a hundred rules,
                  grouped in twenty macro categories. On average, the core of each rule is
                  implemented in less than three lines of XSLT.</p>
               <p>To give the readers an impression of the simplicity of the rule implementation, we
                  show here the main parts of the XSLT that implement one of the example rules
                  described above.</p>
               <div xml:id="examplerule">
                  <head>Example: Rule to Join Words Split at the End of a Line</head>
                  <p>In ENHG, a punctuation sign that we nowadays call a double oblique hyphen was
                     used to mark that a word has been split at the end of a line. In the diplomatic
                     rendition we want to preserve this word division and the forced line break,
                     while in other renditions we want to reconstruct the complete word.</p>
                  <p>The XSLT excerpt in <ref type="crossref" target="#example3">Example 3</ref>
                     shows how split words are joined when a middle double oblique hyphen is found.
                     The joining is performed in a lossless way: all information present in the
                     original witness is preserved. This is possible because this step operates on a
                     supertextual structure that contains information about the structure of the
                     text and the positioning of a token (e.g., <att>eol</att>=<val>true</val>). It
                     must be stressed that this last piece of information, and the supertextual
                     structure in general, are not part of the master TEI file and have been added
                     in the preceding steps. It should also be noted that this rule does not delete
                     any text, it just marks that two words have been joined and what the result of
                     this operation is. Another rule will take care of modifying the structure, and
                     yet another will remove the now superfluous partial word in the next line
                     before creating the final edition file. However, while removing and carrying
                     out all these changes, comments about what is being done will be added as an
                     aid to the readers of the final edition file.</p>
                  <figure xml:id="example3">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xmlns:xsl="www.example.com"
                        valid="true">
                        <xsl:template
                           match="mp:TOKEN[@eol='true'][ends-with(., $char-double-oblique-hyphen)]">
                           <!-- First, the two parts of the split word are identified. -->
                           <xsl:variable name="part1-raw" select="string(.)"/>
                           <xsl:variable name="part1"
                              select="substring-before($part1-raw, $char-double-oblique-hyphen)"/>
                           <xsl:variable name="part2" select="string(following::p:TOKEN[1])"/>
                           <!-- Then the joined word is computed. -->
                           <xsl:variable name="joined-parts">
                              <xsl:value-of select="$part1"/>
                              <xsl:value-of select="$part2"/>
                           </xsl:variable>
                           <!-- Finally, the content of the original element is replaced by
                  the joined word, and the source pieces stored and
                  carried along in extra attributes. -->
                           <xsl:copy>
                              <xsl:apply-templates select="@*"/>
                              <xsl:attribute name="joined" select="true()"/>
                              <xsl:attribute name="part1" select="$part1-raw"/>
                              <xsl:attribute name="part2" select="$part2"/>
                              <xsl:value-of select="$joined-parts"/>
                           </xsl:copy>
                        </xsl:template>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">XSLT implementation of the rule <q>Join words split with a
                           double oblique hyphen</q>.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>The rule in <ref type="crossref" target="#example3">Example 3</ref> is
                     independent from other rules in the pipeline. The scholar is free to use this
                     rule in the generation of a specific edition or to leave it out. In the case of
                     the Marco Polo project, this rule is employed in the pipelines that produce the
                     semi-diplomatic and the interpretative editions, but not in the diplomatic
                     edition.</p>
                  <p>Because it is independent from the other rules used in the pipeline, other
                     scholars can reuse this rule in their projects without being forced to adopt
                     the Marco Polo pipelines, and all their rules, in their entirety.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="oneoff">
               <head>One-off Cases, Exceptions, and Manual Corrections</head>
               <p>Before a rule can be written, a textual phenomenon must first be recognized as
                  such and then a pattern must be identified. At the beginning of the editorial
                  process, when the textual materials are not yet well known and the normalization
                  rules are not yet clear, it is simpler and more productive to address one-off
                  textual phenomena manually. This is done by annotating the word to be normalized
                  or the sign to be changed in the master TEI file. Once a pattern is recognized, a
                  rule can be written and these annotations removed from the master TEI file.</p>
               <p>Similarly, there are cases where the conditions of a rule would normally apply,
                  but where the scholar does not want the transformation to happen. Rather than
                  complicating the condition in the rule to exclude a specific case, it makes sense
                  to mark the specific occurrence as an exception in the master TEI file.</p>
               <p>Finally, the scholar may want to correct an obvious mistake, while keeping track
                  of the original reading. This is done not by writing a rule, but by placing an
                  annotation in the master TEI file.</p>
               <p>All these issues (one-off normalization, exceptions, and manual corrections) are
                  encoded using TEI elements directly in the master TEI file.</p>
               <p>One-off normalizations are marked in the master TEI file using one of the
                  non-standard attributes defined by the ENHG ODD. For example attaching
                     <eg>mp:n1-subst="foo"</eg> to any element will force the substitution of the
                  word <q>foo</q> for the content of that element, but only at the normalization
                  level denoted by N1 (<q>semi-interpretative</q>). Such exceptions are marked using
                     <gi scheme="TEI">w</gi> or <gi scheme="TEI">pc</gi> elements, together with the
                  already cited project-specific <ident>mp:nX-subst</ident> attributes, as shown in
                     <ref type="crossref" target="#example4">Example 4</ref>.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example4">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xmlns:mp="www.example.com"
                     valid="true">
                     <pc mp:n1-subst="|" mp:n2-subst=";">,</pc>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Substitution of a comma with a virgula in the semi-diplomatic
                     edition (n1) and with a semicolon in the interpretative edition (n2).</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Manual corrections are encoded using a combination of <gi scheme="TEI"
                     >choice</gi>,<gi scheme="TEI">orig</gi>, and <gi scheme="TEI">reg</gi>
                  elements, together with the <att>mp:use-in-nX</att> attributes, as illustrated in
                     <ref type="crossref" target="#example5">Example 5</ref>.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example5">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xmlns:mp="www.example.com"
                     valid="true">
                     <persName ref="#marcoPolo">
                        <choice>
                           <orig>Macho</orig>
                           <reg mp:use-in-n1="true">Marcho</reg>
                           <reg mp:use-in-n2="true">Marco</reg>
                        </choice>
                     </persName>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Correction of the typo in the name <q>Marcho</q>, which will
                     appear as <q>Marcho</q> in the semi-diplomatic edition and as <q>Marco</q> in
                     the interpretative edition.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>The ability to quickly deal with occasional exceptions without having to resort to
                  writing a new rule or making the existing ones more complicated greatly simplifies
                  the day-to-day job of the scholar. It also allows for a cleaner separation between
                  rules (theoretically shared by a community) and exceptions (the results of the
                  editor’s own decisions).</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="pipelines">
               <head>Pipelines and Normalization Levels</head>
               <p>Pipelines are used by the scholar to indicate which rules should be applied, and
                  in which order, to turn the master TEI file into a complete edition at a specific
                  level of normalization.</p>
               <p>In the ENHG Marco Polo project there are three pipelines, one for each target
                  level of faithfulness and readability. Achieving a specific level of faithfulness
                  and readability is done by carefully choosing which rules to apply from the
                  catalogue of available rules. Some steps are shared by all pipelines, while others
                  are specific to certain faithfulness levels. <ref type="crossref"
                     target="#figure4">Figure 4</ref> illustrates this approach.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure4">
                  <graphic url="img/figure4_corrected.png" height="210px" width="148px"/>
                  <head type="legend">High-level representation of the pipeline-based workflow. The
                     gray cogs indicate steps shared by all pipelines. The cogs with patterns
                     identify level-specific steps.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Each pipeline is implemented as an XProc pipeline. All the pipelines are simple
                  linear flows (i.e., the output of a rule is the input for the next rule). From a
                  methodological point of view, the XProc pipeline is a record of all the operations
                  that the scholar performs on the transcription. The creation of an edition level
                  is equivalent to replaying this record. <ref type="crossref" target="#example6"
                     >Example 6</ref> shows an excerpt of the XProc pipeline used to generate the
                  semidiplomatic edition.</p>
               <p>It is important to note that pipelines comprise three kinds of steps:</p>
               <list rend="ordered">
                  <item>infrastructural steps: for example, the <term>tokenize</term> step that
                     creates the textual super-structure to which all other steps will refer
                     to;</item>
                  <item>rule-based steps: for example, the <term>adjust-capitalization</term> step
                     that implements the set of rules to fix the capitalization of words after
                     changes in punctuation; and</item>
                  <item>exception-related steps: for example, the <term>apply-punct-n1-subst</term>
                     step that handles all the exceptions to the punctuation rules that are relevant
                     for the N1 level (i.e., semi-diplomatic).</item>
               </list>
               <figure xml:id="example6">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <p:declare-step xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc" version="1.0">
                        <p:input port="source">
                           <p:document href="marco-polo-master.tei.xml"/>
                        </p:input>
                        <p:xslt>
                           <p:input port="stylesheet">
                              <p:document href="tokenize.xsl"/>
                           </p:input>
                        </p:xslt> [...] <p:xslt> Ⓐ <p:input port="stylesheet">
                              <p:document href="remove-line-breaks.xsl"/> Ⓐ </p:input>
                        </p:xslt> [...] <p:xslt> Ⓐ <p:input port="stylesheet">
                              <p:document href="normalize-letters-n1.xsl"/> Ⓐ </p:input>
                        </p:xslt>
                        <p:xslt> Ⓐ <p:input port="stylesheet">
                              <p:document href="normalize-letters-common.xsl"/> Ⓐ </p:input>
                        </p:xslt>
                        <p:xslt> 🅑 <p:input port="stylesheet">
                              <p:document href="apply-punct-n1-subst.xsl"/> 🅑 </p:input>
                        </p:xslt>
                        <p:xslt> Ⓐ <p:input port="stylesheet">
                              <p:document href="adjust-capitalization.xsl"/>
                           </p:input>
                        </p:xslt> [...] <p:xslt>
                           <p:input port="stylesheet">
                              <p:document href="untokenize.xsl"/>
                           </p:input>
                        </p:xslt>
                        <p:store>
                           <p:with-option name="href" select="'marco-polo-n1.tei.xml'"/>
                        </p:store>
                     </p:declare-step>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Excerpt of the XProc pipeline used to generate the
                     semi-diplomatic edition. Steps marked A are steps that implement rules; the
                     step marked B takes care of exceptions.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>The fact that the editorial workflows for all the editions are formalized in XProc
                  pipelines makes it possible, for instance, to compare these pipelines and see in
                  detail (and with utmost precision) how they differ and what is, in this project,
                  the difference between the processes needed to establish a diplomatic, a
                  semi-diplomatic or an interpretative edition. Breaking down the traditional
                  analogue processes into unambiguous discrete steps can contribute to the scholarly
                  debate on edition typology.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="conclusions">
            <head>Conclusions and Future Work</head>
            <p>We have described the workflow and the methodological approach behind a digital
               scholarly edition of the ENHG translation of Marco Polo’s work. The key idea to this
               methodological approach is the encoding of all the scholar’s knowledge (transcribed
               text, normalization rules for words and punctuation, exceptions, corrections) in a
               formalized way. Using this approach, it is possible to produce multiple editions at
               different levels of faithfulness and readability from a single master TEI file while
               keeping the master file lean and readable. In addition, the fact that the whole
               process is logged, and no manual modifications are performed in the generated edition
               files, allows the scholar to rapidly make fixes or test hypotheses. Finally, the sets
               of rules, being separated from the transcriptions, can be debated by the scholarly
               community independently from the edition.</p>
            <p>Compared to other approaches, this pipeline-based approach greatly simplifies the
               programming of rules that modify the structure of the text, leading to simpler and
               more succinct rules. First-class support for structural modifications is necessary to
               properly handle the normalization of punctuation. While textual normalization can, in
               most cases, be carried out through simple textual substitutions, many cases of
               punctuation normalization instead require changes to the structure of the text, as
               well as follow-up adjustments, for instance when full stops are inserted and
               sentences split.</p>
            <p>The adoption of our approach, as well as other similar programming-based approaches,
               forces a reflection on the role of the editor, or more precisely, on the many new
               roles that the editor must embrace. First, the editor stops being a mere transcriber:
               his/her main task is now to record all textual phenomena (each normalization action
               is explicitly recorded in the source files). With a collection of recorded phenomena
               in place, the editor can turn these single occurrences into systematic rules and
               catalogues of rules, becoming a pattern-spotter and knowledge-synthetizer. Once
               various such catalogues of rules have been established (e.g., for different
               languages, different time periods, and different scriptoria) and publicly shared, we
               envision future editors starting their editions by picking and choosing their
               preferred set of rules, thereby explicitly signaling in which philological tradition
               they are placing their work while maintaining the technical support needed to express
               their scholarly freedom to devise new exceptions and new rules. The publication of
               the rules and workflows used (in the form of steps and pipelines) would then become
               part of the expected content of a digital scholarly edition.</p>
            <p>In the future we would like to test various possible improvements. First we would
               like to experiment with creating <term>declarative rule generators</term>. Many rules
               are repetitive in their nature (for example, the normalization of single characters)
               and it should be possible to express them in a declarative fashion. These abstract
               rules would then be translated into XSLT transformations. Another aspect we would
               like to reflect on is how the transformation process directed by the pipelines
               influences the various levels of abstraction of the document being transformed,
               drawing parallels with stratified document models such as CMV+P (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#barabucci2019">Barabucci 2019</ref>). A final thing we would like to test
               is the replacement of the XProc pipelines with pure XSLT pipelines (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#birnbaum2017">Birnbaum 2017</ref>). Replacing XProc with XSLT pipelines
               would reduce the number of technologies that other scholars have to be familiar with
               in order to understand the editorial process in its entirety.</p>
            <p>Another future development that we envision is the deconstruction of the
               visualization of the edition into a series of small, explicit steps, taking place one
               after the other, just like their counterparts in the pipelines: one click would show
               the effects of the normalization of the allographs, another click would expand the
               abbreviations, another one would introduce a different system of punctuation, etc,
               until the last click would finally reveal the scholarly edition in its completeness.
               Our approach, in which all the knowledge of the editor is formalized, recorded, and
               made actionable, would be a solid base for such a future fractally detailed
               edition.</p>
            <p>We hope to be an inspiration for other edition projects. We firmly believe that all
               medieval manuscripts should be accessible in this way. We need to escape the
               constraints of paper editions and to start thinking differently. As Sahle famously
               wrote, a digital scholarly edition is really digital if it cannot be printed without
               a loss of the original contents and functionalities. Only editions that fully embrace
               the digital medium and its tools, including formalization of knowledge and
               programming, can satisfy this condition.</p>
            <p>In this environment where we have no space limits, why should we limit ourselves to
               the presentation of a predefined number of rendition levels? Why only diplomatic,
               semidiplomatic, and interpretative? We believe, in fact, that the granularity can
               increase even further.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <!-- the bibliography for the article, organized as a series of <bibl> elements inside <listBibl> -->
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="andrews2020"><author>Andrews, Tara</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title
                     level="a">Transcription and Collation.</title> Chap. 3.3 in <title level="m"
                     >Handbook of Stemmatology</title>, edited by <editor>Philipp Roelli</editor>,
                     <biblScope unit="page">160–75</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>De Gruyter</publisher>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.1515/9783110684384</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="barabucci2018"><author>Barabucci, Gioele</author>. <date>2018</date>.
                     <title level="u">Funktionale und deklarative Programmierung-basierte Methode
                     für nachhaltige, reproduzierbare und verifizierbare Datenkuration.</title>
                  Paper presented at DHd Konferenz 2018: Kritik der digitalen Vernunft,
                     <pubPlace>Cologne</pubPlace>, <date>February 26–March 2, 2018</date>. <ptr
                     target="https://gioele.io/p/dhd2018"/>; <ptr
                     target="http://dhd2018.uni-koeln.de/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="barabucci2019"><author>Barabucci, Gioele</author>. <date>2019</date>.
                     <title level="a">The CMV+P Document Model, Linear Version.</title> In <title
                     level="m">Versioning Cultural Objects: Digital Approaches</title>, edited by
                     <editor>Roman Bleier</editor> and <editor>Sean M. Winslow</editor>, <biblScope
                     unit="page">153–70</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Norderstedt</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>BoD</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="barabuccietal2017a"><author>Barabucci, Gioele</author>, and
                     <author>Franz Fischer</author>. 2017. <title level="a">The Formalization of
                     Textual Criticism: Bridging the Gap between Automated Collation and Edited
                     Critical Texts.</title> In <title level="m">Advances in Digital Scholarly
                     Editing: Papers Presented at the DiXiT Conferences in The Hague, Cologne, and
                     Antwerp,</title> edited by <editor>Peter Boot</editor>, <editor>Anna
                     Cappellotto</editor>, <editor>Wout Dillen</editor>, <editor>Franz
                     Fischer</editor>, <editor>Aodhán Kelly</editor>, <editor>Andreas
                     Mertgens</editor>, <editor>Anna-Maria Sichani</editor>, <editor>Elena
                     Spadini</editor>, and <editor>Dirk van Hulle</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >47–53</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace>: <publisher>Sidestone
                     Press.</publisher></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="barabuccietal2017b"><author>Barabucci, Gioele</author>, <author>Elena
                     Spadini</author>, and <author>Magdalena Turska</author>. <date>2017</date>.
                     <title level="a">Data vs. Presentation: What Is the Core of a Scholarly Digital
                     Edition?</title> In <title level="m">Advances in Digital Scholarly Editing:
                     Papers Presented at the DiXiT Conferences in The Hague, Cologne and
                     Antwerp,</title> edited by <editor>Peter Boot</editor>, <editor>Anna
                     Cappellotto</editor>, <editor>Wout Dillen</editor>, <editor>Franz
                     Fischer</editor>, <editor>Aodhán Kelly</editor>, <editor>Andreas
                     Mertgens</editor>, <editor>Anna-Maria Sichani</editor>, <editor>Elena
                     Spadini</editor>, and <editor>Dirk van Hulle</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >37–46</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace>: <publisher>Sidestone
                     Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="barabuccietal2011"><author>Barabucci, Gioele</author>, <author>Monica
                     Palmirani</author>, <author>Fabio Vitali</author>, and <author>Luca
                     Cervone</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title level="a">Long-term Preservation of
                     Legal Resources.</title> In <title level="m">International Conference on
                     Electronic Government and the Information Systems Perspective,</title>
                  <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">6866</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                     >78–93</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Springer</publisher>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.1007/978-3-642-22961-9_7</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="benedetto1928"><editor>Benedetto, Luigi F.</editor>, ed.
                     <date>1928</date>. <title level="m">Il Milione.</title> By <author>Marco
                     Polo</author>. Prima edizione integrale. <pubPlace>Firenze</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Leo S. Olschki</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="birnbaum2017"><author>Birnbaum, David J</author>. <date>2017</date>.
                     <title level="a">Patterns and Antipatterns in XSLT Micropipelining.</title> In
                     <title level="m">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2017</title>.
                     <title level="s">Balisage Series on Markup Technologies</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.4242/BalisageVol19.Birnbaum01.</idno></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bosco2003"><author>Bosco Coletsos, Sandra</author>. <date>2003</date>.
                     <title level="m">Storia della lingua tedesca.</title>
                  <pubPlace>Torino</pubPlace>: <publisher>Rosenberg &amp;
                  Sellier</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="buzzoni2016"><author>Buzzoni, Marina</author>. <date>2016</date>.
                     <title level="a">A Protocol for Scholarly Digital Editions? The Italian Point
                     of View.</title> In <title level="m">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and
                     Practices</title>, edited by <editor>Matthew James Driscoll</editor> and
                     <editor>Elena Pierazzo</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">59–82</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Open Book
                  Publishers</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="buzzoni2020"><author>Buzzoni, Marina</author>, ed. <date>2020</date>.
                     <title level="a">Towards the Construction of a Stemma.</title> In <title
                     level="m">Handbook of Stemmatology: History, Methodology, Digital
                     Approaches</title>, edited by <editor>Philipp Roelli</editor>, <biblScope
                     unit="page">139–207</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>: <publisher>De
                     Gruyter</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="contini2014"><author>Contini, Gianfranco</author>. <date>2014†</date>.
                     <title level="m">Filologia</title>, edited by <editor>Lino Leonardi</editor>.
                     <pubPlace>Bologna</pubPlace>: <publisher>Il Mulino</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="cugliana2019"><author>Cugliana, Elisa</author>. <date>2019</date>.
                     <title level="a">Exploring a German Version of Marco Polo’s <title level="m"
                        >Devisement dou Monde</title>.</title>
                  <title level="m">Ecdotica</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                  >9–32</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="darmonetall2020"><author>Darmon, Alexandra N. M.</author>,
                     <author>Marya Bazzi</author>, <author>Sam D. Howison</author>, and
                     <author>Mason A. Porter</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">Pull Out
                     All the Stops: Textual Analysis via Punctuation Sequences</title>. <title
                     level="j">European Journal of Applied Mathematics</title>: <biblScope
                     unit="page">1–37</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.1017/S0956792520000157</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="digilio2008"><author>Digilio, Maria Rita</author>. <date>2008</date>.
                     <title level="a">Scrittura e interpunzione in testi del medioevo tedesco e
                     gotico.</title> In <title level="m">Storia della punteggiatura in
                     Europa</title>, edited by <editor>Bice Mortara Garavelli</editor>, <biblScope
                     unit="page">359–73</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Bari</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Laterza</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ebertetal1993"><author>Ebert, Robert Peter</author>, <author>Oskar
                     Reichmann</author>, <author>Hans-Joachim Solms</author>, and
                     <author>Klaus-Peter Wegera</author>. <date>1993</date>. <title level="m"
                     >Frühneuhochdeutsche Grammatik.</title>
                  <pubPlace>Tübingen</pubPlace>: <publisher>Max Niemeyer Verlag</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="grimm1822"><author>Grimm, Jacob</author>. <date>1822</date>. <title
                     level="m">Deutsche Grammatik</title>, <biblScope unit="volume">Bd.
                     1</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Göttingen</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>Dieterich</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="hartwegetal2005"><author>Hartweg, Frédéric</author>, and
                     <author>Klaus-Peter Wegera</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title level="m"
                     >Frühneuhochdeutsch. Eine Einführung in die deutsche Sprache des
                     Spätmittelalters und der frühen Neuzeit.</title> 2nd rev. ed.
                     <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>: <publisher>De Gruyter</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="hammeretal2017"><author>Hammer, Andreas</author>, <author>Victor
                     Millet</author>, and <author>Timo Reuvekamp-Felber</author>, eds.
                     <date>2017</date>. <editor>Hartmann von Aue</editor>,<title level="m">Ereck:
                     Textgeschichtliche Ausgabe mit Abdruck sämtlicher Fragmente und der Bruchstücke
                     des mitteldeutschen <title level="m">Erek</title>.</title>
                  <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>: <publisher>De Gruyter</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="kirchhoff2017"><author>Kirchhoff, Frank</author>. <date>2017</date>.
                     <title level="m">Von der Virgel zum Komma: Die Entwicklung der Interpunktion im
                     Deutschen</title>. <title level="s">Germanistische Bibliothek</title>,
                     <biblScope unit="volume">Bd. 61</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Heidelberg</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Universitätsverlag Winter</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="maas1950"><author>Maas, Paul</author>. <date>1950</date>. <title
                     level="m">Textkritik.</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>., verb. und verm. Aufl.
                     <pubPlace>Leipzig</pubPlace>: <publisher>B. G. Teubner</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="mitchelletal1998"><editor>Mitchell, Bruce</editor>, and <editor>Fred C.
                     Robinson</editor>, eds. <date>1998</date>. <title level="m">Beowulf: An Edition
                     with Relevant Shorter Texts.</title>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Blackwell Publishing</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="mortara2008"><editor>Mortara Garavelli, Bice</editor>, ed.
                     <date>2008</date>. <title level="m">Storia della punteggiatura in
                     Europa.</title>
                  <pubPlace>Bari</pubPlace>: <publisher>Laterza</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="parkes1992"><author>Parkes, Malcolm B</author>. <date>1992</date>.
                     <title level="m">Pause and Effect: An Introduction to the History of
                     Punctuation in the West.</title>
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Routledge</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pierazzo2016"><author>Pierazzo, Elena</author>. <date>2016</date>.
                     <title level="a">Modelling Digital Scholarly Editing: From Plato to
                     Heraclitus.</title> In <title level="m">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and
                     Practices</title>, edited by <editor>Matthew James Driscoll</editor> and
                     <editor>Elena Pierazzo</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">41–58</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Open Book
                  Publishers</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="renzietal2009"><author>Renzi, Lorenzo</author>, and <author>Alvise
                     Andreose</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="m">Manuale di linguistica e
                     filologia romanza.</title> 3rd ed. <pubPlace>Bologna</pubPlace>: <publisher>Il
                     Mulino</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="rinas2017"><editor>Rinas, Karsten</editor>. <date>2017</date>. <title
                     level="m">Theorie der Punkte und Striche: die Geschichte der deutschen
                     Interpunktionslehre</title>. <title level="s">Germanistische
                  Bibliothek</title>, <biblScope unit="volume">Bd. 62</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>Heidelberg</pubPlace>: <publisher>Universitätsverlag Winter
                     Heidelberg</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="sahle2013"><author>Sahle, Patrick</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
                     level="m">Digitale Editionsformen: zum Umgang mit der Überlieferung unter den
                     Bedingungen des Medienwandels</title>. 3 vols. <title level="s">Schriften des
                     Instituts für Dokumentologie und Editorik</title>, <biblScope unit="volume"
                     >vols. 7–9</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Norderstedt</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>BoD</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="sahle2016"><author>Sahle, Patrick</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title
                     level="a">What Is a Scholarly Digital Edition?</title> In <title level="m"
                     >Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and Practices</title>, edited by
                     <editor>Matthew James Driscoll</editor> and <editor>Elena Pierazzo</editor>,
                     <biblScope unit="page">19–39</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Open Book Publishers</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="scherer1878"><author>Scherer, Wilhelm</author>. <date>1878</date>.
                     <title level="m">Zur Geschichte der deutschen Sprache</title>. 2. ausg.
                     <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>: <publisher>Weidmann</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="stussi1988"><author>Stussi, Alfredo</author>. <date>1988</date>. <title
                     level="m">Nuovo avviamento agli studi di filologia italiana</title>. Nuovo ed.
                     <pubPlace>Bologna</pubPlace>: <publisher>Il Mulino</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tscharner1935"><editor>Tscharner, Eduard Horst von</editor>, ed.
                     <date>1935</date>. <title level="m">Der mitteldeutsche Marco Polo nach der
                     Admonter Handschrift.</title>. <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Weidmannsche Buchhandlung</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="vanzundert2019"><author>Van Zundert, Joris J</author>.
                     <date>2019</date>. <title level="a">Why the Compact Disc Was Not a Revolution
                     and <title level="m">Cityfish</title> Will Change Textual Scholarship, or What
                     Is a Computational Edition?</title>
                  <title level="j">Ecdotica</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                  >129–56</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="wells1990"><author>Wells, Christopher J</author>. <date>1990</date>.
                     <title level="m">Deutsch: Eine Sprachgeschichte bis 1945</title>. Translated by
                     <editor role="translator">Rainhild Wells</editor>.
                     <pubPlace>Tübingen</pubPlace>: <publisher>Niemeyer</publisher>. Originally
                  published as <title level="m">German: A Linguistic History to 1945</title>
                     (<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>,
                     <date>1985</date>).</bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="worterbuch"><author>Akademie der Wissenschaft zu Göttingen</author>.
                     <date>n.d.</date>
                  <title level="m">Frühneuhochdeutsches Wörterbuch.</title> Accessed <date>April 19,
                     2021</date>. <ptr target="https://fwb-online.de/"/>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="haugen2019"><editor>Haugen, Odd Einar</editor>, ed. <date>2019</date>.
                     <title level="m">The Menota Handbook: Guidelines for the Electronic Encoding of
                     Medieval Nordic Primary Sources</title>. <biblScope>Version 3.0</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>Bergen</pubPlace>: <publisher>Medieval Nordic Text
                     Archive</publisher>. Last modified <date>December 12, 2019</date>. <ptr
                     target="https://www.menota.org/HB3_index.xml"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="maceetal2015"><editor>Macé, Caroline</editor>, and <editor>Philipp
                     Roelli</editor>, eds. <date>2015</date>. <title level="m">Parvum Lexicon
                     Stemmatologicum</title>. <biblScope>Version 1.0</biblScope>. Last modified
                     <date>May 3, 2018</date>.<ptr
                     target="https://wiki.helsinki.fi/display/stemmatology"/> .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="marzietalnd"><author>Marzi, Werner</author>, and <author>Kai-Michael
                     Sprenger</author>. <date>n.d.</date>
                  <title level="m">Ingelheimer Haderbücher</title>. Accessed <date>April 19,
                     2021</date>. <ptr target="https://www.haderbuecher.de/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="stolzetal2020"><author>Stolz, Michael</author>, et al.
                     <date>2020</date>. <title level="m">Parzival Projekt</title>. Last modified
                     <date>May 22, 2020</date>. <ptr target="http://www.parzival.unibe.ch/home.html"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="delturcond"><editor>Rosselli Del Turco, Roberto</editor>, ed.
                     <date>n.d.</date>
                  <title level="m">The Digital Vercelli Book</title>. <biblScope>Beta
                     version</biblScope>. Accessed <date>October 22, 2021</date>. <ptr
                     target="http://vbd.humnet.unipi.it/beta2/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="delturco2013"><author>Rosselli Del Turco, Roberto</author>, et al.
                     <date>2013</date>. <title level="m">Edition Visualization Technology</title>.
                  Accessed <date>April 19, 2021</date>.<ptr target="http://evt.labcd.unipi.it/"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="stella2020"><editor>Stella, Francesco</editor>, ed. <date>2020</date>.
                     <title level="m">Corpus Rhythmorum Musicum.</title> Last modified <date>July
                     28, 2020</date>. <ptr target="http://www.corimu.unisi.it/public/frontend"
                  />.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
