<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="full"><title type="main">Re-interpreting the Paintings and Poems of the Lotus Sutra by a Co-occurrence Network</title><title type="sub">The Religion and Life of Aristocratic during the Japanese Medieval Ages</title></title></titleStmt><author><persName><surname>Aida</surname><forename>Aiko</forename></persName><affiliation>Japan society for the Promotion of Science</affiliation><email>nispanna@yahoo.co.jp</email></author><editionStmt><edition><date>43996</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Name, Institution</publisher><address><addrLine>Street</addrLine><addrLine>City</addrLine><addrLine>Country</addrLine><addrLine>Name</addrLine></address></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from an OASIS Open Document</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22"><label>DHConvalidator</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category"><term>Paper</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory"><term>Poster</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords"><term>Buddhist art</term><term>Japanese paintings</term><term>Poetry</term></keywords><keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics"><term>Asia</term><term>English</term><term>5th-14th Century</term><term>attribution studies and stylometric analysis</term><term>natural language processing</term><term>Art history</term><term>Theology and religious studies</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>This presentation intends to explore the correlation between Waka literature and the paintings of the whole Lotus Sutra in Japan from the eleventh to fourteenth centuries, as derived from a correspondence analysis between the two, using extracted vocabularies of annotation and visualization by applying a dimension reduction. In addition, I mainly analyze the twenty-one imperially commissioned poetry anthologies for the literature of the Lotus Sutra, and for paintings, I focus on the frontispieces of the Lotus Sutras written in gold and silver inks on indigo-dyed papers.</p><p>In particular, I attempt to reinterpret the visualization of dimension reduction by using a new method such as t-SNE (t-distributed Stochastic Neighbor Embedding?in addition to conventional PCA (principal component analysis) to emphasize the differences instead of similarities.</p><p>This may further reveal the literary peculiarities of the rhetoric, the nature of the &#8220;narrative&#8221;, or the visual arts-specific rhetoric such as &#8220;decoration&#8221; and newer contexts.</p></body></text></TEI>