<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Digital Literary Stylistics Workshop</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Herrmann</surname>
                        <forename>J. Berenike</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Göttingen University Germany, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>bherrma1@gwdg.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Frontini</surname>
                        <forename>Francesca</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Instituto di Linguistica Computazionale “A. Zampolli”, CNR, Pisa, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>francesca.frontini@ilc.cnr.it</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Gemma</surname>
                        <forename>Marissa</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Max Planck Institute for Empirical Aesthetics, Frankfurt, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>marissa.gemma@aesthetics.mpg.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016-03-19T13:23:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Maciej Eder, Pedagogical University in Krakow</publisher>
                <publisher>Jan Rybicki, Jagiellonian University</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Institute of Polish Studies</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Pedagogical University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ul. Podchorazych 2</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>30-084 Krakow, Poland</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>maciej.eder@ijp-pan.krakow.pl</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.21">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Pre-Conference Workshop and Tutorial</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Stylistics</term>
                    <term>digital literary studies</term>
                    <term>authorship attribution</term>
                    <term>corpus linguistics</term>
                    <term>methods</term>
                    <term>epistemology</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>corpora and corpus activities</term>
                    <term>encoding - theory and practice</term>
                    <term>literary studies</term>
                    <term>natural language processing</term>
                    <term>prosodic studies</term>
                    <term>digitisation, resource creation, and discovery</term>
                    <term>semantic analysis</term>
                    <term>stylistics and stylometry</term>
                    <term>text analysis</term>
                    <term>french studies</term>
                    <term>philology</term>
                    <term>authorship attribution / authority</term>
                    <term>linguistics</term>
                    <term>programming</term>
                    <term>query languages</term>
                    <term>genre-specific studies: prose, poetry, drama</term>
                    <term>english studies</term>
                    <term>german studies</term>
                    <term>linking and annotation</term>
                    <term>data mining / text mining</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                    <term>rhetorical studies</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>The study of textual style by computational means has a long tradition, but only quite recently have such approaches been able to leave the sphere of forensics to become an instrument of legitimate literary analysis of style.</p>
            <p>This new line of research has already yielded a considerable range of digital style studies of epochs, genres, and authors (e.g., Egbert, 2012, Hoover, 2007, Houston, 2013, Mahlberg, 2012). At the same time, questions of conceptualization (e.g., Herrmann et al., 2015) and method (e.g., Jockers, 2013, Moretti, 2013 and 2005) have quickly arisen, and it has become clear that the use of software and computational means does not necessarily imply the adherence to a strictly experimental methodological approach (cf. Ramsay, 2011).</p>
            <p>In this workshop, we shall explore novel empirical findings as well as methodological and epistemological questions connected with the computational study of style. In particular, we intend to address topics that fall within the following domains: </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold">(A.) The technical domain.</hi> Tools/methods of analysis (computational stylistics, corpus stylistics, literary authorship attribution, NLP, digital hermeneutics); research infrastructures and corpus building;
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold">(B.) The empirical domain.</hi> Style variation across factors such as genre, author, gender, epoch and period; narrative perspective and characterization; non-literary registers;
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold">(C.) The conceptual domain. </hi>Notion(s) of style; style and aesthetics; typology of style indicators; style production and reception; research design (“close”, “scalable”, and “distant reading”); epistemological status of data; issues of representativeness.
            </p>
            <p>First, the workshop will feature a set of papers focused on the technical side of digital literary stylistics. 
                <hi rend="bold">Jean-Gabriel Ganascia</hi> will present a tool for establishing stylistic distinctiveness on the basis of syntax (“Towards a computational and syntax-based stylistics”) and 
                <hi rend="bold">Tomoji Tabata</hi> will evaluate a series of Eder's (2015) “Rolling Stylometry” techniques (“Experimental Stylistics: A Meta-analysis to Evaluate Rolling Stylometry”).
            </p>
            <p>Next, we turn our attention to empirical findings about style. Papers in this category include 
                <hi rend="bold">Christof Schöch</hi>’s computationally-informed revision of Spitzer’s take on Racine (“Spitzer on Racine, digitally revisited”); 
                <hi rend="bold">Natalie Houston</hi>’s discussion of period-specific styles in nineteenth-century British poetry (“Towards a Computational Poetics: Some Features of Nineteenth-Century Poetic Style”); 
                <hi rend="bold">Anne Bandry-Scubbi</hi>’s presentation of stylistic differences between male and female authors in a corpus of novels between 1750-1830 (“Women’s Novels 1750s-1830s and the Company They Keep: A Computational Stylistic Approach”); 
                <hi rend="bold">Jan Rybicki</hi>’s analysis of how most frequent word usage changes with time in the oeuvre of authors of various languages and literary periods (“Authorial chronology by most frequent words: do writers’ stylometric thumbprints evolve with age?”), and 
                <hi rend="bold">Christine Knoop</hi>’s analysis of the distribution of rhyme and cadence schemata in German lyrical poetry between 1700-1930 (“Rhyme and Cadence Distribution in Poetry”).
            </p>
            <p>Finally, the workshop will address ‘style’ conceptually within the framework of computational analysis, with papers including a discussion by 
                <hi rend="bold">Mike Kestemont</hi> of different ways of understanding artistic authenticity in various humanistic disciplines (“The Matter of Art: Authenticity Criticism in the Humanities”); a paper by 
                <hi rend="bold">Sarah Allison</hi> on what the humanistic adoption of the statistics concept of a ‘proxy’ means for stylistic research (“A Proxy for Style”); and 
                <hi rend="bold">Fotis Jannidis</hi> on whether the concept of “historical period” is a meaningful notion in stylometry (“Period Styles”). Expanding this conceptual discussion, 
                <hi rend="bold">Hugh Craig</hi> will present some possible remedies to critiques of descriptive quantitative stylistics  (“Beyond Authorship”), and 
                <hi rend="bold">Mark Algee-Hewitt</hi> will examine how two common assumptions in digital literary stylistics (that authors are individuals with identifiable mentalities, and, in the pragmatics of authorship attribution, that these individuals can be reduced to probabilities of word frequencies) affect our notion of the author (“The Author: Between Style and Substance”).
            </p>
            <p>Insights from the three domains will be drawn together in a discussion panel. Here, we will identify current topics and trends, define the horizons of “Digital Literary Stylistics” and map out the avenues of collaboration between its different branches. Our aim is to define a shared roadmap for a Special Interest Group (SIG) within the ADHO for the field of Digital Literary Stylistics. A special issue of a DH journal will comprise the papers as well as a report of this discussion.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Biber, D.</hi> (2011). Corpus linguistics and the study of literature: Back to the future?. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Scientific Study of Literature</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="bold">1</hi>(1): 15–23 doi:10.1075/ssol.1.1.02bib.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Craig, D. H. and Kinney, A. F.</hi> (2009). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Shakespeare, Computers, and the Mystery of Authorship</hi>. Cambridge University Press 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Dalen-Oskam, K. van</hi> (2014). Epistolary voices. The case of Elisabeth Wolff and Agatha Deken. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="bold">29</hi>(3): 443–51 doi:10.1093/llc/fqu023.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Eder, M.</hi> (2015). Rolling stylometry. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="bold">30</hi>, first published online: 7 April 2015, doi: 10.1093/llc/gqv010.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Egbert, J.</hi> (2012). Style in nineteenth century fiction: A Multi-Dimensional analysis. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Scientific Study of Literature</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="bold">2</hi>(2): 167–98 doi:10.1075/ssol.2.2.01egb.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Erlin, M.</hi> (2014). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Distant Readings: Topologies of German Culture in the Long Nineteenth Century</hi>. Boydell and Brewer.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Evert, S., et al.</hi> (2015). Towards a better understanding of Burrows’s Delta in literary authorship attribution. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Fourth Workshop on Computational Linguistics for Literature, at NAACL HLT 2015</hi>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Ganascia, J.G., Glaudes, P. and Lungo, A. D.</hi> (2014). Automatic detection of reuses and citations in literary texts. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="bold">29</hi>(3): 412–21 doi:10.1093/llc/fqu020.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Herbelot, A.</hi> (2015). The semantics of poetry: A distributional reading. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="bold">30</hi>(4): 516–31.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Herrmann, J. B., Dalen-Oskam, K. van and Schöch, C.</hi> (2015). Revisiting Style, a Key Concept in Literary Studies. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Literary Theory</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="bold">9</hi>(1): 25–52 doi:10.1515/jlt-2015-0003.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Holmes, D. I. </hi>(1988). The Analysis of Literary Style--A Review. In Thoiron, P., Labbé, D. and Serant, D. (eds), 
                        <hi rend="italic">Vocabulary Structure and Lexical Richness</hi>. Paris: Champion-Slatkine, pp. 67–76.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Hoover, D. L.</hi> (2007). Corpus Stylistics, Stylometry, and the Styles of Henry James. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Style</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="bold">47</hi>: 174–203.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Houston, N. M.</hi> (2014). Toward a Computational Analysis of Victorian Poetics. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Victorian Studies</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="bold">56</hi>(3): 498–510 doi:10.2979/victorianstudies.56.3.498.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Jockers, M. L.</hi> (2013). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Macroanalysis: Digital Methods and Literary History</hi>. (Topics in the Digital Humanities). University of Illinois Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Kestemont, M., et al.</hi> (2012). Cross-Genre Authorship Verification Using Unmasking. 
                        <hi rend="italic">English Studies</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="bold">93</hi>(3): 340–56 doi:10.1080/0013838X.2012.668793.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Klaussner, C., Nerbonne, J. and Çöltekin, Ç.</hi> (2015). Finding characteristic features in stylometric analysis. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="bold">30</hi>(suppl 1): 114–29.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Lynch, G. and Vogel, C.</hi> (2015). Chasing the Ghosts of Ibsen: A computational stylistic analysis of drama in translation. 
                        <hi rend="italic">SciRate</hi> https://scirate.com/arxiv/1501.00841 (accessed 18 March 2016).
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Mahlberg, M.</hi> (2012). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Corpus Stylistics and Dickens’s Fiction</hi>. 1st ed. (Routledge Advances in Corpus Linguistics). New York: Routledge http://www.routledge.com/books/details/9780415800143/.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Moretti, F.</hi> (2005). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Graphs, Maps, Trees: Abstract Models for a Literary History</hi>. London; New York: Verso.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Ramsay, S.</hi> (2008). Algorithmic Criticism. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Companion to Digital Literary Studies</hi>. (Blackwell Companions to Literature and Culture). Oxford: Blackwell Publishing Professional http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companionDLS/ (accessed 24 February 2010).
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Rybicki, J. and Heydel, M.</hi> (2013). The stylistics and stylometry of collaborative translation: Woolf’s Night and Day in Polish. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> doi:10.1093/llc/fqt027. http://llc.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2013/05/26/llc.fqt027 (accessed 12 June 2013).
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Rybicki, J., Hoover, D. and Kestemont, M.</hi> (2014). Collaborative authorship: Conrad, Ford and Rolling Delta. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="bold">29</hi>(3): 422–31 doi:10.1093/llc/fqu016.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Stajner, S. and Zampieri, M.</hi> (2013). Stylistic Changes for Temporal Text Classification. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 16th International Conference on Text Speech and Dialogue (TSD2013), Lecture Notes in Artificial Intelligence (LNAI)</hi>. Pilsen, Czech Republic.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
