<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Enabling the Encoding of Manuscripts within the DTABf</title>
        <title type="sub">Extension and Modularization of the Format</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Susanne</forename>
            <surname>Haaf</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Susanne Haaf studied German philology and computational linguistics (M.A.) at
            the universities of Heidelberg and Zürich. From 2007 to 2010 she worked as a
              <roleName>research assistant</roleName> for the edition project Martin Bucers Deutsche
            Schriften at the <orgName>Heidelberg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</orgName>. Since
            2010 she has been working as a <roleName>research assistant</roleName> at the
              <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</orgName> for the
            projects Deutsches Textarchiv (DTA) and CLARIN-D.</affiliation>
          <email>haaf@bbaw.de</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Christian</forename>
            <surname>Thomas</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Christian Thomas has studied German literature and philosophy at the
            Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin. Since 2010 he has been working as a <roleName>research
              assistant</roleName> at the <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and
              Humanities</orgName> for the projects Deutsches Textarchiv (DTA) and CLARIN-D.
            Additionally, from 2014 until 2016 he has been working as a <roleName>research
              assistant</roleName> in the project Hidden Kosmos at Berlin’s
              <orgName>Humboldt-University</orgName>.</affiliation>
          <email>thomas@bbaw.de</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>08/08/2017</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Marjorie Burghart</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Emmanuelle Morlock</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Anne Baillot</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="10">Selected Papers from the 2015 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Revues.org -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="strikethrough" scheme="css">text-decoration:line-through;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="super" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;font-size:0.83em;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>annotation of manuscripts</term>
          <term>TEI corpora</term>
          <term>chaining ODDs</term>
          <term>interoperability</term>
          <term>interchange</term>
          <term>TEI customization</term>
          <term>standardization</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2018-01-12" who="#RvdB">technical editor applied changes per author request from
        email dated <date>2017-09-26</date></change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>This paper presents work in progress on the DTA <soCalled>Base Format</soCalled> for
          Manuscripts (DTABf-M), an extension to the DTA <soCalled>Base Format</soCalled> (DTABf)
          for the TEI-conformant annotation of manuscripts. The DTABf is a TEI-subset for the
          consistent, yet unambiguous, annotation of large amounts of historical text. During our
          work on the DTA corpora, the DTABf has continuously been subject to further adaptations to
          specific annotation needs. The latest addition, the DTABf-M, contains elements,
          attributes, and values necessary for the annotation of (historical) handwritten documents.
          The goal is to provide a TEI format for diverse manuscripts in large text corpora.</p>
        <p>While the DTABf covers a wide range of phenomena found not only in printed texts but also
          in manuscripts, there are certain manuscript-specific features which have to be
          additionally represented by the DTABf-M. There are several prerequisites for DTABf-M to be
          suitable for the DTA and its workflows and processes: First, it should be based on the
          original DTABf tagset, and only extend it if unavoidable. Second, like the DTABf, the
          DTABf-M should be created in a bottom-up approach, that is, based on actual phenomena
          found in handwritten texts which are transcribed and encoded using the DTABf. Third, the
          format should complement the DTABf, not replace it. Hence, it is necessary to find a
          modular way of integrating the DTABf-M into the DTABf. This paper describes how we deal
          with these issues in the process of developing the DTABf-M.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="corrections">
        <p>This paper was revised on <date>2018-01-12</date> to correct an error in <ptr
            type="crossref" target="#figure2"/>. The previous version is archived at <ptr
            target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1734"/>.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="introduction">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>Since its beginning in 2007, the <title level="m"><ref
              target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/">Deutsches Textarchiv</ref></title> project
                (DTA)<note><bibl><title level="m">Deutsches Textarchiv: Grundlage für ein
                Referenzkorpus der neuhochdeutschen Sprache</title>, <publisher>Berlin-Brandenburg
                Academy of Sciences and Humanities</publisher>, accessed January 28, 2017, <ptr
                target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/"/>.</bibl></note> has been creating a
          corpus of historical German printed works dating from the seventeenth to the nineteenth
          century. The underlying bibliography comprises works of various text types and domains in
          order to allow for comprehensive insights into the whole range of written material
          available in the German language at different points in time. The corpus allows for
          research on the development of the New High German language as well as research from
          various other disciplines, such as historical or literary studies.</p>
        <p>An important goal in this context was to ensure interoperability of all corpus data,
          which requires homogeneous TEI annotation of the whole corpus. For this purpose, the DTA
              <soCalled><ref target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/doku/basisformat">Base
              Format</ref></soCalled> (DTABf) was developed, a TEI format for the unambiguous,
          homogeneous annotation of corpus data (<ref target="#geyken12" type="bibl">Geyken et al.
            2012</ref>; <ref target="#haaf1415" type="bibl">Haaf, Geyken, and Wiegand
            2014–15</ref>).<note>See <bibl><title level="m">DTA-Basisformat: TEI-Format für die
                Auszeichnung historischer Texte</title>, <publisher>Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of
                Sciences and Humanities</publisher>, accessed January 28, 2017, <ptr
                target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/doku/basisformat"/></bibl>.</note> It was
          continuously adapted to tagging requirements of the DTA core corpus texts as well as of
          external texts curated from other projects (<ref target="#thomas15b" type="bibl">Thomas
            and Wiegand 2015</ref>), and successfully applied to more than 2,800 historical works
          contained in the DTA. Moreover, the DTABf has attracted interest beyond the borders of the
          DTA project (e.g., from the projects <title level="m"><ref
              target="http://juedische-geschichte-online.net/projekt/edition/">Hamburger
              Schlüsseldokumente zur deutsch-jüdischen Geschichte</ref></title><note><bibl><title
                level="m">Hamburger Schlüsseldokumente zur deutsch-jüdischen Geschichte: Eine
                Online-Quellenedition</title>, <publisher>Institut für die Geschichte der deutschen
                Juden</publisher>, accessed January 28, 2017, <ptr
                target="http://juedische-geschichte-online.net/projekt/edition/"/>.</bibl></note>
          and <title level="m"><ref target="http://www.epoetics.de/">ePoetics</ref></title><note
            rend="inside.parenthesis">See <bibl><title level="m">ePoetics: Korpuserschließung und
                Visualisierung deutschsprachiger Poetiken (1770–1960) für den <soCalled>Algorithmic
                  criticism</soCalled></title>, <publisher>Technische Universität
                Darmstadt</publisher>, accessed January 28, 2017, <ptr
                target="http://www.epoetics.de/"/>.</bibl></note>). It is now, among other formats,
          recommended by the CLARIN infrastructure project for the annotation of historical printed
          sources (<ref target="#clarin12" type="bibl">CLARIN-D AP 5 2012, II.6</ref>), as well as
          by the German Research Foundation for basic TEI encoding of linguistic corpora (<ref
            target="#dfg15a" type="bibl">DFG 2015a</ref>) and as an archival format for edition
          projects in literary studies (<ref target="#dfg15b" type="bibl">DFG 2015b</ref>).</p>
        <p>While until recently the DTA corpus and hence the DTABf have been focused on printed
          works, there is an increasing interest in the integration of manuscripts into the DTA
          corpus, as well, for example by scholars who are providing transcriptions and are
          interested in re-using the DTA infrastructure in terms of linguistic analysis or
          collaborative work, or, more generally, for publishing and sharing their project output
          with the scholarly community. Specifications and cautious extensions of the DTABf tagset
          for certain text types have been provided before, based on, for instance, findings by
          cooperating projects and within subcorpora integrated into the DTA platform (e.g., for
          historical newspapers and funeral sermons: see <ref target="#haaf14" type="bibl">Haaf and
            Schulz 2014</ref>). The category <soCalled>manuscripts</soCalled>, however, represents
          an extensive and diverse quantity of texts and text types, containing a significant amount
          of new and sometimes complex structural and textual phenomena.</p>
        <p>Thus, efforts were made to create a pure TEI subset for the unambiguous annotation of
          manuscripts, based on the <ref
            target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/doku/basisformat/manuskript.html"
            >DTABf</ref>.<note>See <bibl><title level="m">DTA-Basisformat für Manuskripte</title>,
                <publisher>Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</publisher>,
              accessed January 28, 2017, <ptr
                target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/doku/basisformat/manuskript.html"
              />.</bibl></note> This paper describes the development of this DTABf for Manuscripts,
          or DTABf-M, its current data basis, its present components, and the efforts towards the
          reorganization of the DTABf system as a whole in order to include the DTABf-M and previous
          extensions to the DTABf, but also to prevent the existing DTABf for printed texts from
          losing its central values of restrictedness and clarity through overly extensive
          growth.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="problem">
        <head>Problem Statement</head>
        <p>Until recently, the textual basis of the DTA corpora has almost exclusively consisted of
          printed texts of the historical New High German period (~1600 to ~1900). Nevertheless, now
          that a solid corpus basis has been created it is desirable to extend the DTA workflow to
          manuscripts as well, mainly for two reasons:</p>
        <p>First, a growing number of scholars dealing with historical German texts (e.g., digital
          scholarly editions) and focusing on the digitization of manuscripts (letters, diaries,
          etc.) would like to use the restrictive DTA guidelines as a starting point for their
          annotation, and to use the DTA platform, which requires DTABf conformity, as a publication
          and working environment for their projects. Thus, adapting the DTABf for
          manuscript-specific use and thereby enabling access to the DTA infrastructure (including
            <ref target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/doku/software#cab">linguistic
            analysis</ref><note>See <bibl><title level="a">Software im Deutschen Textarchiv, 8:
                Linguistische Analyse historischer Texte</title> (Linguistic Analysis for Historical
              Texts) (CAB), accessed January 28, 2017, <ptr
                target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/doku/software#cab"/></bibl>.</note> as
          well as <ref target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/dtaq/about">collaborative text
            correction and annotation</ref><note rend="inside.parenthesis">See <bibl><title
                level="a"><ptr type="software" xml:id="R3"
                  target="#dtaq"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="R3">DTAQ: Kollaborative Qualitätssicherung im Deutschen Textarchiv</rs></title>
              (Collaborative Quality Assurance within the DTA), accessed January 28, 2017, <rs type="url" ref="#R3"><ptr
                target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/dtaq/about"/></rs></bibl>. On the process of
            quality assurance in the DTA, see, for example, <ref target="#haaf13" type="bibl">Haaf,
              Wiegand, and Geyken 2013</ref>.</note>) is a matter of supporting scholarly projects
          in their usage of the DTA infrastructure, which is part of the DTA’s mission. Second,
          while the DTA corpus is fairly diverse with regard to (printed) text types and
          disciplines, the absence of manuscripts causes certain <soCalled>core text
            types</soCalled><note>See <ref target="#gansel11" type="bibl">Gansel 2011, 53</ref>, for
            a reflection on the term <soCalled>Kerntextsorte</soCalled> (i.e., core text
            type).</note> of writing to be underrepresented within the corpus (e.g., private
          letters, diaries, <term>alba amicorum</term>). This is due to the fact that some text
          types were rarely or never distributed in print. Therefore—in addition to the benefit of
          extending the corpus base—it is in the DTA’s own interest to include (historical)
          manuscripts in the corpus.</p>
        <p>While the DTABf covers a wide range of phenomena in printed texts, there are
          manuscript-specific features which are not covered by this format. Thus, in order to
          include manuscripts in the DTA, it is necessary to create a TEI format which provides
          solutions for manuscript-specific phenomena. To be suitable for the DTA, its workflows,
          and its processes, this format needs to address three prerequisites: <list
            rend="inline simple">
            <item>First, it should be based on the original DTABf tagset, mainly reusing it and only
              extending it if unavoidable (see <ptr type="crossref" target="#annotatingManuscripts"
              />).</item>
            <item>Second, like the DTABf, it should be created in a data-driven way, that is, based
              on actual phenomena found in handwritten texts which are transcribed and encoded using
              the DTABf (see <ptr type="crossref" target="#databasis #annotation"/>).</item>
            <item>Third, the format should complement the DTABf, not replace it. Hence, it is
              necessary to find a modular way of integrating the DTABf-M into the DTABf (see <ptr
                target="#inclusion" type="crossref"/>)</item>
          </list>.<note>These premises lead to the method of cautious extensions to the existing
            DTABf rather than the adoption of a new format within the DTA. Of course, there are
            other TEI formats for manuscript tagging, varying with regard to their scope, premises,
            and character of specifications and documentation. These include (to only name a few)
            the guidelines of the project <title level="m">Briefe und Texte aus dem intellektuellen
              Berlin um 1800</title> (<title level="m">Letters and Texts: Intellectual Berlin around
              1800</title>; <title level="a">Edition-specific TEI Encoding Guidelines</title>,
            accessed February 12, 2016, <ptr
              target="http://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/encoding-guidelines.pdf"/>), of the
            Shelley-Godwin Archive (<title level="a">Encoding the S-GA</title>, accessed January 28,
            2017, <ptr target="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/about/#encodingthesga"/>), and of the
            digital edition <title level="m">Theodor Fontane: Notizbücher</title> (<title level="m"
              >Theodor Fontane’s Notebooks</title>; accessed January 28, 2017, <ptr
              target="https://fontane-nb.dariah.eu/doku.html?id=gesamtdokumentation"/>).</note></p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="databasis">
        <head>Data Basis</head>
        <p>The DTABf for Manuscripts (DTABf-M) has been developed primarily in cooperation with the
          project <title level="m"><ref
              target="https://www.culture.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/projekte/hidden-kosmos/">Hidden
              Kosmos</ref></title>, hosted by the Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin.<note><title
              level="m">Hidden Kosmos—Reconstructing Alexander von Humboldt’s
                <soCalled>Kosmos-Lectures</soCalled>,</title> accessed January 28, 2017, <ptr
              target="https://www.culture.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/projekte/hidden-kosmos/"/>. For
            further information on the project’s aims and methods, and on the cooperation between
            DTA and Hidden Kosmos, see, for example, <ref target="#thomas15" type="bibl">Thomas
              2015</ref> and <ref target="#thomas16" type="bibl">Thomas, Fiechter, and Hug
              2016</ref>.</note> Hidden Kosmos publishes handwritten lecture notes by attendees of
          Alexander von Humboldt’s world-famous <soCalled>Kosmos-Lectures</soCalled> in 1827/28.
          Since June 2014, nine complete volumes with a total of more than 3,500 manuscript pages
          have been manually transcribed, annotated in TEI XML, and published via the DTA
          infrastructure. Most of these manuscripts were keyed manually by a vendor and published at
          an early stage in the web-based quality assurance platform <ptr type="software" xml:id="R2" 
            target="#dtaq"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R2">DTAQ</rs>. There, the transcription
          as well as the annotation of each document was checked and corrected, if necessary; DTAQ
          also provided the means to add additional markup, such as the tagging of person names
            (<gi>persName</gi>), directly at page level. After the process of quality control has
          been completed, the manuscripts were released on the DTA website.<note>For the ongoing
            publication of the Hidden Kosmos subcorpus, see the DTA search page, AvHKV subcorpus,
            accessed July 13, 2017, <ptr
              target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/search/metadata?corpus=avhkv"/>.</note>
          While the <title level="m">Hidden Kosmos</title> project is now complete, development of
          the DTABf-M continues through work on other manuscripts.</p>
        <p>The DTABf-M is being used and further enriched for <title level="m"><ref
              target="http://www.bbaw.de/en/research/avh-r">Travelling Humboldt—Science on the
              Move</ref></title>,<note>German Title: <title level="m">Alexander von Humboldt auf
              Reisen—Wissenschaft aus der Bewegung</title>; project homepage, accessed January 28,
            2017, <ptr target="http://www.bbaw.de/en/research/avh-r"/>.</note> a long-term project
          at the Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and the Humanities. The project aims to
          provide a digital critical edition of handwritten documents by Alexander von Humboldt
          connected to his American and Siberian journeys, including his travel journals, which
          display a very complex order of text segments on each page and were composed and altered
          in several writing stages.</p>
        <p>Though these two data sources are homogeneous with regard to time of creation (early
          nineteenth century), they already included various manuscript-specific phenomena, both
          frequent (e.g., additions and deletions to the text basis) and rare (e.g., inline notes),
          that the DTABf-M tagset could be based upon.</p>
        <p>A third addition to the DTA manuscript corpus is provided by the project <title level="m"
              ><ref
              target="http://www.histinst.uni-jena.de/Bereiche/Geschlechtergeschichte/Projekte/Digitale+Edition+der+Briefe+Erdmuthe+Benignas+von+Reuß_Ebersdorf+.html"
              >Digitale Edition der Briefe Erdmuthe Benignas von
              Reuß-Ebersdorf</ref></title>,<note><title level="m">Digitale Edition der Briefe
              Erdmuthe Benignas von Reuß-Ebersdorf (Digital Edition of Erdmuthe Benigna of
              Reuß-Ebersdorf’s letters)</title>, project at the Department of History at
            Friedrich-Schiller-University Jena, accessed January 28, 2017, <ptr
              target="http://www.histinst.uni-jena.de/Bereiche/Geschlechtergeschichte/Projekte/Digitale+Edition+der+Briefe+Erdmuthe+Benignas+von+Reuß_Ebersdorf+.html"
            />.</note> where a corpus of letters and other handwritten documents of this pietistic
          regent from the early eighteenth century is being prepared for a digital scholarly
          edition.</p>
        <p>Plans to further develop DTABf-M will rely on additional historical sources in the course
          of their inclusion in the corpus.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="towardDTABfM">
        <head>Steps toward the DTABf for Manuscripts (DTABf-M)</head>
        <div xml:id="annotatingManuscripts">
          <head>From Annotating Printed Texts to Annotating Manuscripts</head>
          <p>Our approach is to base the DTABf for manuscripts on the established DTABf for printed
            texts, reusing the existing tagset wherever possible and only making changes
            (enhancements or reductions) when new tags are needed to represent phenomena exclusively
            found in manuscripts or printed texts, respectively. This is rather straightforward,
            since, as exemplified by <ptr type="crossref"
              target="#figure1 #figure2 #figure3 #figure4"/>, a large number of textual phenomena
            can be found in both handwritten and printed texts. <ptr target="#figure1"
              type="crossref"/> illustrates a printed page containing some common text structures
            together with the DTABf elements that apply in those cases. Phenomena on this page
            include marginal notes, figures, poems, and paragraphs. <ptr type="crossref"
              target="#figure2 #figure3 #figure4"/> show examples of manuscript pages containing
            similar text structures, showing that the same DTABf elements can be applied there. In
            fact, much of the DTABf tagset for printed texts can similarly be applied to
            manuscripts.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure1" n="1.1">
            <!-- [CT/SH] @RvdB: Either it should be "Fig.s 1–4: Examples of textual structures in printed texts and annotation conventions within the DTABf.", i.e. Examples = plural, or each of the Fig.s should have the legend text "Example of textual structures in printed texts and annotation conventions within the DTABf.", i.e. "Example" in singular. -->
            <graphic url="images/image1.png" height="1083px" width="1455px"/>
            <head type="legend">Example of textual structures in printed texts and annotation
              conventions within the DTABf.</head>
            <head type="license">(<ref target="#andrea1616" type="bibl">Andreä 1616</ref>, <ptr
                target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/valentin_hochzeit_1616/9"/>).</head>
          </figure>
          <figure xml:id="figure2" n="1.2">
            <graphic url="images/image2.png" height="558px" width="1575px"/>
            <head type="legend">Example of textual structures in manuscripts and possible ways to
              annotate them with DTABf tags.</head>
            <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#hufeland1829">Hufeland [ca. 1829]</ref>,
                <ptr target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/hufeland_privatbesitz_1829/149"
              />).</head>
          </figure>
          <figure xml:id="figure3" n="1.3">
            <graphic url="images/image3.png" height="131px" width="624px"/>
            <head type="legend">Example of textual structures in manuscripts and possible ways to
              annotate them with DTABf tags.</head>
            <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#hufeland1829">Hufeland [ca. 1829]</ref>,
                <ptr target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/hufeland_privatbesitz_1829/88"
              />).</head>
          </figure>
          <figure xml:id="figure4" n="1.4">
            <graphic url="images/image4.png" height="175px" width="676px"/>
            <head type="legend">Example of textual structures in manuscripts and possible ways to
              annotate them with DTABf tags.</head>
            <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#hufeland1829">Hufeland [ca. 1829]</ref>,
                <ptr target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/hufeland_privatbesitz_1829/139"
              />).</head>
          </figure>
          <p>As illustrated by <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure1 #figure2 #figure3 #figure4"/>,
            there are many structural similarities between handwritten and printed texts with regard
            to document structure, the arrangement of the text, and the meaning of layout specifics.
            Furthermore, inline phenomena may also display similarities. For instance, even certain
            types of emphasis are at least comparable, if not identical, between printed texts and
            manuscripts.</p>
          <p>One example of change in the style of handwriting is illustrated in <ptr
              target="#figure5" type="crossref"/>. The style changed from old German script
            (Kurrent) for the general text body to Latin script for distinct terms like proper names
            or foreign language material. We consider this to be analogous to the change of font
            from Blackletter (Fraktur) to Antiqua types in print. The DTABf solution for changes
            from Fraktur to Antiqua typeface is to use the <gi>hi</gi> element with
              <att>rendition</att>=<val>#aq</val>. This tagging can thus be used similarly for
            changes from Kurrent to Latin script in manuscripts (<ptr type="crossref"
              target="#figure5"/>).<note>Note that the snippets provided below the figures within
              the following examples illustrate the DTABf-M-conformant transcription and annotation
              of the text passage under consideration. The URL provided in each example leads to the
              page of the document from which the example was taken. The tagging is simplified in
              some instances by leaving out annotations that are not central to the purpose of this
              paper. As described in the introduction, some manuscripts are still being processed
              for quality assurance, and therefore only available in DTAQ, where registration and
              password are required to access the documents.</note></p>
          <figure xml:id="figure5" n="1.5">
            <graphic url="images/image5.png" width="624px" height="40px"/>
            <head type="legend">The proper names <q>Herschel</q>, <q>Bonpland</q>, and
                <q>Jupiter</q> are distinguished by the use of Latin script from the remainder of
              the text written in Kurrent.</head>
            <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#anonym1827a">Anonymous [1827/28a]</ref>,
                <ptr target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/nn_msgermqu2345_1827/58"/>).</head>
          </figure>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> […] haben <hi rendition="#aq"
              >Herschel</hi> und <hi rendition="#aq">Bonpland</hi> den <hi rendition="#aq"
              >Jupiter</hi> noch 18<lb/>[…] </egXML>
          <p>Another example for similar inline phenomena in manuscripts and printed texts is the
            underlining of important phrases or keywords, represented in the DTABf as <tag>hi
              rendition=&quot;#u&quot;</tag> for printed texts and manuscripts alike. Furthermore,
            though this feature is far more frequent in prints, manuscripts may also contain
            catchwords or signature marks at the bottom of the page, which we tag as <gi>fw</gi>
            with <att>type</att>=<val>catch</val> or <att>type</att>=<val>sig</val>,
            respectively.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure6" n="1.6">
            <graphic url="images/image6.png" width="624px" height="119px"/>
            <head type="legend">The last two lines of running text, followed by a signature mark and
              a catchword at the bottom of the page.</head>
            <head type="license">(<ref target="#anonym1827b" type="bibl">Anonymous [1827/28b]</ref>,
                <ptr target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/nn_n0171w1_1828/41"/>).</head>
          </figure>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <p>[…] des vergleichen.</p><lb/>
            <p>Dieſe große Entdeckung trifft merkwürdiger<lb/>
              <fw type="sig" place="bottom">Phyſiſche Erdbeſchreibung <hi rendition="#aq"
                >e</hi>.</fw>
              <fw type="catch" place="bottom"><hi rendition="#u">Weiſe</hi></fw><lb/>[…]</p>
          </egXML>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="annotation">
          <head>DTABf-M: Manuscript-specific Text Annotation</head>
          <p>Despite the abovementioned similarities, there are certain features that are specific
            to manuscripts and which require additional tagging solutions within the DTABf-M. In
            this section, we will give some examples of features which occur in our manuscript
            corpus and introduce their structural representation within the DTABf-M. Subsequently,
            we will give an overview of those manuscript-specific TEI elements which we have
            identified so far as necessary to be included in a DTABf extension for manuscripts
            (DTABf-M). Compared to the DTA corpus of printed texts with its more than 3,000
              works,<note>Approx. 670,000 pages as of December 2016.</note> the data basis for the
            DTABf-M is quite small (129 works).<note>Approx. 4,500 pages as of December 2016.</note>
            Thus, the number of manuscript-specific elements, attributes, and values illustrated in
            the examples is not exhaustive and will not fit any given manuscript precisely. However,
            in comparing the texts of the manuscript corpus it is possible to differentiate common
            from less common features. Thus, though the DTABf-M tagset might still have to be
            augmented in the future, the proposed tagging solutions do cover phenomena common in
            handwritten sources and therefore should be applicable to other manuscripts and for the
            integration of further handwritten sources into the DTA corpora.</p>
          <p>The DTABf had to be extended especially with respect to traces of the writing process,
            such as <foreign xml:lang="la">ad hoc</foreign> corrections by substitution, deletion,
            or addition of characters, words, or passages, and change of hands or writing devices.
            These phenomena can be observed in many manuscripts. Manuscript-specific extensions to
            the DTABf were applied following the principles of simplicity, consistency, and
            avoidance of ambiguousness, as established for the DTABf. To achieve the latter, DTABf-M
            specifications were created not only on element and attribute level, but also with
            regard to attribute values that utilize specified vocabularies for phenomena in
            manuscripts (e.g., for typical methods of deletion or addition).</p>
          <div xml:id="deladd">
            <head>Deletions and Additions</head>
            <p>Common features of manuscripts are corrections to the original text, carried out by
              adding or deleting textual material. Unlike in printed texts, where manual corrections
              are usually made on a text which has previously been finalized for the printed
              publication, corrections in manuscripts are part of the text creation and amelioration
              process. The TEI elements relevant to these phenomena are <title level="a">Core
                Elements for Transcriptional Work</title> within the TEI Guidelines section on
                <title level="a">Representation of Primary Sources</title> (<ref type="bibl"
                target="#tei16">TEI Consortium 2016, 11; 11.3.1.1</ref>). They include <gi>add</gi>
              (for additions) and <gi>del</gi> (for deletions), which can be grouped within
                <gi>subst</gi> to represent the substitution of a correct character or phrase for an
              erroneous one (<ref target="#tei16" type="bibl">TEI Consortium 2016, 11.3.1.4</ref>).
              Thus, while it was possible to leave these elements unconsidered for the DTABf for
              printed material, they became an immensely important part of the DTABf-M.</p>
            <p>Superfluous textual material in manuscripts may be deleted without substitute.
              Similarly, characters, words, or phrases missing in a written text may be added with
              no need to erase text. Thus, the elements <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi> may be used
              separately without the element <gi>subst</gi>, for instance, where an erroneous
              character, word, or passage was crossed out (as illustrated in <ptr type="crossref"
                target="#figure7 #figure8"/>) or erased (<ptr type="crossref" target="#figure9"/>),
              or where missing text was added (<ptr type="crossref" target="#figure10 #figure11"
              />).</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure7" n="2.1">
              <graphic url="images/image7.png" width="524px" height="69px"/>
              <head type="legend">The name <q>Parry</q>,<note>Referring to the English naval officer
                  and Arctic explorer William Edward Parry (1790–1855); for an authority file
                  reference, see <ptr target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/116048166"/> (accessed January
                  30, 2017). Parry is one of the persons most frequently mentioned in the course of
                  Humboldt’s Kosmos-Lectures: see the overview on personal names retrieved from the
                  attendee’s lecture notes of the two courses at the Berlin University and the
                  Sing-Akademie building, accessed January 30, 2017, <ptr
                    target="http://deutschestextarchiv.de/kosmos/person"/>.</note> initially
                misspelled as <q>Parray</q>, was corrected by crossing out the extra
                <q>a</q>.</head>
              <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#anonym1827b">Anonymous
                  [1827/28b]</ref>
                <ptr target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/nn_n0171w1_1828/291"/>).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <p><hi rendition="#aq">Parr<del rendition="#s">a</del>y</hi> hat an der Spitze der
                Maſten […].</p>
            </egXML>
            <figure xml:id="figure8" n="2.2">
              <graphic url="images/image8.png" height="61px" width="624px"/>
              <head type="legend">The (apparently) superfluous word <q>einander</q> (<q>each
                  other</q>) was crossed out.<note>Translation: <q>[…] that were brought near to
                    each other with big winches […]</q>.</note></head>
              <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#parthey1827">Parthey [1827/28]</ref>,
                  <ptr target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/parthey_msgermqu1711_1828/131"
                />).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> […] die man mit grossen Winden <del
                rendition="#s">einander</del> näherte […] </egXML>
            <p>Besides crossing out misspellings or mistakenly-notated characters or words, it is
              also a common method within manuscripts to erase characters or passages by rubbing or
              scraping them out (<ptr type="crossref" target="#figure9"/>).</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure9" n="2.3">
              <graphic url="images/image9.png" width="624px" height="52px"/>
              <head type="legend">The term initially spelled <q>Esquimeaux</q> was altered to the
                more common spelling <q>Esquimaux</q> by erasing the superfluous <q>e</q> (which has
                become almost invisible in the manuscript).<note>Translation: <q>[…] living Eskimos
                    [i.e., Inuit] from Eastern Greenland […]</q>.</note></head>
              <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#anonym1828">Anonymous [1828]</ref>,
                  <ptr target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/nn_msgermqu2124_1827/62"/>).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> […] lebendige <hi rendition="#aq"
                  >Esquim<del rendition="#erased">e</del>aux</hi> aus Ostgrönland […] </egXML>
            <p>Additions of characters or words can be realized within, above, or under the line
                (<ptr target="#figure10 #figure11" type="crossref"/>), or in the right or left
              margin of a page.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure10" n="2.4">
              <graphic url="images/image10.png" width="624px" height="95px"/>
              <head type="legend">The word initially written, <q>Beruhigung</q>, was altered by
                adding the syllable <q>un</q>, changing its meaning to the direct opposite
                    <q>Be<emph>un</emph>ruhigung</q> (from <q>reassurance</q> to
                <q>disturbance</q>).</head>
              <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#anonym1827c">Anonymous
                  [1827/28c]</ref>, <ptr
                  target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/nn_oktavgfeo79_1828/220"/>).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <p>Was die Be<metamark/><add place="superlinear">un</add>ruhigung anbetrifft, […].</p>
            </egXML>
            <figure xml:id="figure11" n="2.5">
              <graphic url="images/image11.png" width="624px" height="87px"/>
              <head type="legend">The words <q>von Paris</q> (<q>of Paris</q>) are added below the
                line, to mark clearly that the <q>mittl[ere] T[emperatur]</q> (<q>average
                  temperature</q>) of this specific place is meant.</head>
              <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#parthey1827">Parthey [1827/28]</ref>,
                  <ptr target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/parthey_msgermqu1711_1828/619"
                />).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> […] wird die mittl. T. <metamark/><add
                place="sublinear">von Paris </add> durch den Monat Mai dargestelt. </egXML>
            <p>The place where added text is meant to be inserted is often marked with some sign or
              arrow (see <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure10 #figure11 #figure16"/>). To enable
              the encoding of such signs in the manuscript text we additionally included the TEI
              element <gi>metamark</gi> in the DTABf-M tagset; the abovementioned figures provide
              transcriptions illustrating the usage of the <gi>metamark</gi> element.</p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="substitutions">
            <head>Substitutions</head>
            <p>Deletions and additions may also be parts of a substitution process, where erroneous
              text was deleted in favor of a correct version which was added to the original text.
              In such cases, <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi> are grouped inside a <gi>subst</gi>
              element according to the TEI P5 Guidelines, as shown in <ptr type="crossref"
                target="#figure12 #figure13 #figure14 #figure15"/> (<ref target="#tei16" type="bibl"
                >TEI Consortium 2016, 11.3.1.5</ref>). Moreover, the following two examples
              illustrate the necessity of adding a value <att>rendition</att>=<val>#ow</val> (for
                <soCalled>overwritten</soCalled>) to the DTABf-M which can be used in this context
              within <gi>del</gi>.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure12" n="3.1">
              <graphic url="images/image12.png" width="624px" height="47px"/>
              <head type="legend">Substitution of the characters <q>d</q> and <q>t</q> by
                overwriting the former with the latter.<note>Translation: <q>[…] no difference
                    between human mummies […]</q>. Either the writer initially set out to write
                    <q>und</q> (<q>and</q>) instead of <q>unter</q> (<q>under</q>), then corrected
                  his mistake immediately by substituting a <q>t</q> for the <q>d</q> and continuing
                  to complete the word as <q>unter</q>, or he initially misspelled the German word
                    <q>unter</q> as <q>under</q>, and fixed his mistake after the word was
                  written.</note></head>
              <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#hufeland1829">Hufeland [ca.
                  1829]</ref>, <ptr
                  target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/hufeland_privatbesitz_1829/28"
                />).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> […] keinen Unterschied un<subst><del
                  rendition="#ow">d</del><add place="across">t</add></subst>er menschlichen Mumien
              […] </egXML>
            <figure xml:id="figure13" n="3.2">
              <graphic url="images/image13.png" width="624px" height="58px"/>
              <head type="legend"><q>vor den</q> (which in the historical New High German language
                in this case means <q>for the</q>, indicating a singular form) was overwritten with
                  <q>für die</q> (<q>for the</q>, here indicating plural form).</head>
              <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#reuss1717">Reuß-Ebersdorf 1717</ref>,
                  <ptr
                  target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/reuss_paragiatsherrschaftabiv15_1717/4"
                />).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> […] iahr <subst><del rendition="#ow"
                  >vor den</del><add place="across">für die</add></subst> ockßen die
                  <choice><orig>wißen</orig><reg>wiesen</reg></choice> ab<lb/>[…] </egXML>
            <figure xml:id="figure14" n="3.3">
              <graphic url="images/image14.png" width="626px" height="55px"/>
              <head type="legend">Here, the superlative <q>entferntesten</q> (<q>most distant</q>)
                is taken back by scratching out the last four letters and replacing them with
                  <q>en</q>, changing the word to <q>entfernten</q> (<q>distant</q>), obviously
                because the comparative form was already indicated by the pronoun <q>meisten</q>
                  (<q>the most</q>) and the additional use of the superlative would have been
                grammatically wrong.</head>
              <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#anonym1827a">Anonymous
                [1827/28]</ref>, <ptr
                  target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/nn_msgermqu2345_1827/83"/>).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> […] die am meisten entfernte<subst><del
                  rendition="#erased">sten</del><add place="across">n</add></subst> […] </egXML>
            <figure xml:id="figure15" n="3.4">
              <graphic url="images/image15.png" width="624px" height="67px"/>
              <head type="legend">The word <q>kleiner</q> (<q>smaller</q>), emphasized by an
                underline, is struck out and replaced by its direct opposite, <q>(hin) grösser</q>
                  (<q>greater</q>), notated above the line.<note>Translation: <q>[…] that the grades
                    [of longitude/latitude] become {<emph rendition="#strikethrough"
                    >smaller</emph>greater} northwards: […]</q>.</note></head>
              <head type="license">(<ref target="#parthey1827" type="bibl">Parthey [1827/28]</ref>,
                  <ptr target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/parthey_msgermqu1711_1828/293"
                />).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> […] dass die Grade gegen Norden
                  <subst><del rendition="#s"><hi rendition="#u">kleiner</hi></del><add
                  place="superlinear">hin grösser</add></subst> werden: […] </egXML>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="hands">
            <head>Different Hands or Writing Devices</head>
            <p>Another manuscript-specific phenomenon is the change of hands and/or writing. To
              distinguish the change of <term>hands</term> (i.e., different scribes) in the course
              of a writing process from the change of <term>writing devices</term> (i.e., the same
              scribe using, e.g., a pencil instead of their regular ink for certain alterations of
              the text), we use the <gi>handNote</gi> element in the TEI Header.<note><ref
                  target="#tei16" type="bibl">TEI Consortium 2016</ref>, <ptr
                  target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.0.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-handNote.html"
                />.</note> There, an <att>xml:id</att> is assigned to the respective scribe, scribal
                act,<note>That is, different <gi>handNote</gi> elements can represent the same
                scribe using different writing devices.</note> or writing device (in case the scribe
              cannot be identified). This <att>xml:id</att> is then used as a referencing value of
                <att>hand</att> in the transcription.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure16" n="4.1">
              <graphic url="images/image16.png" width="624px" height="103px"/>
              <head type="legend">In the second line to be seen in the image scan, the word
                  <q>ein</q> (<q>a</q>) and the words <q>der Lichtstärke</q> (<q>of the light’s
                  intensity</q>) have been inserted. Whereas the first addition was written using
                the same ink and by the same hand as the remainder of the passage, the second
                addition was clearly written with a different, darker ink, but still by the same
                hand, i.e., by the same scribe, in this case Gustav Parthey (therefore labelled as
                  <att>hand</att>=<val>#Parthey_darkInk</val>).<note>Translation: <q>[…] show a
                    bright center surrounded by an illuminated shell: in this illuminated shell an
                    increasing and decreasing of the light’s intensity can be observed, an ebb
                    […]</q>.</note></head>
              <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#parthey1827">Parthey [1827/28]</ref>,
                  <ptr target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/parthey_msgermqu1711_1828/7"
                />).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> […] hellen Kern mit einer Lichthülle
              umgeben zeigen: in dieser<lb/> Lichthülle nimt man <metamark/><add place="superlinear"
                >ein </add> Ab- und Zunehmen <metamark/><add place="superlinear"
                hand="#Parthey_darkInk">der Lichtstärke </add>wahr, eine Ebbe<lb/>[…] </egXML>
            <p>The encoding of these phenomena may help differentiate whether certain alterations
              are <foreign xml:lang="la">ad hoc</foreign> corrections, carried out during the
              writing process, or later interventions performed when proofreading or commenting on
              the finished text or the completed draft.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, we found in our manuscript corpus various occurrences for the phenomenon
              that words or phrases from one scribe were underlined by another, using a different
              writing device, as shown in <ptr target="#figure17" type="crossref"/>. Here, the
              person responsible for the underlining could not be identified. Therefore, the hand
              has the identifier <val>#pencil</val>, referring to both the scribe and the writing
                device.<note>This consistent usage of <att>hand</att> within <gi>hi</gi> and
                  <gi>note</gi> and several other elements was made possible only recently (March
                29, 2016) with the TEI P5 release 3.0.0: see <bibl><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>
                  <date>2016</date>, <title level="a">TEI P5 version 3.0.0 release notes</title>,
                    <ptr
                    target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.0.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/readme-3.0.0.html"
                  /></bibl>.</note>
            </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure17" n="4.2">
              <graphic url="images/image17.png" width="624px" height="92px"/>
              <head type="legend">The main body of the text was written with dark ink and two terms
                were underlined (here, presumably to mark them as questionable) by a different
                scribe using a pencil.<note>Translation: <q>By the time Encke’s Comet reappeared in
                    Paramala [i.e., Paramatta, then a settlement of its own, today a suburb of
                    Sydney], Mister Dummler [probably referring to James Dunlop (1793–1848; see the
                    authority record, accessed January 30, 2017, <ptr
                      target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/102456828"/>)] claims to have observed a rotation
                    of the comet tail of […]</q>.</note></head>
              <head type="license">(<ref target="#anonym1827b" type="bibl">Anonymous
                  [1827/28b]</ref>, <ptr
                  target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/nn_n0171w1_1828/216"/>).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> Als der <hi rendition="#aq"
              >Enke</hi>ſche Comet in <hi rendition="#u" hand="#pencil">Paramala</hi> wieder
              er-<lb/> ſchien will <choice><abbr>H￼</abbr><expan>Herr</expan></choice>
              <hi rendition="#aq"><hi rendition="#u" hand="#pencil">Dummler</hi></hi> eine Rotation
              des Schweifes von<lb/>[…] </egXML>
            <p>In the following example (<ptr target="#figure18" type="crossref"/>) it is obvious
              from the content of the note that this passage was added only in 1850, that is, much
              later than the original text was written (in 1829).<note>See the title page of the
                document from which the example was taken, Hufeland [ca. 1829], <ptr
                  target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/hufeland_privatbesitz_1829/7"/>:
                  <q>geschrieben im Sommer 1829 durch Otto Hufeland</q> (<q>written in the summer of
                  1829 by Otto Hufeland</q>). Otto Hufeland, presumably born in 1806, was a son of
                Gottlieb Hufeland (1760–1817; see the authority record, accessed January 30, 2017,
                at <ptr target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/117053961"/>), a relative of the well-known
                German physician Christoph Wilhelm Hufeland (1762–1836; see the authority record,
                accessed January 30, 2017, <ptr target="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554514"/>). His
                manuscript documenting the Kosmos-Lectures at the Sing-Akademie was written in the
                year after their closure in 1828 and contains several later additions. It is not an
                original account of the lectures, but a copy of another volume of lecture notes (cf.
                  <ref target="#anonym1828" type="bibl">Anonymous [1828]</ref>, <ptr
                  target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/nn_msgermqu2124_1827"/>).</note> Like
              the previous example, this one also contains a change of the writing device, from ink
              to pencil. The addition in this case was, corresponding to its function, tagged as a
                <gi>note</gi>.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure18" n="4.3">
              <graphic url="images/image18.png" width="624px" height="123px"/>
              <head type="legend">The additional information that between the time of Humboldt’s
                lectures (1827/28) and 1850, eleven more planets had been discovered, was inserted
                by the same scribe directly into the line, using a pencil
                  (<att>hand</att>=<val>#Hufeland_pencil</val>).</head>
              <head type="license">(<ref target="#hufeland1829" type="bibl">Hufeland [ca.
                  1829]</ref>, <ptr
                  target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/hufeland_privatbesitz_1829/19"
                />).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> […] Namen <hi rendition="#aq #u"
                >Vesta</hi> erhielt. <note place="mInline" hand="#Hufeland_pencil">(Seitdem, bis
                1850, noch 11 Planeten entdeckt)</note><lb/>[…] </egXML>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="notes">
            <head>Different Types of Notes</head>
            <p>Manuscripts—just like printed materials—may contain different types of notes,
              providing comments on the text or further information about it. While notes at the
              bottom of a page (footnotes) or at the end of a chapter or the text body (endnotes)
              are more typical for printed text types than for manuscripts, marginal notes at the
              right or left margin of a page may occur in both manuscripts and printed texts (<ptr
                target="#figure19" type="crossref"/>).</p>
            <p>In addition, notes in manuscripts may occur at several places other than the ones
              common for printed texts. They may, for example, be inserted inline or at the top or
              bottom of the text area of a page (<ptr type="crossref"
                target="#figure19 #figure20 #figure21"/>). We therefore introduced the additional
                <att>place</att> values <val>mInline</val> | <val>mTop</val> | <val>mBottom</val> to
              the <gi>note</gi> element.<note xml:id="note29">Note that the method of commencing a
                value with a letter (combination) indicating the types of text where that value may
                be used has already been pursued in the context of DTABf extensions for other text
                types, e.g., funeral sermons (<val>fs...</val>) and journals/newspapers
                  (<val>j...</val>) (see <ref type="bibl" target="#geyken12">Geyken, Haaf, and
                  Wiegand 2012, 390</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#haaf14">Haaf and Schulz 2014,
                  53</ref>). We use <val>m...</val> in this case to ensure that the <att>place</att>
                values used for manuscripts are not confused with the DTABf-conformant
                  <att>place</att> values for notes in printed texts.</note> The usage of
                <att>place</att>=<val>mInline</val> within <gi>note</gi> was already illustrated in
                <ptr target="#figure18" type="crossref"/>, while <ptr target="#figure20 #figure21"
                type="crossref"/> provide examples for the usage of
                <att>place</att>=<val>mBottom</val> and <att>place</att>=<val>mTop</val> within
                <gi>note</gi>.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure19" n="5.1">
              <graphic url="images/image19.png" height="309px" width="624px"/>
              <head type="legend">A note has been added at the left-hand side of the manuscript
                stating that the document in question has been prepared according to the addressee’s
                command.</head>
              <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#reuss1717">Reuß-Ebersdorf 1717</ref>,
                  <ptr
                  target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/reuss_paragiatsherrschaftabiv15_1717/4"
                />).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> […] schreiben ist <note rendition="#v"
                place="left" n="ˣ">nach Erldt. <choice><orig>be
                  fehl</orig><reg>befehl</reg></choice><lb/></note>
            </egXML>
            <figure xml:id="figure20" n="5.2">
              <graphic url="images/image20.png" width="624px" height="99px"/>
              <head type="legend">This note, stating that <mentioned>isotherm</mentioned>,
                  <mentioned>isothere</mentioned>, and <mentioned>isocheim</mentioned> must be well
                differentiated from one another, is recorded at the very bottom of the page.
                However, it is not referring to a certain point in the text as a footnote would, but
                is rather a general comment on the topic of the page. Therefore, we use
                  <att>place</att>=<val>mBottom</val>.</head>
              <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#anonym1827a">Anonymous
                  [1827/28a]</ref>, <ptr
                  target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/nn_msgermqu2345_1827/281"/>).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> […]<note place="mBottom">(Isotherme,
                Isothere (von gleicher Sonnenwärme wie <hi rendition="#aq">Moskau</hi><lb/>u. der
                Ausfluß der <hi rendition="#aq">Loire</hi>) = isochaimone Linien sind wohl zu
                unter-<lb/>scheiden.)</note><lb/>[…] </egXML>
            <figure xml:id="figure21" n="5.3">
              <graphic url="images/image21.png" width="624px" height="61px"/>
              <head type="legend">On the very first page of his text, this scribe made a note in the
                top right corner, stating that the table of contents for this document is to be
                found on page 155.</head>
              <head type="license">(<ref type="bibl" target="#hufeland1829">Hufeland [ca.
                  1829]</ref>, <ptr
                  target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/hufeland_privatbesitz_1829/9"/>).</head>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <note place="mTop"><hi rendition="#right">Die Übersicht des Inhaltes siehe <ref
                    target="#f0159"><hi rendition="#aq">pag</hi>: 155</ref>. <choice><orig><gap
                        reason="illegible"/></orig><reg>pp.</reg></choice>
                </hi><lb/></note><lb/>
            </egXML>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="metadata">
          <head>DTABf-M Metadata Annotation</head>
          <p>As for metadata, the DTABf already makes quite extensive use of the TEI Guidelines.
            Thus, most of the metadata information necessary for manuscripts in text corpora was
            already covered by the existing DTABf metadata tagset. There was only one significant
            change to make: instead of <gi>typeDesc</gi> we added the <gi>handDesc</gi> element with
            its child <gi>handNote</gi>.<note>Beyond that, there is only one further small
              adaptation of the metadata concerning the value list of <att>type</att> within
                <gi>bibl</gi>: it is extended by the document type <val>MAN</val> (i.e.,
              manuscript). For documentation on the specifics of DTABf-M metadata annotation, see
              the DTABf documentation section on manuscript metadata, accessed July 12, 2017, <ptr
                target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/doku/basisformat/msMetadata.html"
              />.</note> The <att>xml:id </att>in <gi>handNote</gi> identifies the hand or scribal
            act described and can be referred to from the <att>hand</att> attribute within the
            document. The writing device of each hand or scribal act is specified within a
              <att>medium</att> attribute.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="extension">
          <head>Overview: DTABf Extension for Manuscripts</head>
          <p>In <ptr type="crossref" target="#annotation"/> we presented some examples of typical
            structural and textual phenomena in manuscripts. <ptr type="crossref" target="#table1"/>
            provides an overview of the elements, attributes, and values which were introduced to
            the DTABf for manuscript encoding and of how they are related to already existing DTABf
            tags.</p>
          <p>The proposed format, DTABf-M, is still a work in progress and will be subject to
            continuous development based on further manuscripts added to the DTA corpus. Development
            will occur in a manner similar to the approach used with the DTABf for printed texts:
            extensions will be performed cautiously, in a restrictive and minimalistic manner, and
            based on actual phenomena observed in the historical text sources (<ref type="bibl"
              target="#haaf1415">Haaf, Geyken, and Wiegand 2014–15, §60–61</ref>).</p>
          <table xml:id="table1">
            <head>Manuscript-specific additions to the DTABf; * = new; <hi rendition="#super">+</hi>
              = new in this context.</head>
            <row role="label">
              <cell>Elements</cell>
              <cell>Attributes</cell>
              <cell>Values</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="label">
              <cell cols="3">Text</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rows="2">*<gi>add</gi></cell>
              <cell><hi rendition="#super">+</hi><att>place</att></cell>
              <cell>*<val>superlinear</val> | *<val>intralinear</val> | *<val>across</val> |
                  *<val>sublinear</val> | <val>left</val> | <val>right</val></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>*<att>hand</att></cell>
              <cell>e.g., <val>#JaneDoe</val>, <val>#JohnDoe</val></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><gi>corr</gi> | <gi>expan</gi> | <gi>reg</gi> | <gi>supplied</gi> |
                  <gi>unclear</gi></cell>
              <cell>*<att>resp</att></cell>
              <cell> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rows="3">*<gi>del</gi></cell>
              <cell><hi rendition="#super">+</hi><att>rendition</att></cell>
              <cell>*<val>#ow</val> | *<val>#s</val> | *<val>#erased</val></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>*<att>hand</att></cell>
              <cell>e.g., <val>#JaneDoe</val>, <val>#JohnDoe</val></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rendition="#super">+</hi><att>cert</att></cell>
              <cell><val>low</val> | <val>high</val></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><gi>div</gi></cell>
              <cell><att>type</att></cell>
              <cell>*<val>session</val></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><gi>figure</gi></cell>
              <cell><att>type</att></cell>
              <cell>*<val>stamp</val></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><gi>fw</gi></cell>
              <cell><att>type</att></cell>
              <cell>*<val>folNum</val></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><gi>head</gi></cell>
              <cell><hi rendition="#super">+</hi><att>type</att></cell>
              <cell>*<val>leftMargin</val> | *<val>rightMargin</val></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>*<gi>metamark</gi></cell>
              <cell> </cell>
              <cell> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rows="2"><gi>note</gi></cell>
              <cell><hi rendition="#super">+</hi><att>place</att></cell>
              <cell>*<val>mTop</val> | *<val>mBottom</val> | <val>mInline</val></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>*<att>hand</att></cell>
              <cell> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rows="2"><gi>space</gi></cell>
              <cell><hi rendition="#super">+</hi><att>unit</att></cell>
              <cell><val>chars</val> | <val>lines</val> | <val>pages</val> | <val>words</val></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rendition="#super">+</hi><att>quantity</att></cell>
              <cell><ident>data.count</ident></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>*<gi>subst</gi></cell>
              <cell> </cell>
              <cell> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><gi>supplied</gi></cell>
              <cell><hi rendition="#super">+</hi><att>reason</att></cell>
              <cell>*<val>covered</val> | *<val>damage</val></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>*<gi>unclear</gi></cell>
              <cell><hi rendition="#super">+</hi><att>reason</att></cell>
              <cell><val>illegible</val> | *<val>covered</val></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell cols="3" role="label">Metadata</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><gi>bibl</gi></cell>
              <cell><att>type</att></cell>
              <cell>*<val>MAN</val> (i.e., manuscript)</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>*<gi>handDesc</gi></cell>
              <cell> </cell>
              <cell> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rows="2">*<gi>handNote</gi></cell>
              <cell><hi rendition="#super">+</hi><att>xml:id</att></cell>
              <cell> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>*<att>medium</att></cell>
              <cell>*<val>pencil</val> | *<val>ink</val> | *<val>altInk</val></cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="inclusion">
        <head>Inclusion of the DTABf-M in the DTABf System</head>
        <div xml:id="modularization">
          <head>Consideration of Modularization Possibilities</head>
          <p>So far, when dealing with text type–specific extensions to the DTABf (cf. <ref
              type="bibl" target="#haaf14">Haaf and Schulz 2014</ref>), the adaptations have been
            applied directly to the DTABf schema. Until now, this approach has proved feasible since
            the number of necessary additions to the DTABf subset remained small. Additions that
            were necessary occurred mainly at value or attribute level and in most cases did not run
            the risk of generating ambiguities in the format or evoking uncertainties concerning
            proper application. The practice of extensive documentation, of distinguishing four
            different annotation levels (required, recommended, optional, proscribed), and of
            introducing additional validation via Schematron constraints as well as of marking new
            values as affiliated to certain text types<note>E.g., by commencing the values with
              identifiers for certain text types; see <ptr type="crossref" target="#note29"/> for
              details.</note> (cf. <ref type="bibl" target="#haaf1415">Haaf, Geyken, and Wiegand
              2014–15</ref>), was sufficient to incorporate these respective extensions into the
            DTABf without loss of homogeneity and consistency.</p>
          <p>For manuscripts, however, as shown above, rather extensive additions to the DTABf
            became necessary (see <ptr type="crossref" target="#table1"/>), increasing the risk of
            ambiguities and uncertainties in applying the format. We want to prevent some of these
            insecurities by providing detailed <ref
              target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/doku/basisformat/manuskript.html"
              >documentation</ref> for DTABf-M–conformant tagging based on the DTABf
              documentation.<note>See <title level="a">DTA-Basisformat—Auszeichnung von
                Manuskripten</title> (<q>DTA Base Format—Annotation of Manuscripts</q>), accessed
              July 13, 2017, <ptr
                target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/doku/basisformat/manuskript.html"
              />.</note> However, an additional technical solution on the schema level has proved
            desirable as well.</p>
          <p>The maintenance of two separate TEI customizations (one for DTABf, the other for
            DTABf-M) was to be avoided for reasons of efficiency as well as to prevent workflow
            errors. In fact, we only recently gave up the maintenance of separate customizations and
            schemas for said reasons and introduced Schematron constraints to the format instead
            (see <ref type="bibl" target="#haaf1415">Haaf, Geyken, and Wiegand 2014–15, §25</ref>).
            So, for manuscripts, one possible method would have been the introduction of new <ref
              target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat.sch">Schematron
              constraints</ref> to our existing set of rules.<note>For the DTABf Schematron rule
              set, see <title level="a">Schematron Extension of the DTA <soCalled>Base
                  Format</soCalled></title>, accessed July 13, 2017, <ptr
                target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/basisformat.sch"/>.</note> However,
            Schematron validation is relatively slow and each new rule increases validation runtime.
            Given the significant number of differences between manuscripts and prints, the set of
            rules would have grown substantially, this way increasing the effect of slow
            validation.</p>
          <p>Hence, we wanted to generate different RNG schemas for quick validation, but without
            having to create different separate TEI customizations. Fortunately, the TEI
            infrastructure already offers a technique for this case: the method of chaining ODDs
              (<ref target="#rahtz14" type="bibl">Rahtz and Burnard 2014, 16–17</ref>), where one
            creates ODDs which are based on one another, but which can then be transformed into
            different independent schemas.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="chainedODDs">
          <head>Modular DTABf System of Chained ODDs<note>Thanks to James Cummings (Academic IT
              Services, University of Oxford) for very helpful advice concerning this
            method.</note></head>
          <p>The concept of chaining ODDs is the creation of a large, comprehensive ODD (here:
              <ident>ODD-L</ident>) that considers all possible annotations within the whole DTABf
            system as a derivative of the <ident>TEI_all</ident> ODD and is compiled with regard to
              <ident>TEI_all</ident>. After the larger ODD is in place, additional smaller ODDs are
            created (here: <ident>ODD-S1</ident>, <ident>ODD-S2</ident>, ... <ident>ODD-Sn</ident>)
            that determine reductions to <ident>ODD-L</ident> and thus represent subsets of the
            ODD-L tagset. Schemas can then be created by transformation of an <ident>ODD-S</ident>
            which is based on a compiled version of a comprehensive source <ident>ODD-L</ident>
            (expressed as a URI within the <att>source</att> attribute of
              <gi>schemaSpec</gi>).<note>See <ref type="bibl" target="#rahtz14">Rahtz and Burnard
                2014, 16–17</ref>, and <ptr
                target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.0.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html#TDbuild"
              /> for more information on the implementation of this system.</note> This way, we
            avoid creating similar parallel customizations that have to be maintained separately.
            Instead, each feature needed in the DTABf system is described only once, in one specific
            place, and then reused in the other relevant contexts.</p>
          <p>More concretely, we created a comprehensive DTABf ODD containing the entire DTABf
            tagset (<ident>DTABf-All</ident>) and representing a true subset of the TEI_all tagset.
            Two small ODDs, dependent on <ident>DTABf-All</ident>, specify the encoding of prints or
            manuscripts: first, the (established) DTABf for printed texts (<ident>DTABf</ident>),
            and second, the (new) DTABf for manuscripts (<ident>DTABf-M</ident>). <ptr
              type="crossref" target="#figure22"/> illustrates the system.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure22" n="6">
            <graphic url="images/image22.png" height="923px" width="1396px"/>
            <head type="legend">Chaining ODDs for the harmonization of DTABf and DTABf-M.</head>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="examples">
          <head>Examples</head>
          <p>The following section presents some examples for the chaining method at different
            layers of the DTABf ODDs.</p>
          <div xml:id="egElements">
            <head>Inclusion and Exclusion of Elements</head>
            <p>The <ident>DTABf-All</ident> ODD includes the elements <gi>subst</gi> (module
                <ident>transcr</ident>), <gi>add</gi> (module <ident>core</ident>), and <gi>del</gi>
              (module <ident>core</ident>) for the tagging of revisions and corrections in the
              handwritten text.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example1">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <moduleRef key="transcr" include="fw metamark subst ..."/>
                <moduleRef key="core" include="add del list p sp ..."/>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">ODD for DTABf-All:<note>Note that for reasons of clarity in these
                  examples the <gi>moduleRef</gi>s only contain a small extract of the element set
                  included by the <gi>moduleRef</gi>s within the original DTABf ODDs.</note></head>
            </figure>
            <p>These elements are not part of the DTABf for printed texts, so the
                <ident>DTABf</ident> ODD excludes these elements.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example2">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <moduleRef key="transcr" except="metamark subst"/>
                <moduleRef key="core" except="add del ..."/>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">ODD for DTABf:</head>
            </figure>
            <p>The <ident>DTABf-M</ident> ODD, however, includes these elements by referencing the
              entire modules from the <ident>DTABf-All</ident> ODD. All elements of all the modules
              included in <ident>DTABf-All</ident> will automatically be included here as well,
              unless explicitly excluded.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example3">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <moduleRef key="transcr"/>
                <moduleRef key="core" except="sp ..."/>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">ODD for DTABf-M:</head>
            </figure>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="egClasses">
            <head>Inclusion and Exclusion of Classes</head>
            <p>For DTABf-M, we make use of the new TEI class <ident>att.written</ident>, providing
              us with the attribute <att>hand</att> to encode a change of hands within the source
              text. For printed materials we do not need this attribute.<note>According to the DTA
                guidelines, corrections and notes inserted into printed texts manually are not
                considered for transcription, which means that there is no necessity for
                  <att>hand</att> in printed texts of the DTA corpora.</note> Hence, the class
                <ident>att.written</ident> is included in the <ident>DTABf-All</ident> ODD by
              inclusion of the class <ident>att.transcriptional</ident>, of which
                <ident>att.written</ident> is a sub-class.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example4">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <classSpec ident="att.transcriptional" mode="change" type="atts">
                  <attList>
                    <attDef ident="status" mode="delete"/>
                    <attDef ident="cause" mode="delete"/>
                    <attDef ident="seq" mode="delete"/>
                  </attList>
                </classSpec>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">ODD for DTABf-All:<note>Note that, due to class inheritance,
                    <ident>att.written</ident> is included in the schema by including
                    <ident>att.transcriptional</ident> and by <emph>not excluding it</emph>
                  explicitly.</note></head>
            </figure>
            <p>The class <ident>att.written</ident> is also tacitly included in the
                <ident>DTABf-M</ident> ODD by inheritance from the <ident>DTABf-All</ident> ODD,
              whereas the <ident>DTABf</ident> ODD explicitly excludes this class.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example5">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <classSpec ident="att.written" module="tei" type="atts" mode="delete"/>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">ODD for DTABf:</head>
            </figure>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="egClassChanges">
            <head>Changes within Classes</head>
            <p>For the <att>rendition</att> attribute of class <ident>att.global.rendition</ident>,
              a fixed list of possible values is determined within the DTABf. For manuscripts, we
              had to add two values to this list: <val>#mPrint</val> for printed material in
              manuscript text (e.g., boilerplate material) and <val>#mRetrace</val> for retracing of
              characters in order to highlight them.</p>
            <p><ident>DTABf-All</ident> contains all possible values of <att>rendition</att>.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example6">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <classSpec ident="att.global.rendition" module="tei" type="atts" mode="change">
                  <attList>
                    <attDef ident="rendition" mode="change" usage="opt">
                      <valList type="closed" mode="replace">
                        <valItem ident="#c"/>
                        <valItem ident="#b"/>
                        <valItem ident="#i"/> [...] <valItem ident="#mPrint"/>
                        <valItem ident="#mRetrace"/>
                      </valList>
                    </attDef> [...] </attList>
                </classSpec>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">ODD for DTABf-All:<note>The values <val>#c</val>, <val>#b</val>,
                  and <val>#i</val> represent centered text, bold typeface, and italics,
                  respectively.</note></head>
            </figure>
            <p><ident>DTABf-M</ident> does not change that list. <ident>DTABf</ident>, however,
              deletes the named values from the list.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example7">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <classSpec ident="att.global.rendition" module="tei" type="atts" mode="change">
                  <attList>
                    <attDef ident="rendition" mode="change" usage="opt">
                      <valList type="closed" mode="change">
                        <valItem ident="#mRetrace" mode="delete"/>
                        <valItem ident="#mPrint" mode="delete"/>
                      </valList>
                    </attDef>
                  </attList>
                </classSpec>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">ODD for DTABf:</head>
            </figure>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="egElementChanges">
            <head>Changes of Element Features</head>
            <p>In manuscripts the title of a chapter or section is sometimes written on the right or
              left margin of a page. Those instances cannot be considered marginal notes, but
              represent a type of heading. Therefore, we introduced
                <att>type</att>=<val>rightMargin</val> | <val>leftMargin</val> in <gi>head</gi>.
              Since this is a phenomenon we haven’t (yet) encountered in printed texts, the
                <att>type</att> attribute in <gi>head</gi> is only needed for manuscript
                annotation.<note>With regard to the overall consistency, the usage of
                  <att>place</att> instead of <att>type</att> might seem more appropriate for the
                current scenario. However, we decided to use <att>type</att> in order to remain
                compliant with the TEI Guidelines, which do not provide <att>place</att> for
                  <gi>head</gi>: see <ref target="#tei16" type="bibl">TEI Consortium 2016</ref>,
                  <ptr
                  target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.0.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-head.html"
                />.</note></p>
            <p>To address this phenomenon, the element <gi>head</gi> is provided with the necessary
              attribute-value-pairs within its element specification in
              <ident>DTABf-All</ident>:</p>
            <figure xml:id="example8">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <elementSpec ident="head" module="core" mode="change">
                  <attList>
                    <attDef ident="type" mode="change" usage="opt">
                      <valList type="closed" mode="replace">
                        <valItem ident="rightMargin"/>
                        <valItem ident="leftMargin"/>
                      </valList>
                    </attDef> [...] </attList>
                </elementSpec>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">ODD for DTABf-All:</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Again, within the <ident>DTABf-M</ident> ODD things are left as they are. In the
                <ident>DTABf</ident> ODD, however, <att>type</att> is deleted from
              <gi>head</gi>:</p>
            <figure xml:id="example9">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <elementSpec ident="head" module="core" mode="change">
                  <attList>
                    <attDef ident="type" mode="delete"/>
                  </attList>
                </elementSpec>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">ODD for DTABf:</head>
            </figure>
            <p>These examples illustrate several ways in which ODD chaining is used within the DTABf
              system. While the <ident>DTABf-All</ident> ODD is quite extensive, the ODDs for DTABf
              and DTABf-M could be kept quite narrow and relatively simple. Redundancies are
              generally avoided with this method. Thus, maintenance of the ODDs is easily
              manageable.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="conclusion">
        <head>Conclusion and Further Prospects</head>
        <p>The DTA project is an example of the application of the TEI Guidelines to large-scale
          corpora. Our primary goal is to be as inclusive as possible, allowing for other projects
          to benefit from our resources (i.e., our comprehensive guidelines and documentation as
          well as the technical infrastructure that includes Schemas, ODDs, and <ptr type="software"
            xml:id="R1" target="#xslt"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R1">XSLT</rs> scripts) and
          contribute to our corpora. We also want to ensure interoperability of all data within the
          DTA corpora. The underlying TEI format has to be continuously maintained and adapted to
          new necessities with these two premises in mind.</p>
        <p>In this paper, we presented the workflow implemented at the DTA for the adaptation of the
          DTABf for manuscripts. The challenge here was twofold: On the one hand, we wanted to
          identify frequent structural phenomena one might want to annotate within manuscripts,
          apply DTABf tagging as far as possible, and provide new markup solutions where the DTABf
          was too limited. On the other hand, in case adaptations are needed, we have tried to keep
          the format as unambiguous, robust, and user-friendly as possible in order to ensure truly
          interoperable texts. An important issue is how to include this new format in the existing
          DTABf system. To address this, the approach of chaining ODDs has proved practicable and
          appropriate.</p>
        <p>Interoperability issues are of great interest not only to the DTA but also to large
          infrastructure projects such as <ref target="http://clarin.eu/">CLARIN</ref>,<note>CLARIN:
            project Common Language Resources and Technology Infrastructure, <ptr
              target="http://clarin.eu/"/>; German partner CLARIN-D, <ptr
              target="http://www.clarin-d.de/"/>.</note> where corpora are being combined,
          exchanged, and made available in new contexts. The DTABf and its extensions are meant to
          address these issues.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <head>Literature</head>
          <bibl xml:id="clarin12"><orgName>CLARIN-D AP 5</orgName>. <date>2012</date>. <title
              level="u">CLARIN-D User Guide</title>. <edition>Version 1.0.1</edition>. <ptr
              target="http://www.clarin-d.de/de/hilfe/benutzerhandbuch"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dfg15a"><orgName>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG)</orgName>.
              <date>2015</date>. <title level="u">Handreichung: Empfehlungen zu datentechnischen
              Standards und Tools bei der Erhebung von Sprachkorpora.</title>
            <ptr
              target="http://www.dfg.de/download/pdf/foerderung/grundlagen_dfg_foerderung/informationen_fachwissenschaften/geisteswissenschaften/standards_sprachkorpora.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dfg15b"><orgName>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG)</orgName>.
              <date>2015</date>. <title level="u">Förderkriterien für wissenschaftliche Editionen in
              der Literaturwissenschaft.</title>
            <ptr
              target="http://www.dfg.de/download/pdf/foerderung/antragstellung/forschungsdaten/foerderkriterien_editionen_literaturwissenschaft.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gansel11"><author>Gansel, Christina</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title
              level="m">Textsortenlinguistik</title>. <pubPlace>Göttingen</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="geyken12"><author>Geyken, Alexander</author>, <author>Susanne Haaf</author>,
            and <author>Frank Wiegand</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">The DTA
                <soCalled>base format</soCalled>: A TEI-Subset for the Compilation of Interoperable
              Corpora.</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings of the 11th Conference on Natural
              Language Processing (KONVENS)</title>, edited by <editor>Jeremy Jancsary</editor>,
              <biblScope>383–91</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>: <publisher>Österreichische
              Gesellschaft für Artificial Intelligence</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.oegai.at/konvens2012/proceedings/57_geyken12w/57_geyken12w.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="haaf1415"><author>Haaf, Susanne</author>, <author>Alexander Geyken</author>,
            and <author>Frank Wiegand</author>. <date>2014–15</date>. <title level="a">The DTA
                <soCalled>Base Format</soCalled>: A TEI Subset for the Compilation of a Large
              Reference Corpus of Printed Text from Multiple Sources.</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>. <ptr target="http://jtei.revues.org/1114"/>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.4000/jtei.1114</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="haaf13"><author>Haaf, Susanne</author>, <author>Frank Wiegand</author>, and
              <author>Alexander Geyken</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a">Measuring the
              Correctness of Double-Keying: Error Classification and Quality Control in a Large
              Corpus of TEI-Annotated Historical Text.</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>. <ptr target="http://jtei.revues.org/739"/>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.4000/jtei.739</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="haaf14"><author>Haaf, Susanne</author>, and <author>Matthias
            Schulz</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">Historical Newspapers &amp;
              Journals for the DTA.</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings of the LRT4HDA Workshop,
              Held at the 9th LREC Conference</title>, edited by <editor>Kristín
              Bjarnadóttir</editor>, <editor>Mathew Driscoll</editor>, <editor>Steven
              Krauwer</editor>, <editor>Stelios Piperidis</editor>, <editor>Cristina
            Vertan</editor>, and <editor>Martin Wynne</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >50–54</biblScope>. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>: <publisher>European Language Resources
              Association</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2014/workshops/LREC2014Workshop-LRT4HDA%20Proceedings.pdf#page=57"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rahtz14"><author>Rahtz, Sebastian</author>, and <author>Lou
            Burnard</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="u">Advanced Topics in ODD.</title> In
              <title level="m">ODD: One Document Does it All</title>. Workshop at the Text Encoding
            Initiative Conference and Members Meeting, Oct 22–24 Evanston, IL. <ptr
              target="http://tei.it.ox.ac.uk/Talks/2014-10-odds/talk-05-advanced.xml"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="thomas15"><author>Thomas, Christian</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title
              level="u">Hidden Kosmos—Humboldts <q>Kosmos-Vorträge</q> als Probe der Digital
              Humanities.</title> Presentation at the DHd Annual Conference <title level="u">Von
              Daten zu Erkenntnissen: Digitale Geisteswissenschaften als Mittler zwischen
              Information und Interpretation</title>, February 23–27, Graz, Austria. <ptr
              target="https://www.culture.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/projekte/hidden-kosmos/media/c-thomas-dhd-graz-paper-hidden-kosmos-20150126.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="thomas16"><author>Thomas, Christian</author>, <author>Benjamin
              Fiechter</author>, and <author>Marius Hug</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title
              level="a">Methoden und Ziele der Erschließung handschriftlicher Quellen zu Alexander
              von Humboldts Kosmos-Vorträgen: Das Projekt Hidden Kosmos der Humboldt-Universität zu
              Berlin.</title> In <title level="m">Horizonte der Humboldt-Forschung: Natur, Kultur,
              Schreiben</title>, edited by <editor>Ottmar Ette</editor> and <editor>Julian
              Drews</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">287–318</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Hildesheim</pubPlace>: <publisher>Georg Olms</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="thomas15b"><author>Thomas, Christian</author>, and <author>Frank
              Wiegand</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title level="a">Making Great Work Even Better:
              Appraisal and Digital Curation of Widely Dispersed Electronic Textual Resources (c.
              15th–19th centuries) in CLARIN-D.</title> In <title level="m">Historical Corpora:
              Challenges and Perspectives</title>, edited by <editor>Jost Gippert</editor> and
              <editor>Ralf Gehrke</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">181–96</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Tübingen</pubPlace>: <publisher>Narr</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tei16"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2016</date>. <title
              level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>.
              <edition>Version 3.0.0</edition>. Last updated March 29. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.0.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl>
          <head>Historical Sources</head>
          <bibl xml:id="andrea1616"><author>Andreä, Johann Valentin</author>. <date>1616</date>.
              <title level="a">Chymische Hochzeit Christiani Rosencreutz Anno 1459</title>.
              <pubPlace>Straßburg</pubPlace>. In <title level="m">Deutsches Textarchiv</title>. <ptr
              target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/valentin_hochzeit_1616"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="anonym1827a"><author>Anonymous</author>. [<date>1827/28a</date>]. <title
              level="a">Alexander von Humboldts Vorlesungen über phÿsikalische Geographie nebst
              Prolegomenen über die Stellung der Gestirne. Berlin im Winter von 1827 bis
              1828.</title> [<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>]. In <title level="m">Deutsches
              Textarchiv</title>. <ptr
              target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/nn_msgermqu2345_1827"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="anonym1827b"><author>Anonymous</author>. [<date>1827/28b</date>]. <title
              level="a">Physikalische Geographie von Heinr. Alex. Freiherr v. Humboldt.
              [V]orgetragen im Wintersemester 1827/8.</title> [<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>]. In
              <title level="m">Deutsches Textarchiv</title>. <ptr
              target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/nn_n0171w1_1828"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="anonym1827c"><author>Anonymous</author>. [<date>1827/28c</date>]. <title
              level="a">Die physikalische Geographie von Herrn Alexander v. Humboldt, vorgetragen im
              Semestre 1827/28.</title> [<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>]. In <title level="m">Deutsches
              Textarchiv</title>. <ptr
              target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/nn_oktavgfeo79_1828"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="anonym1828"><author>Anonymous</author>. [<date>1828</date>]. <title
              level="a">Physikalische Geographie. Vorgetragen von Alexander von Humboldt.</title>
              [<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>]. In <title level="m">Deutsches Textarchiv</title>. <ptr
              target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/nn_msgermqu2124_1827"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hufeland1829"><author>Hufeland, Otto</author>. [<date>Ca. 1829</date>].
              <title level="a">Vorlesungen über physicalische Geographie von A. v. Humboldt.
              [G]eschrieben im Sommer 1829 durch Otto Hufeland.</title>
            [<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>]. In <title level="m">Deutsches Textarchiv</title>. <ptr
              target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/hufeland_privatbesitz_1829"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="parthey1827"><author>Parthey, Gustav</author>. [<date>1827/28</date>].
              <title level="a">Alexander von Humboldt[:] Vorlesungen über physikalische Geographie.
              Novmbr. 1827 bis April,[!] 1828. Nachgeschrieben von G. Partheÿ.</title>
              [<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>]. In <title level="m">Deutsches Textarchiv</title>. <ptr
              target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/parthey_msgermqu1711_1828"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="reuss1717"><author>Reuß-Ebersdorf, Erdmuthe Benigna von</author>.
              <date>1717</date>. <title level="m">[Letter to Heinrich XXIV. (Reuß-Köstritz);
              Ebersdorf (Thuringia, Germany), October 8, 1717]</title>.
              <pubPlace>Ebersdorf</pubPlace>. In <title level="m">Deutsches Textarchiv</title>. <ptr
              target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/reuss_paragiatsherrschaftabiv15_1717"
            />.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
