<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Deep Encoding of Etymological Information in TEI</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Jack</forename>
            <surname>Bowers</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Jack Bowers is a <roleName>research assistant</roleName> at the
              <orgName>Austrian Academy of Sciences</orgName> (ÖAW)—Austrian Center for Digital
            Humanities (ACDH). He is the primary curator of the DBÖ (Datenbank der bairischen
            Mundarten in Österreich) corpus and is working on cleaning, converting, and enhancing
            the lexical and metadata in order to facilitate reuse, and to bring it in line with
            international standards and best practice. With a background in cognitive and functional
            approaches to all levels of linguistics and their interfaces (semantics, morphosyntax,
            phonetics, phonology, etymology), he applies linguistic expertise to best represent and
            integrate lexical data (spoken or textual) with metadata and semantic
            knowledge/information resources. He is also interested in working towards
            interoperability between standards for lexical markup (TEI, LMF, ONTOLEX, TBX) and in
            the emerging prospects offered by semantic web/ontological resources in the integration
            of human knowledge across academic and scientific fields. Jack holds a B.A. in history
            and French from San Francisco State University (2009) and an M.A. in linguistics and a
            certificate in computational linguistics from San Jose State University (2012). He is a
            member of the DARIAH-GiST project, which works to promote the use of digital standards
            in the humanities, and became involved in the digital humanities while working on his
            documentation/multimedia resource/corpus creation of the Mixtepec-Mixtec language
            variety (spoken Juxtlahuaca district, Oaxaca, Mexico) (2011– ).</affiliation>
          <email>iljackb@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Laurent</forename>
            <surname>Romary</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Laurent Romary is <roleName>Directeur de Recherche</roleName> at
              <orgName>Inria</orgName>, France, <roleName>director general</roleName> of the
            European infrastructure <orgName>DARIAH</orgName>, and <roleName>guest
              scientist</roleName> at the <orgName>Centre Marc Bloch</orgName> and the
              <orgName>Academy of Sciences in Berlin</orgName>. He carries out research on the
            modeling of semi-structured documents, with a specific emphasis on texts and linguistic
            resources. He received a PhD in computational linguistics in 1989 and his Habilitation
            in 1999. During several years he launched and directed the Langue et Dialogue team at
            Loria in Nancy, France, and participated in several national and international projects
            related to the representation and dissemination of language resources and on
            human–machine interaction. He is the chairman of ISO committee TC 37 and has been a
            member (2001–2007), then chair (2008–2011), of the TEI (Text Encoding Initiative)
            Council and now member of the TEI board (2017–2018). Beyond his research activities, he
            has been responsible for defining and implementing the scientific information and open
            access policies of major research institutions in Europe, namely CNRS, Max Planck
            Society, and Inria.</affiliation>
          <email>laurent.romary@inria.fr</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>11/07/2017</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Marjorie Burghart</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Emmanuelle Morlock</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Anne Baillot</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="10">Selected Papers from the 2015 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Revues.org -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>TEI</term>
          <term>dictionary</term>
          <term>etymology</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>In this paper we provide a systematic and comprehensive set of modeling principles for
          representing etymological data in digital dictionaries using TEI. The purpose is to
          integrate in one coherent framework both digital representations of legacy dictionaries
          and born-digital lexical databases that are constructed manually or
          semi-automatically.</p>
        <p>We provide examples from many different types of etymological phenomena from traditional
          lexicographic practice, as well as analytical approaches from functional and cognitive
          linguistics such as metaphor, metonymy, and grammaticalization, which in many
          lexicographical and formal linguistic circles have not often been treated as truly
          etymological in nature, and have thus been largely left out of etymological
          dictionaries.</p>
        <p>In order to fully and accurately express the phenomena and their structures, we have made
          several proposals for expanding and amending some aspects of the existing TEI
          framework.</p>
        <p>Finally, with reference to both synchronic and diachronic data, we also demonstrate how
          encoders may integrate semantic web/linked open data information resources into TEI
          dictionaries as a basis for the sense, and/or the semantic domain, of an entry and/or an
          etymon.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="introduction">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>This paper aims to provide a comprehensive modeling and representation of etymological
          data in digital dictionaries. The purpose is to integrate in one coherent framework both
          digital representations of legacy dictionaries and born-digital lexical databases that are
          constructed manually or semi-automatically. We propose a systematic and coherent set of
          modeling principles for a variety of etymological phenomena that may contribute to the
          creation of a continuum between existing and future lexical constructs, so that anyone
          interested in tracing the history of words and their meanings will be able to seamlessly
          query lexical resources.</p>
        <p>Instead of designing an ad hoc model and representation language for digital etymological
          data, we will focus on identifying all the possibilities offered by the TEI Guidelines for
          the representation of lexical information. This will lead us to systematize some existing
          constructs offered by the existing TEI framework, in particular the use of citation
            (<gi>cit</gi>) for representing etymons in place of <gi>mentioned</gi>, and referencing
          constructs (<gi>pRef</gi> and <gi>oRef</gi>) for linking etymological information to
          existing or putative lexical entries. We also suggest some amendments to the TEI
          Guidelines that may improve the representation of etymological information as well as
          lexical entries at large (for instance, deprecation of <gi>oVar</gi> and
            <gi>pVar</gi>).<note>Some of these amendments have been validated by the TEI Council.
            See <ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1512"/>.</note></p>
        <p>Since its initial design in the 1990s (<ref target="#ide94" type="bibl">Ide and Véronis
            1994</ref>; <ref target="#ide95" type="bibl">Ide and Véronis 1995</ref>), the TEI <title
            level="a"><ref
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/DI.html"
              >Dictionaries</ref></title><note>Originally titled <soCalled>Print
              Dictionaries</soCalled> before it made an appropriate digital turn to cover lexical
            resources at large.</note> chapter (<ref target="#tei16" type="bibl">TEI Consortium
            2016, chapter 9</ref>) has been the basis for a large number of dictionary projects. It
          has shown its capacity to take into account a variety of perspectives on lexical content,
          whether one wants to closely follow the original structure of the source material
          (so-called <soCalled>editorial view</soCalled>), or abstract away from it to go closer to
          a real lexical database (<soCalled>lexical view</soCalled>). This has led to an important
          body of literature (including <ref target="#erjavec99" type="bibl">Erjavec, Tufis, and
            Varadi 1999</ref>; <ref target="#budin12" type="bibl">Budin, Majewski, and Moerth
            2012</ref>; <ref target="#rennie00" type="bibl">Rennie 2000</ref>; <ref
            target="#banski09" type="bibl">Bański and Wójtowicz 2009</ref>; <ref target="#fomin06"
            type="bibl">Fomin and Toner 2006</ref>). Most of these papers have been focused on
          presenting the general architecture of lexical entries in the corresponding dictionary
          projects, and on describing the way the various TEI elements have been set up and used
          over the course of the editorial workflow.</p>
        <p>Concerning etymological description on the theoretical level within the field of
          linguistics, as we shall see, phenomena such as metaphor, metonymy, and grammaticalization
          are very well established, particularly within cognitive linguistics. However, we know of
          no attempts to represent such processes within any lexical markup system. Additionally,
          with regard to the theoretical background, very little has been written on the
          corresponding digital models when such information is being integrated into a lexical
          database. This is why we will mainly position our work as an elaboration upon the seminal
          proposals of Salmon-Alt (<ref target="#salmon-alt06" type="bibl">2006</ref>), which
          represent a unique set of approaches to data modeling for etymological information.</p>
        <p>Finally, though they are not the primary focus of our paper, we present herein examples
          of how encoders may make use of linked open data URIs<note>Uniform Resource Identifier: A
            naming mechanism to identify a resource on the Internet in a univocal way.</note> in
          defining the semantics (sense and/or domain) of a lexical entry; this issue has been
          discussed recently by Schopper, Bowers, and Wandl-Vogt (<ref target="#schopper15"
            type="bibl">2015</ref>). The integration of the burgeoning resources of the semantic web
          with TEI represents a step toward a model of digital lexicography which enables conceptual
          semantics to play a more prominent role in the representation of linguistic content by
          grounding such information in the growing networks of ontological knowledge bases.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="overview">
        <head>A Quick Overview of the TEI Recommendations for Dictionaries</head>
        <p>The representation of lexical information is only one of many types of textual forms that
          are covered by the wide scope of the TEI Guidelines. A dictionary represented in TEI
          follows all the basic assumptions concerning the general structure of TEI-conformant
          documents. In particular, all metadata elements related to the identification of the
          sources used in the document, the various responsibilities in its digital encoding, as
          well as the possible conditions of publication and reuse can all be described within the
          TEI header (<gi>teiHeader</gi>) element, which is a mandatory component of all TEI
          documents. In the same way, the actual lexical content of a dictionary document expressed
          in TEI can be further structured at any depth using the generic division (<gi>div</gi>)
          mechanisms. As a whole, the structural divisions of TEI dictionary entries and their
          component elements can be seen as analogous to any other type of structured subsection
          (containing elements such as title, section headers, and paragraph) that may occur in a
          document containing prose.<note>For non-expert readers interested in a quick overview of
            general encoding possibilities offered by the TEI Guidelines, we recommend looking at
            the TEI by Example initiative, <ptr target="http://www.teibyexample.org/"/>, or <ref
              target="#romary09" type="bibl">Romary 2009</ref>.</note></p>
        <p>Besides generic textual constructs, the TEI Guidelines provide a variety of elements to
          represent dictionary entries, including a general-purpose <gi>entry</gi> element for
          structured content, a specific <gi>entryFree</gi> element to provide a flat
          representation, for instance in the course of a digitization workflow, and a
            <gi>superEntry</gi> container to group together homonyms. Over the course of this paper
          we will focus on the <gi>entry</gi> element, whose organization reflects a standard
          semasiological model of lexical content.<note>See <ref target="#romary14" type="bibl"
              >Romary and Witt 2014</ref> for an overview of onomasiological and semasiological
            models; <ref target="#lemnitzer13" type="bibl">Lemnitzer, Romary, and Witt 2013</ref>
            and <ref target="#romary12" type="bibl">Romary and Wegstein 2012</ref> for an in-depth
            analysis of the TEI dictionary model; and <ref target="#romary15" type="bibl">Romary
              2015</ref> for a discussion of the relation between the TEI dictionary model and the
            ISO 24613 (LMF) standard (<ref target="#iso08" type="bibl">ISO 2008</ref>).</note>
          Indeed, the <gi>entry</gi> element is mainly organized around two subcomponents:</p>
        <list rend="bulleted">
          <item>a <gi>form</gi> element contains the description of the phonetic, orthographic, and
            morphological characteristics of the headword as well as its possible inflections. This
            element may, for instance, contain further grammatical constraints (using the
              <gi>gramGrp</gi> element);</item>
          <item>one or more <gi>sense</gi> elements that group together all descriptions related to
            the various senses that can be associated with the headword. A variety of further
            descriptors are available in <gi>sense</gi> to provide such information as a definition
              (<gi>def</gi>), examples or translations (<gi>cit</gi>), various grammatical
              (<gi>gramGrp</gi>) or usage (<gi>usg</gi>) constraints, and of course etymological
            information (<gi>etym</gi>).</item>
        </list>
        <p>The TEI <title level="a"><ref
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/DI.html"
              >Dictionaries</ref></title> chapter also provides various mechanisms for
          cross-referencing entries to other components of a dictionary. In particular, we will see
          in this paper how we can make use of references to the orthographic form (<gi>oRef</gi>)
          or pronunciation (<gi>pRef</gi>) of a headword within an etymological description.</p>
        <p>When using the <gi>entry</gi> element, it is particularly important to identify the
          language information attached to any descriptive element within such representations; in
          particular, an encoder needs to be able to clearly state the object language of the entry
          as a whole (the language about which the entry provides a lexical description) and the
          various working languages (the languages in which various descriptive objects such as
          definitions, notes, and etymons are expressed). To this purpose, in compliance with ISO
          standard 16642<note>ISO 16642:2003: <title level="m">Computer applications in terminology
              — Terminological markup framework</title> (<ptr
              target="https://www.iso.org/standard/32347.html"/>); see also <ref target="#romary01"
              type="bibl">Romary 2001</ref>.</note> for terminological data, we recommend using the
            <att>xml:lang</att> attribute as follows: <att>xml:lang</att> is a mandatory attribute
          for each <gi>entry</gi> and indicates the object language of the whole entry. When not
          superseded by another indication further down in the entry structure, it also states the
          working language for all descendant elements within it, when appropriate (i.e., for
          textual content). When the working language differs locally from the object language of
          the entry (e.g., a definition expressed in another language than the one being described),
          a new <att>xml:lang</att> attribute may be attached to the corresponding element.</p>
        <p>The representation of etymological information, whether at entry level or for a specific
          sense, relies on the <gi>etym</gi> element, which we will elaborate upon as we tackle
          specific phenomena. So far, <gi>etym</gi> has been used as a flat construct where relevant
          information concerning language (<gi>lang</gi>), etymon (<gi>mentioned</gi>), or source
            (<gi>bibl</gi>), for instance, would be simply marked up in the flow of a textual
          etymological description. The purpose of this paper is to deepen the possible usage of
            <gi>etym</gi> and systematize the way in which specific etymological phenomena can be
          represented.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="past">
        <head>Past Treatment of Etymological Markup</head>
        <p>None of the previous attempts either to create a lasting, well-formatted digital corpus
          of etymological data, or to establish a widely adopted set of recommendations for encoding
          such information, have ultimately been very successful. Many of the projects which
          attempted to create such resources have seen the same fate as so many others in the
          humanities (despite their stated goals of following best practices for interoperability);
          such problems include obsolescence of formatting and/or encoding scheme, abandonment of
          project, websites that no longer exist, broken links, and incompatibility with existing
          software.</p>
        <p>However, it is useful to review a few publications (and data where possible) that have
          led to our current understanding of a generic way to represent (digital) etymological
          information, as it contributes to establishing an understanding of key questions,
          challenges, and issues that the authors encountered, as well as to recognize what people
          may be looking for when undertaking such projects. To this end, we will review four main
          references that have either paved the way for the current status quo in the TEI Guidelines
          or directly influenced our own understanding of the guidelines and how they should
          evolve.</p>
        <p>A major milestone in the digital dictionary era is the work by Amsler and Tompa (<ref
            target="#amsler88" type="bibl">1988</ref>), which, together with the unifying
          contributions of Ide and Véronis (<ref target="#ide94" type="bibl">1994</ref>), led to the
          earlier TEI <title level="a">Print Dictionaries</title> chapter. Focusing here on their
          contribution to etymology, <ptr target="#example1" type="crossref"/> shows how they have
          introduced a highly structured model based on etymons and links implemented as an
            SGML<note>Standard Generalized Markup Language, ISO standard ISO 8879 published in 1986,
            which is the direct ancestor of XML.</note> DTD.<note>Document Type Definition, the
            grammar of an SGML document.</note> The underlying model is based upon a graph of
          etymons (<gi>etymon</gi>) connected with relations (<gi>rel</gi>), forming a more global
          etymological tree (reflected by the <gi>es</gi>, etymological segment, element).</p>
        <figure xml:id="example1">
          <eg><![CDATA[
            <E>
              <es>
                <etymon lang=ME>appel</etymon></es>
              <es>
                <rel>fr.</rel>
                <etymon lang=OE>&aelig;ppel</etymon></es>
              <es>
                <rel>akin to</rel> 
                <eu>
                  <etymon lang=OHG>apful</etymon>
                  <deftext>apple</deftext></eu> 
                <eu>
                  <etymon lang=OSlav>abl&breve;ko</etymon></eu></es></E>
          ]]></eg>
          <head type="legend">Etymological representation from
            <!-- [RvdB] added 1st author -->Amsler and Tompa (<ref target="#amsler88" type="bibl"
              >1988</ref>)</head>
        </figure>
        <p>The next two examples were early attempts to build corpora capable of representing
          etymological data using standards.</p>
        <p>An early pre-XML application of the TEI Guidelines to the systematic recording of
          etymological information can be found in Good and Sprouse (<ref target="#good00"
            type="bibl">2000</ref>). The work was carried out in the context of the Comparative
          Bantu Online Dictionary (CBOLD), a complex database for multiple Bantu languages, and used
          the SGML P3 edition of the TEI Guidelines.<note>The P4 edition of the TEI Guidelines,
            which was completely based upon XML, was not published until 2001.</note> The content
          corresponds to the digitization of existing print dictionaries and word lists, and the
          authors marked up these texts according to the TEI Guidelines, with some tags added to the
          standard set. Since the project had to deal extensively with etymological information, it
          used <gi>etym</gi> with a refined recommendation to link etymons (marked up as
            <gi>xref</gi>) to a list of reconstructed historical forms.</p>
        <p>In the same vein, Jacobson and Michailovsky (<ref target="#jacobson02" type="bibl"
            >2002</ref>) used an even simpler approach for their etymological references within a
          TEI-based encoding of their lexical data. Instead of implementing <gi>etym</gi>, they make
          a plain use of the generic <gi>ptr</gi> element, typed as <val>cfetym</val>, to point to
          other entries in their dictionary that may be seen as etymological sources.</p>
        <div xml:id="crist">
          <head>Crist (2005)</head>
          <p>Sean Crist provides some analyses of approaches and a correspondingly precise set of
            principles to be applied to the <ref target="http://lexicon.ff.cuni.cz/">Germanic
              Lexicon Project</ref>,<note>Germanic Lexicon Project, accessed June 16, 2017, <ptr
                target="http://lexicon.ff.cuni.cz/"/>.</note> which digitized a collection of
            dictionaries of various Germanic languages whose copyright had expired. The ultimate
            goal for markup formatting was TEI, but (for reasons unknown) it was apparently never
            achieved. Notably, Crist mentions the likely need to extend the guidelines in the area
            of etymology because the <gi>etym</gi> element lacks the means for precisely encoding
            etymological relationships between entries and forms. Key components of this work were
            the following:</p>
          <list>
            <item>XML markup of some of the data, while other portions remain as plain text, or
              simply image scans of the originals;</item>
            <item>formal interrelations among all of the words in an etymology; those specified are
              cognation, inheritance, and borrowing;</item>
            <item>the use of attribute inheritance for the nodes in the data structure as per Ide,
              Kilgarriff, and Romary (<ref target="#ide00" type="bibl">2000</ref>);</item>
            <item>a proposal for the system to require no privileged frame of reference, which would
              allow data to follow one of three formats.</item>
          </list>
          <p>The following excerpt is from the paper, assuming that the structures represent the
            place in the XML hierarchy in which each data type would occur.</p>
          <figure xml:id="example2">
            <eg><![CDATA[
1. (From the vantage point of Modern English) Modern English stone is a reflex of Old English stān, which is a reflex of Proto-Germanic *stainaz:
     word
          form: stone
          language: Modern English
          etymon
               word
                    form:     stān
                    language: Old English
                    etymon
                         word
                              form: stainaz
                              language: Proto-Germanic
                              attested: no

2. (From the vantage point of Old English) Old English stān is an etymon of Modern English stone, and is also a reflex of Proto- Germanic *stainaz:
     word
          form:     stān
          language: Old English
               reflex
                    word
                         form: stone
                         language: Modern English
               etymon
                    word
                         form: stainaz
                         language: Proto-Germanic
                         attested: no

3. (From the vantage point of Proto-Germanic) Proto-Germanic *stainaz is an etymon of Old English stān, which is an etymon of Modern English stone:
     word
          form: stainaz
          language: Proto-Germanic
          attested: no
          reflex
               word
                    form:     stān
                    language: Old English
                    form: stone
                    language: Modern English  
]]></eg>
            <head type="legend">Abstracted model of etymological description (<ref target="#crist05"
                type="bibl">Crist 2005, 8–9</ref>)</head>
          </figure>
          <p>Crist outlined a typology of the treatment of etymological markup at the time, while
            the adoption of standards and the fields of digital humanities and lexicography have
            been steadily gaining momentum since then. With regard to etymological markup, Crist’s
            typology remains fairly valid. The classifications are as follows:</p>
          <list rend="simple">
            <item><quote source="#quoteref1">Type I. Markup schemes which make no provision for
                etymological data</quote> (the majority of lexical markup systems);</item>
            <item><quote source="#quoteref1">Type II. Markup schemes where etymological data is
                delimited as such, but is treated as unstructured prose</quote> (including TEI;
              Crist points out the need for further structure, possibly reusing structures from
              other sections of the TEI specifications, especially the dictionary chapter);</item>
            <item><quote source="#quoteref1">Type III. Markup schemes where the mathematical
                relationships recognized in historical/comparative linguistics are somehow embodied
                in the markup system in (semi-)machine-readable form.</quote> These systems,
              according to Crist, <quote source="#quoteref1">make some provision for the formal
                encoding of etymological relationships between words</quote> (<ref target="#crist05"
                xml:id="quoteref1" type="bibl">Crist 2005, 13, 17</ref>).</item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="salmon-alt">
          <head>Salmon-Alt (2006)</head>
          <p>The most significant attempt at devising this kind of dynamic system of etymological
            markup was that of Susanne Salmon-Alt. While etymology is not addressed in the LMF (ISO
            24613:2008) standard (<ref target="#iso08" type="bibl">ISO 2008</ref>),<note>In the
              context of the ongoing revision of the LMF document as a multipart standard, there is
              now provision for a specific part on diachrony and etymology.</note> Salmon-Alt
            attempted to develop an extension of the model for the encoding of etymological markup.
            The extension module allows for the integration and linking of the etymological
            information of an entry with the synchronic data and any classifications of a given
            word/entry within the core module of LMF.</p>
          <cit>
            <quote source="#quoteref2">Our model is based on the overall hypothesis that
              etymological data might be thought of as a lexical network, i.e., a graph, whose nodes
              are lexical units (located in space and time) and whose arcs are typed etymological
              relations.</quote>
            <ref target="#salmon-alt06" xml:id="quoteref2" type="bibl">Salmon-Alt 2006, 3</ref>
          </cit>
          <p>The scope of the model was limited to semasiological organizational principles for
            single lexical entries, such as those outlined in the TEI P5 Guidelines, and did not
            attempt to support the approaches of many traditional etymological dictionaries in which
            the structural principles and contents vary significantly from one another.</p>
          <p>In laying the conceptual and functional foundation for the approach, Salmon-Alt defines
            etymology proper as concerning the origin and evolution of a lexeme before its entrance
            into the lexicon of a given language, as it is materialized by one or more etymons.</p>
          <p>The metamodel of the LMF etymology extension from the paper is shown in the diagram
            below.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure1">
            <graphic url="images/image1.png" height="952px" width="1296px"/>
            <head type="legend">Etymological extension to LMF (<ref target="#salmon-alt06"
                type="bibl">Salmon-Alt 2006</ref>)</head>
          </figure>
          <p>This diagram reflects the XML representation suggested by Salmon-Alt (<ref
              target="#salmon-alt06" type="bibl">2006</ref>),<note>Since the paper was written
              before the XML serialization of LMF was stabilized, Salmon-Alt (<ref
                target="#salmon-alt06" type="bibl">2006</ref>) construed an XML representation
              partially informed by the then-ongoing discussions and partially inspired by the TEI
              Guidelines.</note> with two dedicated elements, <gi>etymon</gi> and
              <gi>etymologicalLink</gi>, that each contain a specific set of information. They are
            defined as follows:</p>
          <list type="gloss">
            <label>Etymon: <gi>etymon</gi></label>
            <item>
              <p>The basis for describing and encoding etymons in this model is parallel to that of
                synchronic lexical entries. Specifically, they are characterized by: language
                  (<att>xml:lang</att>); the linguistic form(s) (<gi>form</gi>)—orthographic
                  (<gi>orth</gi>) and/or phonetic (<gi>pron</gi>); sense (<gi>sense</gi>); gloss
                  (<gi>glose</gi>); grammatical classification (<gi>pos</gi>); and inflectional
                information (if applicable).</p>
              <p>Additionally, within the etymon portion of the markup are the optional etymological
                notes,which serve as a kind of <soCalled>et cetera</soCalled> section where one can
                include other relevant information about the etymon, such as discussions and/or
                bibliographic references regarding intermediate stages of development, phonetic
                evolution, concurrent hypotheses, statements of confidence, and secondary etymons.
                In our system presented herein, we have refined and given more structure to the
                markup of these datatypes.</p>
            </item>
            <label>Etymological Link: <gi>etymologicalLink</gi></label>
            <item>
              <p>The <gi>etymologicalLink</gi> section is intended to be where the relations between
                the synchronic and diachronic elements, or possibly between multiple stages,
                etymological relationships, or alternative hypotheses of diachronic components are
                specified and defined. The main way in which this is done in the data structure is
                through the pointer mechanisms (<att>source</att>, <att>target</att>) in the
                attributes which link the lexical entry to an etymological classification specified
                by means of an <gi>etymologicalClass</gi> element which can occur within each
                  <gi>etymologicalLink</gi>.</p>
              <p>Specified as element values, etymological classes in the model are inheritance,
                loan word, and word generation, though in the case of disputed word origins, each
                alternative may have different classifications if need be, and levels of confidence
                can also be specified (<att>confidenceScore</att>).</p>
            </item>
          </list>
          <p>After reviewing the literature on this topic, we can identify several commonalities,
            the first of which is that all authors looked to the TEI, but none found it sufficient
            to adopt without alterations. Additionally, all works reviewed desire the markup system
            to have:</p>
          <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>a systematic inventory of typed pointers to link between: etymological forms
              (etymons) and their synchronic descendants; parallel synchronic forms in related
              languages (e.g., cognates); multiple synchronic forms in a single language;</item>
            <item>structures dynamic and consistent enough to enable automatic processing,
              manipulation, and evaluation with software applications;</item>
            <item>the ability to classify and assign typological labels to an etymological
              entry;</item>
            <item>a means of expressing level of certainty of etymological analysis;</item>
            <item>a means of decomposing compounds and components of derivational morphology.</item>
          </list>
          <p>In this paper, we elaborate on the sources presented above. We specifically focus on
            building upon the general model proposed by Salmon-Alt (<ref target="#salmon-alt06"
              type="bibl">2006</ref>), which is based on a network of etymons and links. Moreover,
            we identify a more precise group of link types between etymons and explore the
            consequences in terms of both theoretical implications and possible representations in
            the TEI framework. Whereas this was not completely stated in Salmon-Alt (<ref
              target="#salmon-alt06" type="bibl">2006</ref>), we are describing etymological links
            as the expression of specific etymological processes between etymons (forms), lexical
            entries, or even senses within entries. The following sections describe the type
            ontology that we have devised.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="basicmechanisms">
        <head>Basic Mechanisms for Representing Etymological Processes</head>
        <div xml:id="etymons">
          <head>An Extended TEI-based Representation of Etymons</head>
          <p>The current content model of the <gi>etym</gi> element and the documentation and
            examples available in the TEI Guidelines favor a flat annotation of etymological content
            that does not put forward either the actual nature of etymons as references to
            dictionary entries or the central role of etymological links in the diachronic
            processes. Starting from the following example expressed in current recommendations of
            the TEI Guidelines, we show in this section a better representation of etymons in
            etymological description: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <entry>
                <form type="headword">
                  <orth>Âbend</orth>
                </form>
                <gramGrp>
                  <gen>Mask.</gen>
                </gramGrp>
                <!-- sense, other info here -->
                <etym>
                  <lang>Ahd.</lang>
                  <mentioned>âband</mentioned>, <lang>mhd.</lang>
                  <mentioned>âbent</mentioned>; <bibl>zur Etym. s. Kluge Mitzka 18. Aufl. unter
                    ,,Abend'', ferner Schwäb. Wb. 1, 11ff. Schweizdt. Wb. 1,34ff.</bibl>
                </etym>
              </entry>
            </egXML>
          </p>
          <p>As we can see, the TEI Guidelines have thus far favored the use of the
              <gi>mentioned</gi> element as the basis for marking up etymons.</p>
          <p>The first reason we think this representation is problematic is that it introduces a
            specific mechanism to refer to lexical items, whereas the TEI <title level="a"><ref
                target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/DI.html"
                >Dictionaries</ref></title> chapter also provides <gi>oRef</gi> and <gi>pRef</gi> in
            examples and <gi>ref</gi> in external references. Therefore we suggest that such
            references be considered a single process of referring to other lexical entries at
            large, whether within the same entry, within the same dictionary, or potentially to a
            lexical entry from another dictionary. In the latter case, the dictionary may or may not
            exist for the corresponding language, and thus the reference may be used as a
            placeholder for a potential construction. This is typically the case for etymons that
            refer to other languages or ancient forms thereof, even if such forms are not (yet) part
            of a real lexical description.</p>
          <p>To this purpose, we make the recommendation to systematically use <gi>oRef</gi> and
              <gi>pRef</gi> in all three constructs (examples, etymology, and external references),
            and thus supersede both <gi>mentioned</gi> and <gi>ref</gi> for such usages.</p>
          <p>The schematic structure that we propose for this construct is as sketched below: <eg><![CDATA[
<cit type="etymon">
	<oRef>|<pRef>
	<date>|<gramGrp>|<usg>|<gloss>|<ref>
</cit>
]]></eg>
          </p>
          <p>Here we see that we can have <gi>oRef</gi> or <gi>pRef</gi> (or possibly both) to refer
            to the form of the etymon, to which we add further information or constraints related to
            dating (<gi>date</gi>), grammatical information (<gi>gramGrp</gi>), semantic domain or
            register (<tag>usg type="…"</tag>), or translational equivalence (<gi>gloss</gi>). There
            could of course be additional constraints depending on the complexity of the available
            etymological information, for instance when there is an explicit reference to an
            externally defined sense, beyond the shallow capacity of <gi>gloss</gi>,<note>A possible
              replacement for <gi>gloss</gi> could be a construct such as <tag>ref corresp="…"
                type="sense"</tag>.</note> as we shall see later in the paper.</p>
          <p>Moreover, the use of <gi>oRef</gi> and <gi>pRef</gi> here is quite important in our
            model, since it reflects the vision that an etymon is a potential reference to a lexical
            entry in a dictionary for the corresponding language either synchronically (e.g., in the
            case of loan words) or, more often, diachronically.</p>
          <p>The second flaw with the current TEI proposals for etymology is the lack of mechanisms
            to group together an etymon with the possible constraints (language, grammar, usage)
            that may be associated with it. The flat annotation format leaves such pieces of
            information isolated, as we can see in the previous example, for even the central
            language information (coded with <gi>lang</gi>).</p>
          <p>Here again, we take up a construct that already exists in the TEI <title level="a"><ref
                target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/DI.htm"
                >Dictionaries</ref></title> chapter to encompass this new use case, namely
              <gi>cit</gi>. By definition, <gi>cit</gi> groups together a linguistic segment with
            additional features that document its usage, and it is currently used for examples and
            translations in dictionary entries. We suggest extending its scope to make it the
            central construct for the representation of etymons in combination with the use of
              <gi>oRef</gi> and <gi>pRef</gi> we have just described.</p>
          <p>If we take up the preceding example, we can turn it into our suggested representation
            as follows:<note>For the sake of conciseness we have not added the bibliographic
              description (<gi>bibl</gi>) to this example, although it would also fit into the
                <gi>cit</gi> construct outlined here.</note>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <etym> … <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="gmh">
                  <oRef>âbent</oRef>
                  <lang>mhd.</lang>
                </cit> … </etym>
            </egXML>
          </p>
          <p>We will show more examples of this construct in the course of our paper, but we can
            already see how it allows us both to precisely localize etymological descriptions and to
            provide the basic unit for the creation of a generic lexical network across a variety of
            dictionaries.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="etymologicalstructure">
          <head>Generic Representation of an Etymological Structure</head>
          <p>In this section we describe some examples of common types of etymological processes,
            their linguistic features, and their key data points, and we present strategies for
            encoding each of them using TEI.</p>
          <p>At the most basic level, the origin of any lexical item or subform can be described as:
              <list rend="inline simple">
              <item>a) inheritance from a <soCalled>parent</soCalled>, <soCalled>proto-</soCalled>,
                or predecessor form of a language;</item>
              <item>b) borrowing from a foreign language;</item>
              <item>c) processes that occurred within a contemporary language or subvarieties of a
                language</item>
            </list>.<note>It may of course be the case that the source of a lexical item is
              unknown.</note> With the exception of a lexical item that was inherited and underwent
            no change to its surface form (phonetic or phonological), its grammatical role, or its
            semantic profile, the etymology of a lexical item originating by any one of these means
            will be comprised of any number of processes that occur on one or more levels of
            language.</p>
          <p>An important aspect to be mentioned at this stage is that etymological description can
            actually occur at two different levels in the organization of a lexical entry. When one
            deals with the actual etymology of the word, in the sense of the occurrence of the whole
            lexical entry in the repertoire of a given language, the <gi>etym</gi> element will
            obviously appear as a child of <gi>entry</gi>. It can also be the case that one has to
            deal with the emergence of a new sense for a given word, in which case <gi>etym</gi>
            should be attached to the corresponding <gi>sense</gi> element. Clearly, this
            distinction is correlated with etymological types, borrowing being more likely to be
            related to lexical entries whereas metaphors would more often correspond to new
            senses.</p>
          <p>Any change that occurs within a lexicon can be labeled in the <att>type</att> attribute
            of the <gi>etym</gi> element in a TEI dictionary;<note>Currently the use of
                <att>type</att> in the <gi>etym</gi> element is not permitted in the TEI schema as
              the aforementioned element is not a member of the <ident>att.typed</ident> class.
              However, a proposal for this use has been accepted by the TEI Council and will be
              implemented in a future version of the TEI Guidelines; meanwhile, the ticket is
              available at <ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1512"/>. In our proposal,
              the <gi>etym</gi> element has to be made recursive in order to allow the fine-grained
              representations we propose here. The corresponding ODD customization, together with
              reference examples, is available on <ptr type="software" xml:id="R1"
                target="#github"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R1">GitHub</rs>.</note> and the
            fact that a change occurred within the contemporary lexicon (as opposed to its parent
            language) is indicated by means of <att>xml:lang</att> on the source form.<note>There
              may also be cases in which it is unknown whether a given etymological process occurred
              within the contemporary language or parent system; in such cases the encoder can just
              use the main language tag for both the diachronic and synchronic portions of the entry
              as a default (see, for instance, <ptr target="#example11" type="crossref"
            />).</note></p>
          <p>In the TEI encoding, the former two can be respectively labeled as: <egXML
              xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><etym type="borrowing">…</etym></egXML> and
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><etym type="inheritance"
              >…</etym></egXML> Each of the above would represent the top level <gi>etym</gi>
            element, and any other subprocesses can be encoded as embedded <gi>etym</gi> elements
            with <att>type</att> attributes.</p>
          <p>Alternatively, they can be implicitly encoded as the value of the attribute
              <att>xml:lang</att> within the source <gi>oRef</gi> and/or <gi>pRef</gi> form without
            having to embed one or more <gi>etym</gi> elements where this information is redundant
            or implicitly understood, thus simplifying the data structure. For instance, in an entry
            denoting changes to the morphological and phonological form of a given Bavarian word
            inherited from Middle High German, rather than doing the following for every instance of
              inheritance:<!-- [RvdB] moved up this footnote before the example --><note>The
              language information of an etymon can also be specified within the <tag>cit
                type="etymon"</tag> in which the <gi>pRef</gi> or <gi>oRef</gi> is embedded (as
              explained above).</note>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <etym type="inheritance">
                <etym type="phonological-processA"> … <pRef xml:lang="gmh">…</pRef>
                </etym>
              </etym>
            </egXML> it may be desirable to simply specify the source etymon form thus: <egXML
              xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <etym type="phonological-processA"> … <pRef xml:lang="gmh">…</pRef>
              </etym>
            </egXML>
          </p>
          <p>As long as the parent or source language(s) of an entry form are known, and a
            project-specific or external ontology or schema is declared somewhere, this method
            allows for a lighter means of expressing the source language of a form.</p>
          <p>The fact that the origin of the form is borrowed from another language or inherited
            from a <soCalled>parent</soCalled> language can also be implicitly encoded by simply
            including a language tag distinct from that of the main (synchronic) portion of the
            entry.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="cit">
          <head>Using <gi>cit</gi> for Etymons and More</head>
          <p>Having covered the proposed usage model for <tag>cit type="etymon"</tag> we now move on
            to two further functions for the <gi>cit</gi> element, namely to represent
            (sub-)components of an etymological form (e.g., decomposition) and attestations of their
            usage.</p>
          <p>Components are significant lexical subunits which editors may want to isolate
            explicitly within various types of etymological formation. They are indeed objects that
            are very close to etymons but cover a wider variety of linguistic segments such as
            morphemes. We will see in the course of the paper how a <tag>cit type="component"</tag>
            makes sense for this purpose.</p>
          <p>Attestations of historical forms of an etymon in source context can be included within
            a citation element as <tag>cit type="attestation"</tag>. As the contents of the citation
            are a quotation, the sampled linguistic content of the attestation is contained within
            the <gi>quote</gi> element. Within <gi>quote</gi>, the referenced form of the attested
            etymon can be encoded in the <gi>oRef</gi> element to specify which portion of the text
            corresponds to the given etymon.</p>
          <p>Furthermore, where an attestation of an etymological form is in a language other than
            the entry itself, it can be necessary to include translations of the attestations, which
            can simply be encoded with <tag>cit type="translation"</tag> embedded within the
              <tag>cit type="attestation"</tag> (they are embedded within the attestation because
            they pertain specifically to the language content of the attestation). Thus, the XML
            structure mirrors that of attestation, with the only differences being the value of
              <att>type</att> and <att>xml:lang</att>.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="languages">
          <head>Encoding Languages and Representational Aspects of Linguistic Forms</head>
          <p>Over the course of our research we have constantly faced issues related to the actual
            encoding of language-related information for headwords in dictionary entries as well as
            for etymons and similar references. This covers the whole range of TEI elements we are
            considering here: <gi>orth</gi> and <gi>pron</gi>, with their referential counterparts
              <gi>oRef</gi> and <gi>pRef</gi>.</p>
          <p>As a basis for our representation, we have of course taken up the use of
              <att>xml:lang</att> over these elements together with the constraints applicable to
            its values and the guidelines of <ref target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/bcp47">BCP
              47</ref> (<ref target="#ietf09a" type="bibl">IETF 2009a</ref>). We will not go into
            detail here about the possible limits of this recommendation; instead, we need to
            explain some of the choices that are applied in our paper.</p>
          <p>First, there is a general issue with the language coverage offered by BCP 47, which is
            based upon the <ref
              target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/language-subtag-registry/language-subtag-registry"
              >IANA registry</ref><note>IANA Language Subtag Registry, accessed June 16, 2017, <ptr
                target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/language-subtag-registry/language-subtag-registry"
              />.</note> and only offers language tags for a small number of the historical
            languages that are needed even from the reduced perspective of Western European
            etymology: Latin <val>la</val>, Old French <val>fro</val>, and Middle French
              <val>frm</val>.<note>Romance dialectologists estimate the range of dates that Vulgar
              Latin began to become distinct in Gaul/France anywhere between the second century CE
              and the fall of the Roman Empire around the end of the fifth century CE (<ref
                target="#bazin01" type="bibl">Bazin-Tacchella 2001</ref>). Vulgar Latin gave way in
              the ninth century to Old French (ISO 639–3 <val>fro</val>), which is designated by the
              registration body as dating between circa 842 and 1400; however, in the example, the
              antepenultimate form in the phonological development <mentioned>šyé̥f</mentioned> is
              dated as having been used in the eighth century, which means anywhere from 700 to 799
              CE, the later end of which is just 43 years prior to the early portion of Old French.
              This issue raises the question of whether it is really useful to designate a separate
              language for a period of roughly forty-three years.</note></p>
          <p>Additionally, we identify a problem with the abstract context of general language
            markup BCP 47 recommendations, which specify that both the content language and
            orthographic script be labeled within the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute (<ref
              target="#ietf09a" type="bibl">IETF 2009a</ref>). This is neither a conceptually
            accurate (as an orthographic system is of course not a language), nor a functionally
            pragmatic means of representing this information. Functionally, there is no difference
            between orthography and phonetic notation (with various degrees of nuance and exceptions
            for logographic, logosyllabic, and other such systems); they are both representations of
            the language information at some level. With regards to phonetic information (at least
            in the dictionary module), in any linguistic data there is an obvious need to
            distinguish between the various phonetic transcription systems, and the TEI already has
            a solution in <att>notation</att>.</p>
          <p>Similarly, we have observed difficulties in relying on the <att>xml:lang</att>
            attribute alone to cater for the various ways orthographic forms can actually occur
            beyond simple script variations, such as vocalized/non-vocalized in Arabic, kana/kanji
            in Japanese, and competing transliteration systems. Whereas BCP 47 at times introduces
            ways of dealing with such variations or even allows one to define its private subtags to
            do so, we found it cumbersome to overload <att>xml:lang</att>, the main disadvantage
            being the loss of systematicity in the way a given language is marked in an encoded
              text.<note>The interested reader may ponder here the possibility to also encode
              scripts by means of the <att>notation</att> attribute instead of using a cluttering of
              language subtags on <att>xml:lang</att>. For more on this issue, see the proposal in
                the TEI <ptr type="software" xml:id="R2" target="#github"/><rs type="soft.name"
                ref="#R2">GitHub</rs> (<ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1510"
              />).</note> This is why we have extended the <att>notation</att> attribute to
              <gi>orth</gi> in order to allow for better representation of both language
            identification and the orthographic content. With this double mechanism, we intend to
            describe content expressed in the same language by means of the same language tag, thus
            allowing more reliable management, access, and search procedures over our lexical
            content.</p>
          <p>We are aware that we open a can of worms here, since such an editorial practice could
            be easily extended to all text elements in the TEI Guidelines. We have actually
            identified several cases in the sole context of lexical representations (e.g.,
              <gi>quote</gi>) where this practice would be of immediate use.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="encodingsequence">
          <head>Encoding Sequence (Diachronic or Order of Presentation in Source)</head>
          <div xml:id="sourcestructure">
            <head>Maintaining Source Structure vs. Accurate Representation of Etymological
              Process</head>
            <p>When encoding multistage diachronic etymologies from existing sources such as
              attestations from etymological dictionaries or academic papers, it may be the case
              that the source information is not in chronological order for one reason or another.
              In such cases it is up to the encoder to decide whether maintaining the format of the
              source is of any benefit to the data quality.</p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="sequence">
            <head>Sequence</head>
            <p>Because the etymology being encoded in the example has multiple stages in which the
              sequence is both known and theoretically relevant, each <gi>cit</gi> should be given
              an <att>xml:id</att> in combination with one or both of the sequential pointer
              attributes: <att>prev</att>, <att>next</att>. The combination of these within the data
              structure encodes relative occurrence of the given etymon within the diachrony of any
              example.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="inheritance">
        <head>Inheritance</head>
        <p>While inheritance is not itself an etymological process, it identifies lexical items
          known, or presumed, to be inherited from predecessor or <soCalled>parent</soCalled>
          languages; these forms are sometimes referred to as <soCalled>native</soCalled>. A
          simplified view of inheritance is that it is the etymological counterpart to
            borrowing.<note>The theoretical line between the two (<term>inheritance</term> and
              <term>borrowing</term>) becomes blurry when the scope of a language’s history is
            expanded; depending on how far back one looks, an item that was inherited from a direct
            ancestor may have been borrowed at an earlier time. Where such cases are known, it is
            possible to encode both etymological lineages within the same entry.</note> In the most
          basic use of an inheritance etymology, an encoder can simply distinguish the given lexical
          item as having originated directly from its known parent language, or even theoretical
          protolanguage.</p>
        <p>However, within the historical trajectory of most inherited lexical items, any number of
          different etymological processes may occur on every level of language, including
          phonetic/phonological, phonotactic, morphological, grammatical, and/or semantic.</p>
        <p>The basic concepts necessary for a minimal encoding of a simple inheritance etymology
          are:</p>
        <list rend="bulleted">
          <item>language of the (synchronic) entry;</item>
          <item>parent/predecessor language;</item>
          <item>the synchronic orthographic and/or phonetic form(s), sense(s), and/or grammatical
            information;</item>
          <item>the diachronic orthographic and/or phonetic form(s), sense(s), and/or grammatical
            information.</item>
        </list>
        <p>The following is a very simple example from Sardinian <mentioned>semper</mentioned>
          <q>always, still</q>, in which the etymology shows that, at least as far as the
          orthographic form of the lexical item is concerned, it has not changed from its Latin
          source. This is perhaps noteworthy in its own right, and sampling an entire lexicon in
          which such information is included could be useful in measuring how much a language has
          changed over a given period of time.</p>
        <figure xml:id="example3">
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <entry xml:id="semper" xml:lang="srd">
              <form type="lemma">
                <orth>semper</orth>
                <gramGrp>
                  <pos>temporalAdverb</pos>
                </gramGrp>
              </form>
              <sense> ... </sense>
              <etym type="inheritance">
                <cit type="etymon">
                  <oRef xml:lang="la">semper</oRef>
                </cit>
              </etym>
            </entry>
          </egXML>
          <head type="legend">TEI modeling: <tag>etym type="inheritance"</tag></head>
        </figure>
        <p>Note here that we could have a <att>corresp</att> attribute on <gi>oRef</gi> if we had a
          reference Latin dictionary at hand and wanted to point to the actual entry for
            <mentioned>semper</mentioned>.</p>
        <div xml:id="inheritance-changes">
          <head>Inheritance and Phonetic/Phonological Changes</head>
          <p>For any lexical item—regardless of other types of etymological processes undergone over
            a sufficient span of time—it is likely that it will undergo some degree of phonetic
            change. Such changes may occur either over a span of time during which a descendant
            language has become distinct from its <soCalled>parent</soCalled> (such as Vulgar Latin
            &gt; French) or within a span of time in which they are regarded as having occurred
            within the same language. Phonetic and phonological changes often occur in stages and
            have their own set of classifications and terminology that require their own level of
            encoding separate from those occurring on the higher levels of language such as
            morphosyntax and semantics.</p>
          <p>The basic concepts necessary for a minimal encoding of a phonological etymology within
            an inherited entry are: <list rend="bulleted">
              <item>the language of the synchronic entry;</item>
              <item>the parent/predecessor language at the given stage of etymology;</item>
              <item>the synchronic orthographic and/or phonetic form(s);</item>
              <item>the diachronic orthographic and/or phonetic form(s);</item>
              <item>the relative order of their usage/occurrence (if multiple stages are shown, and
                their sequence is known).</item>
            </list> Additionally beneficial are: <list rend="bulleted">
              <item>dates for each of the diachronic forms;</item>
              <item>bibliographic sources for forms, and for the analysis.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="phonologicalChanges">
          <head>Stages of Phonological Changes in Inherited Forms</head>
          <p>The following is our proposal to encode an example of the most significant stages of
            the phonetic evolution of the French <mentioned>chef</mentioned> from the Vulgar
              Latin<note>Despite the fact that it is widely accepted among researchers that the
              actual language spoken by most Roman peoples in everyday life was a non-standardized
              and non-literary language referred to as Vulgar Latin (VL), there is no ISO 639
              language code for this. Instead, there only exists a single tag for Latin (ISO 639–3:
                <val>la</val>). Not distinguishing at least between Classical, Vulgar, and Medieval
              Latin is just not an accurate depiction of the etymological information. Needless to
              say, this issue needs to be addressed and one or more proposals made for the creation
              of these tags within the ISO 639 system.</note>
            <mentioned>CÁPŬ</mentioned> as per Laborderie and Thomasset (<ref target="#laborderie94"
              type="bibl">1994</ref>). Each <tag>cit type="etymon"</tag> element cluster contains
            the historical phonetic forms posited by the authors in the <gi>pRef</gi> element, as
            well as other relevant information pertaining to the given stage in the diachrony of the
            entry. The etymon clusters begin with the Vulgar Latin form (top) and end with the
            Middle French form (bottom).<note>The final form given is the Middle French (and not
              Modern) because according to the source, it was the final stage in the phonological
              evolution of that item and is identical to the present-day form.</note>
          </p>
          <!-- [RvdB] PDF font problem -->
          <figure xml:id="example4">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <entry xml:id="chef" xml:lang="fr">
                <form type="lemma">
                  <orth>chef</orth>
                  <pron notation="ipa">ʃɛf</pron>
                  <gramGrp>
                    <pos>noun</pos>
                    <gen>masc</gen>
                  </gramGrp>
                </form>
                <sense> ... </sense>
                <etym type="inheritance">
                  <cit type="etymon" xml:id="kápŭ" next="#kábu">
                    <pRef notation="private" xml:lang="la">kápŭ</pRef>
                  </cit>
                  <cit type="etymon" xml:id="kábu" prev="#kápŭ">
                    <!-- intervocalic voicing -->
                    <date notBefore="0350" notAfter="0399"/>
                    <pRef notation="private" xml:lang="la">kábu</pRef>
                    <!-- gallo-latin or (VL-Gaul) -->
                  </cit>
                  <cit type="etymon" xml:id="k̯áβo̥" prev="#kábu" next="#t̯áβo̥">
                    <date notBefore="0400" notAfter="0499"/>
                    <pRef notation="private">k̯áβo̥</pRef>
                    <!-- late gallo-latin ?-->
                  </cit>
                  <cit type="etymon" xml:id="t̯ávo̥" prev="#k̯áβo̥" next="t͡sávo̥">
                    <date notBefore="0400" notAfter="0499"/>
                    <pRef notation="private">t̯áβo</pRef>
                    <!-- late gallo-latin ?-->
                  </cit>
                  <cit type="etymon" xml:id="t͡sávo̥" prev="#t̯ávo̥" next="#t͡šíe̥vo̥">
                    <date notBefore="0400" notAfter="0499"/>
                    <pRef notation="private">t͡sávo̥</pRef>
                    <!-- late gallo-latin ?-->
                  </cit>
                  <cit type="etymon" xml:id="t͡šíe̥vo̥" prev="#t͡šávo̥" next="#tšíe̥f">
                    <date notBefore="0450" notAfter="0550"/>
                    <pRef notation="private">t͡šíe̥vo̥</pRef>
                    <!-- late gallo-latin ?/early gallo-romance-->
                  </cit>
                  <cit type="etymon" xml:id="tšíe̥f" prev="#t͡šíe̥vo" next="#šye̥f">
                    <date notBefore="0600" notAfter="0699"/>
                    <pRef notation="private">tšíe̥f</pRef>
                    <!-- early gallo-romance-->
                  </cit>
                  <cit type="etymon" xml:id="šyé̥f" prev="#tšíe̥f" next="#šé̥f">
                    <date notBefore="0700" notAfter="0799"/>
                    <pRef notation="private">šyé̥f</pRef>
                    <!-- early/Proto Old French (?) -->
                  </cit>
                  <cit type="etymon" xml:id="šé̥f" prev="#šyé̥f" next="#šę́f">
                    <date notBefore="1500" notAfter="1650"/>
                    <pRef notation="private" xml:lang="frm">šé̥f</pRef>
                  </cit>
                  <cit type="etymon" xml:id="šę́f" prev="#šé̥f">
                    <date notBefore="1500" notAfter="1650"/>
                    <pRef notation="private" xml:lang="frm">šę́f</pRef>
                  </cit>
                  <bibl>Laborderie, N. and Thomasset, C. (1994). Précis de phonétique historique.
                    Paris: Nathan.</bibl>
                </etym>
              </entry>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Phonological stages in inherited form<note>In other examples, the
                values of <att>notation</att> used in <gi>pron</gi> and <gi>pRef</gi> have been
                well-known standard systems with conventional names, e.g., <val>ipa</val> and
                  <val>xsampa</val>. However, in this example, while in the source the author
                explains the phonetic correlate for the transcription notation used in the work, and
                there are some characters that are used in the IPA, this system has no proper name,
                thus we have chosen to label it <val>private</val>.</note></head>
          </figure>
          <p>The diachronic sequence of the forms is encoded in our markup as follows: the
              <att>xml:id</att> attribute is included for each <gi>cit</gi> for which the given
            language information is available; the ordering of each is encoded in the data structure
            by the use of the pointing attributes <att>prev</att> and <att>next</att>, the values of
            which are the unique identifiers of the previous and next <gi>cit</gi> block
            respectively.</p>
          <p>The <gi>date</gi><note>The element <gi>date</gi> as a child of <gi>cit</gi> is another
              example which does not adhere to the current TEI standards. We have allowed this
              within our ODD document. A feature request proposal will be made on the <ptr
                type="software" xml:id="R3" target="#github"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R3"
                >GitHub</rs> page and this feature may or may not appear in future versions of the
              TEI Guidelines.</note> element is listed within each etymon block; the values of
            attributes <att>notBefore</att> and <att>notAfter</att> specify the range of time
            corresponding to the period of time that the given form was in use according to the
              authors.<note>In the (French language) source of this example (<ref
                target="#laborderie94" type="bibl">Laborderie and Thomasset 1994, 97</ref>) the
              dates were given in a combination of roman numerals with superscripted numbers and
              letters to indicate the century, e.g., IVe2, which corresponds to <hi rend="italic"
                >deuxième moitié du 4e siècle</hi>, second half of the fourth century (CE).
              Optionally, the encoder could include the original date as the value of the
                <gi>date</gi> element for human readability. In such a case, for the purposes of
              quality data structuring, compatibility, and retrievability the dating information
              should nonetheless also be included as attribute value(s): e.g.,
                <code><![CDATA[<date notBefore="0350" notAfter="0399"> IVe2 </date>]]></code>.</note>
            The attribute values encode the date according to W3C recommendations<note>See
                  <bibl><author>Misha Wolf</author> and <author>Charles Wicksteed</author>, <title
                  level="u">Date and Time Formats</title> (W3C Note), <date>1997</date>, accessed
                April 26, 2017, <ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/NOTE-datetime"/></bibl>.</note>
            and must have a four-digit representation of the year.<note>One of our anonymous
              reviewers kindly noted that we should bear in mind that these attributes are for
              Gregorian dates only. If we are ever encoding anything more specific than a year, it
              is necessary to use <att>datingMethod</att> and custom dating attributes to clarify
              that the Julian calendar is the one we are using here, rather than the proleptic
              Gregorian.</note> Finally, we have the <gi>pRef</gi> element, which, as always,
            contains the language of the given etymon as the value of <att>xml:lang</att> and the
            notation attribute <att>notation</att>.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="morphologicalChanges">
          <head>Morphological and Morphosyntactic Changes in Inherited Forms</head>
          <p>Changes in morphological inflection paradigms in which there is no difference need not
            be explicitly represented in a dictionary but instead can be done implicitly.</p>
          <p>Because an entry in a TEI or other semasiological dictionary represents the etymology
            of an individual etymon as pertaining to an individual lexical item, diachronic changes
            in morphological inflection patterning are manifested in the differences in the phonetic
            and often orthographic forms. These differences are evident when contrasting a large
            sample of synchronic and diachronic phonological and phonotactic forms with respect to a
            given historical or contemporary morphological or morphosyntactic feature.</p>
          <p>When attempting to extract any global information about changes to the grammatical
            feature inventory of a language from a dictionary, such information can also be inferred
            through the contrast between the contents of <gi>gramGrp</gi> in the source etymon (in
            the <tag>cit type="etymon"</tag> cluster) and the resulting (synchronic) form. For
            example, where the source form has a specific case and the entry in question does not
            have any case information, the general phenomenon that is the loss of grammatical case
            is implicitly present.</p>
          <p>The following Sicilian entry shows an example of such a scenario in combination with a
            change in grammatical gender. Whereas in Latin, the etymon had the neuter gender, the
            inherited form in Sicilian is of the masculine gender. Additionally, Sicilian no longer
            has a neuter gender.<note>This would be referred to as case loss from the perspective of
              the item’s morphosyntactic etymology.</note> Both of these changes are implicit in the
            data structure we propose:</p>
          <figure xml:id="example5">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <entry xml:id="mare" xml:lang="scn">
                <form type="lemma">
                  <orth>mari</orth>
                  <gramGrp>
                    <pos>noun</pos>
                    <gen>masc</gen>
                  </gramGrp>
                </form>
                <sense> ... </sense>
                <etym type="inheritance">
                  <cit type="etymon">
                    <oRef xml:lang="la">mare</oRef>
                    <gramGrp>
                      <pos>noun</pos>
                      <gen>neut</gen>
                      <case>nom</case>
                      <iType>-i stem</iType>
                    </gramGrp>
                    <gloss>sea</gloss>
                  </cit>
                </etym>
              </entry>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Implicit morphosyntactic changes: Latin &gt; Sicilian</head>
          </figure>
          <p>As with morphology and phonology, grammatical etymological can be globally inferred.
            This means that, in a Sicilian TEI dictionary (of sufficient size) containing such
            synchronic and diachronic information, a search for all entries containing all of the
            following facets would enable the conclusion that there is no more neuter gender:</p>
          <list rend="bulleted">
            <item><code><![CDATA[<pos>noun</pos>]]></code>, or
                <code><![CDATA[<pos>adjective</pos>]]></code>;<note>Or any terminological equivalent
                to either.</note></item>
            <item><tag>etym type="inheritance"</tag> in which value of <att>xml:lang</att> in
                <gi>oRef</gi> and/or <gi>pRef</gi> is <val>la</val>);</item>
            <item><tag>cit type="etymon"</tag> in whose <gi>gramGrp</gi> there is
                <code><![CDATA[<gen>neut</gen>]]></code>;</item>
            <item>Get synchronic gender: value of <gi>gramGrp</gi>, <gi>gen</gi> within <tag>form
                type="lemma"</tag>.<note>Which one could easily retrieve by means of a simple XPath
                instruction such as
                  <code><![CDATA[./cit[@type='etymon']/gramGrp[gen='neut']]></code>]</note></item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="morphologicalInheritance">
          <head>Morphological Inheritance: Inflected Forms</head>
          <p>Individual morphologically inflected forms of entries may have different etymological
            histories than the lemma forms with which they are associated. This could be for reasons
            connected with a separate origin from the lemma, or, more commonly, with the fact that
            the phonological composition of the lemma and inflected forms were and are distinct and
            they each underwent unique changes.</p>
          <p>To encode the etymology of any individual form (when the entry contains more than one
            that must be distinguished):</p>
          <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>a unique identifier <att>xml:id</att> should be included in the given form;</item>
            <item>the corresponding <gi>etym</gi> should point to the form as the value of the
              attribute <att>corresp</att>.</item>
          </list>
          <p>In the following example from Italian, phonotactic changes are reflected in the
            orthographic form (e.g., <mentioned>perdidi</mentioned> &gt;
              <mentioned>persí</mentioned>), and the aspect of an inherited inflected form
              <mentioned>persí</mentioned> has also changed. In particular, it shows that the etymon
            originates from the Latin past tense, perfective aspect: <mentioned>perdidi</mentioned>.
            In Standard Italian and many (mainly northern) dialects, descendants of the Latin
            perfective past have come to be used as the remote past tense (i.e., remote aspect).</p>
          <figure xml:id="example6">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <entry xml:id="perdere" xml:lang="it">
                <form type="lemma">
                  <orth>perdere</orth>
                  <gramGrp>
                    <pos>verb</pos>
                  </gramGrp>
                  <!-- rest of inflected forms here -->
                  <form type="inflected" xml:id="perdere-1s-rem-pt-indic">
                    <orth>persí</orth>
                    <gramGrp>
                      <per>1</per>
                      <number>sg</number>
                      <tns>past</tns>
                      <mood>indic</mood>
                      <gram type="aspect">remote</gram>
                      <gram type="voice">active</gram>
                    </gramGrp>
                  </form>
                </form>
                <sense>
                  <!-- sense info here -->
                </sense>
                <etym type="inheritance">
                  <cit type="etymon">
                    <oRef xml:lang="la">perdere</oRef>
                  </cit> … <etym type="inheritance" corresp="#perdere-1s-rem-pt-indic">
                    <cit type="etymon">
                      <oRef xml:lang="la">perdidi</oRef>
                      <gramGrp>
                        <per>1</per>
                        <number>sg</number>
                        <tns>past</tns>
                        <mood>indic</mood>
                        <gram type="aspect">perfective</gram>
                        <gram type="voice">active</gram>
                      </gramGrp>
                    </cit>
                  </etym>
                </etym>
              </entry>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Italian—etymological change in aspect
                (<mentioned>perdere</mentioned>)</head>
          </figure>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="borrowing">
        <head>Borrowing</head>
        <p>Borrowing (a.k.a. loaning, importing, transferring, copying) can generally be described
          as the process in which a lexical item, phrase, or other linguistic feature from a foreign
          language or dialect is conventionalized into another language or dialect.</p>
        <p>Matras and Sakel (<ref target="#matras07" type="bibl">2007</ref>) distinguish between two
          primary types of borrowing: <term>material borrowing</term> and <term>structural
            borrowing.</term> Material borrowing pertains to the borrowing of sound–meaning pairs
          (e.g., loanwords, phrases and/or affixes); structural borrowing pertains to the copying of
          syntactic, morphological, or semantic patterns.</p>
        <p>A major factor in borrowing is contact between a foreign culture and a given language
            (<ref target="#haugen50" type="bibl">Haugen 1950</ref>). There are often historical,
          sociological, and practical explanations for how and why the process occurred and thus
          such information encoded by a linguist or lexicographer may be relevant to those studying
          other fields such as history, anthropology, and sociology.<note>The question <q>Why do
              languages borrow?</q> is examined by Haspelmath (<ref target="#haspelmath09"
              type="bibl">2009</ref>). This work also gives an excellent overview of the various
            typological differences discussed in past works.</note></p>
        <p>Along these lines, distinctions have been made between <term>cultural borrowings</term>
          and <term>core borrowings</term> (<ref target="#myers-scotton02" type="bibl">Myers-Scotton
            2002</ref>). Cultural borrowings are when a lexical item is borrowed for a new concept;
          these can appear over a very short period of time. Core borrowings duplicate existing
          items and are introduced over a longer period of time by bilinguals (<ref
            target="#myers-scotton02" type="bibl">Myers-Scotton 2002</ref>; <ref
            target="#haspelmath03" type="bibl">Haspelmath 2003</ref>).</p>
        <p>When in some manner a borrowed item is not compatible with that of the recipient
          language, loanwords undergo one or more adaptations to their orthographic, phonological,
          and/or morphological forms (<ref target="#haugen50" type="bibl">Haugen 1950</ref>). Our
          examples will demonstrate encodings for each of these different types of adaptation.</p>
        <p>The basic concepts necessary for a minimal encoding of a <soCalled>borrowing</soCalled>
          etymology are:</p>
        <list rend="bulleted">
          <item>borrowing language (a.k.a. recipient language);</item>
          <item>source language (a.k.a. donor language);</item>
          <item>source form (orthographic and/or phonetic);</item>
          <item>borrowed form (orthographic and/or phonetic);</item>
          <item>semantic profile/metalinguistic concept or grammatical function of borrowed form (in
            the case of grammatical borrowing).</item>
        </list>
        <p>The combination of these elements in a TEI-based model naturally leads to the overall
          model depicted in <ptr target="#figure2" type="crossref"/>.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure2">
          <graphic url="images/image2.png" width="1454px" height="550px"/>
          <head type="legend">Basic components of the model for etymological borrowing</head>
        </figure>
        <p>Borrowing-typed etymologies should be direct children of <gi>entry</gi>, as the process
          of borrowing does not affect the sense of a pre-existing lexical item within the target
          language. The source language should be labeled with the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute
          within the <gi>pRef</gi> and/or <gi>oRef</gi>, and can optionally be labeled explicitly
          for human readability as the value of the element <gi>lang</gi> (see <ref
            target="#example7" type="crossref">following example</ref>). If desired, in addition to
          the <gi>lang</gi> element, other key terms can be included in the <gi>lbl</gi> element to
          modify the language (e.g., <code><![CDATA[<lbl>source</lbl>]]></code>,
            <code><![CDATA[<lbl>from</lbl>]]></code>, etc.). If the semantics of the item in the
          source language differ from that of the borrowing language, the original can be included
          in the element <gi>gloss</gi>.</p>
        <p><ptr target="#example7" type="crossref"/> shows our TEI adaptation from LMF (<ref
            target="#salmon-alt06" type="bibl">Salmon-Alt 2006</ref>) of the French
            <mentioned>pamplemousse</mentioned>, which is a borrowing from Dutch. The bibliographic
          source of this entry is the <title level="m">Trésor de la Langue Française</title>, which
          is cited in the <gi>ref</gi> element both in the value of the attribute
            <code>@target="#TLF"</code>, and as the content of the <gi>ref</gi> element. The former
          points to a bibliographic entry for the <title level="m">Trésor de la Langue
            Française</title> that is necessarily located within the given document or project; the
          latter is included for human readability.</p>
        <figure xml:id="example7">
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <entry xml:id="LE1" xml:lang="fr">
              <form type="lemma">
                <orth>pamplemousse</orth>
                <gramGrp>
                  <pos>commonNoun</pos>
                  <gen>masculine</gen>
                </gramGrp>
              </form>
              <sense> .... </sense>
              <etym type="borrowing">
                <lang>Dutch</lang>
                <cit type="etymon">
                  <oRef xml:lang="nl">pompelmoes</oRef>
                  <gloss xml:lang="lat">Citrus maxima</gloss>
                  <gramGrp>
                    <pos>commonNoun</pos>
                    <gen>feminine</gen>
                  </gramGrp>
                  <note>probablement d'origine tamoule, De Vries, Nedrl</note>
                  <ref target="#TLF">TLF</ref>
                </cit>
              </etym>
            </entry>
          </egXML>
          <head type="legend">Simple borrowing <mentioned>pamplemousse</mentioned> from <ref
              target="#salmon-alt06" type="bibl">Salmon-Alt 2006</ref>; converted from LMF</head>
        </figure>
        <div xml:id="orthographicAdaptation">
          <head>Orthographic Adaptation in Borrowed Forms</head>
          <p>The following example is a revised version of an entry from the TEI Guidelines of the
            word <mentioned>biryani</mentioned> (or <mentioned>biriani</mentioned>), which was
            borrowed into English from Urdu. Herein we observe that in English there is variation in
            the orthographic adaptation of the borrowed item, which is most commonly spelled
              <q>biryani</q>, but also sometimes <q>biriani</q>. This relative frequency between the
            two variant forms is encoded in the entry by embedding the less frequent <gi>orth</gi>
            form within a second <gi>form</gi> element, labeled <code>@type="variant"</code>, which
            is a direct child of the <tag>form type="lemma"</tag>.</p>
          <p>This orthographic variation stems from the fact that there is not a standard 1 for 1
            system of transliterating between the Arabic script of Urdu and the Latin script of
            English. This information is recorded within the <gi>note</gi> element in the
            etymological section as the origin of this issue lies in the item’s etymology.</p>
          <figure xml:id="example8">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <entry xml:id="biryani" xml:lang="en">
                <form type="lemma">
                  <form type="preferred">
                    <orth>biryani</orth>
                    <pron notation="xsampa">%bIrI"A:nI</pron>
                  </form>
                  <form type="variant">
                    <orth>biriani</orth>
                  </form>
                  <gramGrp>
                    <pos>noun</pos>
                  </gramGrp>
                </form>
                <sense corresp="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Biryani">
                  <def>any variety of Indian dishes…</def>
                </sense>
                <etym type="borrowing">
                  <lbl>from</lbl>
                  <lang>Urdu</lang>
                  <oRef xml:lang="ur">بریانی</oRef>
                  <note>The variation in the English orthographic form of this entry is due to the
                    fact that there is no standard transliteration between English (Latin) and
                    Urdu’s (Arabic) scripts </note>
                </etym>
              </entry>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Borrowing and transliteration: <mentioned>biryani</mentioned></head>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="phonologicalAdaptation">
          <head>Phonological Adaptation in Borrowed Forms</head>
          <p><ptr target="#example9" type="crossref"/> also contains transliteration between the
            orthographies of the source (in this case English) and borrowing (Japanese) languages.
            Additionally, Japanese has multiple orthographic systems into which the borrowed form is
            integrated; each of these systems is identified in the <gi>orth</gi> element as the
            value of the <att>notation</att> attribute. In contrast to the previous example
              (<mentioned>biryani</mentioned>), the presence of a phonetic form in both the source
            and borrowing languages implicitly shows the difference in the pronunciation between the
            English source:</p>
          <!-- [RvdB] PDF font problem -->
          <figure xml:id="example9">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <entry xml:id="taxi" xml:lang="ja">
                <form type="lemma">
                  <orth type="transliterated" notation="rōmaji">takushī</orth>
                  <orth notation="katakana">タクシー</orth>
                  <pron notation="ipa">takushi:</pron>
                  <gramGrp>
                    <pos>noun</pos>
                  </gramGrp>
                </form>
                <sense corresp="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Taxicab">
                  <usg type="dom">Transportation</usg>
                </sense>
                <etym type="borrowing">
                  <lbl>source</lbl>
                  <lang>English</lang>
                  <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="en">
                    <oRef corresp="http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/taxi#English">taxi</oRef>
                    <pRef notation="ipa" corresp="http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/taxi#Pronunciation"
                      >ˈtæksi</pRef>
                  </cit>
                </etym>
              </entry>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Borrowing—phonological and orthographical adaptation:
                <mentioned>takushī</mentioned></head>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="morphologicalAdaptation">
          <head>Morphological Adaptation in Borrowed Forms</head>
          <p>In the case that a language whose grammatical system has a feature such as gender
            borrows a (nominal) item from a language that has no grammatical gender, the borrowing
            language will generally need to assign a gender to the loanword. In the example below
            showing the French borrowing of the English <mentioned>weekend</mentioned>, the lack of
            gender is implicitly encoded by the absence of a <gi>gen</gi> element within the
              <gi>gramGrp</gi> element cluster within the <tag>cit
              type="etymon"</tag>.<note>Alteration to the gender property in the borrowed form is
              also evident in the first example <mentioned>pamplemousse</mentioned>, as in French it
              is a masculine noun, whereas in Dutch it was feminine.</note> The adaptation made in
            assimilating this item into the French language is visible in the inverse manner (e.g.,
            in the inclusion of the <code><![CDATA[<gen>masc</gen>]]></code>) within the
              <gi>gramGrp</gi> element cluster within the <tag>form type="lemma"</tag>).</p>
          <p>In modeling this for French, it is especially important to include the gender
            information because of the implications for the specific forms that will occur in
            context of and in reference to <mentioned>weekend</mentioned> in the context of natural
            language (e.g., articles, pronouns, determiners, demonstratives, and gender forms of
            adjectives).</p>
          <figure xml:id="example10">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <entry xml:id="weekend" xml:lang="fr">
                <form type="lemma">
                  <orth>week-end</orth>
                  <gramGrp>
                    <pos>nom</pos>
                    <gen>masc</gen>
                  </gramGrp>
                </form>
                <sense corresp="http://fr.dbpedia.org/page/Week-end">
                  <def>Le week-end (variante weekend, comme en anglais), issu de l’anglais weekend;
                    ou la fin de semaine est une période hebdomadaire d’un ou deux jours,
                    généralement le samedi et le dimanche, pendant laquelle la plupart des gens sont
                    au repos.</def>
                </sense>
                <etym type="borrowing">
                  <cit type="etymon">
                    <oRef>weekend</oRef>
                    <gramGrp>
                      <pos>nom</pos>
                    </gramGrp>
                  </cit>
                </etym>
              </entry>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Borrowing—morphological adaptation:
              <mentioned>weekend</mentioned></head>
          </figure>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="metaphor">
        <head>Metaphor</head>
        <p>Metaphor is undeniably one of the primary motors of lexical innovation as well as of
          (synchronic) polysemy in languages. On the cognitive level, metaphor can be roughly
          defined as the process of understanding one concept from one domain of experience in terms
          of another concept from a separate domain of experience. This is mirrored lexically, where
          one concept in a given domain is described or referred to using lexical items (and/or
          vocabulary) from another (<ref target="#lakoff80" type="bibl">Lakoff and Johnson
            1980</ref>; <ref target="#lakoff87" type="bibl">Lakoff 1987</ref>; <ref
            target="#lakoff93" type="bibl">Lakoff 1993</ref>).</p>
        <p>While this process is not commonly mentioned as a primary category for linguistic change
          in lexicographical sources such as etymological dictionaries, it is an essential component
          of linguistic analysis and is relevant to cognitive sciences and anthropology as well.</p>
        <p>Metaphorical mappings often follow patterns in directionality; most commonly, the source
          is a more concrete or primitive domain and the target is a more abstract, less
          conceptually primitive domain (<ref target="#lakoff80" type="bibl">Lakoff and Johnson
            1980</ref>; <ref target="#lakoff87" type="bibl">Lakoff 1987</ref>; <ref
            target="#lakoff93" type="bibl">Lakoff 1993</ref>). Examples of conceptual primitive
          domains are space, temperature, olfaction, location, motion, quantity, body, food, and
          water.</p>
        <p>The driving forces for this process are ontological correspondences between the
          attributes or internal structures of entities in the source domain with those of the
          target domain (<ref target="#lakoff93" type="bibl">Lakoff 1993</ref>). Where this is true,
          the potential for mapping is activated, or is rendered salient on the conceptual level,
          which in turn enables the linguistic encoding of these structures for communicative
          purposes. Thus, metaphor in language is a surface level reflection or by-product of
          operations that occur at the cognitive level. Given the fundamental implication of such
          ideas, not paying attention to metaphor when documenting language change is missing out on
          an enormous source of incredibly fascinating information.</p>
        <p>The basic concepts necessary for a minimal encoding of a <soCalled>metaphor</soCalled>
          etymology are:</p>
        <list rend="bulleted">
          <item>Source form (the same as target form at time of process);</item>
          <item>Target form (the same as source form at time of process);</item>
          <item>Domain of concept (y): source domain;</item>
          <item>Domain of concept (x): target domain.</item>
        </list>
        <p>The model below shows an abstract representation of the essential structures for such an
          entry.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure3">
          <graphic url="images/image3.png" height="570px" width="1332px"/>
          <head type="legend">TEI modeling: <tag>etym type="metaphor"</tag>.</head>
        </figure>
        <p><ptr target="#example11" type="crossref"/> shows an instance of an encoding of the
          lexical item for <q>kidney</q> in Mixtepec-Mixtec language, which was derived
          metaphorically from <q>bean</q>. This metaphorical mapping is clearly due to the physical
          similarity (color and shape) between a bean and a kidney. While both terms refer to
          concrete (physical) concepts, the source, which is a primary food source for the speakers
          of the language, is more conceptually primitive than its target, which is an internal
          organ and thus seen much less frequently, if at all, by most speakers.</p>
        <figure xml:id="example11">
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <entry xml:id="kidney" xml:lang="mix">
              <form type="lemma">
                <orth>ntuchi</orth>
                <pron notation="ipa">ndú.ʧì</pron>
                <gramGrp>
                  <pos>noun</pos>
                </gramGrp>
              </form>
              <sense corresp="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Kidney">
                <usg type="dom" corresp="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Human_body">Body</usg>
                <usg type="dom" corresp="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Human_organs"
                  >InternalOrgans</usg>
                <etym type="metaphor">
                  <cit type="etymon">
                    <oRef corresp="#bean">ntuchi</oRef>
                    <pRef notation="ipa" corresp="#bean">ndú.ʧì</pRef>
                    <ref type="sense" corresp="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Bean"/>
                    <usg type="dom" corresp="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Edible_legumes"
                      >Legume</usg>
                    <gloss>bean</gloss>
                  </cit>
                </etym>
                <cit type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                  <oRef>kidney</oRef>
                </cit>
              </sense>
            </entry>
          </egXML>
          <head type="legend">Metaphor: Mixtepec-Mixtec <q>kidney</q><note>In the digital source
              quoted here, entries are associated with an identifier (<att>xml:id</att>) named from
              the English gloss. Besides, different senses correspond to different entries. The
              identifier <val>#bean</val> thus refers to the entry for <mentioned>ntuchi</mentioned>
              with the meaning <q>bean</q>. In many cases, such a reference would normally point to
              senses instead of separate entries.</note></head>
        </figure>
        <p>Metaphor-typed etymologies should always be direct children of <gi>sense</gi> as the
          lexical change affects the sense of an existing lexical item. In order to know that it is
          a metaphor, it is of course necessary to know <list rend="inline simple">
            <item>a) the original meaning of the source (encoded in <gi>gloss</gi>, or
              <gi>def</gi>), and</item>
            <item>b) the domains of the source and target items, such as source domain (semantic
              domain of etymon) and target domain (semantic domain of entry)</item>
          </list>. In pursuit of the latter, the TEI <gi>usg</gi> element can be used with the
          attribute–value pair <code>@type="dom"</code>, in which the element value represents the
          domain. Given that the semantic profiles of concepts are not always limited to a single
          domain, it may be necessary to include multiple <tag>usg type="dom"</tag> element–value
          pairs, as in the example. In our model, <tag>usg type="dom"</tag> is used in both the
          synchronic (<gi>sense</gi>) and the diachronic (<gi>cit</gi>) portions of the entry.</p>
        <p>However, although such structures, if used consistently, do have the capacity to greatly
          enhance any data that do not include this information, they inevitably fall short of the
          extent of knowledge that is truly necessary to create an accurate model of metaphorical
          processes. In order to do this, it is necessary to make use of one or more ontologies,
          which could be locally defined within a project, and of external linked open data sources
          such as <ptr type="software" xml:id="R4"
            target="#dbpedia"/><rs type="soft.name url" ref="#R4"><ref target="http://wiki.dbpedia.org/">DBpedia</ref></rs> and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R5"
              target="#wikidata"/><rs type="soft.name url" ref="#R5"><ref
                  target="https://www.wikidata.org/">Wikidata</ref></rs>, or some combination thereof. Within
          TEI dictionary markup, URIs for existing ontological entries can be referenced in the
            <gi>sense</gi>, <gi>usg</gi>, and <gi>ref</gi> elements as the value of the attribute
            <att>corresp</att>.</p>
        <p>Within the etymon, the <gi>oRef</gi> and/or <gi>pRef</gi> can be included with a pointer
          to the source form using the <att>corresp</att> attribute, the value of which is a
          reference to the source entry’s unique identifier (if such an entry exists within the
          dataset). In such cases, the etymon pointing to the source entry can be assumed to inherit
          the source’s domain and sense information, and this information can be automatically
          extracted with a fairly simple <ptr type="software" xml:id="R6"
            target="#xslt"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R6">XSLT</rs> program; thus the encoders may choose to leave some or
          all of this information out of the etymon section. However, in the case that the dataset
          does not actually have entries for the source terms, or the encoder wants to be explicit
          in all aspects of the etymology, as mentioned above, the source domain and the
          ontologically based sense of an etymon can be encoded within <gi>cit</gi> as <gi>ref</gi>
          and <gi>usg</gi> respectively.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="metonymy">
        <head>Metonymy</head>
        <p>Like metaphor, metonymy is another process based in human cognition which is reflected in
          language and leads to synchronic lexical polysemy. Again like metaphor, metonymy is often
          central to linguistic etymological analyses, but is also not commonly mentioned as a
          primary category for language change in lexicographical sources such as etymological
          dictionaries.</p>
        <p>In metonymy, one vehicle entity provides mental access to a target entity within a single
          domain by highlighting different aspects of part–whole relationships (meronymy) (<ref
            target="#kovecses98" type="bibl">Kövecses and Radden 1998</ref>). There are two primary
          types of relationships that commonly provide the motivation, or what Vandeloise (<ref
            target="#vandeloise06" type="bibl">2006</ref>) refers to as <soCalled>logical
            impetus</soCalled>, for the occurrence of metonymy: <list rend="inline simple">
            <item>a) where a part of an entity’s profile stands for the whole;</item>
            <item>b) when a domain’s subpart stands for its whole (ibid.)</item>
          </list>.</p>
        <p>The basic concepts necessary for a minimal encoding of a <soCalled>metonymy</soCalled>
          etymology are:</p>
        <list rend="bulleted">
          <item>synchronic (polysemous) form(s) of item;</item>
          <item>source form(s) (orthographic and/or phonetic);</item>
          <item>semantic profile/metalinguistic concept or entity of borrowed form.<note>Sometimes
              the semantic, grammatical, or other aspects of the source item and those of the
              importing language are not equivalent. In such a case, the contrast can be inherently
              represented through the differing information within the synchronic portion of the
              entry and that in the <tag>cit type="etymon"</tag> section. Additionally, the encoder
              can also include a prose description of this with a <gi>note</gi> element.</note>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>The TEI modeling of metonymy is very similar to that of metaphor with the exception that
          the semantic domain between source and target is the same. Thus the model is as follows:
          metonymy-typed etymologies should be embedded in the <gi>sense</gi> element, which can
          also contain the <att>corresp</att> with a URI to the conceptual entry in an external
          ontology; within the <tag>cit type="etymon"</tag> element block, the source orthographic
          and/or phonetic forms should be included in <gi>oRef</gi> and/or <gi>pRef</gi> elements;
          within these elements, the value of the attribute <att>corresp</att> specifies the unique
          identifier of the source entry. Often metonymy leads to a change in grammatical role, and
          thus it is often the case that a <gi>gramGrp</gi> element block is necessary, which then
          should include whatever subelements are necessary.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure4">
          <graphic url="images/image4.png" height="668px" width="1300px"/>
          <head type="legend">Abstract TEI modeling for metonymy</head>
        </figure>
        <p>In the example below from Mixtepec-Mixtec, the words for <q>animal</q> and <q>horse</q>
          are polysemous, the origin of which can clearly be identified as metonymy. Here, the
          language reflects the history of the people; since there were no horses in Mexico until
          the arrival of the Spanish, there was no Mixtecan word for <q>horse</q>, and the
          categorical noun for <q>animal</q> was used to describe the unnamed animal.</p>
        <p>In the TEI entry, the synchronic orthographic and phonetic forms are identical to those
          of the source term <q>animal</q>. Within the etymology element block (<tag>etym
            type="metonymy"</tag>) and the etymon (<tag>cit type="etymon"</tag>) the source term’s
          URI is referenced in <gi>oRef</gi> and <gi>pRef</gi> as the value of <att>corresp</att>
            (<code>@corresp="#animal"</code>).</p>
        <p>In <gi>sense</gi>, the URI corresponding to the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R7"
          target="#dbpedia"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R7">DBpedia</rs> entry for <q>horse</q> is the
          value for the attribute <att>corresp</att>. Additionally, the <tag>date
            notBefore="…"</tag> element–attribute pairing is used to specify that the term has only
          been used for the <q>horse</q> since 1517 at maximum (corresponding to the first Spanish
          expedition into Mexico). Within the actual document, the contents of <gi>note</gi> discuss
          the historical context of this word origin (commented out in the <ref target="#example12"
            type="crossref">example</ref>).</p>
        <!-- [RvdB] PDF font problem? -->
        <figure xml:id="example12">
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <entry xml:id="animal-horse" xml:lang="mix">
              <form type="lemma">
                <orth>kiti</orth>
                <pron notation="ipa">kì.t̪í</pron>
                <gramGrp>
                  <pos>noun</pos>
                </gramGrp>
              </form>
              <sense corresp="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Horse">
                <usg type="dom" corresp="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Animal">Animal</usg>
                <etym type="metonymy">
                  <date notBefore="1517"/>
                  <cit type="etymon">
                    <oRef corresp="#animal">kiti</oRef>
                    <pRef notation="ipa" corresp="#animal">kì.t̪í</pRef>
                    <gloss>animal</gloss>
                  </cit>
                  <note><!--  notes on historical context of term here --></note>
                </etym>
                <cit type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                  <oRef>horse</oRef>
                </cit>
                <cit type="translation" xml:lang="es">
                  <oRef>caballo</oRef>
                </cit> … </sense>
            </entry>
          </egXML>
          <head type="legend">Metonymy: Mixtepec-Mixtec <mentioned>kiti</mentioned></head>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="compounding">
        <head>Compounding</head>
        <p>For various reasons, the lexical process of compounding has traditionally been treated in
          linguistic literature focused on synchronic themes, often in the context of such issues as
          morphology and word formation. One of the least theoretically controversial reasons for
          this is that novel compounds can be formed, used, and understood by speakers
          instantaneously. However, there is significant discord in the linguistics literature as to
          how compound lexical items and the process of compounding should be analyzed. This is most
          distinctly evident in the contrasting approaches between linguistic theories that make
          strict divisions between lexicon and grammar (traditional generative grammar) and those
          that do not make such distinctions (cognitive linguistic theories) (<ref
            target="#langacker87" type="bibl">Langacker 1987</ref>, <ref target="#langacker91"
            type="bibl">1991</ref>, <ref target="#langacker00" type="bibl">2000</ref>; <ref
            target="#jackendoff09" type="bibl">Jackendoff 2009</ref>).</p>
        <p>In attempting to create typologies and/or generalizations about the nature of compound
          word forms and the process in which they are created, the aforementioned viewpoints
          emphasize different aspects of the phenomena. Studies by authors adhering to more formal,
          generative theoretical frameworks often focus on analyzing the morphosyntactic makeup of
          compound forms in the context of rule patterning: e.g., N+N, A+A, V+V, N+A, P+N. Those
          adhering to the cognitive-based theory generally focus on the semantic profiles and
          ontological relationships of the constituent parts, as well as on the cognitive processes
          (metaphor and/or metonymy) active in the resulting meaning (<ref target="#goossens94"
            type="bibl">Goossens 1994</ref>; <ref target="#geeraerts02" type="bibl">Geeraerts
            2002</ref>; <ref target="#benczes06a" type="bibl">Benczes 2006a</ref>, <ref
            target="#benczes06b" type="bibl">2006b</ref>; <ref target="#guevara08" type="bibl"
            >Guevara and Scalise 2008</ref>). Examples of such semantic/ontological relationships
          commonly found in compound forms are type–of (hyponymy), cause–effect, part–whole
          (meronymy), and location–located (<ref target="#benczes06b" type="bibl">Benczes
            2006b</ref>).</p>
        <p>A common means of classifying compounds in linguistics literature (both formal and
          cognitive) is according to two main typologies: <term>endocentric</term> and
            <term>exocentric</term> compounds (<ref target="#bloomfield33" type="bibl">Bloomfield
            1933</ref>).<note>While our examples do not show the use of the exocentric/endocentric
            typology, if so desired, the basic components of this could be encoded in the synchronic
            portion of an entry using the attribute <att>subtype</att>, e.g., <tag>entry
              type="compound" subtype="endocentric"</tag>.</note> There are numerous different
          typological interpretations according to which the concepts of endocentric and exocentric
          compounds are defined in the literature. Many of these differences are attributable to
          problems with the classification criteria, the types of compounds examined, and the
          languages analyzed (<ref target="#scalise05" type="bibl">Scalise and Guevara 2005</ref>;
            <ref target="#benczes06a" type="bibl">Benczes 2006a</ref>).</p>
        <p>Generally, endocentric compound constructions have a <soCalled>head</soCalled> element
          which is the hypernym while the full compound represents a subclassification or hyponym of
          that head (<ref target="#benczes06a" type="bibl">Benczes 2006a</ref>, <ref
            target="#benczes06b" type="bibl">2006b</ref>). An example of this is the bird called a
          scrub jay, the head of which is <q>jay</q>; the compound <q>scrub jay</q> is a type of
          jay. Exocentric compounds are considered <soCalled>headless</soCalled>, and while there is
          no single standard ontological relationship between the compound and/or its components,
          they can contain any variety of relations other than hyponymy.<note>Studies using a
            cognitive linguistic framework have additionally shown that metaphor and metonymy are
            very often active in both exocentric and endocentric compounds across languages and
            regardless of the grammatical subcomponents (<ref target="#langacker87" type="bibl"
              >Langacker 1987</ref>, <ref target="#langacker91" type="bibl">1991</ref>, <ref
              target="#langacker00" type="bibl">2000</ref>; <ref target="#benczes05a" type="bibl"
              >Benczes 2005a</ref>, <ref target="#benczes05b" type="bibl">2005b</ref>; <ref
              target="#benczes06a" type="bibl">Benczes 2006a</ref>, <ref target="#benczes06b"
              type="bibl">2006b</ref>).</note> An example of this from Benczes (<ref
            target="#benczes06b" type="bibl">2006b</ref>) is the English compound <q>hay fever</q>,
          which has a cause–effect relation as hay causes the effect of fever.</p>
        <p>While it would be impossible to give a full account of all of the various typologies
          proposed in the extensive literature, our markup framework for compounding is capable of
          handling the key pieces of information for a wide array of theoretical approaches for
          explicit and implicit encoding of the relevant information within a single entry.</p>
        <p>Basic pieces of information for modeling compounds and compounding include:</p>
        <list rend="bulleted">
          <item>the delimitation between the components</item>
          <item>the grammatical profiles of the components</item>
          <item>the meanings (senses) of the components</item>
          <item>the semantic domain of the components.</item>
        </list>
        <div xml:id="compoundsSynchronic">
          <head>Encoding Compounds: Synchronic Portion</head>
          <p>Modeling compounding in TEI dictionaries can (and ideally should) be done in both the
            synchronic and diachronic portions of an entry. On the synchronic level, the attribute
            value <code>@type="compound"</code> should always be placed in the <gi>entry</gi>
            element in order to specify that the contents of form (<gi>orth</gi> and/or
              <gi>pron</gi>) can be further parsed.</p>
          <figure xml:id="example13">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <entry xml:id="merle-noir" type="compound" xml:lang="fr">
                <form type="lemma">
                  <orth>merle noir</orth>
                  <gramGrp>
                    <pos>nom</pos>
                    <gen>masc</gen>
                  </gramGrp>
                </form> … </entry>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Compounding (synchronic encoding): French <mentioned>merle
                noir</mentioned></head>
          </figure>
          <p>From a processing point of view, this is of particular use when the compound form
            includes whitespace. Optionally, the editor may choose the more thorough method of
            encoding the individual component strings of a compound form with <gi>seg</gi>. Where
            corresponding entries exist within a project for each of these portions of the compound,
            an editor may choose to connect them with the components encased within <gi>seg</gi>
            using <att>corresp</att> with the value being the unique identifier for the given
            entry.</p>
          <p>The following example shows the encoding of the number thirteen in Mixtepec-Mixtec,
            which is a case of an exocentric compound, as there is no <soCalled>head</soCalled>. As
            is the case with the lexical composition of numbers in many languages, this compound
            form is the sum of its component parts semantically and phonologically:
              <mentioned>utsi</mentioned>
            <q>ten</q> + <mentioned>uni</mentioned>
            <q>three</q>.</p>
          <figure xml:id="example14">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <entry xml:id="num-13" type="compound" subtype="exocentric" xml:lang="mix">
                <form type="lemma">
                  <orth>
                    <seg corresp="#num-10">utsi</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#num-3">uni</seg>
                  </orth>
                  <gramGrp>
                    <pos>cardinalNumber</pos>
                  </gramGrp>
                </form>
                <!-- sense, etym, translation,etc… -->
              </entry>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Exocentric compounding (synchronic encoding): Mixtepec-Mixtec
                <mentioned>utsi uni</mentioned></head>
          </figure>
          <p>Where there is a hyphen in a compound, this can be differentiated from the content
            portion of the string by using the TEI character element <gi>pc</gi>. The French example
            below is a type of bird whose name is usually spelled with a hyphen but is also
            occasionally written as a continuous word without whitespace or a hyphen:</p>
          <figure xml:id="example15">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <entry xml:id="rouge-gorge" type="compound" xml:lang="fr">
                <form type="lemma">
                  <orth>
                    <seg>rouge</seg><pc>-</pc><seg>gorge</seg>
                  </orth>
                  <form type="variant">
                    <orth>
                      <seg>rouge</seg><pc> </pc><seg>gorge</seg>
                    </orth>
                  </form>
                  <gramGrp>
                    <pos>nom</pos>
                    <gen>masc</gen>
                  </gramGrp>
                </form> … </entry>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Compounding (synchronic encoding): French
                <mentioned>rouge-gorge</mentioned>, <mentioned>rouge gorge</mentioned></head>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="compoundsDiachronic">
          <head>Encoding Compounds: Diachronic Portion</head>
          <p>Below is the diachronic portion of the entry of the Mixtepec-Mixtec number
              <q>thirteen</q> discussed above.</p>
          <figure xml:id="example16">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <entry xml:id="num-13" type="compound" xml:lang="mix">
                <!-- form, gramGrp, etc. -->
                <sense corresp="http://dbpedia.org/resource/10_(number)">
                  <usg type="dom" corresp="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Cardinal_numbers"
                    >CardinalNumbers</usg>
                </sense>
                <etym type="compounding">
                  <cit type="etymon">
                    <oRef corresp="#num-10">utsi</oRef>
                    <gramGrp>
                      <pos>cardinalNumber</pos>
                    </gramGrp>
                    <gloss>ten</gloss>
                  </cit>
                  <cit type="etymon">
                    <oRef corresp="#num-3">uni</oRef>
                    <gramGrp>
                      <pos>cardinalNumber</pos>
                    </gramGrp>
                    <gloss>three</gloss>
                  </cit>
                </etym> … </entry>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Compounding: Mixtec-Mixtec <mentioned>utsi uni</mentioned></head>
          </figure>
          <p>The components of the compound which were encased in the <gi>seg</gi> element within
            the synchronic forms correspond to the etymons on the diachronic level; as in any other
            etymological process in our encoding system, each subunit of the compound and its given
            lexical information is represented as a separate <tag>cit type="etymon"</tag>. Each of
            these citation-etymon crystals is embedded within the compound-typed <gi>etym</gi>.
            Since compounds do not represent new senses of a <emph>single</emph> existing entry
            form, the etymology element is placed as a direct child of <gi>entry</gi>. As we have
            seen before, the <att>corresp</att> attribute in the <gi>oRef</gi> and/or <gi>pRef</gi>
            points to the URI for the entry of each component of the compound; in this example these
            entries are within the same document. The comprehensive model is depicted in <ptr
              target="#figure5" type="crossref"/> below.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure5">
            <graphic url="images/image5.png" height="798px" width="1324px"/>
            <head type="legend">TEI modeling diagram: compounding (diachronic portion)</head>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="cooccurrence">
          <head>Co-occurrence of Compounding and Other Etymological Processes</head>
          <div xml:id="compundMetaphor">
            <head>Compounding and Metaphor</head>
            <p>The German item <mentioned>Handschuh</mentioned>
              <q>glove</q> is an example of a compound in which metaphor is clearly present;
                <mentioned>Schuh</mentioned>
              <q>shoe</q>, which is an article of clothing specific to the feet (e.g., domain =
              feet), is used as an article of clothing for the hands (e.g., domain = hand). In the
              encoding of this item in the entry below, the structure is a combination of everything
              we have previously seen in examples of compounding- and metaphor-typed etymologies,
              but with the difference that since <tag>etym type="metaphor"</tag> is a subpart in the
              larger word-formation process of compounding, it is embedded within <tag>etym
                type="compound"</tag>. Since compounding is the top-level component of the
              etymology, <gi>etym</gi> is placed as a direct child node of <gi>entry</gi>, following
              the guidelines for that element.</p>
            <p>Also noteworthy is that this example is an <soCalled>endocentric</soCalled> compound
              as the head is <mentioned>schuh</mentioned>
              <q>shoe</q>.<note>While we do not show an example here, if the editor desires to label
                the head of the compound it could be done using the attribute <att>ana</att>, the
                value of which can correspond to a feature structure that is defined and declared
                within the project. Where tagging within the synchronic portion of the entry,
                  <att>ana</att> should be included in the <gi>seg</gi> of the head component. Where
                tagging within the diachronic portion, <att>ana</att> should be included on the
                  <tag>cit type="etymon"</tag> of the head component of the compound. The ISOcat has
                an entry for the category <soCalled>head</soCalled> whose persistent identifier is
                  <ptr target="http://www.isocat.org/datcat/DC-2306"/>.</note></p>
            <figure xml:id="example17">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <entry xml:lang="de" xml:id="handschuh" type="compound" subtype="endocentric">
                  <form type="lemma">
                    <orth><seg>Hand</seg><seg>schuh</seg></orth>
                    <pron notation="ipa"><seg>ˈhant</seg><seg>ʃuː</seg></pron>
                    <gramGrp>
                      <pos>subst.</pos>
                      <gen>mask.</gen>
                    </gramGrp>
                  </form>
                  <sense corresp="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Handschuh"> ... </sense>
                  <etym type="compounding">
                    <cit type="etymon">
                      <oRef xml:lang="de">Hand</oRef>
                      <pRef xml:lang="de" notation="ipa">ˈhant</pRef>
                      <gloss>hand</gloss>
                    </cit>
                    <etym type="metaphor">
                      <cit type="etymon">
                        <oRef xml:lang="de">Schuh</oRef>
                        <pRef xml:lang="de" notation="ipa">ʃuː</pRef>
                        <gloss>shoe</gloss>
                      </cit>
                    </etym>
                  </etym>
                </entry>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">Compounding and metaphor:<note>Note that the structure for
                  modeling <mentioned>compounding + metaphor</mentioned> applies in the exact same
                  manner to <mentioned>compounding + metonymy</mentioned>, which is not shown in
                  these examples.</note> German <mentioned>Handschuh</mentioned></head>
            </figure>
            <p>The classification of a lexical item as a compound hinges on the semantic
              transparency of its components to the speakers of a language. An item corresponding to
              a single conceptual entity that was derived through compounding in a source can be
              borrowed by another language and the fact that it was a compound is not relevant to
              the meaning in the target lexicon. In such cases it is up to the encoder whether or
              not to include the etymological details that occurred in the source language. Below is
              the full encoding of the earlier example of <mentioned>pamplemousse</mentioned> from
              Salmon-Alt (<ref type="bibl" target="#salmon-alt06">2006</ref>).</p>
            <figure xml:id="example18">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <entry xml:id="LE1" xml:lang="fr">
                  <form type="lemma">
                    <orth>pamplemousse</orth>
                    <gramGrp>
                      <pos>commonNoun</pos>
                    </gramGrp>
                  </form>
                  <sense> ... </sense>
                  <etym type="borrowing">
                    <lbl>source</lbl>
                    <lang>Dutch</lang>
                    <cit type="etymon" xml:id="L2">
                      <oRef xml:lang="nl">pompelmoes</oRef>
                      <gloss xml:lang="lat">Citrus maxima</gloss>
                      <gramGrp>
                        <pos>commonNoun</pos>
                        <gen>feminine</gen>
                      </gramGrp>
                      <note>probablement d'origine tamoule, De Vries, Nedrl</note>
                      <ref target="TLF">TLF</ref>
                    </cit>
                    <etym type="compounding">
                      <cit type="etymon">
                        <oRef xml:lang="nl">pompel</oRef>
                        <gramGrp>
                          <pos>adjective</pos>
                        </gramGrp>
                        <gloss>gros, enflé</gloss>
                      </cit>
                      <cit type="etymon">
                        <oRef xml:lang="nl">limoes</oRef>
                        <gramGrp>
                          <pos>commonNoun</pos>
                        </gramGrp>
                        <gloss>citron</gloss>
                      </cit>
                      <ref target="#Boulan-König">Boulan, König...</ref>
                    </etym>
                  </etym>
                </entry>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">Borrowing and compounding: <mentioned>pamplemousse</mentioned>
                  (<ref target="#salmon-alt06" type="bibl">Salmon-Alt 2006</ref>)</head>
            </figure>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="lexicalization">
            <head>Lexicalization</head>
            <p>Compounds, like morphologically-derived coalesced forms and idiomatic forms or other
              types of phrases, may or may not become integrated into the lexicon of a language.
              When they do, the process may occur over an extended period of time, during which the
              original meaning of part or all of the components may become oblique to
                speakers<note>An example of this in English is <q>horseradish</q>, which speakers
                can parse into the components of <q>horse</q> and <q>radish</q>; however, the
                antiquated figurative sense of horsewhich meant <q>large, strong, or coarse</q> and
                which gave rise to the compound is no longer used in modern English (<title
                  level="m">OED Online</title>, June 2017, s.v. <q>horse, n.</q> [Compounds, section
                2, sense c], Oxford University Press, accessed June 19, 2017, <ptr
                  target="http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/88583?rskey=ODVZef&amp;result=1"/>).</note>
              to the degree that the item is not recognized as the sum of its parts; this phenomenon
              is called lexicalization (<ref target="#jackendoff09" type="bibl">Jackendoff
                2009</ref>). While lexicalization is indeed a lexico-cognitive process with
              etymological implications, it is not a process that can be summarized and represented
              in a dictionary, as there are often different degrees of lexicalization between
              different speakers.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="grammaticalization">
        <head>Grammaticalization</head>
        <p>A major phenomenon of lexical change is the process of grammaticalization in which, over
          time, a lexical item undergoes changes to its semantic profile, morphosyntactic form, and
          possibly phonological form via systematic patterns of usage in certain linguistic contexts
          to serve more grammatical functions within the language.</p>
        <p>Because of the complexity of the process and the continuing debate as to the details of
          precisely what it entails, any single definition of grammaticalization inevitably raises
          theoretical debate, and may potentially be modified down the line within the field.
          Antoine Meillet (<ref target="#meillet12" type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref3">1912</ref>), who
          coined the term, described it as follows:</p>
        <cit>
          <quote source="#quoteref3">The development of grammatical forms by progressive
            deterioration of previously autonomous words is made possible by <gap/> a weakening of
            the pronunciation, of the concrete sense of the words, and of the expressive value of
            words and groupings of words. The ancillary word can end up as an element lacking
            independent meaning as such, linked to a principal word to mark its grammatical
            role.</quote>
        </cit>
        <p>Studies of grammaticalization have shown that there are certain tendencies for forms to
          undergo the same types of functional shifts to their semantic, syntactic, morphological,
          and phonological properties, which occur in relatively similar orders<note>Examples of
            some of the most common grammaticalization patterns (<soCalled>clines</soCalled>)
            include the following (from <ref target="#croft03" type="bibl">Croft 2003</ref>): noun
            &gt; adposition; adposition &gt; case affix; verb &gt; classifier; demonstrative or
            article &gt; gender/noun class marker; main verb &gt; tense, aspect, mood marker.</note>
            (<ref target="#svorou94" type="bibl">Svorou 1994</ref>; <ref target="#croft03"
            type="bibl">Croft 2003</ref>; <ref target="#hopper03" type="bibl">Hopper and Traugott
            2003</ref>). These evolutionary pathways are commonly referred to as
            <soCalled>clines</soCalled> (ibid.). On the semantic level, the most generic
          characterization of the tendency is for the profile to undergo changes from concrete to
          abstract (ibid.). Moreover, there is significant evidence that the semantic profiles of a
          lexical source may motivate and/or constrain the potential structural characteristics and
          grammatical roles that emerge from a lexical source (<ref target="#svorou94" type="bibl"
            >Svorou 1994</ref>; <ref target="#hopper03" type="bibl">Hopper and Traugott
          2003</ref>).</p>
        <p>Parallel to the semantic shifts are the clines that occur on the syntactic and
          morphological levels, of which there are a number of different specific possibilities, but
          which can be generalized as follows: <eg>less grammatical → more grammatical</eg></p>
        <p>Hopper and Traugott (<ref target="#hopper03" type="bibl">2003</ref>) discuss a
          correlation between the degree of grammaticalization (grammatical status) and the loss of
          certain morphological and syntactic properties that are commonly observed in prototypical
          members of major grammatical categories (decategorization).</p>
        <p><eg>majority category → (intermediate category) → minor category</eg>It should be noted
          that because of polysemy, a single form may simultaneously have several grammatical
          functions in which multiple <soCalled>stages</soCalled> in different clines can coexist
          synchronically (<ref type="bibl" target="#svorou94">Svorou 1994</ref>; <ref
            target="#hopper03" type="bibl">Hopper and Traugott 2003</ref>). According to Svorou
            (<ref target="#svorou94" type="bibl">1994</ref>), the study of grammaticalization
          requires a <soCalled>panchronic</soCalled> view of language change, viewing the component
          evolutionary processes as continuous, rather than applying the artificially discrete
          concepts of synchronic and diachronic.<note>Svorou’s panchronic view of grammaticalization
            is supported by Hopper and Traugott (<ref target="#svorou94" type="bibl">2003</ref>),
            who state that clines are both diachronic (schema of evolution) and synchronic
            (all/multiple forms of evolutionary stages may co-exist).</note></p>
        <p>The negotiation of meaning by speakers, using metaphor and metonymy to extend the
          contexts in which a lexical item is used, enables such changes as pragmatic/semantic
          bleaching or enrichment on the cognitive, semantic, and pragmatic levels. On the syntactic
          and morphological levels, these higher-level changes are manifested in
            reanalysis<note>According to Hopper and Traugott (<ref target="#hopper03" type="bibl"
              >2003</ref>), reanalysis modifies underlying representations (semantic, syntactic,
            morphophonological) and brings out rules changes. Langacker (<ref target="#langacker77"
              type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref4">1977, 58</ref>) has provided the basis for the
            definition of reanalysis, describing it as <quote source="#quoteref4">change in the
              structure of an expression or class of expressions that does not involve any immediate
              or intrinsic modification of its surface manifestation.</quote> Harris and Campbell
              (<ref target="#harris95" type="bibl">1995</ref>) and Hopper and Traugott (<ref
              target="#hopper03" type="bibl">2003</ref>) have added to the description of the
            phenomenon, pointing out that reanalysis can only be manifested through analogy.</note>
          and analogy.<note>Analogy involves paradigmatic organization, changes in surface
            collocations, and changes in patterns of usage, which in turn make unobservable changes
            from reanalysis observable (<ref target="#hopper03" type="bibl">Hopper and Traugott
              2003</ref>).</note></p>
        <p>Grammaticalization is thus very complex and involves multiple possible subprocesses which
          may or may not co-occur on different levels. As a consequence, encoding such etymologies
          may require the use of any number of the strategies discussed above.</p>
        <div xml:id="basicEncoding">
          <head>Overview of Basic Encoding Recommendations</head>
          <p>Since grammaticalization potentially involves multiple etymological processes on any
            level of language at different stages in the diachrony of an item, the formatting
            recommendations depend on the specifics of a given scenario and involve the integration
            of concepts and data structures from multiple processes discussed elsewhere in this
            paper. It is up to the editor to determine what aspects and features of the etymology
            they want to emphasize within an encoding of grammaticalization (e.g., processes on
            different levels, bibliographic attestations, discourse, semantics, morphosyntax, or
            phonology); its nuances and complexities make it impossible to write an entirely
            comprehensive set of encoding recommendations. However, the constants which can always
            be included in a grammaticalization etymology are as follows:</p>
          <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>given that grammaticalization inherently entails a shift in the sense of an
              etymon, <tag>etym type="grammaticalization"</tag> should be embedded within
                <gi>sense</gi>;</item>
            <item>all forms of the etymon that are hypothesized or attested as having occurred
              within the span of the time corresponding to the stages of the grammaticalization
              process should be encoded within <tag>cit type="etymon"</tag> (as we have previously
              seen).</item>
          </list>
          <p>Conceptual information necessary in the encoding of grammaticalization includes: <list
              rend="bulleted">
              <item>the synchronic form(s);<note>Given the prominent role of phonological change in
                  grammaticalization (e.g., coalescence, phonological reduction, loss), inclusion of
                    <gi>pron</gi> is recommended though it is not always possible to present such
                  forms with full certainty (in which case there is always the TEI attribute
                    <att>cert</att>).</note></item>
              <item>the grammatical information.</item>
            </list> If the grammaticalized item is one of multiple senses of a polysemous
              form:<note>While not entirely essential, including any known contextual, pragmatic, or
              collocational information greatly enhances the usefulness of the synchronic data
              modeling and enhances the precision of the etymological account.</note>
            <list rend="bulleted">
              <item>the grammatical, semantic, and/or pragmatic context in which the given sense
                occurs;</item>
              <item>the collocates with which it occurs (if any);</item>
              <item>the source form(s);</item>
              <item>whether the source form(s) is/are attested or hypothesized.</item>
            </list> If attested: <list rend="bulleted">
              <item>bibliographic source of attestation;</item>
              <item>date or date range for each attested form.</item>
            </list> If hypothesized: <list rend="bulleted">
              <item>semantic profile of source (e.g., semantic domain or metalinguistic
                concept);</item>
              <item>grammatical profile of source.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>The placement of the <tag>etym type="grammaticalization"</tag> is dependent on the
            specific diachrony of the etymon. For example, if the item was inherited, it can be
            placed within <tag>etym type="inheritance"</tag>.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="traugott">
          <head>Traugott (1995): Grammaticalization of the English Discourse Marker
            <q>besides</q></head>
          <p>In the following example from Traugott (<ref target="#traugott95" type="bibl"
              >1995</ref>), we show in our encoding a sample of several stages of the
            grammaticalization process of the English discourse particle <q>besides</q>. The author
            makes the case that the following cline (e.g., the process of grammaticalization for a
            given lexical item) should be added to the scope of grammaticalization
              phenomena:<note>In Traugott (<ref target="#traugott95" type="bibl">1995</ref>),
              discourse markers are a subtype of discourse particle.</note>
            <eg>Adverbial of Extension &gt; Sentence Adverbial &gt; Discourse Particle</eg></p>
          <p>The major stages of this process are presented in a semichronological order and in
            terms of the following stages:</p>
          <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>Stage 0: Full lexical noun;</item>
            <item>Stage I: Adverbial of extension;</item>
            <item>Stage II: Sentence adverbial;</item>
            <item>Stage III: Discourse marker/particle.</item>
          </list>
          <p>The example below is an encoded representation of the arguments put forth in the
            source. We have attempted to represent the linguistic information, terminology, and
            etymological processes as accurately as possible without adding or subtracting from the
            original based on our own interpretation or external data.</p>
          <div xml:id="stage0">
            <head>Stage 0: Full lexical noun</head>
            <figure xml:id="example19">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <entry>
                  <!-- form, gramGrp, etc. -->
                  <sense> ... <etym type="grammaticalization">
                      <cit type="etymon" xml:id="at-850-950" next="#at-1225-a">
                        <date notBefore="0850" notAfter="0950"/>
                        <oRef xml:lang="ang">
                          <seg xml:id="e1s1">sid</seg>
                          <seg xml:id="e1s2">an</seg>
                        </oRef>
                        <gloss>side</gloss>

                        <gramGrp>
                          <!-- inherently applies to the top level structure -->
                          <pos>locativeNoun</pos>
                        </gramGrp>

                        <cit type="component" corresp="#e1s1">
                          <gramGrp>
                            <pos>noun</pos>
                          </gramGrp>
                        </cit>

                        <cit type="component" corresp="#e1s2">
                          <gramGrp>
                            <case>dative</case>
                          </gramGrp>
                        </cit>
                        <cit type="attestation" xml:lang="ang">
                          <quote>&amp; þonne licge on ða swiðran <oRef>sidan</oRef> gode
                            hwile</quote>
                          <cit type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                            <quote>and then lie on the right side for a good while</quote>
                          </cit>
                        </cit>
                        <bibl>(850-950 Lacnunga Magicand&amp;Med., p. 120 [HC])</bibl>
                      </cit>
                      <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 20-27 --> ... </etym> ...
                  </sense>
                </entry>
              </egXML>
              <!-- [RvdB] I've moved the footnote from the example to the head -->
              <head type="legend">Grammaticalization of Old English
                  <mentioned>sidan</mentioned><note>Additional information related to this etymon
                  could be added here, for instance that sid is a stem and the head of the inflected
                  noun form. This would be a typical application of <att>ana</att> on the
                    <gi>cit</gi> element.</note></head>
            </figure>
            <p>This first stage <mentioned>sidan</mentioned> is from Old English (ISO 639–3:
                <val>ang</val>); as usual the <gi>cit</gi> element is typed as
                <code>@type="etymon"</code>. Within this first etymon, the noun is inflected in the
              dative case. This is represented in the encoding, with the nominal root <q>sid-</q>
              and the dative inflection <q>-an</q> each being given unique <gi>seg</gi> tags with
              their own <att>xml:id</att>s. These components are annotated grammatically within the
                <gi>gramGrp</gi> element blocks embedded in <tag>cit type="component"</tag>, each of
              which points to the given segment with the <att>corresp</att> attribute.</p>
            <p>The source of this is dated sometime between 850 and 950. As we have discussed
              previously, a range of dates can be expressed using the attributes
                <att>notBefore</att> and <att>notAfter</att> in the <gi>date</gi> element. While the
              bibliographic source (the last direct child element of <tag>cit type="etymon"</tag>)
              does contain the date itself, using the <gi>date</gi> element helps keep the
              consistency of the data structure, which will likely have benefits to any automatic
              retrieval process.</p>
            <list rend="bulleted">
              <item>a partial example of the context in which the etymon form was observed is given
                in the <gi>quote</gi> element whose parent is an embedded <tag>cit
                  type="attestation"</tag>. Also specified here is the language attribute and tag,
                which as always are expressed in the form <code>@xml:lang="ang"</code>. The form
                itself is encased in an <gi>oRef</gi> with no attributes.</item>
              <item>finally, embedded within the attestation is the translation of the Old English
                source sentence into Modern English: <tag>cit type="translation"
                xml:lang="en"</tag></item>
            </list>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="stage0.5">
            <head>Stage 0.5: Dative nouns with prefix</head>
            <p>These next two attested etymons are both from 1225 (Middle English), and from the
              same bibliographic source, yet they have different grammatical functions; by including
              the range of dates for each with their contrasting grammatical usage, the encoded
              information is able to capture the emerging state of polysemy for the lexical
              item:</p>
            <list rend="bulleted">
              <item>each has the prefix bi-;</item>
              <item>each is dative case.</item>
            </list>
            <figure xml:id="example20">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <entry>
                  <!-- form, gramGrp, etc. -->
                  <sense> ... <etym type="grammaticalization"> ... <!-- <cit type="etymon"> element from example 19 -->
                      <cit type="etymon" xml:id="at-1225-a" prev="#at-850-950" next="#at-1225-b">
                        <date when="1225"/>
                        <oRef xml:lang="enm">
                          <seg xml:id="e2s1">bi</seg>
                          <pc>-</pc>
                          <seg xml:id="e2s2">sid</seg>
                          <seg xml:id="e2s3">en</seg>
                        </oRef>
                        <gloss>at his side</gloss>
                        <gramGrp>
                          <pos>locativeAdverbial</pos>
                        </gramGrp>
                        <cit type="component" corresp="#e2s1">
                          <gramGrp>
                            <pos>adverb</pos>
                          </gramGrp>
                        </cit>
                        <cit type="component" corresp="#e2s2">
                          <gramGrp>
                            <pos>noun</pos>
                          </gramGrp>
                        </cit>
                        <cit type="component" corresp="#e2s3">
                          <gramGrp>
                            <case>dative</case>
                          </gramGrp>
                        </cit>
                        <cit type="attestation" xml:lang="enm">
                          <quote>His pic he heold <oRef>bi-siden</oRef></quote>
                          <cit type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                            <quote>He held his staff at his side</quote>
                          </cit>
                        </cit>
                        <bibl>(1225 Lay. Brut 30784 [MED])</bibl>
                      </cit>
                      <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 21-27 --> ... </etym> ...
                  </sense>
                </entry>
              </egXML>
              <!-- [RvdB] I've moved the footnote from the example to the head -->
              <head type="legend">Grammaticalization of Middle-English
                  <mentioned>bisiden</mentioned> 1225 (a)<note>In this example, the adverbial
                  component of the etymon, the additional feature of prefix, which would be
                  specified as the entry type within a synchronic entry, could be labelled within a
                    <att>ana</att> attribute, e.g., <tag>cit type="component" corresp="#e2s1"
                    ana="#prefix"</tag>.</note></head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="example21">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <entry>
                  <!-- form, gramGrp, etc. -->
                  <sense> ... <etym type="grammaticalization"> ... <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 19-20 -->
                      <cit type="etymon" xml:id="at-1225-b" prev="#at-1225-a" next="#at-c1300">
                        <date when="1225"/>
                        <oRef xml:lang="enm">
                          <seg xml:id="e3s1">bi</seg>
                          <pc>-</pc>
                          <seg xml:id="e3s2">sid</seg>
                          <seg xml:id="e3s3">en</seg>
                        </oRef>
                        <gloss>in addition</gloss>
                        <gramGrp>
                          <pos>conjunctiveAdverbial</pos>
                        </gramGrp>
                        <cit type="component" corresp="#e3s1">
                          <gramGrp>
                            <pos>preposition</pos>
                          </gramGrp>
                        </cit>
                        <cit type="component" corresp="#e3s2">
                          <gramGrp>
                            <pos>nominalAdposition</pos>
                          </gramGrp>
                        </cit>
                        <cit type="component" corresp="#e3s3">
                          <gramGrp>
                            <case>dative</case>
                          </gramGrp>
                        </cit>
                        <cit type="attestation" xml:lang="ang">
                          <quote>Heo letten forð <oRef>bi-siden</oRef> an oþer folc riden, ten
                            þusend kempen</quote>
                          <cit type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                            <quote>They sent another army forth in addition, 10,000 warriors</quote>
                          </cit>
                        </cit>
                        <bibl>(1225 Lay Brut 5498 [MED])</bibl>
                      </cit>
                      <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 22-27 --> ... </etym> ...
                  </sense>
                </entry>
              </egXML>
              <!-- [RvdB] I've moved the footnote from the example to the head -->
              <head type="legend">Grammaticalization of Middle-English
                  <mentioned>bisiden</mentioned> 1225 (b)<note>One etymon from the source has been
                  skipped in this example: <mentioned>beside</mentioned> in the prepositional sense
                  attested ca. 1450.</note></head>
            </figure>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="stage1">
            <head>Stage I: Adverbial of extension/verbal adverbs</head>
            <p>A major feature of interest in adverbials of extension is where they occur at the end
              of a clause; in these cases, the adverbs are often an oblique syntactic argument. This
              is the case in the section of the example below in which the tag
                <soCalled>extensionAdverb</soCalled> is used in the source for adverbials of
                  extension.<note><soCalled>Extension adverbials</soCalled> are also referred to by
                Traugott as <q>verbal adverbials</q>.</note></p>
            <list rend="bulleted">
              <item>prefix <mentioned>be-</mentioned> now fused onto
                <mentioned>side</mentioned>;</item>
              <item>adverb oblique argument, labeled as value of <att>ana</att> in the <gi>oRef</gi>
                in the attestation.</item>
            </list>
            <figure xml:id="example22">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <entry>
                  <!-- form, gramGrp, etc. -->
                  <sense> ... <etym type="grammaticalization"> ... <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 19-21 -->
                      <cit type="etymon" xml:id="at-1514-1518" prev="#at-1450" next="#at-1535-1543">
                        <date notBefore="1514" notAfter="1518"/>
                        <oRef xml:lang="emodeng">beside</oRef>
                        <gramGrp>
                          <pos>extensionAdverb</pos>
                        </gramGrp>
                        <cit type="attestation">
                          <!-- early modern english -->
                          <quote>In whiche albeit thei ment as muche honor to hys grace as wealthe
                            to al the realm <oRef ana="#Oblq">beside</oRef>, yet were they not sure
                            howe hys grace woulde take it,</quote>
                        </cit>
                        <bibl>(1514-18 More, History of Richard III, p. 78)</bibl>
                      </cit>
                      <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 23-27 --> ... </etym> ...
                  </sense>
                </entry>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">Grammaticalization of Early Modern English <q>beside</q>
                1514–1518</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="example23">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <entry>
                  <!-- form, gramGrp, etc. -->
                  <sense> ... <etym type="grammaticalization"> ... <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 19-22 -->
                      <cit type="etymon" xml:id="at-1535-1543" prev="#at-1514-1518" next="#at-1567">
                        <date notBefore="1535" notAfter="1543"/>
                        <oRef xml:lang="emodeng">beside</oRef>
                        <gramGrp>
                          <pos>extentionAdverb</pos>
                        </gramGrp>
                        <cit type="attestation">
                          <quote>The toune of Chester is chiefly one streate of very meane building
                            yn lenght: ther is <oRef>beside</oRef> a smaul streat or 2. about the
                            chirch; that is collegiatid, .... </quote>
                        </cit>
                        <bibl>(1535-43 Leland, Itinerary I p. 74 [HC])</bibl>
                      </cit>
                      <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 24-27 --> ... </etym> ...
                  </sense>
                </entry>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">Grammaticalization of Early Modern English
                  <mentioned>beside</mentioned> 1535–1543</head>
            </figure>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="stage2">
            <head>Stage II: Sentential Adverb</head>
            <p>One of the two contextual conditions in which sentential adverbials
              (sententialAdverb) occur is that they need to immediately follow a complementizer.
              This is represented in the data by the encoding of the relevant item within the
                <gi>seg</gi> element, and the <att>ana</att> attribute is used to label it with the
              needed data category (complementizer).</p>
            <figure xml:id="example24">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <entry>
                  <!-- form, gramGrp, etc. -->
                  <sense> ... <etym type="grammaticalization"> ... <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 19-23 -->
                      <cit type="etymon" xml:id="at-1552-1563" prev="#at-1535-1543" next="#at-1554">
                        <date notBefore="1552" notAfter="1563"/>
                        <oRef xml:lang="emodeng">besides</oRef>
                        <gramGrp>
                          <pos>sententialAdverb</pos>
                        </gramGrp>
                        <cit type="attestation">
                          <quote>…when the end is knowen, all wil turne to a iape ['trick,deceit'],
                            Tolde he not you <seg ana="#Complimentizer">that</seg>
                            <oRef>besides</oRef> she stole your Cocke that tyde?</quote>
                        </cit>
                        <note>The adverbial of extension which signals the extension of a list of
                          referents as per (sense in example “at-#at-1535-1543”) is presumed to be
                          the source of the clause-initial, focused sentence adverbial, which
                          extends the propositional content with additional, non-central
                          material:</note>
                        <bibl>(1552-63 Gammer Gurton, p. 61 [HC])</bibl>
                      </cit>
                      <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 25-27 --> ... </etym> ...
                  </sense>
                </entry>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">Grammaticalization of Early Modern English
                  <mentioned>beside</mentioned> 1552–1563</head>
            </figure>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="stage3">
            <head>Stage III: Discourse Marker/Particle</head>
            <p>In this next stage, <mentioned>besides</mentioned> serves to refocus the attention on
              the purposes of the discourse, and occurs on the left periphery of the sentence
              structure serving a pragmatic function. As in the previous example, the context is
              labeled using <gi>seg</gi> with the attribute <att>ana</att>.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example25">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <entry>
                  <!-- form, gramGrp, etc. -->
                  <sense> ... <etym type="grammaticalization"> ... <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 19-24 -->
                      <cit type="etymon" xml:id="at-1554" prev="#at-1552-1563" next="#stage3-26a">
                        <date when="1554"/>
                        <oRef xml:lang="emodeng">besides</oRef>
                        <gramGrp>
                          <pos>discourseMarker</pos>
                        </gramGrp>
                        <cit type="attestation">
                          <quote>...<seg ana="#LPeriph">And <oRef>besides</oRef></seg>, it is very
                            unlike, that </quote>
                        </cit>
                        <bibl>(bef. 1554 Trial Throckmorton I,66.C1 [HC])</bibl>
                      </cit>
                      <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 26-27 --> ... </etym> ...
                  </sense>
                </entry>
              </egXML>
              <!-- [RvdB] I've moved the footnote from the example to the head -->
              <head type="legend">Grammaticalization of Early Modern English
                  <mentioned>besides</mentioned> 1554<note>Etymon given in the source but not
                  encoded here: <mentioned>besides</mentioned> in the sense of an adverbial of
                  extension attested 1567.</note></head>
            </figure>
            <p>In these examples from 1619 and 1872 the usage of <q>beside</q> extends the discourse
              with afterthoughts:</p>
            <figure xml:id="example26">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <entry>
                  <!-- form, gramGrp, etc. -->
                  <sense> ... <etym type="grammaticalization"> ... <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 19-25 -->
                      <cit type="etymon" xml:id="at-1619" prev="#at-1554" next="#at-1872">
                        <date when="1619"/>
                        <oRef xml:lang="emodeng">beside</oRef>
                        <gramGrp>
                          <pos>discourseMarker</pos>
                        </gramGrp>
                        <cit type="attestation">
                          <quote>..and <oRef>beside</oRef>, my complexion is so blacke,
                            that..</quote>
                        </cit>
                        <bibl>(1619 Deloney, Jack of Newbury, p.70 [HC])</bibl>
                      </cit>
                      <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from example 27 --> ... </etym> ... </sense>
                </entry>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">Grammaticalization of Early Modern English
                  <mentioned>beside</mentioned> 1619</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="example27">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <entry>
                  <!-- form, gramGrp, etc. -->
                  <sense> ... <etym type="grammaticalization"> ... <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 19-26 -->
                      <cit type="etymon" xml:id="at-1872" prev="#at-1619">
                        <date when="1872"/>
                        <oRef xml:lang="en">besides</oRef>
                        <gramGrp>
                          <pos>discourseMarker</pos>
                        </gramGrp>
                        <cit type="attestation">
                          <quote>The whooping cough seems to be a providential arrangement to force
                            you to come, as the expense will be little greater than going anywhere
                            else; <oRef>besides</oRef> if you put a trusty female at Ravenscroft…
                          </quote>
                        </cit>
                        <bibl>(1872 Amberley Ltrs, p. 513 [CLME])</bibl>
                      </cit> ... </etym> ... </sense>
                </entry>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">Grammaticalization of Modern English <q>besides</q> 1872</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Finally the source of the etymological data is cited as a child element of
                <gi>etym</gi>:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <entry>
                <!-- form, gramGrp, etc. -->
                <sense> ... <etym type="grammaticalization">
                    <!-- <cit type="etymon"> elements from examples 19-27 --> ... <bibl>(Traugott,
                      1995)</bibl>
                  </etym>
                </sense>
              </entry>
            </egXML>
            <p>This example is obviously an extremely complex yet informative representation of the
              history of the lexical item in question (English: <q>besides</q>).</p>
            <p>Despite its importance within the field of linguistics, grammaticalization is rarely
              if ever identified as such in any kind of etymological or print dictionary. Moreover,
              to our knowledge, there have not been any attempts to encode such processes within
              XML, or any other digital markup standards. Grammaticalization is thus a major
              untapped resource of highly advanced etymological data. Establishing a practice in
              which this kind of markup is done may help linguists and lexicographers begin to more
              regularly make maximum use (and reuse) of the research being done.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="problems">
        <head>Problematic and Unresolved Issues</head>
        <p>For the issues regarded as the most fundamentally important to creating a dynamic and
          sustainable model for both etymology and general lexicographic markup in TEI, we have
          submitted formal requests for changes to the TEI <ptr type="software" xml:id="R8"
            target="#github"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R8">GitHub</rs>, and will continue to
          submit change requests as needed. While this work represents a large step in the right
          direction for those looking for means of representing etymological information, there are
          still a number of unresolved issues that will need to be addressed. These remaining issues
          pertain to: <list rend="inline simple">
            <item>(i) expanding the types of etymological information and refining the
              representation of the processes and features which are covered; and</item>
            <item>(ii) the need for continued progress in a number of issues within the body of
              international standards on which lexical markup relies</item>
          </list>.</p>
        <p>Some examples of issues from (i) are as follows:</p>
        <list rend="bulleted">
          <item>encoding onomasiological etymological information, which groups and represents the
            converging and diverging histories of related forms across multiple related
            languages;</item>
          <item>relatedly, the markup of existing non-semasiological etymological dictionaries,
            which can be extremely long and which can be organized in extremely complex ways;</item>
          <item>sense shifts not involving metaphor or metonymy, but subtle, often usage- and
            context-based patterns such as pejoration–amelioration or narrowing–widening;</item>
          <item>changes to a lexical item which stem from corresponding changes and functional
            linguistic pressures occurring within other parts of the lexicon, such as semantic
            bleaching.</item>
        </list>
        <p>An example of issues from (ii) is:</p>
        <list rend="bulleted">
          <item>the need for expansion of the inventory of categories in <ref
              target="http://www.isocat.org/">ISOcat</ref><note>ISOcat is currently stalled, with
              two initiatives from ISO TC 37 and CLARIN taking up the legacy. We shall be working on
              making the two initiatives converge again.</note> to include well-established
            etymological processes, such as metaphor and metonymy, as well as other features not
            specific to etymology.</item>
        </list>
        <p>Several significant issues regarding language identification are as follows:</p>
        <list rend="bulleted">
          <item>the need for continued expansion of the inventory of the IANA registry, probably in
            conjunction with the maintenance of future versions of ISO 639;</item>
          <item>the need for more granularity in the means by which <att>xml:lang</att> is specified
            without using the private tag (<code>-x-</code>) (see BCP 47 [<ref target="#ietf09a"
              type="bibl">IETF 2009a</ref>]);<note>Currently, labeling language varieties while
              remaining interoperable is limited to the specification of the following information:
              (language-country-region).</note></item>
          <item>the lack of existing codes within any body of standards for historical places such
            as Gaul and Carthage;</item>
          <item>the lack of a way to label when the language data is from an intermediate,
            transitional period for which there are neither IANA entries nor even commonly used
            terms within the body of literature.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="conclusion">
        <head>Conclusion</head>
        <p>In this paper, we have proposed a number of markup scenarios for encoding different types
          of etymological information within TEI dictionaries, drawing both from traditional
          lexicographic practice and from analytical approaches from functional and cognitive
          linguistics. Our examples have shown a number of cases in which, in order to represent the
          lexical data as accurately as possible, it has been necessary to alter the content models
          of certain elements and attributes in ways we think should actually be considered
          necessary evolutions for the TEI Guidelines in the future. Relevant to both etymological
          and synchronic lexical markup, we have also touched upon how encoders can make use of
          linked open data URIs as a means of linking the sense and semantic domain(s) of an item to
          multilingual knowledge bases. Future work that remains to be undertaken is the encoding of
          onomasiological lexical data such as that found in dialectal and traditional etymological
          dictionaries.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="amsler88"><author>Amsler, Robert A.</author>, and <author>Frank Wm.
              Tompa</author>. <date>1988</date>. <title level="a">An SGML-Based Standard for English
              Monolingual Dictionaries</title>. In <title level="m">Proceedings of the 4th Annual
              Conference of the UW Centre for the New Oxford English Dictionary</title>, <biblScope
              unit="page">61–80</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="http://projects.oucs.ox.ac.uk/teiweb/Vault/AI/aiw04.ps"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="banski09"><author>Bański, Piotr</author>, and <author>Beata
              Wójtowicz</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="u">FreeDict: An Open Source
              Repository of TEI-Encoded Bilingual Dictionaries</title>. <ptr
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/MembersMeetings/2009/files/Banski+Wojtowicz-TEIMM-presentation.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bazin01"><author>Bazin-Tacchella, Sylvie</author>. <date>2001</date>. <title
              level="a">Rupture et continuité du discours médical à travers les écrits sur la peste
              de 1348.</title> In <title level="m">Air, miasme et contagion: les épidémies de
              l’Antiquité au Moyen Âge</title>, edited by <editor>S. Bazin-Tacchella</editor>,
              <editor>D. Quéruel</editor>, and <editor>E. Samama</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >105–56</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Langres</pubPlace>: <publisher>Guéniot</publisher>.
            Author version available at <ptr target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00526759/"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="benczes05a"><author>Benczes, Réka</author>. <date>2005a</date>. <title
              level="a">Metaphor- and Metonymy-based Compounds in English: A Cognitive Linguistic
              Approach.</title>
            <title level="j">Acta Linguistica Hungarica</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">2–3</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">173–98</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="benczes05b"><author>Benczes, Réka</author>. <date>2005b</date>. <title
              level="a">Creative Noun–Noun Compounds.</title>
            <title level="j">Annual Review of Cognitive Linguistics</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">250–68</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="benczes06a"><author>Benczes, Réka</author>. <date>2006a</date>. <title
              level="m">Creative Compounding in English: The Semantics of Metaphorical and
              Metonymical Noun-Noun Combinations</title>. <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>John Benjamins</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="benczes06b"><author>Benczes, Réka</author>. <date>2006b</date>. <title
              level="a">Analysing Metonymical Noun–Noun Compounds: The Case of Freedom
              Fries.</title> In <title level="m">The Metaphors of Sixty: Papers Presented on the
              Occasion of the 60th Birthday of Zoltán Kövecses</title>, edited by <editor>Réka
              Benczes</editor> and <editor>Szilvia Csábi</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >46–54</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Budapest</pubPlace>: <publisher>Eötvös Loránd
              University</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="benczes09"><author>Benczes, Réka</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title
              level="a">What motivates the production and use of metaphorical and metonymical
              compounds?</title> In <title level="m">Cognitive Approaches to English: Fundamental,
              Methodological, Interdisciplinary and Applied Aspects</title>, edited by <editor>Mario
              Brdar</editor>, <editor>Marija Omazić</editor>, and <editor>Višnja Pavičić
              Takač</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">49–67</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Newcastle-upon-Tyne</pubPlace>: <publisher>Cambridge
            Scholars</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bisetto05"><author>Bisetto, Antonietta</author>, and <author>Sergio
              Scalise</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title level="a">The Classification of
              Compounds</title>. <title level="j">Lingue e Linguaggio</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">319–32</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="idno"
            >10.1418/20728</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bloomfield33"><author>Bloomfield, Leonard</author>. <date>1933</date>.
              <title level="m">Language</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Henry
              Holt</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="botne06"><author>Botne, Robert</author>. <date>2006</date>. <title level="a"
              >Motion, Time, and Tense: On the Grammaticization of <mentioned>Come</mentioned> and
                <mentioned>Go</mentioned> to Future Markers in Bantu</title>. <title level="j"
              >Studies in African Linguistics</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">127–88</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="brinton05"><author>Brinton, Laurel J.</author>, and <author>Elizabeth Closs
              Traugott</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title level="m">Lexicalization and Language
              Change</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Cambridge University
              Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="budin12"><author>Budin, Gerhard</author>, <author>Stefan Majewski</author>,
            and <author>Karlheinz Mörth</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">Creating
              Lexical Resources in TEI P5: A Schema for Multi-purpose Digital Dictionaries</title>.
              <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>. <ptr target="http://jtei.revues.org/522"/>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.4000/jtei.522</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="crist05"><author>Crist, Sean</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title level="u"
              >Toward a Formal Markup Standard for Etymological Data</title>. Paper presented at the
            LSA Annual Meeting. Accessed April 16, 2017. <ptr
              target="http://www.sean-crist.com/professional/publications/crist_etym_markup.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="croft03"><author>Croft, William</author>. <date>2003</date>. <title
              level="m">Typology and Universals</title>, <edition>2nd ed.</edition>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Cambridge University
            Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="erjavec99"><author>Erjavec, Tomaž</author>, <author>Dan Tufiş</author>, and
              <author>Tamás Váradi</author>. <date>1999</date>. <title level="a">Developing
              TEI-Conformant Lexical Databases for CEE Languages</title>. In [<title level="m"
              >Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Computational Lexicography],
              COMPLEX’99</title>, edited by <editor>Ferenc Kiefer</editor>, <editor>Gábir
              Kiss</editor>, and <editor>Júlia Pajzs</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >205–209</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Budapest</pubPlace>: <publisher>Hungarian Academy of
              Sciences</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.racai.ro/media/Erjavec-TV-COMPLEX1999.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fauconnier07"><author>Fauconnier, Gilles</author>. <date>2007</date>. <title
              level="a">Mental Spaces</title>. In <title level="m">The Oxford Handbook of Cognitive
              Linguistics</title>, edited by <editor>Dirk Geeraerts</editor> and <editor>Hubert
              Cuyckens</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">351–76</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fauconnier96"><author>Fauconnier, Gilles</author>, and <author>Mark B.
              Turner</author>. <date>1996</date>. <title level="a">Blending as a Central Process of
              Grammar</title>. In <title level="m">Conceptual Structure, Discourse, and
              Language</title>, edited by <editor>Adele Goldberg</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >113–29</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Center for the Study of
              Language and Information</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fauconnier98a"><author>Fauconnier, Gilles</author>, and <author>Mark B.
              Turner</author>. <date>1998a</date>. <title level="a">Conceptual Integration
              Networks</title>. <title level="j">Cognitive Science</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">133–87</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1207/s15516709cog2202_1</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fauconnier98b"><author>Fauconnier, Gilles</author>, and <author>Mark B.
              Turner</author>. <date>1998b</date>. <title level="a">Principles of Conceptual
              Integration</title>. <title level="m">Discourse and Cognition: Bridging the
              Gap</title>, edited by <editor>Jean-Pierre Koenig</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >269–83</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Center for the Study of
              Language and Information</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fauconnier00"><author>Fauconnier, Gilles</author>, and <author>Mark B.
              Turner</author>. <date>2000</date>. <title level="a">Compression and Global
              Insight</title>. <title level="j">Cognitive Linguistics</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">3/4</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">283–304</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1515/cogl.2001.017</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fauconnier03"><author>Fauconnier, Gilles</author>, and <author>Mark B.
              Turner</author>. <date>2003</date>. <title level="m">The Way We Think: Conceptual
              Blending and the Mind’s Hidden Complexities</title>. <publisher>Basic
              Books</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fomin06"><author>Fomin, Maxim</author>, and <author>Gregory Toner</author>.
              <date>2006</date>. <title level="a">Digitizing a Dictionary of Medieval Irish: The
              eDIL Project</title>. <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">83–90</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.1093/llc/fqh050</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="geeraerts02"><author>Geeraerts, Dirk</author>. <date>2002</date>. <title
              level="a">The Interaction of Metaphor and Metonymy in Composite Expressions</title>.
            In <title level="m">Metaphor and Metonymy in Comparison and Contrast</title>, edited by
              <editor>René Dirven</editor> and <editor>Ralf Pörings</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >435–65</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>: <publisher>Mouton de
              Gruyter</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="good00"><author>Good, Jeff</author>, and <author>Ronald Sprouse</author>.
              <date>2000</date>. <title level="u">SGML Markup of Dictionaries with Special Reference
              to Comparative and Etymological Data</title>. Paper presented at the workshop on
            Web-Based Language Documentation and Description, December 12–15, Philadelphia.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="goossens94"><author>Goossens, Louis</author>. <date>1994</date>. <title
              level="a">Metaphtonymy: The Interaction of Metaphor and Metonymy in Figurative
              Expressions for Linguistic Action</title>. In <title level="m">By Word of Mouth:
              Metaphor, Metonymy and Linguistic Action in a Cognitive Linguistic
            Perspective</title>, by <author>Louis Goossens</author>, <author>Paul Pauwels</author>,
              <author>Brygida Rudzka-Ostyn</author>, <author>Anne-Marie Simon-Vandenbergen</author>,
            and <author>Johan Vanparys</author>, <biblScope unit="page">159–74</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>: <publisher>John Benjamins</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="guevara08"><author>Guevara, Emiliano</author>, and <author>Sergio
              Scalise</author>. <date>2008</date>. <title level="u">Heads in Compounding: Variation
              and Patterns</title>. Paper presented at the 13th International Morphology Meeting,
            Main Theme: Variation and Change in Morphology, Vienna, February 3–6. Abstract available
            at <ptr
              target="https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/d2b5/652c01aca9306dc3f7f7e70cb38a6587ce0f.pdf"
            />, p. 43.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="harris95"><author>Harris, Alice C.</author>, and <author>Lyle
              Campbell</author>. <date>1995</date>. <title level="m">Historical Syntax in
              Cross-linguistic Perspective</title>. <series>Cambridge Studies in
              Linguistics</series>
            <biblScope unit="issue">74</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="haspelmath03"><author>Haspelmath, Martin</author>. <date>2003</date>. <title
              level="a">The Geometry of Grammatical Meaning: Semantic Maps and Cross-linguistic
              Comparison</title>. In <title level="m">The New Psychology of Language: Cognitive and
              Functional Approaches to Language Structure</title>, vol.2, edited by <editor>Michael
              Tomasello</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">211–42</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Mahwah,
              NJ</pubPlace>: <publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="haspelmath09"><author>Haspelmath, Martin</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title
              level="a">Lexical Borrowing: Concepts and Issues</title>. In <title level="m"
              >Loanwords in the World’s Languages: A Comparative Handbook</title>, edited by
              <editor>Martin Haspelmath</editor> and <editor>Uri Tadmor</editor>, <biblScope
              unit="page">35–54</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>: <publisher>De Gruyter
              Mouton</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="haspelmath09b"><editor>Haspelmath, Martin</editor>, and <editor>Uri
              Tadmor</editor>, eds. <date>2009</date>. <title level="m">World Loanword
              Database</title>. <pubPlace>Leipzig</pubPlace>: <publisher>Max Planck Institute for
              Evolutionary Anthropology</publisher>. Accessed April 6, 2015. <ptr
              target="http://wold.clld.org"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="haugen50"><author>Haugen, Einar</author>. <date>1950</date>. <title
              level="a">The Analysis of Linguistic Borrowing.</title>
            <title level="j">Language</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">210–31</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
            >10.2307/410058</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hopper03"><author>Hopper, Paul J.</author>, and <author>Elizabeth Closs
              Traugott</author>, <date>2003</date>. <title level="m">Grammaticalization</title>.
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Cambridge University
            Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ide00"><author>Ide, Nancy</author>, <author>Adam Kilgarriff</author>, and
              <author>Laurent Romary</author>. <date>2000</date>. <title level="a">A Formal Model of
              Dictionary Structure and Content</title>. In <title level="m">Proceedings of the Ninth
              EURALEX International Congress, EURALEX 2000</title>, edited by <editor>Ulrich
              Heid</editor>, <editor>Stefan Evert</editor>, <editor>Egbert Lehmann</editor>, and
              <editor>Christian Rohrer</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">113–26</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="http://euralex.org/category/publications/euralex-2000/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ide94"><author>Ide, Nancy</author>, and <author>Jean Véronis</author>.
              <date>1994</date>. <title level="a">Machine Readable Dictionaries: What Have We
              Learned, Where Do We Go?</title> In <title level="m">Proceedings of the Post-COLING
              ’94 International Workshop on Directions of Lexical Research</title>, <biblScope
              unit="page">137–46</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Beijing</pubPlace>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ide95"><author>Ide, Nancy</author>. <date>1995</date>. <title level="a"
              >Encoding Dictionaries</title>. <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">167–79</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ietf09a"><orgName>IETF (Internet Engineering Task Force)</orgName>.
              <date>2009a</date>. <title level="m">BCP [Best Current Practice] 47: Tags for
              Identifying Languages</title>. Edited by <editor>Addison Phillips</editor> and
              <editor>Mark Davis</editor>. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>: <publisher>IETF</publisher>,
            September. <ptr target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/bcp47"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ietf09b"><orgName>IETF (Internet Engineering Task Force)</orgName>. 2009b.
              <title level="m">RFC (Request for Comments) 5645: Update to the Language Subtag
              Registry</title>. Edited by <editor>Doug Ewell</editor>. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>IETF</publisher>, September. <ptr
              target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5645"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="iso07"><orgName>ISO (International Organization for
              Standardization)</orgName>. <date>2007</date>. <title level="m"
              >Presentation/representation of entries in dictionaries — Requirements,
              recommendations and information</title>. ISO 1951:2007. <pubPlace>Geneva</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>ISO</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="iso08"><orgName>ISO (International Organization for
              Standardization)</orgName>. <date>2008</date>. <title level="m">Language resource
              management — Lexical markup framework (LMF)</title>. ISO 24613:2008.
              <pubPlace>Geneva</pubPlace>: <publisher>ISO</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jackendoff09"><author>Jackendoff, Ray</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title
              level="a">Compounding in the Parallel Architecture and Conceptual Semantics.</title>
            In <title level="m">The Oxford Handbook of Compounding</title>, edited by
              <editor>Rochelle Lieber</editor> and <editor>Pavol Štekauer</editor>.
              <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>,
              <biblScope unit="page">105–28</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jacobson02"><author>Jacobson, Michel</author>, and <author>Boyd
              Michailovsky</author>. <date>2002</date>. <title level="u">Linking Linguistic
              Resources: Time Aligned Corpus and Dictionary</title>. Paper presented at the
            International Workshop on Resources and Tools in Field Linguistics, Las Palmas, Canary
            Islands, Spain, May 26–27. <ptr
              target="http://www.mpi.nl/lrec/2002/papers/lrec-pap-27-JACMICv2.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kovecses98"><author>Kövecses, Zoltán</author>, and <author>Günter
              Radden</author>. <date>1998</date>. <title level="a">Metonymy: Developing a Cognitive
              Linguistic View</title>. <title level="j">Cognitive Linguistics (includes Cognitive
              Linguistic Bibliography)</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">37–77</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1515/cogl.1998.9.1.37</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="laborderie94"><author>Laborderie, Noëlle</author>, and <author>Claude
              Thomasset</author>. <date>1994</date>. <title level="m">Précis de phonétique
              historique</title>. <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>Nathan</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lakoff87"><author>Lakoff, George</author>. <date>1987</date>. <title
              level="m">Women, Fire and Dangerous Things: What Categories Reveal about the
              Mind</title>. <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Chicago
              Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lakoff93"><author>Lakoff, George</author>. <date>1993</date>. <title
              level="a">The Contemporary Theory of Metaphor</title>. In <title level="m">Metaphor
              and Thought</title>, <edition>2nd ed.</edition>, edited by <editor>Andrew
              Ortony</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">202–51</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Cambridge University
            Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lakoff80"><author>Lakoff, George</author>, and <author>Mark
            Johnson</author>. <date>1980</date>. <title level="m">Metaphors We Live By</title>.
              <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Chicago
            Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="langacker77"><author>Langacker, Ronald W.</author>
            <date>1977</date>. <title level="a">Syntactic Reanalysis</title>. In <title level="m"
              >Mechanisms of Syntactic Change</title>, edited by <editor>Charles N. Li</editor>,
              <biblScope unit="page">57–139</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Austin</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>University of Texas Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="langacker87"><author>Langacker, Ronald W.</author>. <date>1987</date>.
              <title level="m">Foundations of Cognitive Grammar. Vol. 1, Theoretical
              Prerequisites.</title>
            <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="langacker91"><author>Langacker, Ronald W.</author>. <date>1991</date>.
              <title level="m">Foundations of Cognitive Grammar. Vol. 2, Descriptive
              Application.</title>
            <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="langacker00"><author>Langacker, Ronald W.</author>. <date>2000</date>.
              <title level="m">Grammar and Conceptualization</title>. <pubPlace>Berlin and New
              York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Mouton de Gruyter</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lehmann62"><author>Lehmann, Winfred P.</author>
            <date>1962</date>. <title level="m">Historical Linguistics: An Introduction</title>.
              <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Holt, Rinehart &amp;
            Winston</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lemnitzer13"><author>Lemnitzer, Lothar</author>, <author>Laurent
              Romary</author>, and <author>Andreas Witt</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
              level="a">Representing Human and Machine Dictionaries in Markup Languages</title>.
              <title level="m">Dictionaries: An International Encyclopedia of Lexicography.
              Supplementary Volume: Recent Developments with Focus on Computational
              Lexicography</title>, edited by <editor>Rufus H. Gouws</editor>, <editor>Ulrich
              Heid</editor>, <editor>Wolfgang Schweickard</editor>, and <editor>Herbert Ernst
              Wiegand</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">1195–1208</biblScope>. HSK 5.4.
              <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>: <publisher>De Gruyter Mouton</publisher>. Author version
            available at <ptr target="https://hal.inria.fr/inria-00441215"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="matras07"><editor>Matras, Yaron</editor>, and <editor>Jeanette
              Sakel</editor>, eds. <date>2007</date>. <title level="m">Grammatical Borrowing in
              Cross-Linguistic Perspective</title>. <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>: <publisher>Mouton
              de Gruyter</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="meillet12"><author>Meillet, Antoine</author>. <date>1912</date>. <title
              level="a">L’Evolution des Formes Grammaticales</title>. <title level="j">Scientia
              (Rivista di scienza)</title>, <biblScope unit="volume">XII:XXVI</biblScope>,<biblScope
              unit="issue">6</biblScope>. Reprinted (1965) in <title level="m">Linguistique
              Historique et Linguistique Cimerale</title>. <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Librairie Honoré Champion</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="myers-scotton02"><author>Myers-Scotton, Carol</author>. <date>2002</date>.
              <title level="m">Contact Linguistics: Bilingual Encounters and Grammatical
              Outcomes</title>. <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Oxford University
              Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pagliuca94"><editor>Pagliuca, William</editor>, ed. <date>1994</date>.
              <title level="m">Perspectives on Grammaticalization</title>.
              <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>: <publisher>Benjamins</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rennie00"><author>Rennie, Susan</author>. <date>2000</date>. <title
              level="a">Encoding a Historical Dictionary with the TEI (with Reference to the
              Electronic Scottish National Dictionary Project)</title>. In <title level="m"
              >Proceedings of the Ninth EURALEX International Congress, EURALEX 2000</title>, edited
            by <editor>Ulrich Heid</editor>, <editor>Stefan Evert</editor>, <editor>Egbert
              Lehmann</editor>, and <editor>Christian Rohrer</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >261–71</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Stuttgart</pubPlace>: <publisher>Institut für
              Maschinelle Sprachverarbeitung, Universität Stuttgart</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://euralex.org/category/publications/euralex-2000/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="romary01"><author>Romary, Laurent</author>. <date>2001</date>. <title
              level="u">An Abstract Model for the Representation of Multilingual Terminological
              Data: TMF - Terminological Markup Framework</title>. Paper presented at TAMA 2001,
            February 1–2, Antwerp, Belgium. <ptr target="https://hal.inria.fr/inria-00100405"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="romary09"><author>Romary, Laurent</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title
              level="a">Questions &amp; Answers for TEI Newcomers</title>. In <title level="j"
              >Jahrbuch für Computerphilologie</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Paderborn, Germany</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Mentis</publisher>. Author version available at <ptr
              target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00348372"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="romary11"><author>Romary, Laurent</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title
              level="a">Stabilizing Knowledge through Standards: A Perspective for the
              Humanities</title>. In <title level="m">Going Digital: Evolutionary and Revolutionary
              Aspects of Digitization</title>, edited by <editor>Karl Grandin</editor>.
              <pubPlace>Stockholm</pubPlace>: <publisher>Center for History of Science at the Royal
              Swedish Academy of Sciences</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="romary15"><author>Romary, Laurent</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title
              level="a">TEI and LMF Crosswalks</title>. <title level="j">Journal for Language
              Technology and Computational Linguistics</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">47–70</biblScope>. Author version available at <ptr
              target="http://hal.inria.fr/hal-00762664"/>; <ptr
              target="http://www.jlcl.org/2015_Heft1/3Romary.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="romary12"><author>Romary, Laurent</author>, and <author>Werner
              Wegstein</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">Consistent Modeling of
              Heterogeneous Lexical Structures</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the Text
              Encoding Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>. <ptr target="http://jtei.revues.org/540"/>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.4000/jtei.540</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="romary14"><author>Romary, Laurent</author>, and <author>Andreas
              Witt</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">Méthodes pour la représentation
              informatisée de données lexicales/Methoden der Speicherung lexikalischer
            Daten</title>. <title level="j">Lexicographica: International Annual for
              Lexicography</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">30</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">152–86</biblScope>.
            Author version available at <ptr target="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00991745"/>. doi:<idno
              type="doi">10.1515/lexi-2014-0006</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="salmon-alt06"><author>Salmon-Alt, Susanne</author>. <date>2006</date>.
              <title level="a">Data Structures for Etymology: Towards an Etymological Lexical
              Network</title>. <title level="j">BULAG</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">31</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">101–12</biblScope>.
            Author version available at <ptr target="http://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00110971"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="salmon-alt05"><author>Salmon-Alt, Susanne</author>, <author>Laurent
              Romary</author>, and <author>Eva Buchi</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title level="u"
              >Modeling Diachrony in Dictionaries</title>. Paper presented at ACH/ALLC Conference
            2005, Victoria, BC, Canada, June 15–18.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="scalise05"><author>Scalise, Sergio</author>, and <author>Emiliano
              Guevara</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title level="a">The Lexicalist Approach to
              Word-formation and the Notion of the Lexicon</title>. In <title level="m">Handbook of
              Word-formation</title>, edited by <editor>Pavol Štekauer</editor> and <editor>Rochelle
              Lieber</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">147–87</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Dordrecht</pubPlace>: <publisher>Springer</publisher>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1007/1-4020-3596-9_7</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="scholz15"><author>Scholz, Johannes</author>, <author>Thomas J.
              Lampoltshammer</author>, <author>Norbert Bartelme</author>, and <author>Eveline
              Wandl-Vogt</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title level="a">Spatial-Temporal Modeling of
              Linguistic Regions and Processes with combined Indeterminate and Crisp
              Boundaries</title>. In <title level="m">Proceedings of the 1st ICA European Symposium
              on Cartography</title>, edited by <editor>Georg Gartner</editor> and <editor>Haosheng
              Huang</editor>, EuroCarto 2015, 10–12 November 2015, Vienna, Austria.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="schopper15"><author>Schopper, Daniel</author>, <author>Jack Bowers</author>,
            and <author>Eveline Wandl-Vogt</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title level="u">dboe@TEI:
              Remodelling a Database of Dialects into a Rich LOD Resource</title>. Paper presented
            at the Text Encoding Initiative Conference and Members’ Meeting 2015, Lyon, France,
            October 28–31. Abstract available at <ptr
              target="http://tei2015.huma-num.fr/en/papers/#146"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="svorou94"><author>Svorou, Soteria</author>. <date>1994</date>. <title
              level="m">The Grammar of Space</title>. <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>: <publisher>J.
              Benjamins</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sweetser88"><author>Sweetser, Eve E.</author>
            <date>1988</date>. <title level="m">Grammaticalization and Semantic Bleaching</title>.
            In <title level="m">Proceedings of the Fourteenth Annual Meeting of the Berkeley
              Linguistics Society</title>, edited by <editor>Shelley Axmaker</editor>, <editor>Annie
              Jaisser</editor>, and <editor>Helen Singmaster</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >389–405</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA</pubPlace>: <publisher>Berkeley
              Linguistics Society</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tei16"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2016</date>. <title
              level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>.
              <edition>Version 3.1.0</edition>. Last updated December 15. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="traugott95"><author>Traugott, Elizabeth C.</author>
            <date>1995</date>. <title level="u">The Role of the Development of Discourse Markers in
              a Theory of Grammaticalization</title>. Paper presented at the Twelfth International
            Conference on Historical Linguistics (ICHL XII), Manchester, England, August
            13–18.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="vandeloise06"><author>Vandeloise, Claude</author>. <date>2006</date>. <title
              level="a">Are There Spatial Prepositions?</title> In <title level="m">Space in
              Languages: Linguistic Systems and Cognitive Categories</title>, edited by <editor>Maya
              Hickmann</editor> and <editor>Stéphane Robert</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >139–54</biblScope>. <series>Typological Studies in Language</series>
            <biblScope unit="issue">66</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>: <publisher>J.
              Benjamins</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="windhouwer12"><author>Windhouwer, Menzo</author>, and <author>Sue Ellen
              Wright</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">Linking to Linguistic Data
              Categories in ISOcat</title>. In <title level="m">Linked Data in Linguistics:
              Representing and Connecting Language Data and Language Metadata</title>, edited by
              <editor>Christian Chiarcos</editor>, <editor>Sebastian Nordhoff</editor>, and
              <editor>Sebastian Hellmann</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">99–107</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>: <publisher>Springer</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="yin10"><author>Yin, Hui</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title level="a">The
              So-called Chinese VV Compounds—A Continuum between Lexicon and Syntax</title>. In
              <title level="m">Proceedings of the 2010 Annual Conference of the Canadian Linguistic
              Association</title>, edited by <editor>Melinda Heijl</editor>.
              <pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>: <publisher>CLA</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://homes.chass.utoronto.ca/~cla-acl/actes2010/actes2010.html"/>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
