<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!-- $Id: jtei-reule-211-source.xml 1082 2022-01-31 08:32:29Z pietro.liuzzo $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Encoding the Ethiopic Miracles of Mary</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Dorothea</forename>
                  <surname>Reule</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Dorothea Reule has been a member of the project <title level="u"
                     >Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine digitale
                     Forschungsumgebung</title> since 2016. Her work therein focuses mainly on the
                  encoding of historical catalogues of Ethiopic manuscripts. She is also a doctoral
                  candidate in Semitic Languages at Philipps-Universität Marburg, preparing a thesis
                  on the textual history of the Geez Synaxarion.</affiliation>
               <email>dorothea.reule@uni-hamburg.de</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>22/01/2022</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor>Tanja Wissik</editor>
            <editor>Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
            <editor>Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
            <editor>Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="rolling">Open Issue</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for
               journals in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking
               to publish full-text articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Ethiopic literature</term>
               <term>research environment</term>
               <term>catalogue</term>
               <term>manuscripts</term>
               <term>Ethiopian studies</term>
               <term>Eritrean studies</term>
               <term>Miracles of Mary</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p>This article will illustrate the challenges of digitizing of historical manuscript
               catalogues, taking as an example the widespread and complex work of the <title
                  level="a">Miracles of Mary</title>. This work is typically composed of framing
               texts and miracle texts proper, often accompanied by miniatures, and it circulates in
               collections of varying standardization. A flexible encoding system with different
               identifiers for textual units and art themes has been developed, answering the most
               common challenges of encoding the Ethiopic literary tradition, improving the
               cataloguing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="acknowledgements">
            <p>I am very grateful to Eliana Dal Sasso, Pietro Maria Liuzzo and Nafisa Valieva for
               their valuable comments on preliminary versions of this article.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="intro">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>This article addresses the encoding of an Ethiopic text known as the <title level="a"
                  >Miracles of Mary</title> (<foreign>Taʾamməra Māryām</foreign>) for the project
                  <title level="a">Beta maṣāḥəft: Manuscripts of Ethiopia and Eritrea</title>.<note>
                  <p>The project, officially <foreign>Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und
                        Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung</foreign>, in the following
                     Beta maṣāḥəft, is funded within the framework of the Academies’ Programme
                     (coordinated by the Union of the German Academies of Sciences and Humanities)
                     under the purview of the Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg for 2016–2040.
                     It is headed by Prof. Alessandro Bausi and coordinated by Eugenia Sokolinski,
                     the technical lead 2016–2022 was Pietro Maria Liuzzo. The former and current
                     research fellows are Daria Elagina, Denis Nosnitsin, Dorothea Reule, Solomon
                     Gebreyes, and Massimo Villa.</p>
               </note> The <title level="a">Miracles of Mary</title> is a fluid collection of
               stories, each of which recounts a miraculous deed said to be performed by the Virgin
               Mary. Most versions of the <title>Miracles of Mary</title> are preceded by various
               introductory texts. The work has been transmitted in multiple-text or composite
               manuscripts, some of which place thematically related texts before or after.
               Individual miracle texts are attested outside of the collection. The large number of
               manuscripts, unknown but numbering at least several hundred, show that the stories
               were widespread.<note>
                  <p>See Balicka-Witakowska and Bausi (<ref type="bibl" target="#BalickaBausi2010"
                        >2010, 792–93</ref>). Some of the quantitative research opportunities
                     presented by the large amount both of manuscripts and of miracle texts are
                     formulated in the <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/research-questions/"
                        >research questions</ref> of the PEMM project.</p>
               </note> The earliest manuscript dates to the reign of King Dāwit I (r. 1380–1413)
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#BalickaBausi2010">Balicka-Witakowska and Bausi
                  2010</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#Kropp2017">Kropp 2017, 65–66</ref>), and the
               text continues to be copied, as manuscript culture in Ethiopia is still alive.
               Despite the variable manuscript tradition, recurring patterns can be recognized.<note>
                  <p>As usual for the history of Ethiopian and Eritrean studies, editions and
                     translations were preceded by thorough catalogue descriptions of the related
                     work, see in particular Zotenberg (<ref target="#Zotenberg1877" type="bibl"
                        >1877, 62–71</ref>). An early edition and translation still regarded as a
                     reference is Budge (<ref type="bibl" target="#Budge1900">1900</ref>). For an
                     overview of the research in Ethiopian and Eritrean Studies carried out on the
                        <title level="a">Miracles of Mary</title>, see Balicka-Witakowska and Bausi
                        (<ref target="#BalickaBausi2010" type="bibl">2010</ref>). Cerulli (<ref
                        target="#Cerulli1943" type="bibl">1943</ref>), while intended as a
                     preparatory work, remains the most comprehensive study to date. Alessandro
                     Bausi has studied the case of the <title level="a">Miracles of Mary</title> as
                     an example for a corpus-organizer (<ref target="#Bausi2016" type="bibl">2016,
                        121–26</ref>) and as a paradigmatic work of interaction and adaptation
                     between Ethiopia and the Christian Orient (<ref target="#Bausi2020" type="bibl"
                        >2020, 238–39</ref>).</p>
                  <p>This current interest is also well illustrated by the recent <ref
                        target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">Princeton Ethiopian Miracles of Mary
                        Project (PEMM)</ref>, led by Wendy Belcher, that investigates the corpus and
                     particularly the miracle of the cannibal of Qəmr, from a literary studies’
                     perspective. Interaction with this project has been very fruitful for our
                     encoding, and I am very grateful in particular to Wendy Belcher and Evgeniia
                     Lambrinaki for our exchanges on this subject.</p>
               </note> Three manuscripts have been chosen to illustrate the variety: <list>
                  <item>[A] <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/BLorient651">London, British
                        Library, BL Oriental 651</ref> (sixteenth century),<note>
                        <p>See Dorothea Reule, <title level="a">London, British Library, BL Oriental
                              651</title>, <title level="j">Die Schriftkultur des christlichen
                              Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta
                              maṣāḥǝft</title>, edited by Alessandro Bausi, accessed January 27,
                           2022, <ptr target="https://betamasaheft.eu/BLorient651"/>.</p>
                     </note></item>
                  <item>[B] <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/BLadd16192">London, British
                        Library, BL Add. 16,192</ref> (composite manuscript consisting of
                     codicological units dating from between the fourteenth and the nineteenth century),<note>
                        <p>See Massimo Villa, Dorothea Reule, Eugenia Sokolinski, <title level="a"
                              >London, British Library, BL Add. 16,192</title>, <title level="j">Die
                              Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine
                              multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</title>, edited by
                           Alessandro Bausi, accessed January 27, 2022,<ptr
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/BLadd16192"/>.</p>
                     </note> and</item>
                  <item>[C] <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/BAVet8">Vatican City, Biblioteca
                        Apostolica Vaticana, Aeth. 8</ref> (sixteenth century).<note>
                        <p>See Massimo Villa, <title level="a">Vatican City, Biblioteca Apostolica
                              Vaticana, Aeth. 8</title>, <title level="j">Die Schriftkultur des
                              christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                              Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</title>, edited by Alessandro
                           Bausi, accessed January 27, 2022, <ptr
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/BAVet8"/>.</p>
                     </note></item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>All three manuscripts contain miracles of Mary together with other texts, all are
               multiple text manuscripts, and B is a composite manuscript. In addition to the
               miracles, two of the manuscripts, A and B, contain introductory texts pertaining to
               the collection of the <title>Miracles of Mary</title>. These introductory texts are
               partly identical in both manuscripts. However, despite these commonalities, the three
               manuscripts feature significant variation. The number and identity of miracles in
               each manuscript is vastly different. A contains the so-called <title>ʾAkko-nu bǝʾsi
                  collection</title>, a fixed sequence of 33 miracles (30 in this manuscript), each
               followed by a hymn stanza (see below, <ptr target="#Collections" type="crossref"/>).
               B contains 72 different miracles, whose sequence has also been attested, with minor
               variation, in other manuscripts, for instance EMML 3536 (fifteenth century) (<ref
                  target="#Getatchew1985" type="bibl">Getatchew Haile 1985</ref>). C contains eight
               miracles also partly attested in the other two manuscripts, but in a different order.
               The introductory texts in A and B are ordered differently, while C contains none of
               these texts, and a colophon has been used to introduce the miracles. Lastly, the
               remaining texts in the manuscripts A, B, and C are all different.<note>
                  <p>See also <ptr target="#Example2" type="crossref"/>.</p>
               </note></p>
            <p>Beta maṣāḥəft encodes historical catalogues and undertakes new cataloguing endeavors
               to promote the study of the Ethiopian and Eritrean manuscript culture.<note>
                  <p>The Ethiopian and Eritrean highlands, located in the territories of the modern
                     states of Ethiopia and Eritrea, formed one continuous cultural space throughout
                     most of their history. For the sake of readability, this region will be
                     referred to as <q>Ethiopia(n)</q> in the following. The catalogue encoding is
                     being carried out by all past and present project members and external
                     collaborators: Ashlee Benson, Augustine Dickinson, Daria Elagina, Marcin
                     Krawcuk, Ralph Lee, Denis Nosnitsin, Dorothea Reule, Eugenia Sokolinski,
                     Solomon Gebreyes, and Massimo Villa. See the project note Reule (<ref
                        target="#Reule2018" type="bibl">2018</ref>). A more in-depth presentation of
                     the project’s encoding is given in Liuzzo (<ref target="#Liuzzo2017"
                        type="bibl">2017</ref>).</p></note> All encoding decisions are taken to
               improve both these types of cataloguing work. As a result, encoding strategies for
               the <title level="a">Miracles of Mary</title> have to be precise but flexible: they
               must apply to in-depth cataloguing of a manuscript containing the <title level="a"
                  >Miracles of Mary</title>, offering solutions for describing all of its aspects
               that may be of interest to scholars of various backgrounds, and succeed equally well
               in encoding previously published descriptions, which might deviate considerably from
               current cataloguing standards. The encoding results must be accessible and usable for
               scholars of any level of digital competence.</p>
            <p>Two significant works for the encoding were Cerulli’s <title level="m">Il libro
                  etiopico dei Miracoli di Maria e le sue fonti nelle letterature del Medio Evo
                     <emph>latino</emph></title> (<ref target="#Cerulli1943" type="bibl">Cerulli
                  1943</ref>) and the unpublished miracle handlist compiled by William Macomber in
               his function as cataloguer for the EMML project,<note>
                  <p><ptr target="https://hmml.org/about/global-operations/ethiopia/"/>.</p>
               </note> and made available to the project by Alessandro Bausi (<ref
                  target="#Macomber" type="bibl">Macomber n.d.</ref>). This handlist contains 643
               single miracle texts, often identifying distinct recensions, each listed with a
               summarizing title, manuscript witnesses, and one or more incipits.</p>
            <p>Encoding the information contained in these two works as TEI allows us to: <list
                  rend="bulleted">
                  <item>group and connect them in the digital research environment, where they can
                     easily be accessed and queried,</item>
                  <item>aid the identification of textual units, their delimitations and recensions
                     by assigning stable identifiers, for internal and external use,</item>
                  <item>facilitate further philological and codicological research on the
                     collection, particularly on its formation and evolution across time and
                     space.</item>
               </list></p>
            <p>To achieve these aims, the encoding must:<list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>allow for a variable level of detail,</item>
                  <item>be transparent and flexible, allowing revisions and corrections reflecting
                     changes in the scholars’ understanding of the textual units and their
                     relationships,</item>
                  <item>make the most out of the vagueness of existing descriptions.</item>
               </list>Based on this encoding applications may allow interested scholars to find
               references to miracle texts and other texts of the Miracles of Mary, as well as their
               placement in manuscripts.</p>
            <p>Several challenges originating in the peculiarities of historical catalogue
               descriptions became apparent during the encoding of the <title level="a">Miracles of
                  Mary</title>:<note>
                  <p>While the challenges listed here result, from the modern point of view, mainly
                     from shortcomings of the historical catalogues, it must not be forgotten that
                     these catalogues were pioneering works in the study of Ethiopic literature, and
                     their level of scholarship remains often unattained today.</p>
               </note>
               <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>insufficient identification of miracle texts, framing texts, and the entire
                     collection,</item>
                  <item>inconsistent descriptions with varying depth within one catalogue or even
                     one manuscript description,</item>
                  <item>lack of codicological awareness and a limited understanding of the
                     manuscripts’ stratigraphy, which is crucial when studying the genesis of such
                     an evolving collection.</item>
               </list> These limitations hinder the identification and delimitation of collections
               and their constituting textual units, which presupposes thorough philological,
               codicological, and stratigraphical analysis.</p>
            <p>These problems are less pronounced when describing a manuscript to which one has
               access, either because images are available to improve on the existing catalogue
               description or because the manuscript is described for the first time based on good
               images or on the artefact itself. However, such descriptions have their own challenges.<note>
                  <p>That the cataloguing of manuscripts containing the <title level="a">Miracles of
                        Mary</title> is far from trivial has been demonstrated in Bausi (<ref
                        target="#Bausi2016" type="bibl">2016, 123–24</ref>).</p>
               </note> In many manuscripts, the collection of the <title level="a">Miracles of
                  Mary</title> can be very long, raising questions about the depth of the
               description, which might be answered differently by different cataloguers. The
               absence of a critical edition or a study identifying the recensions of the
               constituent texts of the collections remains problematic.</p>
            <p>All the challenges noted above for the <title level="a">Miracles of Mary</title> are
               common throughout the Ethiopic literary and manuscript tradition. Producing a
               practical solution for this text will provide a template for future work in other texts.<note>
                  <p>For a presentation of the complex constitution and evolution of Ethiopic
                     multiple-text manuscripts, see Bausi (<ref target="#Bausi2016" type="bibl"
                        >2016</ref>), which includes the example of the <title level="a">Miracles of
                        Mary</title>.</p>
               </note></p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="Miracles">
            <head>The <title level="a">Miracles of Mary</title></head>
            <p>Texts narrating miracles performed by a saint during or after their lifetime are a
               classical hagiographical genre, widely attested throughout all Christian literary traditions.<note>
                  <p>For an overview of the genre’s origins and early development, see for example
                     Efthymiadis (<ref target="#Efthymiadis2014" type="bibl">2014</ref>).</p>
               </note> Though not as common as lives or <soCalled>Vitae</soCalled> of saints
                  (<foreign>gadlāt</foreign>), miracles (<foreign>taʾammər</foreign>) stories or
               collections of miracles ascribed to particular saints are a significant part of the
               Ethiopic hagiographic corpus.<note>
                  <p>For a recent overview of the Ethiopic hagiographic genre, see Brita (<ref
                        target="#Brita2020" type="bibl">2020, 261–81</ref>). The same contribution
                     also includes an outline of the history of the <title level="a">Miracles of
                        Mary</title> as an outstanding example of a translated work that shaped
                     Ethiopic culture (<ref target="#Brita2020" type="bibl">Brita 2020,
                     254–55</ref>). For a short presentation of the development and content of the
                     genre of <foreign>taʾammǝr</foreign>, see Nosnitsin (<ref
                        target="#Nosnitsin2010" type="bibl">2020</ref>).</p>
               </note> Most miracle texts are relatively short and self-contained, designed to fit
               easily within the broader context of a saint’s hagiographic dossier, appealing both
               for their storytelling and spiritual purpose. In most manuscripts, miracle texts
               appear after the <soCalled>Vitae</soCalled>, but can also occur within other
               collections. The <title level="a">Miracles of Mary</title> is the most famous of
               several miracle collections that circulated in Ethiopic literature. As noted above,
               single miracle texts from the <title>Miracles of Mary</title> circulated in
               manuscripts containing other works, often as <q>guest texts</q>.<note>
                  <p>Defined by Gumbert (<ref xml:id="q1" target="#Gumbert2004" type="bibl">2004,
                        42</ref>) as <quote source="#q1">a text which has been added as an
                        enrichment, into an existing codicological unit</quote>.</p>
               </note> This variety is one of the factors contributing to the complexity of their
               encoding.</p>
            <p>The historical nucleus of the <title>Miracles of Mary</title> began in
               twelfth-century France. We know of versions in vernacular European languages (<ref
                  target="#Cerulli1943" type="bibl">Cerulli 1943, 7–15</ref>), and a translation
               into Arabic in the thirteenth century (<ref target="#Cerulli1943" type="bibl">Cerulli
                  1943, 531–35</ref>; <ref target="#Kropp2017" type="bibl">Kropp 2017, 61–64</ref>).
               New miracle narratives were added continuously in all versions, forming the
               collection into an outstanding example of cultural transmission and adaptation.
               Scholarly consensus dates the translation of the <title level="a">Miracles of
                  Mary</title> into Ethiopic to the end of the fourteenth century from an Arabic
               intermediate witness.<note>
                  <p>It should be noted that this Arabic Vorlage consisted exclusively of miracles
                     of European origin, while the numerous Ethiopic miracles set in Egypt and the
                     Levant must have other sources (<ref target="#Cerulli1943" type="bibl">Cerulli
                        1943, 148–57; 530–31</ref>).</p>
               </note> The reception of the <title level="a">Miracles of Mary</title> in Ethiopia
               has to be set against the background of theological developments which took place in
               the fifteenth and sixteenth century within the Ethiopian court and church (<ref
                  target="#GetatchewNosnitsin2007" type="bibl">Getatchew and Nosnitsin 2007</ref>).
               During this time, the corpus of the Ethiopic <title level="a">Miracles of
                  Mary</title> increased considerably and incorporated accounts of Mary’s miraculous
               interventions in the course of Ethiopian history. Texts of the <title level="a"
                  >Miracles of Mary</title> were also read during the liturgy and in so doing
               obtained high cultural and identity forming value (<ref
                  target="#FritschHabtemichael2020" type="bibl">Fritsch and Habtemichael 2020,
                  187</ref>).</p>
            <p>The oldest known manuscripts of the <title level="a">Miracles of Mary</title> are
               those kept at the churches of ʾAmbā Gǝšen and Beta Ləḥem in Ethiopia, and date from
               the time of King Dāwit I (r. 1380–1413) (<ref target="#BalickaBausi2010" type="bibl"
                  >Balicka-Witakowska and Bausi 2010</ref>; <ref target="#Kropp2017" type="bibl"
                  >Kropp 2017, 65–66</ref>).<note>
                  <p>Hundreds of manuscripts containing the <title level="a">Miracles of
                        Mary</title> are now available to scholars digitally or in libraries; see
                     Balicka-Witakowska and Bausi (<ref target="#BalickaBausi2010" type="bibl">2010,
                        792–93</ref>).</p>
               </note></p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="MiraclesEncoding">
            <head>Encoding the <title level="a">Miracles of Mary</title></head>
            <p>Describing this complex collection in a catalogue is a challenge. Ms London, British
               Library, BL Orient. 650, the first manuscript of the <title level="a">Miracles of
                  Mary</title> described in Wright (<ref target="#Wright1877" type="bibl">1877,
                  46</ref>), is an excellent example of the catalogue’s narrative style, its varying
               level of depth in the identification of textual units, and its codicological
                  shortcomings:<figure xml:id="Example1">
                  <graphic url="img/Wright.jpg" width="980px" height="1277px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Excerpt of the description of the content of MS London,
                     British Library, BL Orient. 650 in Wright (<ref target="#Wright1877"
                        type="bibl">1877, 46</ref>).</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>The description states the number of miracle texts attested in this manuscript and
               their location in relation to the other texts the manuscript contains, the exact
               identification of one miracle text and of a further text included in the collection,
               and quotes the colophon.<note>Whether this text actually constitutes a colophon may
                  be disputed, see, accessed January 27, 2022, <ptr
                     target="https://betamasaheft.eu/Guidelines/?id=colophon"/>.</note> While
               allowing researchers to discover whether the manuscript is relevant for their work,
               the description suffers from the typical shortcomings of its period. Why has only the
               last miracle text been identified? What is meant by <q>appended</q>? Are the miracle
               texts included after the colophon written by the same hand as those before it? These
               questions, which must remain open until consultation of the manuscript or its
               digitization, are related to the manuscript’s stratigraphy, whose reconstruction
               based on this description must remain rudimentary.</p>
            <p>TEI encoding methods for literary works (<ptr target="#Works" type="crossref"/>) and
               art themes (<ptr target="#Art" type="crossref"/>) allow us to encode Wright’s and
               similar catalogue descriptions, and scholars can adapt it to modern descriptions. The
               system is presented below and illustrated by the encoded version of this catalogue
               entry.</p>
            <div xml:id="Works">
               <head>Literary works</head>
               <p>Beta maṣāḥǝft considers as works all texts with <quote
                     source="#quoteref1 #quoteref2">a fixed content occurring in a fixed sequence
                     which can circulate independently</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref1"
                     target="#Villa2018" type="bibl">Villa 2018, 143</ref>; <ref xml:id="quoteref2"
                     target="#Liuzzo2019" type="bibl">Liuzzo 2019, 79–81</ref>). A TEI file is
                  created for each work. In each work TEI file, an <att>xml:id</att> with a semantic
                  value is assigned to the root <gi>TEI</gi> element.<note>
                     <p>This value is referred to in the following as the TEI file’s <q>ID</q>. On
                        the criteria for the construction of these project-specific IDs, see Villa
                           (<ref target="#Villa2018" type="bibl">2018, 143</ref>).</p>
                  </note> Within this type of TEI file each <code>div[@type]</code> in the
                     <tag>text</tag> can be assigned an <att>xml:id</att>, to represent the work’s
                  subdivisions. While this is not a special practice, retaining the structure of
                     <tag type="start">div type="textpart"</tag>s even without textual content
                  allows precise references to the value of the <tag type="start">div
                     type="textpart"</tag>s <att>xml:id</att>s from other TEI files within the
                  project, which increases the homogeneity and precision of cataloguing. The text of
                  one or more parts of a work encoded as a <tag type="start">div
                     type="textpart"</tag>s may also be attested elsewhere. For example one of the
                  introductory texts preceding the miracle texts in manuscripts of the
                     <title>Miracles of Mary</title> contains a commemoration of Mary receiving the
                  Covenant of Mercy for the 16th <foreign>Yakkātit</foreign>. The Ethiopic
                     <title>Synaxarion</title>, a collection of daily commemorative texts, also
                  contains the same commemoration. In this case, a TEI file for this commemoration
                  has been created: <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5050Mary16Yakkatit "
                           ><title><foreign>Sǝnkǝssār</foreign> Commemoration of Mary for the 16th
                           <foreign>Yakkātit</foreign></title> (CAe 5050)</ref>.<note><p>Accessed
                        January 23, 2022, <ptr
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5050Mary16Yakkatit "/>. The numerical
                        part of work TEI files’ ID becomes the Clavis Aethiopica (CAe) reference
                        number, used to refer to the textual unit. The CAe developed by Beta
                        maṣāḥǝft sets out to become a comprehensive repertory of the Ethiopic
                        written tradition, identifying all texts with an alphanumeric string and
                        providing bibliography for them. Its aims and background are referred to in
                        Liuzzo (<ref type="bibl" target="#Liuzzo2019">2019, xxiii</ref>).</p>
                  </note> This identifier, LIT5050Mary16Yakkatit, is referred to in the
                     <title>Synaxarion</title> TEI file, <tag type="start">div type="textpart"
                     subtype="commemoration" xml:id="Yakk16KidanaM"
                     corresp="LIT5050Mary16Yakkatit"</tag>.</p>
               <p>In accordance with these principles, several TEI files have been created for the
                     <title>Miracles of Mary</title>. Typically attestation of the <title>Miracles
                     of Mary</title> is as a collection of several miracle texts, usually
                  accompanied by framing texts. While fixed sequences of miracle texts exist, this
                  collection often exhibits variation in the miracle texts and their number. <ptr
                     target="#Example2" type="crossref"/> comparing the three example manuscripts
                  above, which contain the collection, shows the variance in the beginning of the
                     <title>Miracles of Mary</title> as it becomes clear when the different parts of
                  the collection have been identified. <figure xml:id="Example2">
                     <graphic url="img/MiracleCompare1new.jpg" width="969px" height="673px"/>
                     <head type="legend">Comparison of three manuscripts showing the different
                        beginning of the collection. Accessed January 27, 2022, <ptr
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/compareSelected?mss=BLorient651,BAVet8,BLadd16192"
                        />.</head>
                  </figure> Individual miracle texts can also be attested outside of the collection
                  as guest texts added to manuscripts with a different main content. <ptr
                     target="#Example3" type="crossref"/> shows a comparison of <ref
                     target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3622Miracle"><title level="m">Miracle of
                        Mary: Homily on a potter from Syria</title> (CAe
                        3622)</ref>,<note><p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3622Miracle"/>.</p></note> in this
                  case focusing on an individual story rather than on the collection, and showing
                  the same miracle text, respectively, as part of a collection of the
                     <title>Miracles of Mary</title>, as one item in a composite multiple-text
                  manuscript, and as a guest text in the third. <figure xml:id="Example3">
                     <graphic url="img/MiracleCompare2.jpg" width="626px" height="972px"/>
                     <head type="legend">Comparison of <title level="m">Miracle of Mary: Homily on a
                           potter from Syria</title> (CAe 3622). Accessed January 27, 2022, <ptr
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/compare?workid=LIT3622Miracle"/>.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <div xml:id="Collections">
                  <head>Collections</head>
                  <p>Two TEI files have been created for the collection of the <title>Miracles of
                        Mary</title>: <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme">Miracles
                        of Mary (CAe 2384, ID: LIT2384Taamme)</ref><note><p>Accessed January 27,
                           2022 <ptr target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme"/>.</p></note>
                     for collections of the <title>Miracles of Mary</title> declared as such and
                     containing in addition to the miracle texts also framing texts, and <ref
                        target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3585Taamme">Miracles of Mary (CAe 3585,
                        ID: LIT3585Taamme)</ref><note><p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3585Taamme"/>.</p></note> for a
                     collection of more than one miracle of Mary without framing texts. The
                     existence of these two TEI files acknowledges the essential difference between
                     the <title level="a">Miracles of Mary</title> as a self-contained collection
                     and often smaller groups of Miracles of Mary. These groups of miracles
                     constitute a different category both from the collection proper and single
                     miracle texts. This system is also particularly useful when working within the
                     limits of historical catalogue descriptions. These two TEI files do not contain
                     a structure of <tag type="start">div type="textpart"</tag>s with reference to
                     individual miracle IDs in <tag type="start">div type="edition"</tag>s. This
                     system allows their use in identifying any collection of the <title>Miracles of
                        Mary</title> in a manuscript without knowing which miracle texts it contains
                     and in which order. The IDs of the individual miracle texts attested in the
                     manuscripts in question will be stated in the respective manuscript
                     descriptions only (<ptr type="crossref" target="#Example21"/>, <ptr
                        target="#Manuscripts" type="crossref"/>). This method also allows the use of
                     both collection IDs in the encoding of catalogue descriptions which do not
                     specify the identity and number of miracle texts contained in a manuscript.</p>
                  <figure xml:id="Example21">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                           <locus from="3ra" to="121va">Fols 3ra–121va</locus>
                           <title ref="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme">Taʾāmmǝra Māryām
                              "Miracles of Mary"</title>
                           <textLang mainLang="gez"/>
                           <!--    -->
                        </msItem>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Example attestation of <ref
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme">LIT2384Taamme</ref> in a
                        manuscript description.<note>
                           <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                                 target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme"/>.</p>
                        </note></head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>The scope of these TEI files and the use of their IDs within the digital
                     research environment are stated in <gi>abstract</gi><note>
                        <p>The content of <gi>abstract</gi> is among the first, and often only,
                           parts of the TEI files accessed by many users of the web application. It
                           has therefore proven crucial that all data identifying and distinguishing
                           this TEI file be offered here.</p>
                     </note> (<ptr type="crossref" target="#Example4"/>)<note>
                        <p>All examples follow the style guidelines of Beta maṣāḥəft.</p>
                     </note> and <gi>listRelation</gi> (<ptr type="crossref" target="#Example5"/>).
                        <figure xml:id="Example4">
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                           <abstract>
                              <p> The collection of the Miracles of Mary is one of the most popular
                                 works of Gǝʿǝz literature. It circulates as collections of varying
                                 constitution, of which the <ref type="work"
                                    corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5673AkkonuColl">Miracles of
                                    Mary: ʾAkko-nu bǝʾsi collection</ref> is the most standardised
                                 one. In the unpublished list compiled by William Macomber,
                                 <!--...-->
                              </p>
                              <p> This record refers to any collection of the Miracles of Mary
                                 declared as such and containing in addition to the miracles also
                                 introductory texts such as the <ref type="work"
                                    corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT1968Mashaf">መጽሐፈ፡ ሥርዓት፡
                                    ዘወጽአ፡ እመንበረ፡ ማርቆስ፡ ሐዋርያ፡ እመካነ፡ መዓልቃ፡ </ref>. For groups of
                                 miracles of Mary without introductory texts, see <ref type="work"
                                    corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3585Taamme">ተአምረ፡
                                    ማርያም፡</ref>, for the so-called <foreign xml:lang="gez">ʾAkko-nu
                                    bǝʾsi</foreign> collection of 33 miracles, see <ref type="work"
                                    corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5673AkkonuColl">Miracles of
                                    Mary: ʾAkko-nu bǝʾsi collection</ref> . </p>
                           </abstract>
                        </egXML>
                        <head type="legend"><gi>abstract</gi> of <ref
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme">LIT2384Taamme</ref>.<note>
                              <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                                    target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme"
                           />.</p></note></head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure xml:id="Example5">
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                           <listRelation>
                              <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about"
                                 ref="http://erlangen-crm.org/current/P129_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/is_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/about"
                                 active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme"
                                 passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/PRS6819Mary"/>
                              <relation name="saws:contains"
                                 ref="http://purl.org/saws/ontology#contains"
                                 active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme"
                                 passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3584Intro">
                                 <desc>
                                    <ref type="work" corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3584Intro"
                                       >Introductive exhortation to the Taʾammǝra Māryām</ref> is
                                    one of several introductory texts attested in varying sequence
                                    in manuscripts containing the <ref type="work"
                                       corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme">ተአምረ፡
                                       ማርያም፡</ref>. </desc>
                              </relation>
                              <relation name="saws:contains"
                                 ref="http://purl.org/saws/ontology#contains"
                                 active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme"
                                 passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT1968Mashaf">
                                 <desc>
                                    <ref type="work" corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT1968Mashaf"
                                       >መጽሐፈ፡ ሥርዓት፡ ዘወጽአ፡ እመንበረ፡ ማርቆስ፡ ሐዋርያ፡ እመካነ፡ መዓልቃ፡ </ref> is
                                    one of several introductory texts attested in varying sequence
                                    in manuscripts containing the <ref type="work"
                                       corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme">ተአምረ፡
                                       ማርያም፡</ref>. </desc>
                              </relation>
                              <relation name="saws:contains"
                                 ref="http://purl.org/saws/ontology#contains"
                                 active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme"
                                 passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3585Taamme">
                                 <desc> Typically, the <ref type="work"
                                       corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme">ተአምረ፡
                                       ማርያም፡</ref> contains a varying number of miracles. </desc>
                              </relation>
                           </listRelation>
                        </egXML>
                        <head type="legend"><gi>listRelation</gi> of <ref
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme">LIT2384Taamme</ref>.<note>
                              <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                                    target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme"
                           />.</p></note></head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>A TEI file has also been created for the so-called <title><foreign>ʾAkko-nu
                           bəʾsi</foreign> collection</title> of <title>Miracles of Mary</title>:
                        <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5673AkkonuColl"><title>Miracles of
                           Mary: <foreign>ʾAkko-nu bǝʾsi</foreign> collection</title> (CAe 5673, ID:
                        LIT5673AkkonuColl)</ref>.<note>
                        <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5673AkkonuColl"/>.</p></note> This
                     collection is composed typically of introductory texts and a sequence of 33
                     miracle texts. Each miracle is followed by a stanza of the hymn
                           <title><foreign>ʾAkko-nu bəʾsi</foreign></title>, which is also attested
                     in continuous form outside of the <title>Miracles of Mary</title>: <ref
                        target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT4274AkkonuB"><title><foreign>ʾAkko-nu
                              bǝʾsi</foreign></title> (CAe 4274, ID: LIT4274AkkonuB)</ref> (<ref
                        target="#Grohmann1919" type="bibl">Grohmann 1919, 322–83</ref>).<note>
                        <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT4274AkkonuB"/>.</p></note> The
                     stanzas are all thematically related to the miracle texts they follow.
                     Typically, each miracle text is also followed by a miniature. As <ptr
                        target="#Example6 #Example7" type="crossref"/> illustrate, these miniatures
                     are as fixed in their content as the text and vary only in style (<ref
                        target="#Balicka2010" type="bibl">Balicka-Witakowska 2010, 794</ref>; <ref
                        target="#Annequin1972" type="bibl">Annequin 1972</ref>): <figure
                        xml:id="Example6">
                        <graphic url="img/Miniature1.jpg" width="1915px" height="2253px"/>
                        <head type="legend">Miniature illustrating <ref
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3593Miracle"><title>Miracle of
                                 Mary: Miracle of the young girl called Mary, from Dafrā</title>
                              (CAe 3593)</ref><note><p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                                    target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3593Miracle"/>.</p></note> on
                           f. 31v of MS <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/ESdd001"
                                 ><title>Bǝḥerāwi Kǝllǝlāwi Mangǝśti Tǝgrāy, Dabra Dāmmo ʾAbuna
                                 ʾAragāwi, DD-001</title></ref> (digitized by the Ethio-SPaRe
                                 project),<note><p>See Susanne Hummel, Denis Nosnitsin, Pietro Maria
                                 Liuzzo, Eugenia Sokolinski, <title level="a">Bǝḥerāwi Kǝllǝlāwi
                                    Mangǝśti Tǝgrāy, Dabra Dāmmo ʾAbuna ʾAragāwi, DD-001</title>,
                                    <title level="j">Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens
                                    und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta
                                    maṣāḥǝft</title>, edited by Alessandro Bausi, accessed January
                                 27, 2022, <ptr target="https://betamasaheft.eu/ESdd001"
                              />.</p></note>
                           <title>Miracles of Mary</title> (1632–1664), Catalogued by Susanne
                           Hummel, image accessed on 11 November 2020. Used with permission.</head>
                     </figure>
                     <figure xml:id="Example7">
                        <graphic url="img/Miniature2.jpg" width="1280px" height="578px"/>
                        <head type="legend">Miniature illustrating <ref
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3593Miracle"><title>Miracle of
                                 Mary: Miracle of the young girl called Mary, from Dafrā</title>
                              (CAe 3593)</ref><note><p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                                    target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3593Miracle"/>.</p></note> on
                           f. 59r of <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/BLorient641">MS
                                 <title>London, British Library, BL Oriental
                                 641</title></ref>,<note><p>Dorothea Reule, <title level="a">London,
                                    British Library, BL Oriental 641</title>, <title level="j">Die
                                    Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine
                                    multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</title>, edited
                                 by Alessandro Bausi, accessed January 27, 2022, <ptr
                                    target="https://betamasaheft.eu/BLorient641"/>.</p></note>
                           <title>Miracles of Mary</title> (seventeenth century), image accessed on
                           11 November 2020. © British Library Board. Used with permission.
                           (permission given by British Library on 28.02.2021)</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>To represent this structure, the TEI file LIT5673AkkonuColl contains a
                     structure of nested <gi>div</gi>s for all introductory texts and each unit of
                     miracle text, stanza and miniature (<ptr target="#Example8" type="crossref"/>).
                     Decorative elements such as miniatures are generally not referred to in TEI
                     files for literary works, which as a general rule only deal with texts.
                     Typically, miniatures would be described in the <gi>decoDesc</gi> of the
                     manuscript TEI files, and, within the project, a TEI file would also be created
                     for typical motifs of Ethiopic manuscript decorations.<note>For the use of art
                        themes, see below <ptr target="#Art" type="crossref"/>.</note> An exception
                     has been made for the miniatures that form part of the <title><foreign>ʾAkko-nu
                           bəʾsi</foreign> collection</title> due to their standardized inclusion in
                     the work and rendering. Therefore, the IDs for each miniature’s art theme are
                     referred to in analogy to the IDs of the work TEI files of the miracle texts
                     and <title><foreign>ʾAkko-nu bəʾsi</foreign></title> stanzas.</p>
                  <figure xml:id="Example8">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <div type="textpart" xml:id="AkkColl11">
                           <label>Miracle of Juliana and Barbara from Bethlehem</label>
                           <div type="textpart" xml:id="AkkMir11"
                              corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3597Miracle">
                              <label>Miracle</label>
                           </div>
                           <div type="textpart" xml:id="AkkSta11"
                              corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT4274AkkonuB#Stanza11">
                              <label>ʾAkko-nu bǝʾsi stanza</label>
                           </div>
                           <div type="textpart" xml:id="AkkMin11"
                              corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/AT1118MMYolyana">
                              <label>Miniature</label>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Structure of the subdivisions in <ref
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5673AkkonuCol">LIT5673AkkonuColl</ref>
                        illustrated with the eleventh miracle of the collection.<note>
                           <p>Accessed 27 January, 2022 <ptr
                                 target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5673AkkonuCol"/>.</p>
                        </note></head>
                  </figure>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="MiracleRecords">
                  <head>Miracle Texts</head>
                  <p>A work TEI file was created for all known texts included in any of the
                     collections of the miracles of Mary. Though not all miracle texts are yet
                     attested independently, the significant variation in their attestation and
                     their potential independence of circulation make this the best option. The
                     titles, incipits and manuscript attestations given for miracle texts listed in
                        <ref target="#Macomber" type="bibl">Macomber (n.d.)</ref> were each encoded
                     in a dedicated TEI file.</p>
                  <p>Each TEI file for a miracle of Mary contains the title given to the miracle by
                        <ref target="#Macomber" type="bibl">Macomber (n.d.)</ref>, as well as any
                     titles given to this miracle in the literature (<ptr target="#Example9"
                        type="crossref"/>). One of the highest priorities of <title level="s">Beta
                        maṣāḥəft</title> is for its encoded data to be findable and usable for all
                     users of the web application. The inclusion and indexing of (ideally) all
                     titles used to refer to a miracle text contributes to this goal. <figure
                        xml:id="Example9">
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                           <title xml:id="t1" xml:lang="en">Miracle of Mary: Miracle of the girl
                              called Mary, from Dafrā</title>
                           <title xml:id="t2" xml:lang="en">Māryām from Dǝfrā, a child who wanted to
                              receive Communion, but was shut up in the house when her family went
                              to church</title>
                        </egXML>
                        <head type="legend">Titles of the miracle TEI file <ref
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3593Miracle">LIT3593Miracle</ref>.<note>
                              <p>Accessed 27 January, 2022 <ptr
                                    target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3593Miracle"/>.</p>
                           </note></head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>More information on the miracle text’s content may be given in a summarized
                     form in <gi>abstract</gi> (<ptr target="#Example10" type="crossref"/>). This
                     information is beneficial in newly described miracle texts, which are not
                     included in <ref target="#Macomber" type="bibl">Macomber (n.d.)</ref>.<note>
                        <p>The identification of not-yet-described miracle texts, as well as the
                           distinction of recensions and corrections of previous identifications,
                           are and will be common events as more and more manuscripts have been
                           described thoroughly. This has become particularly apparent through
                           cooperation with the PEMM project, to whose members we are very grateful
                           for their indicating several new identifications and corrections.</p>
                     </note>
                     <figure xml:id="Example10">
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                           <abstract>
                              <p>A young, devout man is sent together with a companion by his father
                                 to another city during the rainy season. As they are surrounded by
                                 the flood, he prays to God and St Mary to deliver them.
                                 Miraculously, they find no rain anymore. They arrive at the city
                                 they were sent to, and, on their return, see many soldiers. Again,
                                 the young man prays for deliverance, and in the very last moment,
                                 the soldier, who is about to rob them, repents and goes on his way
                                 without damaging them.</p>
                           </abstract>
                        </egXML>
                        <head type="legend"><gi>abstract</gi> of the miracle <ref
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5907MMRain">LIT5907MMRain</ref>,<note>
                              <p>Accessed 27 January, 2022 <ptr
                                    target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5907MMRain"/>.</p>
                           </note> identified in the cataloguing of MS London, British Library, BL
                           Oriental 652.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>Each miracle TEI file contains a <gi>listRelation</gi> with at least one
                        <gi>relation</gi>,<note>
                        <p>For the use of relations, see, accessed 27 January, 2022 <ptr
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/Guidelines/?id=relations"/>, where all
                           used values are listed, and Liuzzo (<ref target="#Liuzzo2019" type="bibl"
                              >2019, 208–11</ref>) for a conceptual overview.</p>
                     </note> between the concerned TEI file and the collection ID LIT2384Taamme
                        (<ptr type="crossref" target="#Example11"/>): by connecting the TEI files
                     LIT5108MiracleYohannes and LIT2384Taamme with <val>saws:formsPartOf</val>, this
                     relation states that the former forms a part of the latter and links all
                     miracles of Mary to the collection LIT2384Taamme, making them easily findable.
                     More relations, such as with mentioned persons, literary works or other
                     entities, or versions of the same miracle text, are possible. In <ptr
                        target="#Example11" type="crossref"/>, the relation
                        <val>ecrm:P129_is_about</val> connects the TEI file <ref
                        target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5108MiracleYohannes"><title>Miracle of
                           Mary: Yoḥannǝs finds a copy of the Acts of St Juliana and St Barbara that
                           he had lost</title> (CAe 5108, ID
                        LIT5108MiracleYohannes)</ref><note>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5108MiracleYohannes"/>.</note> with
                     entities mentioned in this miracle text, TEI files for persons PRS5789Juliana
                     and PRS2497Barbara, and the work TEI file LIT4509GadlaBarb. The relation
                        <val>lawd:hasAttestation</val> is used to connect the work with manuscripts
                     containing it and is equivalent to <ptr target="#Example21" type="crossref"/>
                     allowing the editor not to have to intervene in the cataloguing directly.<note>
                        <p>This information has been encoded from <ref target="#Macomber"
                              type="bibl">Macomber (n.d.)</ref>. Encoding the presence of the
                           miracle text in all concerned TEI files for manuscripts would be
                           preferable, but this must await a further stage of the work process.</p>
                     </note>
                     <figure xml:id="Example11">
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                           <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about"
                              ref="http://erlangen-crm.org/current/P129_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/is_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/about"
                              active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5108MiracleYohannes"
                              passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/PRS5789Juliana"/>
                           <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about"
                              ref="http://erlangen-crm.org/current/P129_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/is_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/about"
                              active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5108MiracleYohannes"
                              passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/PRS2497Barbara"/>
                           <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about"
                              ref="http://erlangen-crm.org/current/P129_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/is_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/about"
                              active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5108MiracleYohannes"
                              passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT4509GadlaBarb"/>
                           <relation name="saws:formsPartOf"
                              ref="http://purl.org/saws/ontology#formsPartOf"
                              active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5108MiracleYohannes"
                              passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme"/>
                           <relation name="lawd:hasAttestation"
                              ref="http://lawd.info/ontology/hasAttestation"
                              active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5108MiracleYohannes"
                              passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/EMML6938">
                              <desc>
                                 <locus corresp="EMML6938" target="#45r">f. 45r </locus>
                              </desc>
                           </relation>
                        </egXML>
                        <head type="legend"><gi>relation</gi>s of the miracle TEI file <ref
                              target="LIT5108MiracleYohannes">LIT5108MiracleYohannes</ref>.<note>
                              <p>Accessed 27 January, 2022 <ptr
                                    target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5108MiracleYohannes"/>.</p>
                           </note></head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>The incipits given in <ref target="#Macomber" type="bibl">Macomber (n.d.)</ref>
                     could be partly included in the work TEI files (<ptr target="#Example12"
                        type="crossref"/>).<note>
                        <p>This work has been carried out by Angela Müller. Please note however that
                           the PEMM project’s <ref target="https://pemm.cdh.princeton.edu/">incipit
                              tool</ref> is now available, which was not the case at the beginning
                           of our work.</p>
                     </note> They contribute to the growing corpus of Ethiopic text available in the
                     digital research environment.</p>
                  <figure xml:id="Example12">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit" xml:lang="gez">
                           <note> This incipit is taken from <ref type="mss"
                                 corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/EMML6938">Collegeville, Hill
                                 Museum and Manuscript Library, MS EMML no. 6938</ref>. </note>
                           <ab> ስምዑ፡ አበውየ፡ ወአኃውየ፡ ዘንተ፡ ነገረ፡ ዘኮነ፡ በእንተ፡ እግዝእትነ፡ <gap
                                 reason="ellipsis" resp="PRS6437Macomber"/> እመ፡ ምሕረት፡ በአማን፡ መሐሪት፡
                              ወመስተፍሥሒት፡ ወመናዝዚት፡ ለዘሰአለ፡ ኀቤሃ፡ በጥቡዕ፡ ልብ፡ ወበጽኑዕ፡ ሃይማኖት። ወኮነ፡ እንዘ፡ ሀሎኩ፡
                              አነ፡ ነዳይ፡ ዮሐንስ፡ እስቁፍ፡ በገዳመ፡ አስቄጥስ፡ ነገሩኒ፡ ሰብእ፡ መሃይምናን፡ ኄራን፡ ከመ፡ ሀሎ፡ አሐዱ፡
                              ብእሲ፡ ፈራሄ፡ እግዚአብሔር፡ ወያፈቅራ፡ ለእግዝእትነ፡ <gap reason="ellipsis"
                                 resp="PRS6437Macomber"/>
                              <supplied resp="PRS6437Macomber" reason="omitted">ወ</supplied> ሀገሩሰ፡
                              ድፍራ። </ab>
                        </div>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Incipit of the miracle TEI file <ref
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3593Miracle">LIT3593Miracle</ref>.<note>
                           <p>Accessed 27 January, 2022 <ptr
                                 target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3593Miracle"/>.</p>
                        </note></head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Building upon these minimal requirements, each TEI file can be expanded as much
                     as desired in adherence to the <ref
                        target="https://betamasaheft.eu/Guidelines/?id=schemaView">Beta maṣāḥəft
                        customization of the TEI Guidelines</ref>.<note>
                        <p>Accessed 27 January, 2022 <ptr
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/Guidelines/?id=schemaView"/>.</p>
                     </note> Desiderata are, for instance, the inclusion of explicits, which would
                     contribute considerably to the identification of recensions, more
                        <gi>relation</gi>s with persons and places, and more extended summaries.</p>
                  <p>Already in the earliest editions of the <title>Miracles of Mary</title>, the
                     existence of several recensions of the same miracle story was noted.<note>
                        <p>See for example Budge (<ref target="#Budge1923" type="bibl">1923,
                              208–13</ref>) for two recensions of a miracle of the monk who blew a
                           horn. Macomber (<ref target="#Macomber" type="bibl">n.d.</ref>) also
                           distinguishes numerous recensions.</p>
                     </note> It is clear that only one TEI file per miracle text would be
                     insufficient to distinguish recensions and catalogue manuscripts as precisely
                     as possible. In such cases, one TEI file has been created for each recension.
                     Additionally, one TEI file has been created for use when the recension cannot
                     be determined, for instance, when the miracle text has been listed in a
                     catalogue with only a generic title. This strategy has the necessary
                     flexibility for future adaptation: whenever new recensions of a miracle text
                     are identified, TEI files can be created for them. The relationship between a
                        <soCalled>general</soCalled> TEI file and the individual work TEI files
                     which are recensions of it is expressed in a paragraph form in the files’
                        <gi>abstract</gi>s (<ptr target="#Example13" type="crossref"/>) and through
                        <gi>relation</gi>s (<ptr target="#Example14" type="crossref"/>).</p>
                  <figure xml:id="Example13">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <abstract>
                           <p> This miracle exists in at least two recensions: <ref type="work"
                                 corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5017MiracleSophiaConfessor"
                                 >Miracle of Mary: Miracle of Sophia who distributed all her jewelry
                                 to the poor, and her husband who did not let her go to the
                                 church</ref> names the noblewoman as Sophia, while she remains
                              unnamed in <ref type="work"
                                 corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3916Miracle">Miracle of Mary:
                                 How a wealthy lady who dressed in mean attire to give alms was
                                 carried to Church by the Virgin Mary</ref> . This is the general ID
                              to be used in cases where the recension cannot be identified. </p>
                        </abstract>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Abstract of the general work TEI file <ref
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT6033MMLadyGen">LIT6033MMLadyGen</ref>.<note>
                           <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                                 target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT6033MMLadyGen"/>.</p>
                        </note></head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure xml:id="Example14">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <listRelation>
                           <relation name="saws:isVersionOf"
                              ref="http://purl.org/saws/ontology#isVersionOf"
                              active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5017MiracleSophiaConfessor"
                              passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT6033MMLadyGen"/>
                           <relation name="saws:isRelatedTo"
                              ref="http://purl.org/saws/ontology#isRelatedTo"
                              active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5017MiracleSophiaConfessor"
                              passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3916Miracle">
                              <desc>This miracle seems to be very close or nearly identical to the
                                 one edited E.W. Budge, but contains the name of the person (Sophia)
                                 and the geographical location presented here as an island in the
                                 “Northern Sea”.</desc>
                           </relation>
                           <relation name="saws:formsPartOf"
                              ref="http://purl.org/saws/ontology#formsPartOf"
                              active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5017MiracleSophiaConfessor"
                              passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme"/>
                        </listRelation>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Relations of its version <ref
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5017MiracleSophiaConfessor"
                           >LIT5017MiracleSophiaConfessor</ref>.<note>
                           <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                                 target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5017MiracleSophiaConfessor"
                              />.</p>
                        </note></head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>In the encoding of catalogues, another requirement is to state the presence of
                     a Miracle of Mary in which the content has not been identified by the
                     cataloguer. A TEI file for a single, unidentified miracle text was created to
                     answer this: <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3993Miracle"
                           ><title>Miracle of Mary: unidentified miracle</title> (CAe 3993, ID:
                        LIT3993Miracle)</ref>.<note>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3993Miracle"/>.</note> This ID can be
                     updated with the ID of the exact miracle text in question whenever a project
                     collaborator has access to the manuscript and updates the description.</p>
                  <p>Many miracle texts have been composed in cycles of individual miracles centered
                     around the same protagonist, locality, or event.<note>
                        <p>For the use of the term <term>cycle</term> and its limitations, see
                           Cerulli (<ref target="#Cerulli1943" type="bibl">1943, 158</ref>).</p>
                     </note> Different <gi>relation</gi>s have been used between them and other
                     entities such as person TEI files to group these miracle texts. <ptr
                        target="#Example15" type="crossref"/> shows the <gi>relation</gi>s of the
                     work TEI file <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5202MiracleBasilIcon"
                           ><title>Miracle of Mary: St Basil finds the buried icon of St
                           Mary</title> (CAe 5202, ID: LIT5202MiracleBasilIcon)</ref>,<note>Accessed
                        January 27, 2022 <ptr
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5202MiracleBasilIcon"/>.</note> which
                     is one in a group of miracle texts narrating apparitions of Mary to Basil of
                     Caesarea. Apart from the <gi>relation</gi>
                     <val>saws:formsPartOf</val> with the collection ID LIT2384Taamme, this miracle
                     TEI file is linked to the protagonist with <val>ecrm:P129_is_about</val> and to
                     all other miracle TEI files of this cycle with <val>saws:isRelatedTo</val> or
                        <val>saws:follows</val>. <figure xml:id="Example15">
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                           <listRelation>
                              <relation name="saws:formsPartOf"
                                 ref="http://purl.org/saws/ontology#formsPartOf"
                                 active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5202MiracleBasilIcon"
                                 passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme"/>
                              <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about"
                                 ref="http://erlangen-crm.org/current/P129_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/is_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/about"
                                 active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5202MiracleBasilIcon"
                                 passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/PRS2546Basilth"/>
                              <relation name="saws:isRelatedTo"
                                 ref="http://purl.org/saws/ontology#isRelatedTo"
                                 active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5202MiracleBasilIcon"
                                 passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3686Miracle"/>
                              <!--...-->
                              <relation name="saws:follows"
                                 ref="http://purl.org/saws/ontology#follows"
                                 active="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5202MiracleBasilIcon"
                                 passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3686Miracle"/>
                           </listRelation>
                        </egXML>
                        <head type="legend"><gi>relation</gi>s linking <ref
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5202MiracleBasilIco"
                              >LIT5202MiracleBasilIcon</ref><note>
                              <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                                    target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5202MiracleBasilIco"/>.</p>
                           </note> to the collection ID of the <title>Miracles of Mary</title>,
                           LIT2384Taamme, its protagonist, and other miracle TEI files of the same
                           cycle.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>This information has also been summarized in paragraph form in
                        <gi>abstract</gi> (<ptr target="#Example16" type="crossref"/>). Though this
                     may be considered redundant, many users prefer descriptive information to other
                     formats and thus can access the data more effectively. <figure
                        xml:id="Example16">
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                           <abstract>
                              <p> This miracle can also occur divided into two distinct miracles,
                                    <ref type="work"
                                    corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5649MMStephanites1">Miracle
                                    of Mary: The judgment of the court of Zarʿa Yāʿqob against the
                                    Stephanites (part 1)</ref> and <ref type="work"
                                    corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5650MMStephanites2">Miracle
                                    of Mary: The judgment of the court of Zarʿa Yāʿqob against the
                                    Stephanites (part 2)</ref>. There are apparently several
                                 recensions of the first part of the miracle, ending either in the
                                 stoning or repentance of the heretics. </p>
                           </abstract>
                        </egXML>
                        <head type="legend"><gi>abstract</gi> of <ref
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5248MiracleStephanites"
                              >LIT5248MiracleStephanites</ref>.<note>
                              <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                                    target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT5248MiracleStephanites"
                                 />.</p>
                           </note></head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>Encoding the <title>Miracles of Mary</title> in a flexible, potentially
                     hierarchical system consisting of IDs for different collections, units of
                     miracle texts with accompanying items, and single (miracle) texts allows the
                     precise encoding of all possible forms under which these texts are attested in
                     manuscripts. This method opens many possibilities for researching these forms
                     synchronically and diachronically.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="Art">
               <head>Art Themes</head>
               <p>The importance of miniatures in collections of the Miracles of Mary, particularly
                  in the <title><foreign><foreign>ʾAkko-nu bəʾsi</foreign>
                     collection</foreign></title>, has been already noted above (<ptr
                     target="#Collections" type="crossref"/>). The encoding of these miniatures
                  follows the <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/Guidelines/?id=artThemes"
                     >guidelines for creating art theme TEI files</ref><note>
                     <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/Guidelines/?id=artThemes"/>.</p>
                  </note> and the <ref
                     target="https://betamasaheft.eu/Guidelines/?id=decorationDescription"
                     >description of decoration in manuscript TEI files</ref>.<note>
                     <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/Guidelines/?id=decorationDescription"
                        />.</p>
                  </note> Art theme TEI files are created for recurring motifs of Ethiopic art. The
                  individual articulation of the miniatures is then described in the
                     <gi>decoDesc</gi> of the manuscript TEI files. Such art theme TEI files have
                  been created for each of the fixed set of 33 miniatures which follow the miracle
                  texts and hymn stanzas of the <title><foreign>ʾAkko-nu bəʾsi</foreign>
                     collection</title>.<note>
                     <p>I am very grateful to Jacopo Gnisci for his advice in the creation of these
                        TEI files, and his revision of them.</p>
                  </note> These art theme IDs are referred to in the work ID of the
                        <title><foreign>ʾAkko-nu bəʾsi collection</foreign></title><note>
                     <p>See above <ptr target="#Collections" type="crossref"/>.</p>
                  </note> and in the corresponding <gi>decoNote</gi>s in the manuscript TEI files.
                  Art theme TEI files contain an unambiguous title (<ptr target="#Example17"
                     type="crossref"/>), an abstract describing the typical content of this art
                  theme (<ptr target="#Example18" type="crossref"/>), and a relation to the miracle
                  TEI file this art theme illustrates (<ptr target="#Example19" type="crossref"
                  />).</p>
               <figure xml:id="Example17">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <title>Miracle of Mary: Elizabeth, the blind daughter of Abraham and Gerā
                        ʾAnǝśt of Badǝrmān</title>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend"><gi>title</gi> of the Miracle of Mary art theme <ref
                        target="https://betamasaheft.eu/AT1123MMElsabet">AT1123MMElsabet</ref>.<note>
                        <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/AT1123MMElsabet"/>.</p>
                     </note></head>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="Example18">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <abstract>
                        <p> A miniature illustrating <ref type="work"
                              corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3602Miracle">Miracle of Mary:
                              Miracle of Abraham, his wife Gerā and their blind daughter Elisabeth
                              from Badramān</ref>, typically with as a sequence of three
                           episodes/events, showing: first, the woman and her blind daughter
                           standing praying before the icon of the <ref type="authFile"
                              corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/AT1031VirginAndChild"/>; second, both
                           lying asleep before <persName ref="https://betamasaheft.eu/PRS6819Mary"
                              >Mary</persName>, who wakes up the girl; third, the girl standing
                           before the icon of <persName ref="https://betamasaheft.eu/PRS6819Mary"
                              >Mary</persName>, who takes out her breast and drops her milk into the
                           girl's eyes. </p>
                     </abstract>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend"><gi>abstract</gi> of the Miracle of Mary art theme <ref
                        target="https://betamasaheft.eu/AT1123MMElsabet">AT1123MMElsabet</ref>.<note>
                        <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/AT1123MMElsabet"/>.</p>
                     </note></head>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="Example19">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <listRelation>
                        <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about"
                           ref="http://erlangen-crm.org/current/P129_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/is_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/about"
                           active="https://betamasaheft.eu/AT1123MMElsabet"
                           passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3602Miracle"/>
                     </listRelation>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend"><gi>relation</gi> of the Miracle of Mary art theme <ref
                        target="https://betamasaheft.eu/AT1123MMElsabet">AT1123MMElsabet</ref>.<note>
                        <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/AT1123MMElsabet"/>.</p>
                     </note></head>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="Manuscripts">
               <head>Manuscripts</head>
               <p>The system developed for the encoding of work and art theme TEI files of the
                     <title>Miracles of Mary</title> can now be applied to a manuscript description,
                  encoding the historical catalogue description given in <ptr
                     target="#MiraclesEncoding" type="crossref"/>.</p>
               <p>In encoding historical catalogue descriptions, Beta maṣāḥǝft aims to interlink all
                  information contained in these TEI files to produce a searchable union catalogue
                  of the Ethiopian and Eritrean manuscript tradition. At this stage of the work
                  process, the catalogue descriptions have not necessarily been updated by
                  consultation of the manuscript. This step may be carried out at a later stage for
                  chosen manuscripts.</p>
               <p>The work described by Wright (<ref target="#Wright1877" type="bibl">1877,
                  46</ref>) (<ptr type="crossref" target="#Example1"/>) can be identified as a
                  collection of the <title>Miracles of Mary</title> with framing texts (CAe 2384, ID
                  LIT2384Taamme). We have rendered the structure of textual units within the
                  collection as described in the catalogue in the following way: <figure
                     xml:id="Example20">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <msItem xml:id="ms_i5">
                           <locus from="18r">ff. 18r- </locus>
                           <title type="complete" ref="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT2384Taamme">ተአምረ፡
                              ማርያም፡</title>
                           <textLang mainLang="gez"/>
                           <note> This manuscript contains 51 miracles before <ref target="#coloph1"
                              /> and four after it. </note>
                           <msItem xml:id="ms_i5.1">
                              <locus from="18r">ff. 18r- </locus>
                              <title type="complete" ref="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3585Taamme"
                                 >ተአምረ፡ ማርያም፡</title>
                              <textLang mainLang="gez"/>
                              <note>50 miracles of Mary</note>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem xml:id="ms_i5.2">
                              <locus from="131r">ff. 131r- </locus>
                              <title type="complete" ref="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3622Miracle"
                                 >Miracle of Mary: Homily on a potter from Syria</title>
                              <textLang mainLang="gez"/>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem xml:id="ms_i5.3">
                              <locus from="134r">ff. 134r- </locus>
                              <title type="complete" xml:lang="gez">Excerpt from <ref type="work"
                                    corresp="LIT2713Luke"/>, the dialogue of Mary and the
                                 angel</title>
                              <textLang mainLang="gez"/>
                              <incipit xml:lang="gez">ቃል፡ ዘእምወንጌለ፡ ሉቃስ፡ ውዳሴ፡</incipit>
                           </msItem>
                           <colophon xml:id="coloph1">
                              <locus target="#135v">f. 135v </locus>
                              <note> The colophon states that this manuscript was written for
                                    <persName ref="https://betamasaheft.eu/PRS10626ZaraY">Zarʾa
                                    Yāʿqob</persName> , who donated it to a church of Mary. </note>
                              ዘንተ፡ ተአምረ፡ ማርያም፡ ዘአጽሐፈ፡ ንጉሥነ፡ <persName
                                 ref="https://betamasaheft.eu/PRS10626ZaraY" role="patron">ዘርአ፡
                                 ያዕቆብ፡</persName> ወዘወሀበሂ፡ ከመ፡ ይኩን፡ ለማርያም፡ ወኢያውፅኡ፡ እምኔሃ፡ እስከ፡ ለዓለም፡
                              ዘእንበለ፡ ለአንብቦ፡ ዘንተ፡ መጽሐፈ፡ ለእመ፡ አውፅኡ፡ ውጉዛነ፡ ለይኩኑ፡ በአፈ፡ አብ፡ ወወልድ፡ ወመንፈስ፡
                              ቅዱስ፡ እስከ፡ ለዓለም፡ አሜን። </colophon>
                           <msItem xml:id="ms_i5.4">
                              <locus from="136r">ff. 136r- </locus>
                              <title type="complete" ref="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3993Miracle"
                                 >Miracle of Mary: unidentified miracle</title>
                              <textLang mainLang="gez"/>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem xml:id="ms_i5.5">
                              <title type="complete" ref="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3993Miracle"
                                 >Miracle of Mary: unidentified miracle</title>
                              <textLang mainLang="gez"/>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem xml:id="ms_i5.6">
                              <title type="complete" ref="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3993Miracle"
                                 >Miracle of Mary: unidentified miracle</title>
                              <textLang mainLang="gez"/>
                           </msItem>
                           <msItem xml:id="ms_i5.7">
                              <title type="complete" ref="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3993Miracle"
                                 >Miracle of Mary: unidentified miracle</title>
                              <textLang mainLang="gez"/>
                           </msItem>
                        </msItem>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Encoding of the description of <ref
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/BLorient650">MS London, British Library,
                           BL Orient. 650.</ref><note>
                           <p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                                 target="https://betamasaheft.eu/BLorient650"/>.</p>
                        </note></head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>For the first unidentified group of miracle texts, the ID LIT3585Taamme is
                  appropriate. The information on the number of miracle texts has been provided in a
                  paragraph form in <gi>note</gi>. Theoretically, 50 child <gi>msItem</gi>s of <tag
                     type="start">msItem xml:id="ms_i5"</tag> with the ID for a single unidentified
                  miracle, LIT3993Miracle, would also be possible, but would render the TEI file
                  cumbersome to read and offer no additional information. The miracle text
                  identified descriptively in the catalogue has been identified here with its ID,
                     <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3622Miracle"><title>Miracle of Mary:
                        Homily on a potter from Syria</title> (CAe 3622, ID
                        LIT3622Miracle)</ref>.<note><p>Accessed January 27, 2022 <ptr
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3622Miracle"/>.</p></note> The
                  following text, identified in the catalogue as the dialogue of Mary and the Angel,
                  has been identified descriptively with reference to the Gospel of Luke. The
                  colophon has been encoded in <gi>colophon</gi>. The four miracle texts following
                  it have been encoded as single <gi>msItem</gi>s, identified as <title>Miracle of
                     Mary: unidentified miracle</title> (CAe 3993, ID LIT3993Miracle). This encoding
                  outside of <val>ms_i5.1</val>, the collection LIT3585Taamme, reflects their
                  unresolved stratigraphical status.</p>
               <p>Several textual units are then listed in the catalogue as prefixed to the above.
                  They possibly constitute one or more separate units of production. As the
                  information provided in the catalogue is too scarce to reconstruct the
                  manuscript’s strata, the decision was made to not offer a hypothesis by a division
                  into <gi>msPart</gi>s, and the uncertainty in this regard has been stated
                  explicitly in a <gi>note</gi> in the first <gi>msItem</gi>. <figure
                     xml:id="Example22">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <note>The catalogue description does not allow for the correct
                           identification of this manuscript’s codicological units. It is possibly a
                           composite manuscript, but treated here in a simple manuscript description
                           until examination to avoid wrong delimitations of units.</note>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Use of <tag>note</tag> in the manuscript
                        description.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>A revision of the TEI file following consultation of the (digital) manuscript
                  would be desirable.<note><p>Such a revision would now also be possible, as the
                        digital manuscript has been made available by the British Library. Updates
                        to the description given here may appear in the future at <ptr
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/manuscripts/BLorient650/main"
                     />.</p></note> This revision would probably allow us to identify units of
                  production and split the description into the appropriate number of
                     <gi>msPart</gi>s. While awaiting this update, the current encoding reflects all
                  detail given in the catalogue and states open questions clearly.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="Conclusion">
            <head>Conclusions</head>
            <p>A flexible system of encoding the <title>Miracles of Mary</title> was developed by
               the creation of different level IDs for miracle texts and their collections. This
               system allows all levels of depth of cataloguing—from stating a particular work is
               present in a manuscript to describing each sub-part of a collection in detail. It has
               proved efficient for Beta maṣāḥǝft. Here, it accommodates the encoding of historical
               catalogues and new manuscript descriptions, both of which benefit from such
               flexibility. A historical catalogue may list all miracle texts of the <title>Miracles
                  of Mary</title> while only mentioning introductory texts in passing. One
               cataloguing project may produce an inventory, another a full catalogue.</p>
            <p>This project is laying the groundwork for further studies of the <title>Miracles of
                  Mary</title>. The continuing identification of miracle texts and their recensions
               and immediate clarification of these through the creation of TEI work files and
               relations between them will benefit future philological research on the
                  <title>Miracles of Mary</title>. All insights are immediately available to the
               interested community on Beta maṣāḥǝft.</p>
            <p>Even in the first steps of developing a consistent encoding system for the
                  <title>Miracles of Mary</title>, it has become abundantly clear that consistent
               and thorough encoding encourages best practices in cataloguing. The creation and
               interlinking of IDs for manuscripts, works, and other entities make it much easier to
               find similar manuscripts to the one catalogued. This approach improves the quality of
               catalogue descriptions. The same is true for identifying miracle recensions, which in
               the absence of a critical edition cannot be established by studying only one
               manuscript. Building upon Macomber’s work and in cooperation with many scholars
               working in the digital research environment, new recensions are continually
               identified. Much deeper encoding of this work would be possible, for instance,
               through narrative unit IDs connecting miracle texts and other works.<note>
                  <p>For the use of narrative unit IDs, see Liuzzo (<ref target="#Liuzzo2019"
                        type="bibl">2019, 83</ref>) and Villa (<ref target="#Villa2018" type="bibl"
                        >2018, 147–48</ref>).</p>
               </note> This enhancement must remain the focus of dedicated further research efforts.
               We hope that this work is one step towards a better understanding of the textual
               history of the <title>Miracles of Mary</title> within the Ethiopian tradition and
               will enable further codicological and philological study.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Annequin1972">
                  <author>Annequin, Guy</author>. <date>1972</date>. <title level="a">L’illustration
                     des Ta’amra Maryam de 1630 à 1730. Quelques remarques sur le premier style de
                     Gondar</title>. <title level="j">Annales d’Éthiopie</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                  >193–219</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="https://www.persee.fr/doc/ethio_0066-2127_1972_num_9_1_898"/> .</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Balicka2010">
                  <author>Balicka-Witakowska, Ewa</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title level="a"
                     >Täʾammǝrä Maryam in Art</title>. In <title level="m">Encyclopaedia
                     Aethiopica</title>, edited by <editor>Siegbert Uhlig</editor> and
                     <editor>Alessandro Bausi</editor>, <biblScope unit="volume">IV</biblScope>:
                     <biblScope unit="page">789b–95</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Harrassowitz Verlag</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="BalickaBausi2010">
                  <author>Balicka-Witakowska, Ewa</author>, and <author>Alessandro Bausi</author>.
                     <date>2010</date>. <title level="a">Täʾammǝrä Maryam</title>. In <title
                     level="m">Encyclopaedia Aethiopica</title>, edited by <editor>Siegbert
                     Uhlig</editor> and <editor>Alessandro Bausi</editor>, <biblScope unit="volume"
                     >IV</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">789b–93</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace>: <publisher>Harrassowitz
                  Verlag</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Bausi2016">
                  <author>Bausi, Alessandro</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">Composite
                     and Multiple Text Manuscripts: The Ethiopian Evidence</title>. In <title
                     level="m">One-Volume Libraries: Composite and Multiple Text
                  Manuscripts</title>, edited by <editor>Michael Friedrich</editor> and
                     <editor>Cosima Schwarke</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">111–53</biblScope>.
                     <title level="s">Studies in Manuscript Cultures</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Berlin - New York</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>De Gruyter</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://www.degruyter.com/downloadpdf/books/9783110496956/9783110496956-005/9783110496956-005.pdf"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Bausi2020">
                  <author>Bausi, Alessandro</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">Ethiopia
                     and the Christian Ecumene: Cultural Transmission, Translation, and
                     Reception</title>. In <title level="m">A Companion to Medieval Ethiopia and
                     Eritrea</title>, edited by <editor>Samantha Kelly</editor>, <biblScope
                     unit="page">217–51</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Brill</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Brita2020">
                  <author>Brita, Antonella</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">Genres of
                     Ethiopian-Eritrean Christian Literature with a Focus on Hagiography</title>. In
                     <title level="m">A Companion to Medieval Ethiopia and Eritrea</title>, edited
                  by <editor>Samantha Kelly</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">252–81</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace>: <publisher>Brill</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Budge1900">
                  <author>Budge, Ernest Alfred Wallis</author>. <date>1900</date>. <title level="m"
                     >The Miracles of the Blessed Virgin Mary, and the Life of Ḥannâ (Saint Anne),
                     and the Magical Prayers of ʾAhĕta Mîkâêl. The Ethiopic Texts edited with
                     English Translations</title>. <title level="s">Lady Meux Manuscripts</title> 
                     <biblScope unit="volume">2–5</biblScope>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>W. Griggs</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://digitale-sammlungen.ulb.uni-bonn.de/content/titleinfo/191631"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Budge1923">
                  <author>Budge, Ernest Alfred [Thompson] Wallis</author>. <date>1923</date>. <title
                     level="m">One hundred and Ten Miracles of Our Lady Mary</title>.
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Medici Society</publisher>.</bibl>
               <!--<bibl xml:id="Bulakh2016">
                  <author>Bulakh, Maria</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">Some Problems
                     of Transcribing Geez</title>. In <title level="m">150 Years after Dillmann’s
                        <title>Lexicon</title>: Perspectives and Challenges of Gǝʿǝz
                  Studies</title>, edited by <editor>Alessandro Bausi</editor> and <editor>Eugenia
                     Sokolinski</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">103–37</biblScope>. <title
                     level="s">Supplement to Aethiopica</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Harrassowitz Verlag</publisher>. </bibl>-->
               <bibl xml:id="Cerulli1943">
                  <author>Cerulli, Enrico</author>. <date>1943</date>. <title level="m">Il libro
                     etiopico dei Miracoli di Maria e le sue fonti nelle letterature del Medio Evo
                     latino</title>. <title level="s">Studi orientali pubblicati a cura della Scuola
                     Orientale</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Rome</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Dott. Giovanni Bardi</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Efthymiadis2014">
                  <author>Efthymiadis, Stephanos</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a"
                     >Collections of Miracles (Fifth-Fifteenth Centuries)</title>. In <title
                     level="m">The Ashgate Research Companion to Byzantine Hagiography. Volume II:
                     Genres and Contexts</title>, edited by <editor>Stephanos Efthymiadis</editor>,
                     <biblScope unit="volume">II</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                     >103–42</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Farnham–Burlington, VT</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Ashgate</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="FritschHabtemichael2020">
                  <author>Fritsch, Emmanuel</author>, and <author>Habtemichael Kidane</author>.
                     <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">The Medieval Ethiopian Orthodox Church and
                     Its Liturgy</title>. In <title level="m">A Companion to Medieval Ethiopia and
                     Eritrea</title>, edited by <editor>Samantha Kelly</editor>, <biblScope
                     unit="page">162–93</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Brill</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Getatchew1985"><author>Getatchew Haile.</author>
                  <date>1985.</date>
                  <title level="m">A Catalogue of Ethiopian Manuscripts Microfilmed for the
                     Ethiopian Manuscript Microfilm Library, Addis Ababa, and for the Hill Monastic
                     Manuscript Library, Collegeville, VIII: Project Numbers 3001–3500</title>.
                     <pubPlace>Collegeville, MN</pubPlace>:<publisher>Hill Monastic Manuscript
                     Library, St. John’s Abbey and University</publisher><ptr
                     target="https://archive.org/details/EMMLCatalog08"/>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="GetatchewNosnitsin2007">
                  <author>Getatchew Haile</author>, and <author>Denis Nosnitsin</author>.
                     <date>2007</date>. <title level="a">Marian Literature</title>. In <title
                     level="m">Encyclopaedia Aethiopica</title>, edited by <editor>Siegbert
                     Uhlig</editor>, <biblScope unit="volume">III</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">814a–17</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Harrassowitz Verlag</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Grohmann1919">
                  <author>Grohmann, Adolf</author>. <date>1919</date>. <title level="m">Aethiopische
                     Marienhymnen</title>. <title level="s">Abhandlungen der Sächsischen Akademie
                     der Wissenschaften</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">68, Abhandlungen der philologisch-historischen Klasse der
                     Sächsischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 33/4</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>Leipzig</pubPlace>: <publisher>Bei B. G. Teubner</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://digital.slub-dresden.de/werkansicht/dlf/447/9/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Gumbert2004">
                  <author>Gumbert, J. Peter</author>. <date>2004</date>. <title level="a"
                     >Codicological Units: Towards a Terminology for the Stratigraphy of the
                     Non-Homogenous Codex</title>. <title level="j">Segno e testo</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                  >17–42</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Kropp2017">
                  <author>Kropp, Manfred</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">Die ältest
                     bekannten äthiopischen Sammlungen der Marienwunder im Codex Aureus der
                     Marienkirche von Amba Gǝšen und der Bethlehemkirche bei Däbrä Tabor</title>.
                     <title level="j">Oriens Christianus</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                     >57–103</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Liuzzo2017">
                  <author>Liuzzo, Pietro Maria</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a"
                     >Encoding and Representation Challenges of the Project Beta Maṣāḥǝft:
                     Manuscripts of Ethiopia and Eritrea</title>. In <title level="m">Proceedings of
                     Balisage: The Markup Conference 2017, Washington, DC, August 1–4, 2017</title>.
                     <title level="s">Balisage Series on Markup Technologies</title>, <biblScope
                     unit="volume">19</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Balisage</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://doi.org/10.4242/BalisageVol19.Liuzzo01"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Liuzzo2019">
                  <author>Liuzzo, Pietro Maria</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title level="m">Digital
                     Approaches to Ethiopian and Eritrean Studies</title>. <title level="s"
                     >Supplement to Aethiopica</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Harrassowitz Verlag</publisher>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.2307/j.ctvrnfr3q</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Macomber">
                  <author>Macomber, William</author>. <date>n.d.</date>
                  <title level="u">Miracles of Mary</title>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Nosnitsin2010">
                  <author>Nosnitsin, Denis</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title level="a"
                     >Täʾammǝr</title>. In <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Aethiopica</title>, edited
                  by <editor>Siegbert Uhlig</editor> and <editor>Alessandro Bausi</editor>,
                     <biblScope unit="volume">IV</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                     >787a–88</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace>: <publisher>Harrassowitz
                     Verlag</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Reule2018">
                  <author>Reule, Dorothea</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">Beta
                     Maṣāḥǝft: Manuscripts of Ethiopia and Eritrea</title>. <title level="j"
                     >Comparative Oriental Manuscript Studies Bulletin</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">1 = Linking
                     Manuscripts from the Coptic, Ethiopian and Syriac Domain: Present and Future
                     Synergy Strategies</biblScope>): <biblScope unit="page">13–28</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="https://www.aai.uni-hamburg.de/en/comst/pdf/bulletin4-1/13-28.pdf"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Villa2018">
                  <author>Villa, Massimo</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">Encoding
                     Strategies and the Ethiopic Literary Heritage: The Physiologus as a Case
                     Study</title>. <title level="j">Comparative Oriental Manuscript Studies
                     Bulletin</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">1 = Linking
                     Manuscripts from the Coptic, Ethiopian and Syriac Domain: Present and Future
                     Synergy Strategies</biblScope>): <biblScope unit="page">143–50</biblScope>.
                     <ptr
                     target="https://www.aai.uni-hamburg.de/en/comst/pdf/bulletin4-1/143-150.pdf"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Wright1877">
                  <author>Wright, William</author>. <date>1877</date>. <title level="m">Catalogue of
                     the Ethiopic Manuscripts in the British Museum Acquired since the Year
                     1847</title>. <pubPlace>Piccadilly, Covent Garden–Berlin</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Longmans, Asher</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://reader.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/fs1/object/display/bsb11357511_00005.html"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Zotenberg1877">
                  <author>Zotenberg, Hermann</author>. <date>1877</date>. <title level="m">Catalogue
                     des manuscrits éthiopiens (gheez et amharique) de la Bibliothèque
                     nationale</title>. <title level="s">Manuscrits Orientaux</title>.
                     <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>Imprimerie nationale</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="http://menadoc.bibliothek.uni-halle.de/ssg/content/titleinfo/834596"
                  />.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
