<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!--$Id: jtei-hewan-214-source.xml 1070 2022-01-24 09:00:41Z pietro.liuzzo $-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Digitization of the Concise Sociopolitical and Mass-Media Dictionary (English — Amharic)</title>
            <author>
               <name><forename>Hewan Semon Marye</forename><surname></surname></name>
               <affiliation>Hewan Semon is a student of modern Ethiopian history, interested in urban social history as well as the traditions and history of the Ethiopian Orthodox Church. Hewan has just completed her <roleName>PhD</roleName>, <title level="u">The Rhetorics and Polemics of Humor in Addis Abäba Ethiopia, 2005—2019</title> at <orgName>Universität Hamburg</orgName>. Besides working on the Concise Sociopolitical and Mass-Media Dictionary, she also has short essays, translation works, and articles mostly relating to Addis Abeba and its contemporary realities.</affiliation>
               <email>hewanmarye15@gmail.com</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>22/01/2022</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt> 
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor>Tanja Wissik</editor>
            <editor>Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
            <editor>Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
            <editor>Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="rolling">Open Issue</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>dictionary</term>
               <term>edition</term> 
               <term>XML tool</term>
               <term>eXist-db</term>
               <term>Ethiopia</term>
               <term>Ethiopian studies</term>
               <term>Amharic</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Pietro Liuzzo" when="2021-04-30">Encoded from revised doc converted with Pandoc.</change>
         <change who="Pietro Liuzzo" when="2022-01-22">Updated with copyedits from latest docx version on OJS.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract"><p>The Concise Sociopolitical and Mass-Media Dictionary is an English-to-Amharic dictionary that was prepared primarily by Professor Zdeněk Poláček and digitized at the Hiob Ludolf Center for Ethiopian and Eritrean Studies (HLCEES) under the supervision of Professor Alessandro Bausi. The edition and digitization were carried out initially on Microsoft Word and then through XML using similar technology to other production work at the HLCEES. By using a lightly modified TEI Publisher application within eXist-db, this project successfully produced a 1,600-page PDF that may also be published as a book. This project note highlights the key steps taken in the process of digitizing the dictionary. It gives a succinct exploration of how TEI Publisher simplified the digitization process in comparison to Word. It also presents some of the extra revision steps that had to be taken using eXide after a dictionary entry was entered into the application. We supplement this note with figures to demonstrate these points.</p></div>
      </front>
      <body>            
         <p>The Concise Sociopolitical and Mass-Media Dictionary is an English-to-Amharic dictionary that was prepared primarily by Professor Zdeněk Poláček. It was edited and digitized at the Hiob Ludolf Center for Ethiopian and Eritrean Studies (HLCEES) from 2017 until 2020. In this brief note, I describe the project that led to a forthcoming print publication of the dictionary.</p>
         <div xml:id="firstdiv">
            <head>Dictionary Description</head>
            <p>The dictionary consists of words that are associated with the sociopolitical and mass media. Before digitization, each dictionary entry was written on a small index card with definitions and examples given as necessary. These index cards were delivered to the HLCEES in 2017 in eight boxes. In addition to these boxes, the English words beginning with A were delivered in a bound document separately from the boxes with index cards. This bound document also included the introduction to the project, the appendices, linguistic explorations by the original author, and the sources that were consulted. The HLCEES, under the guidance of Professor Alessandro Bausi and with funding from Universität Hamburg, took the manuscript to edit and create a digital version that would then be used for publication.</p>
            <p>At first, it seemed that the project would be undertaken using Microsoft Word. I worked through the introduction and the English words beginning with A from the bound document by typing the entries into Word. The dictionary entries were inserted into a two-columned table. The left-hand column included the words, in bold format, with the part of speech (noun, adjective, adverb, and so on) in italics, as well as a definition of the word if the definition was supplied in the original hand-written document. This same column gave some English-language examples, as complete sentences or phrases, of the word in use. The right-hand column included the Amharic equivalent term or the meaning of the English word in Amharic. It also included translations of the examples listed in the left-hand column.</p>
          <figure xml:id="f1">
             <graphic url="media/image1.png" width="2627px" height="1688px"/>
             <head type="legend">Entry for <term>abdicate</term>
                from the Word document</head>
            </figure>
            <p>In general, working with Word seemed simple enough. However, it was difficult and time-consuming to change the style selection that varied with each word entry, its constituent part of speech, and the usage examples. These elements had to be manually updated for each entry of the dictionary.</p>
            <p>In total, 125 pages of the dictionary were typed into Word before Professor Bausi suggested using XML instead because it would be an interesting experiment. More out of curiosity than out of necessity, we decided that some brief training on XML and its tools would be helpful to accomplish this. Professor Bausi predicted that a tool that was developed for digitizing the dictionary would also minimize the time taken to mark the different parts of speech of each word entry. At this point, we turned to the technology used by the 
               <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/Dillmann/"><title level="m">Online <emph>Lexicon Linguae
                  Aethiopicae</emph></title></ref> (<ref type="bibl" target="#dillmann150">Bausi and Sokolinski 2016</ref>)<note><p>Accessed January 22, 2022, <ptr target="https://betamasaheft.eu/Dillmann/"/>.</p></note> at the HLCEES to see what methods and tools I would be able to use to generate a digital version of the dictionary. Some of the technology used by the<title level="m">Online <emph>Lexicon Linguae
                     Aethiopicae</emph></title> could have been reused, but we eventually opted for a different workflow, which only had the use of TEI and
               <ref target="http://exist-db.org/">exist-db</ref><note><p>Accessed January 18, 2022, <ptr target="http://exist-db.org/"/>.</p></note> in common with that resource.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="xmlencoding">
            <head>XML Encoding</head>
            <p>The dictionary was digitized using a lightly modified version of an early release of the TEI Publisher application<note>
                  <p><title level="a">TEI Publisher: The Instant Publishing Toolbox</title>, accessed November
                     10, 2020, <ptr target="https://teipublisher.com/index.html"/>.</p>
            </note> within eXist-db, with a simple ODD that was dedicated to the task that used the TEI Dictionary module (see <ref type="bibl" target="#tei">TEI Consortium 2020</ref>, <ref target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/DI.html">chap. 9, <title level="a">Dictionaries</title></ref>).<note>
               <p><ptr target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/DI.html"/>. <ref target="https://dariah-eric.github.io/lexicalresources/pages/TEILex0/TEILex0.html ">TEI Lex-0</ref> would have been too restrictive and specialized a customization for this workflow, while the Dictionary module allows enough freedom. The aim of this project was not to exchange data, but only to prepare to publish a book.</p>
            </note> The application in itself was never an intended output and was used simply as a tool to obtain the PDF version of the entire dictionary for the printable book. In comparison with other dictionary projects such as the digitization and updating of Dillmann’s Lexicon (see<ref target="#dillmann150" type="bibl">Bausi and Sokolinski 2016</ref>, <ref type="bibl" target="#liuzzo2019">Liuzzo 2019, 143–159</ref>), this digitization work could not be automated, as it was started from scratch and needed a solution to support data entry as well as a professional layout of the final product. This PDF was produced with an XQuery<note><p>See <ptr target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xquery-31/"/>, accessed January 21, 2022. </p></note> script that transforms the data in XSL-FO<note><p>See <ptr target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xsl11"/>, accessed January 21, 2022. </p></note> and renders it with APACHE FOP,<note><p>See <ptr target="https://xmlgraphics.apache.org/fop/"/>, accessed January 21, 2022. </p></note> which is common practice for producing professional output (<ref type="bibl" target="#liuzzo2019">Liuzzo 2019, 219–32</ref>).</p>
            <p>As shown in <ptr target="#f2" type="crossref"/>, instead of entering every word entry into
               <ref target="https://exist-db.org/exist/apps/eXide/index.html">eXide</ref>,<note><p><ptr target="https://exist-db.org/exist/apps/eXide/index.html"/>, accessed January 18, 2022.</p></note> I entered the term, definition (in English) if available, the part of speech, and the usage examples, and then the Amharic term, definition, and examples. After each term was entered, a link to eXide for further editing was produced.</p>
           <figure xml:id="f2">
              <graphic url="media/image2.png" width="2627px" height="1688px"/>
              <head type="legend">The application data
                 entry interface</head>
            </figure>
            
            <p>After entering the data in this TEI Publisher application with the interface shown in <ptr target="#f2" type="crossref"/>, I returned
               to eXide to check if the data were appropriately marked (e.g., using italics or boldface); and if not, then I selected the particular term. For example, if a part-of-speech term (for example, <term>plural</term> [pl.]) in
               the definition or the examples provided did not appear in italics, I returned to eXide and entered <gi>emph</gi>
               around the parts of speech so the final result would be italicized.
               Another example is when a part of speech, or the entries themselves,
               needed to appear in bold. I entered <gi>orth</gi> around those phrases.</p>
            <p><ptr target="#f3" type="crossref"/> gives a sample record that presents the XML encoding for the
               word <term>abdicate</term>. It also demonstrates how the English and Amharic
               equivalents are encoded through parallel numbering.</p>
           <figure xml:id="f3">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                 <text>
                    <body>
                       <div>
                          <entry xml:id="CSPMDb389f92c-9942-46d9-89f9-2c994236d9fc" n="5122">
                             <form>
                                <orth>abdicate </orth>
                                
                                <pos>
                                   <emph>v.t.i.</emph>,<orth> -cates, -cating, -cated</orth>
                                </pos>
                                
                             </form>
                             <sense xml:lang="en">
                                <cit n="1" type="example">
                                   <quote>&lt;to&gt; abdicate from power</quote>
                                </cit>
                                <cit n="2" type="example">
                                   <quote>&lt;to&gt; abdicate one’s rights</quote>
                                </cit>
                                <cit n="3" type="example">
                                   <quote>The King decided (<emph>hon. 3rd</emph>) to abdicate.</quote>
                                </cit>
                                <cit n="4" type="example">
                                   <quote>The Queen abdicated/gave up, renounced/ (<emph>hon. 3rd</emph>) the throne in favour of the Crown Prince.</quote>
                                </cit>
                                <cit n="5" type="example">
                                   <quote>They have abdicated/have abandoned/all responsibility for the project.</quote>
                                </cit>
                             </sense>
                             <sense xml:lang="am">
                                <cit n="1" type="example">
                                   <quote>ሥልጣንን ለቀቀ (መልቀቅ)</quote>
                                </cit>
                                <cit n="2" type="example">
                                   <quote>መብቱን በራሱ ፈቃድ ተወ (መተው)</quote>
                                </cit>
                                <cit n="3" type="example">
                                   <quote>ንጉሡ ሥልጣናቸውን ለመልቀቅ ወሰኑ። ንጉሡ ከሥልጣናቸው ለመውረድ ወሰኑ።</quote>
                                </cit>
                                <cit n="4" type="example">
                                   <quote>ንግሥቲቱ ዙፋናቸውን /አልጋቸዉን/ በገዛ ፈቃዳቸው ለአልጋ ወራሹ ለቀቁ።</quote>
                                </cit>
                                <cit n="5" type="example">
                                   <quote>ፕሮጀክቱን በሚመለከት የነበራቸውን ኃላፊነት ሁሉ ለቀቁ /ተዉ/። </quote>
                                </cit>
                             </sense>
                          </entry>
                       </div>
                    </body>
                 </text>
                 </egXML>
              <head type="legend">XML
                 encoding for the word <term>abdicate</term></head>
            </figure>
            
            <p>The rendering was not checked every time for the entire PDF, but it
               was checked within TEI Publisher using <gi>modelSequence</gi> and
               <gi>model</gi>s to define the rendering. The alignment of the English and
               Amharic was simply achieved by styling a table of the two <gi>sense</gi>
               elements with <att>xml:lang</att>.</p>
            <figure xml:id="f4">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <elementSpec ident="sense" mode="change">
                     <modelSequence predicate="@xml:lang='en'">
                        <model behaviour="block">
                           <outputRendition>display: table-cell; min-width:
                              300px; padding-right: 30px</outputRendition>
                        </model>
                     </modelSequence>
                     <modelSequence predicate="@xml:lang='am'">
                        <model behaviour="block">
                           <outputRendition>display: table-cell; width: 100%; vertical-align:
                              top;</outputRendition>
                        </model>
                     </modelSequence>
                  </elementSpec>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Using <gi>elementSpec</gi> to define the table of <gi>sense</gi> elements</head>
            </figure>
            <p><ptr target="#f5" type="crossref"/> shows a sample image for the entry <term>abdicate</term> when generated
               as a PDF. We observe that this particular entry does not have an Amharic
               equivalent for the word, it only provides some examples to demonstrate
               how the word can be used.</p>
            <figure xml:id="f5">
               <graphic url="media/image4.png" width="2627px" height="1688px"/>
               <head type="legend">Image of the
                  dictionary entry <term>abdicate</term> in the output PDF</head>
            </figure>
            
            <p>Note that in the fourth example, there is no space between
               <term>abdicated</term> and the slash (<term>/</term>); we had to add one in eXide. The fifth example also presents a similar error, and neither of these errors is present in the Amharic translation of the examples. Checking for particular entries is done in the database directly using the behaviors specified in the ODD.</p>
            <p>For a user accustomed to Word, the transition to XML was not easy at first. However, it was much easier after the application was developed and after learning the most important codes for the dictionary. The application is efficient and it minimized the amount of time needed to digitize the dictionary. In comparison, Word was a great drain of time and energy. There are, of course, some things to keep in mind when using XML. One is regarding the parts of speech that are given in the definition and examples section. These have to be marked in eXide. Another is to check the spacing between words and symbols for each entry. </p>
            <p>
               Another point that has not been addressed thus far concerns tables. In the introduction of the dictionary, there are instances where short tables needed to be inserted. It was easier to create tables in Word than in eXide, but this could generally be a limit of our knowledge regarding XML. It would be useful if some of the tools readily available in Word were also accessible in eXide. But it is evident that dictionaries and works of lexicography can be edited with the tools we used in the future.</p>
            <p>TEI Publisher and ODD sufficed as a working setting for this project and, after three years of work, the dictionary was ready for publication. The output is an almost 1,600-page-long searchable PDF version of the dictionary, which will also be published in print.</p>
            
         </div>
         
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="dillmann150"><editor>Bausi, Alessandro</editor>, and <editor>Eugenia Sokolinski</editor>, eds.
                  <title level="m">150 Years After Dillmann’s
                  Lexicon Perspectives and Challenges of
                  Gǝʿǝz Studies</title>. <biblScope>Supplement to Aethiopica</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>Harrassowitz Verlag</publisher>, <date>2016</date>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="liuzzo2019"><author>Liuzzo, Pietro Maria</author>. <title level="m">Digital
                  Approaches to Ethiopian and Eritrean Studies</title>. <biblScope>Supplement to Aethiopica</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope> <pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>Harrassowitz Verlag</publisher>, <date>2019</date>. <idno type="DOI">doi:10.2307/j.ctvrnfr3q</idno>.</bibl>
               
               <bibl xml:id="tei"><author>TEI Consortium</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>. <biblScope>Version 4.1.0.</biblScope> Last updated August 19. <ptr target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html"/>.</bibl>
               
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
