<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!-- $Id: jtei-dalsasso-216-source.xml 1094 2022-02-02 09:33:18Z pietro.liuzzo $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Describing Ethiopian Bookbinding in TEI</title>
            <!-- author information in separate <author> elements per author -->
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Eliana</forename>
                  <surname>Dal Sasso</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation><!-- a prose description of this author's affiliation, containing <roleName> and <orgName>-->
                  Eliana Dal Sasso is a <roleName>doctoral researcher</roleName> at <orgName>Hamburg
                     University</orgName> affiliated with the Cluster of Excellence
                     <soCalled>Understanding Written Artefact</soCalled> of the <orgName>Centre for
                     the Study of Manuscript Cultures</orgName> with the project <title level="u"
                     >Bookbindings as Archival Instruments: Defining, Ordering and Transmitting
                     Knowledge in Christian Egypt (4th–11th centuries)</title>. She holds an MA in
                  conservation and restoration of library and archival material. In 2018 she was a
                  research guest at the Hiob Ludolf Center for Ethiopian and Eritrean Studies for
                  the study of Ethiopian bookbinding and in 2019 a research fellow at Sapienza
                  University of Rome for the ERC project <title level="u">PAThs: An Atlas of Coptic
                     Literature.</title>
               </affiliation>
               <email>eliana.dal.sasso@uni-hamburg.de</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>22/01/2022</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor>Tanja Wissik</editor>
            <editor>Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
            <editor>Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
            <editor>Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="rolling">Open Issue</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for
               journals in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking
               to publish full-text articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Ethiopian Studies</term>
               <term>bookbinding</term>
               <term>manuscripts</term>
               <term>vocabulary</term>
               <term> TEI customization</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change><!-- Description of a change to the article; we recommend using @who and @when. --></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <!-- The abstract for the article, in a couple of paragraphs. -->
            <p>Ethiopian bookbinding is one of the material expressions of the ancient manuscript
               culture of Ethiopia and Eritrea, which is the research field of the Beta maṣāḥǝft
               project. Despite the significance of the materials and techniques adopted in
               bookbinding manufacture for the understanding of the manuscript they enclose, they
               have never been systematically recorded, until very recently. The present paper
               introduces the Beta maṣāḥǝft project’s innovative approach to bookbinding
               descriptions and its customization of the TEI schema to record the small variations
               of Ethiopian bookbinding elements. Since a standard vocabulary for Ethiopian
               bookbinding features was lacking, Beta maṣāḥǝft developed a tailored taxonomy to
               create consistent descriptions. The encoding of the binding occurs in the
                  <gi>binding</gi> element, within which a <gi>decoNote</gi> element is assigned to
               each significant bookbinding feature. The descriptions consist partly of free text
               and partly of markup using keywords enforced by the taxonomy. This paper presents
               some applications offered by the Beta maṣāḥǝft project that use the recorded
               bookbinding features, and it shows how the encoding of this large amount of
               previously ignored data could open new research perspectives on Ethiopian book
               production.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="acknowledgements">
            <p>The research for this paper was funded by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG,
               German Research Foundation) under Germany’s Excellence Strategy – EXC 2176 <title
                  level="u">Understanding Written Artefacts: Material, Interaction and Transmission
                  in Manuscript Cultures</title>, project no. 390893796. The research was conducted
               within the scope of the Centre for the Study of Manuscript Cultures (CSMC) at
               Universität Hamburg.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <!-- text divisions, each with an @xml:id and <head> -->
         <div xml:id="roleof">
            <head>The Role of Bookbinding Studies in Understanding the Manuscript</head>
            <p>Looking at the codex as an object, one of its most noticeable—if present—yet
               overlooked attributes is its binding. Bookbindings capture onlookers’ gaze and
               through their design, they convey specific messages without needing the book to be
               opened. Paraphrasing Rousseau (<ref type="bibl" target="#rousseau2007">2007,
               1</ref>), it is possible to note that bindings can inspire religious veneration or
               aesthetic admiration, or simply manifest the purpose for which the manuscript was
               created. The information transmitted by the binding varies according to the materials
               and techniques adopted in the manufacture, which are determined by temporal and local
               factors. The choice of materials depends on what can be found at a precise moment in
               the place of production. Techniques, imparted by tradition, evolve across time,
               taught by one generation to the next, and assume distinctive traits according to the
               area to which they belong. Hence, the characterization of the materials and
               techniques helps to locate and date the production of the binding, while their
               fineness offers clues to the prestige of a manuscript, to its use, and to the context
               in which it is produced or transformed.<note>For a typological classification of the
                  transformations a manuscript can undergo, see Andrist, Canart, and Maniaci (<ref
                     type="bibl" target="#andrist2013">2013, 61–91</ref>). Specifically on bindings,
                  Pickwoad (<ref type="bibl" target="#pickwoad1995">1995, 213</ref>; <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#pickwoad2014">2014, 238</ref>) notes how books sold in
                  temporary retail bindings may be rebound according to the taste and the needs of
                  the owner. Velios and Pickwoad (<ref type="bibl" target="#velios2019">2019</ref>)
                  show how the CIDOC CRM ontology (<ptr target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org"/>) can be
                  used to represent the modifications (variants) of a binding across time. Beta
                  maṣāḥǝft evaluates implementing this methodology to enrich binding
                  descriptions.</note> Therefore, to understand the information transmitted through
               the binding, a careful examination of the materiality of the codex is necessary.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="bookbinding">
            <head>Bookbinding Recording: The State of the Art</head>
            <p>Despite their significance for the study of the context of production, use, and
               transformation of the manuscripts they enclose, bindings have never been
               systematically recorded (<ref type="bibl" target="#pickwoad2012">Pickwoad
               2012</ref>). This situation was common to all material aspects of the codex until
               scholars recognized the importance of codicology for a holistic understanding of the
               manuscript.</p>
            <p>Yet additional factors delayed the development of bookbinding studies in particular,
               as, for example, the scarcity of original bindings.<note>The term
                     <term>original</term> indicates the first binding the manuscript received,
                  whose manufacture is usually contemporary with the writing.</note> In fact, as a
               practice, bindings had been thrown away and replaced with new ones when they had
               deteriorated too much to perform their protective function or simply when their
               design grew out of fashion. The finely decorated covers escaped this fate more often
               than the plain ones did, which partly explains why the first studies on bookbindings
               focused on their aesthetics. Far more common is the case in which the bindings have
               been preserved thanks to the repairs they underwent through time—which, however, also
               significantly altered their original structure. To detect the modifications to which
               a binding had been subjected, distinguishing strata of original and altered elements,
               a certain familiarity with the methods of creating the codex is required. However,
               the domain of book technology has been for a long time a prerogative of craftsmen
               rather than scholars involved in manuscript studies. Therefore, the description of
               structural elements of bindings, when given, was mostly brief and inconsistent, and
               so of little use for research purposes. The lack of data regarding bookbinding
               structures constitutes a further obstacle to the development of research in the
               field.</p>
            <p>As interest in the materiality of the codex grew, structural elements of the binding
               received greater attention and pioneer scholars included them in their observations.
               The book started to be considered valuable not only for the text it carries, but also
               for its materiality, which bears witness to historical, economic, technological, and
               artistic aspects of the context in which it has been produced and used. This
               awareness led the English bookbinders Roger Powell (1896–1990) and Sydney Morris
               Cockerell (1906–1987) to develop a new approach to book conservation. The aim was to
               preserve the original elements as much as possible, balancing the need to use the
               book with the need to preserve it from further damage. Such a methodology was passed
               on to the conservators who gathered in Florence after the Arno’s flood in 1966 to
               repair the damaged books of the Central National Library, thus marking the start of
               modern conservation practice (<ref type="bibl" target="#campagnolo2020">Campagnolo
                  2020, 55–60</ref>). The study of bookbinding structures made it possible to to
               highlight the presence of recurring patterns and to group bindings accordingly, thus
               identifying macro-areas corresponding to different bookbinding traditions (Coptic,
               Ethiopic, Islamic, Byzantine, etc.). In this context, Janos A. Szirmai’s work stands
               as a milestone in the systematization of bookbinding studies (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#szirmai1999">Szirmai 1999</ref>).</p>
            <p>Recently, digital technologies have improved the quality of bookbinding records. In
               2001, their application in the Saint Catherine’s Project<note>A project by Ligatus
                  and the University of the Arts London for the conservation and preservation of the
                  library of the monastery of St. Catherine in Sinai, Egypt. See, accessed January
                  25, 2022, <ptr target="https://www.ligatus.org.uk/stcatherines/"/>.</note>
               resulted in the development of a consistent terminology—the Language of Bindings
                  thesaurus<note>The Language of Bindings (LoB) thesaurus is a reference tool for
                  the description of historical bookbinding structures created by the Ligatus
                  Research Unit at the University of the Arts London with the contributions of
                  international experts in the field of bookbinding studies. LoB is a structured
                  vocabulary, freely available to the research community, based on the Simple
                  Knowledge Organization System (SKOS) and published as linked open data (LOD). See,
                  accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr target="https://www.ligatus.org.uk/lob/"/>.</note>
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#velios2014">Velios, Pickwoad, and Martin 2014</ref>;
                  <ref type="bibl" target="#velios2020">Velios and Pickwoad 2020</ref>)—and a
               database (<ref type="bibl" target="#velios2005">Velios and Pickwoad 2005</ref>) for
               the collection and ordering of the surveyed data (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#pickwoad2004">Pickwoad 2004</ref>). After creating a relational database,
               Ligatus developed an XML schema to describe bookbinding structures (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#campagnolo2015a">Campagnolo 2015a, 141–145</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#ligatus2007">Ligatus 2007</ref>). The experience strongly encouraged the
               improvement of efficient documentation systems to obtain consistent descriptions to
               share with the research community and overcome the long-standing absence of binding
               descriptions in manuscript catalogs (<ref type="bibl" target="#campagnolo2017"
                  >Campagnolo 2017</ref>). In this framework, the Beta maṣāḥǝft<note><q><title
                        level="m">Beta maṣāḥǝft: Manuscripts of Ethiopia and Eritrea (Schriftkultur
                        des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: eine multimediale
                        Forschungsumgebung)</title> is a long-term project headed by Prof.
                     Alessandro Bausi and funded within the framework of theAcademies’ Programme
                     (coordinated by the Union of the German Academies of Sciences and Humanities)
                     under survey of the Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg. The project is
                     hosted by the Hiob Ludolf Centre for Ethiopian Studies at the University of
                     Hamburg (HLCEES).</q> See, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                     target="https://www.betamasaheft.uni-hamburg.de"/> and <ptr
                     target="https://betamasaheft.eu"/>.</note> project, whose aim is to provide a
               digital research environment for the exhaustive description of the written heritage
               of Christian Ethiopia and Eritrea, set up a protocol for bookbinding description.
               This paper presents how the project customized the TEI schema to encode peculiar
               features of Ethiopian bookbindings and collect consistent and accurate data useful
               for future research.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="object">
            <head>The Object of Inquiry: Ethiopian Bookbinding</head>
            <p>Ethiopic manuscripts were said to be <quote source="#quoteref1">bound in a very
                  simple codex form, which has in fact remained almost unchanged until the present
                  day</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref1" type="bibl" target="#szirmai1999">Szirmai
                  1999, 45</ref>), but recent studies have pointed out the existence of some
               previously unrecorded characteristics (<ref type="bibl" target="#dibella2014">Di
                  Bella and Sarris 2014</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#nosnitsin2016">Nosnitsin
                  2016</ref>) that would make us reconsider what we know about Ethiopian
               bookbinding. Indeed, it is not an immutable tradition but the technical and aesthetic
               variations are limited to detail.</p>
            <p>An in-depth description of Ethiopian bookbinding<note>Ethiopian bookbinding is a term
                  deeply rooted in literature and refers to the traditional technique used to bind
                  Christian Ethiopian and Eritrean manuscripts.</note> features is beyond the scope
               of this paper.<note>See Bausi et al. (<ref type="bibl" target="#bausi2015">2015,
                     168–70</ref>), for an overview and further references; details can be found
                  also in Di Bella and Sarris (<ref type="bibl" target="#dibella2014">2014</ref>);
                  Winslow (<ref type="bibl" target="#winslow2015">2015, 201–62</ref>); and Nosnitsin
                     (<ref type="bibl" target="#nosnitsin2016">2016</ref>).</note> Therefore, the
               general characteristics of Ethiopian binding will be only briefly introduced to
               highlight, for each structural component, the possible existing variants. This will
               make it possible to understand the challenge faced by the Beta maṣāḥǝft project in
               setting up a protocol to encode every binding in detail without renouncing the
               principle of consistency, and possibly to record enough of those small variations to
               prove the idea of their relevance.</p>
            <p>The ancient tradition of bookmaking has been handed down, and is practiced still
               today, in monastic centers as part of religious education (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#bausi2015">Bausi et al. 2015, 168–70</ref>). Traditionally, the quires,
               after being written and decorated, are sewn together to the boards with a paired
                  <term>link-stitch</term>.<note>For a detailed explanation of the technique and its
                  variations with diagrams, see Szirmai (<ref type="bibl" target="#szirmai1999"
                     >1999, 16–19</ref>).</note> Within this general category Bozzacchi (<ref
                  target="#bozzacchi2000" type="bibl">2000</ref>, <ref target="#bozzacchi2007"
                  type="bibl">2007</ref>), in his study on fifty-six Ethiopic codices kept at the
               Library of the Accademia Nazionale dei Lincei e Corsiniana in Rome, was able to
               identify and describe twelve different sewing patterns. The variability of the
               structures depends on the number of sewing stations<note>For the definition of
                     <term>sewing stations</term> see LoB, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                     target="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/1579"/>.</note> of the codex (see <ptr
                  target="#figure1" type="crossref"/>)—and thus on its dimensions—and on how the
               front board is attached to the first quire. Bozzacchi found that the binder could
               start sewing either from the center of the first quire or from the upper board. The
               thread used for sewing can be of animal (see <ptr target="#figure1" type="crossref"
               />)—probably sinew or gut—or vegetable origin. In recent times the use of synthetic
               fibers has also been documented (<ref type="bibl" target="#bausi2015">Bausi et al.
                  2015, 173</ref>).</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure1">
               <graphic width="1216px" height="789px" url="media/image1.jpeg"/>
               <head type="legend">Sewing on four sewing stations with a thread of animal origin
                     (<ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/GAet7">Grottaferrata, Exarchic Greek
                     Abbey of St. Mary of Grottaferrata, Crypt. Aet. 7</ref>)<note>See Eliana Dal
                     Sasso, <title level="a">Grottaferrata, Exarchic Greek Abbey of St. Mary of
                        Grottaferrata, Crypt. Aet. 7</title>, in <title level="j">Die Schriftkultur
                        des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                        Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</title>, edited by Alessandro Bausi,
                     accessed January 22, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://betamasaheft.eu/manuscripts/GAet7"/>.</note></head>
            </figure>
            <p>Ethiopic codices are generally bound in wooden <term>boards</term>. Literature
               reports that the most-used wood types for producing the boards are <term>Cordia
                  africana</term>, <term>Olea africana,</term> and cedarwood. However, Mellors and
               Parsons (<ref type="bibl" target="#mellors2002">2002</ref>) and Mersha Alehegne (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#mersha2011">2011</ref>) documented the use of thirteen
               further wood types. In some cases, the boards are made of stiff leather instead of
               wood, perhaps hinting at the need to use a less expensive material (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#nosnitsin2016">Nosnitsin 2016, 81</ref>).</p>
            <p>Wooden boards can be left bare or be covered with leather. Commonly the cover extends
               over the entire board but, as highlighted recently (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#bausi2015">Bausi et al. 2015, 172</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#nosnitsin2016">Nosnitsin 2016, 78</ref>), in some cases it covers only
               the spine and the back edge of the boards. Covering material that exceeds the size of
               the boards is folded over to form turn-ins.<note>For the definition of
                     <term>turn-ins</term> see LoB, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                     target="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/1694"/>.</note> The shape of these turn-ins
               varies enormously in the ways in which they are trimmed or overlapped. Furthermore,
               textiles of varying quality can inlay the inner surface of the boards (see <ptr
                  target="#figure2" type="crossref"/>). A less common feature is the presence in
               this area of a mirror, the function of which is still not clear. The cover is then
               often embellished with blind-tooled decoration<note>For the definition of
                     <term>blind-tooled decoration</term> see LoB, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                     target="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/2288"/>.</note> using a variety of tools.
               Despite some authors dedicating part of their research to the study of these tools
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#sergew1981">Sergew Hable Selassie 1981</ref>; <ref
                  type="bibl" target="#tafarra2010">Faqāda Śellāse Tafarrā 2010</ref>; <ref
                  target="#winslow2015" type="bibl">Winslow 2015</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#tomaszewski2015">Tomaszewski and Gervers 2015</ref>), a comprehensive
               classification system has not yet been developed. Even less is known about the
               recurring decorative patterns and layout of the covers.<note>The only study on the
                  topic, to my knowledge, is that of Pankhurst (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#pankhurst1984">1984</ref>). A tentative classification of bookbinding
                  tools and designs is under preparation by the author for the catalog of the
                  Ethiopic manuscripts of the Bodleian Library, a project initiated by Jacopo Gnisci
                  and Dorothea Reule with the cooperation of Eliana Dal Sasso, Solomon Gebreyes
                  Beyene, Susanne Hummel, and Massimo Villa.</note> In a few cases the boards are
               covered with metal sides<note>For the definition of <term>metal sides</term> see LoB,
                  accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr target="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/4488"
                  />.</note> or bear metal bosses (<ref type="bibl" target="#bausi2015">Bausi et al.
                  2015, 172</ref>).</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure2">
               <graphic width="1216px" height="789px" url="media/image2.jpeg"/>
               <head type="legend">Textile inlay on the inner upper board and a parchment guard
                  along the fold of the first quire (Exarchic Greek Abbey of St. Mary of
                  Grottaferrata, Crypt. Aet. 7)</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Usually, <term>endbands</term><note>For the definition of <term>endbands</term> see
                  LoB, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr target="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/2370"
                  />.</note> made of slit-braided leather tongues are added to the leather-covered
               codices, but a less common type, similar in technique to a Coptic one (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#szirmai1999">Szirmai 1999, 39, fig. 3.7a</ref>), has been
               documented on two manuscripts with bare boards (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#dibella2014">Di Bella and Sarris 2014, 293, fig. 27b</ref>).</p>
            <p>Sources of variance depend on other features, related to:</p>
            <list>
               <item>Pastedowns<note>For the definition of <term>pastedowns</term> see LoB, accessed
                     January 25, 2022, <ptr target="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/1493"/>.</note> and
                  their position in relation to turn-ins;</item>
               <item>The spine, such as the presence of a piece of parchment folded around the text
                  block and sewn with the first and last quire as a sort of spine lining<note>For
                     the definition of <term>spine linings</term> see LoB, accessed January 25,
                     2022, <ptr target="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/1619"/>.</note> (<ref
                     type="bibl" target="#dibella2014">Di Bella and Sarris 2014, 301</ref>). In
                  particular, the presence of rows of holes close to the head and tail of the quires
                  is important. This feature can be related to the former presence of endbands or
                  tackets (<ref type="bibl" target="#bausi2015">Bausi et al.2015, 159</ref>);</item>
               <item>Fastenings or traces of them (<ref type="bibl" target="#dibella2014">Di Bella
                     and Sarris 2014, 299</ref>);</item>
               <item>Parchment guards<note><term>Guards</term> (see LoB, accessed January 25, 2022,
                        <ptr target="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/1379"/>) either reinforce the folds
                     of quires (precisely defined in LoB as <term>sewing guards</term>, accessed
                     January 25, 2022, <ptr target="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/3282"/>) or attach
                     single leaves to a textblock (precisely defined in LoB as <term>extension
                        guards</term>, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/1322"/>).</note> (see <ptr
                     target="#figure2" type="crossref"/>), their position and technique of
                  attachment to the quire;</item>
               <item>Bookmark types;</item>
               <item>The traditional two-part leather slip case (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#bausi2015">Bausi et al. 2015, 172</ref>).</item>
            </list>
            <div xml:id="taxonomy">
               <head>A Taxonomy for the Description of Ethiopian Bookbinding Features</head>
               <p>The first step in the development of consistent descriptions is the use of a
                  controlled vocabulary. The adoption of a selected terminology avoids the confusion
                  which arises when different terms are used to describe the same concept.
                  Therefore, a controlled vocabulary increases the efficiency of the documentary
                  system by limiting data redundancy. Furthermore, the homogeneous descriptions
                  created following this method have the great advantage of being easily comparable,
                  thus making it easier to identify similarities and differences in a group of
                  items.</p>
               <p>For this purpose, the terminology used in binding descriptions
                     (<gi>bindingDesc</gi>)<note>See <ref type="bibl" target="#tei2020">TEI
                        Consortium 2020</ref>, 10.7.3.1: <title level="a">Binding
                        Descriptions</title>, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html#msphbi"
                     />.</note> in Beta maṣāḥǝft is partly enforced by the schema, customized so to
                  pick up keywords from a specifically conceived taxonomy. The Beta maṣāḥǝft
                  taxonomy included in each XML file within the element <gi>taxonomy</gi> contains a
                  main <gi>category</gi> for binding.</p>
               <p>The taxonomy is hierarchically structured so that broader <gi>category</gi>
                  elements corresponding to selected bookbinding features (that is, sewing pattern,
                  thread material, wood type, board lining, decoration motives, endband type,
                  guards, and bookmarks) include one or more child <gi>category</gi> elements
                  corresponding to keywords which describe the possible variants of that feature
                  (see <ptr target="#example1" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example1">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <taxonomy xml:id="ethioauthlist">
                        <category>
                           <desc>Binding Description</desc>
                           <category>
                              <desc>Endband Type</desc>
                              <category xml:id="slitBraid"
                                 corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/authority-files/slitBraid/main">
                                 <catDesc>Slit-braid</catDesc>
                              </category>
                              <category xml:id="linkStitch"
                                 corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/authority-files/linkStitch/main">
                                 <catDesc>Link-stitch</catDesc>
                              </category>
                           </category> […] </category>
                     </taxonomy>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Part of the taxonomy dedicated to the category <term>Endband
                        Type</term></head>
               </figure>
               <p>Each keyword in the taxonomy corresponds to a file in the authority-files
                  repository of the project, which is also a TEI file, to accommodate future
                  information about each of these concepts. Authority files for binding description
                  reflect the hierarchical structure of the taxonomy. They usually contain just a
                     <gi>title</gi>, a brief explanation of what the keyword stands for, and the
                  bibliographic references for the concept. This also makes the concept a published,
                  versioned, citable entity on the web with a stable identifier.</p>
               <p>Keywords are indexed in the Beta maṣāḥǝft web application so that the user can
                  visualize which bookbinding features are taken into consideration in manuscript
                  records and which keywords are used to describe their possible variants. When
                  selecting a keyword, the application displays the corresponding authority file,
                  which also shows all the occurrences of that keyword in the manuscript records
                  (see <ptr target="#figure3" type="crossref"/>).<note>See Beta maṣāḥǝft, accessed
                     January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://betamasaheft.eu/authority-files/list?keyword=slitBraid"
                     />.</note></p>
               <figure xml:id="figure3">
                  <graphic width="1216px" height="789px" url="media/image3.png"/>
                  <head type="legend"><term>Slit-braid</term> keyword displayed in the web
                     application</head>
               </figure>
               <p>The keywords are also listed in the ODD<note>ODD stands for <q>One Document Does
                        it all.</q> It is a TEI file which contains both machine- and human-readable
                     information about the choices made by the project in the customization of the
                     standard TEI schema.</note> (see <ptr target="#figure4" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure4">
                  <graphic width="1216px" height="789px" url="media/image4.png"/>
                  <head type="legend">The values in the Beta maṣāḥǝft ODD as presented in the
                     Guidelines</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Since the aforementioned Language of Bindings thesaurus (LoB) describes in detail
                  many aspects of ancient book structures, Beta maṣāḥǝft uses it as much as possible
                  in its controlled vocabulary. When the concept expressed by a keyword can be
                  related to a LoB one, the authority file is set to provide the link to the LoB URI
                  as well. The alignment with LoB is done—like other alignments in Beta
                  maṣāḥǝft—with <gi>relation</gi>. The <att>name</att> attribute permits one to
                  specify the semantic relationship between Beta maṣāḥǝft and LoB concepts by using
                  the SKOS<note>The Simple Knowledge Organization System (SKOS) is a <quote
                        source="#quoteref2">common data model for sharing and linking knowledge
                        organization systems via the Web</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref2"
                        type="bibl" target="#miles2009">Miles and Bechhofer 2009</ref>).</note>
                  semantic relation <code>skos:broader</code> or choosing a value from the SKOS
                  mapping properties <code>skos:exactMatch</code> and <code>skos:broadMatch</code>.
                  When a Beta maṣāḥǝft concept does not match an exact LoB concept but it is
                  possible to establish a sematic relation with a more general LoB concept, the
                  relation <code>skos:broader</code> is used. For example, Beta maṣāḥǝft
                  distinguishes between various hardwood types which are not defined in LoB (which
                  lists among the hardwoods only beech and oak). In this case the Beta maṣāḥǝft
                  concepts declare a semantic hierarchical relation with the more general LoB
                  concept <term>hardwood</term> by using the relation <code>skos:broader</code> (see
                     <ptr target="#example3" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example2">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <listRelation>
                        <relation name="skos:broader" active="cordiaAfricana"
                           passive="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/1386"/>
                     </listRelation>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Use of <term>skos:broader</term> for the alignment to
                     LoB</head>
               </figure>
               <p>The property <term>skos:broadMatch</term> permits one to match a Beta maṣāḥǝft
                  concept with an external concept with which there is no exact correspondence. For
                  example, LoB defines <term>board linings</term> as the pieces of sheet material
                  adhered to the boards before the book is covered.<note>For the definition of
                        <term>board linings</term>, see LoB, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/1219"/>.</note> As explained above, a
                  common board lining in Ethiopian bookbinding tradition is made of textile. Since
                  the concept <term>textile</term> in Beta maṣāḥǝft specifically refers to the use
                  of the material as board lining, it has a broad match with the LoB concept
                     <term>board lining</term>. Nevertheless, it has a semantic exact equivalence
                  with the LoB concept <term>textile</term>.<note>For the definition of
                        <term>textile</term> in LoB see, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/2470"/>.</note> The authority file
                  specifies both relations using a <code>skos:broadMatch</code> with the LoB
                     <term>board lining</term> and a <code>skos:exactMatch</code> with the LoB
                     <term>textile</term> (see <ptr target="#example3" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example3">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <listRelation>
                        <relation active="textile" passive="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/1219"
                           name="skos:broadMatch"/>
                        <relation active="textile" passive="http://w3id.org/lob/concept/2470"
                           name="skos:exactMatch"/>
                     </listRelation>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Use of <code>skos:broadMatch</code> and
                        <code>skos:exactMatch</code> for the alignment to LoB</head>
               </figure>
               <p>In this way the alignment to LoB occurs within the authority files and reflects
                  directly on each manuscript entry where the file is used. This procedure regards
                  LoB vocabulary as a semantic resource, without impacting its integrity but instead
                  improving cooperation and reuse of open data.</p>
               <p>Nevertheless, a standard terminology to refer to the specific characteristics of
                  Ethiopian bookbinding tradition was still lacking. Therefore, Beta maṣāḥǝft
                  developed a tailored terminology to offer accurate research data to the users of
                  the application as well as to encoders. Thus, keywords—normally chosen from among
                  the most frequently occurring terms in the bibliography—have been discussed among
                  Beta maṣāḥǝft team and external contributors in issues opened in the GitHub
                  repository page of the project. Once the group reached an agreement, the taxonomy
                  file was edited, an authority file was created, and the ODD was updated. When
                  necessary, parts of the Guidelines were also edited, although changes to the ODD
                  are immediately reflected.<note>See Beta maṣāḥǝft, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://betamasaheft.eu/Guidelines/?id=bindingDescription"
                  />.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="descriptions">
               <head>Bookbinding Descriptions in Beta maṣāḥǝft: A Customization of the TEI
                  Schema</head>
               <p>Manuscript records in Beta maṣāḥǝft follow the TEI Guidelines for manuscript
                  description (<ref type="bibl" target="#tei2020">TEI Consortium 2020</ref>).
                  Therefore, the description of the current binding of the manuscript is located in
                     <gi>physDesc</gi>, within <gi>bindingDesc</gi>, in the element
                  <gi>binding</gi>. As stated in the Guidelines,<note><ref type="bibl"
                        target="#tei2020">TEI Consortium 2020</ref>, Appendix C: Elements,
                        <gi>binding</gi>, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-binding.html"
                     />.</note>
                  <gi>binding</gi> can take <att>notBefore</att>
                  <att>notAfter</att> and <att>contemporary</att> when it is possible to provide
                  information on the dating of its manufacture.</p>
               <p>To produce useful data for scholars, every relevant structural element of the
                  binding should be described, thus encoded, separately. In this way, the data about
                  specific features become searchable and retrievable via the web application. Beta
                  maṣāḥǝft and other projects have developed their own ways of meeting this
                  requirement as well as solutions to cope with the issue. According to the TEI
                  Guidelines, the element <gi>binding</gi> may contain <gi>p</gi>, <gi>ab</gi>,
                     <gi>condition</gi>, and <gi>decoDesc</gi> child elements. It appears that most
                  manuscript catalogs using TEI listed in the TEI Wiki<note>See, accessed January
                     25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php?title=TEI_manuscript_catalogues"
                     />.</note> have chosen to encode binding descriptions in one or more <gi>p</gi>
                  elements, as paragraphs of free text.<note>Examples of bookbinding descriptions in
                     TEI can be found in <ref type="bibl" target="#tei2020">TEI Consortium
                        2020</ref>, Example: <gi>binding</gi>, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/examples-binding.html"
                     />.</note> This is the case, for example, with the projects
                     Manuscriptorium<note>See Manuscriptorium, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="http://www.manuscriptorium.com/en"/>.</note> and e-Codices.<note>See
                     e-Codices, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="http://www.e-codices.unifr.ch/"/>.</note> The latter does at least
                  permit filtering the bindings according to their date and isolating the
                     <term>luxurious bindings</term> (see <ptr target="#example4" type="crossref"
                  />).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example4">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <bindingDesc>
                        <binding notBefore="1646" notAfter="1646">
                           <p>Der Band wurde im Zuge der neuen <locus from="Vorderseite"
                                 >Bindung</locus>
                              <date>1646</date> neu eingefasst mit silbernen Beschlägen versehen,
                              die dem Landbuch den heutigen Namen gaben. </p>
                        </binding>
                     </bindingDesc>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Binding description in e-Codices (Appenzell, Landesarchiv
                     Appenzell I. Rh., E.10.02.01.01)<note>Appenzell, Landesarchiv Appenzell I. Rh.,
                        E.10.02.01.01, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                           target="http://www.e-codices.unifr.ch/en/description/laai/E-10-02-01-01/Rechtsquellen"
                        />.</note></head>
               </figure>

               <p>A similar approach is adopted in the ENRICH<note>European Networking Resources and
                     Information concerning Cultural Heritage. The documents related to the project
                     are available at, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="http://projects.oucs.ox.ac.uk/ENRICH/"/>.</note> Schema on which the
                  entries in Manuscriptorium are based (<ref type="bibl" target="#driscoll2010"
                     >Driscoll 2010</ref>). According to the Reference Guide (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#burnard2008">Burnard 2008</ref>), the description of the binding is
                  places in <gi>p</gi> elements and <gi>decoNote</gi> elements are used to describe
                  its decorative features.</p>
               <p>Since the FIHRST<note>Union catalog of manuscripts from the Islamicate World: see
                     accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr target="https://www.fihrist.org.uk"/>.</note>
                  and SENMAI<note>Union catalog of manuscripts of Shan Buddhist lik lu ṅ manuscripts
                     in UK and Southeast Asian collections: see accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://senmai.bodleian.ox.ac.uk"/>.</note> union catalogs are based
                  on a customization of the ENRICH schema, they structure the binding description
                  uniformly. In addition, their ODD<note>See, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://github.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/blob/231ec69b8e769d6649ae644004bc3affa39198e6/msdesc.odd#L3071"
                     />.</note> states that the <gi>term</gi> element with <att>type</att> attribute
                  marks relevant features of the binding and the <att>ref</att> attribute is used to
                  refer to the appropriate URI in the Ligatus thesaurus. Nevertheless, the link does
                  not seem to have been implemented in the records. An attempt at further
                  structuring of binding records appears in the FIHRST description of some
                  manuscripts in the Wellcome collection in London. Here the description of the
                  binding is always set in <gi>p</gi> paragraphs, but <gi>seg</gi> elements with
                     <att>type</att> and <att>subtype</att> attributes permit segmenting the
                  paragraph and describing bookbinding structural elements separately (see <ptr
                     target="#example5" type="crossref"/>). Nevertheless, the website does not offer
                  a dedicated search on bookbinding features.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example5">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <bindingDesc>
                        <binding contemporary="true">
                           <p>
                              <seg type="structure" subtype="unsupported"/>
                              <seg type="board">
                                 <dimensions type="binding" unit="mm">
                                    <height>355</height>
                                    <width>246</width>
                                 </dimensions>
                                 <material>Paper; </material>
                              </seg>
                              <seg type="covers" subtype="unattached">
                                 <seg type="spine_formation" subtype="flush"/>
                                 <material facs="#i0001">leather; </material>
                              </seg>
                              <seg type="endbands">
                                 <seg type="primary">
                                    <seg type="color"> primary endbands natural colour; </seg>
                                 </seg>
                                 <seg type="secondary">
                                    <seg type="color">secondary endbands natural colour; </seg>
                                 </seg>
                                 <desc> evidence of endband is visible.</desc>
                              </seg>
                           </p>
                        </binding>
                     </bindingDesc>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Binding description in FIHRST (London, Wellcome Trust,
                     Wellcome Collection, MS Arabic 495)<note>London, Wellcome Trust, Wellcome
                        Collection, MS Arabic 495, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                           target="https://github.com/fihristorg/fihrist-mss/blob/master/collections/wellcome%20trust/WMS_Arabic_495.xml"
                        />.</note></head>
               </figure>
               <p>A customization of the TEI schema is also used for manuscript descriptions
                  exported from Manus Online<note>See Manus OnLine, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://manus.iccu.sbn.it"/>.</note> (MOL), the Italian national
                  catalog of manuscripts. The binding description is arranged in <gi>p</gi> elements
                  where <gi>note</gi> child elements with <att>n</att> and <att>type</att>
                  attributes are added to encode the fields of MOL that do not have a corresponding
                  tag in the TEI schema (<ref type="bibl" target="#barbero2014">Barbero and
                     Trasselli 2014</ref>). In this way the boards and cover can be described
                  separately (see <ptr target="#example6" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example6">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <bindingDesc>
                        <p>
                           <origDate>1801-1900</origDate>
                           <material n="2Assi">Cartone</material>
                           <material n="6Coperta">Carta</material>
                           <note n="33" type="descrmatcoperta">dorso in pergamena</note>
                        </p>
                        <condition>
                           <p> Ha subito interventi di restauro </p>
                        </condition>
                     </bindingDesc>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Binding description in MOL (Arezzo, Biblioteca Città di
                     Arezzo, Manoscritti, 118)<note>Arezzo, Biblioteca Città di Arezzo, Manoscritti,
                        118, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                           target="https://manus.iccu.sbn.it/opac_SchedaScheda.php?ID=49065"
                        />.</note></head>
               </figure>
               <p>The Bibliothèque national de France (BnF) created the website Reliures de la
                  Bibliothèque nationale de France<note>See BnF, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="http://reliures.bnf.fr"/>.</note> which offers a selection of
                  digitized French bindings from BnF’s collection with a detailed description, using
                  a customization of the TEI schema. As stated in the ODD<note>See accessed January
                     25, 2022, <ptr target="http://bibnum.bnf.fr/reliure_20161025/index.html"
                     />.</note> and explained in the manual of use (<ref target="#lebars2016"
                     type="bibl">Le Bars et al. 2016</ref>),<note>See, accessed January 25, 2022,
                        <ptr
                        target="http://bibnum.bnf.fr/reliure_20161025/manuel/bnf_reliure_tei_manuel.html#n2.6"
                     />.</note> bookbinding descriptions may contain, beyond the elements expected
                  in the TEI schema, <gi>dimensions</gi>, <gi>index</gi>,
                  <gi>globalDescription</gi>, and <gi>structure</gi> elements. The last two elements
                  were created as part of the project to give a summary identification and
                  information on structural elements of the binding respectively (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#campagnolo2015b">Campagnolo 2015b, 98–99</ref>). The <gi>index</gi>
                  element takes a mandatory <att>indexName</att> attribute with values controlled by
                  the BnF Binding Scheme which serve to identify categories relative to the type,
                  the technique, the material, and the place of production of the binding—in a
                  similar way to the use made by MOL of the <gi>note</gi> element. An exhaustive
                  description of the binding is based on <gi>decoNote</gi> elements with
                     <att>type</att> attributes with values that specify the structural element
                  being described (see <ptr target="#example7" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example7">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <bindingDesc>
                        <binding contemporary="true">
                           <p>
                              <index indexName="typo_reliure">
                                 <term>Reliure à décor</term>
                              </index>
                              <index indexName="typo_decor">
                                 <term>Entrelacs géométriques</term>
                              </index> Reliure en <material>maroquin</material> brun jaspé</p>
                           <decoNote type="plats"> à décor d’entrelacs géométriques (structure de
                              losange et rectangle) complété de fers évidés.</decoNote>
                           <decoNote type="plat_sup">Titre <q>ivvenalis. persivs</q> et ex-libris de
                              Jean Grolier <q>io. grolierii et amicorvm.</q> dorés respectivement au
                              centre et au bas du plat supérieur. </decoNote>
                           <decoNote type="plat_inf">Devise de Jean Grolier<q>portio mea sit in
                                 terra viventivm</q> dorée au centre du plat inférieur.</decoNote>
                           <decoNote type="dos">Dos à cinq nerfs, sans décor ; simple filet doré sur
                              chaque nerf et en encadrement des caissons ; passages de chaînette
                              marqués de même.</decoNote>
                           <decoNote type="tranchefiles">Tranchefiles simples unicolores, vert
                              foncé.</decoNote>
                           <decoNote type="coupes">Filet doré sur les coupes.</decoNote>
                           <decoNote type="annexes"/>
                           <decoNote type="tranches">Tranches dorées.</decoNote>
                           <decoNote type="contreplats">Contreplats en vélin.</decoNote>
                           <decoNote type="chasses">Filet doré sur les chasses.</decoNote>
                           <!-- Description des gardes : gardes blanches ; gardes couleurs (marbrées, gaufrées, peintes, dominotées, etc.) généralement suivies de gardes blanches ; dans tous les cas, spécifier le nombre de gardes (début + fin du volume)-->
                           <decoNote type="gardes">Gardes en papier et vélin (2+1+2 / 2+1+2) ;
                              filigrane au pot.<ref>Briquet N° XX</ref>
                           </decoNote>
                           <!-- Élément qui inclut aussi bien des remarques sur la couture que les charnières, claies ou modes d'attaches des plats : tous éléments de la structure dont la description est jugée utile à la description et l'identification de la reliure-->
                           <decoNote type="structure">Defet manuscrit utilisé comme claie au
                              contreplat inférieur (visible par transparence, sous la contregarde en
                              vélin).</decoNote>
                           <condition>Traces de mouillures anciennes plus ou moins importantes au
                              bas des feuillets, qui n'ont pas affecté la reliure ; éraflure en tête
                              du plat inférieur.</condition>
                        </binding>
                     </bindingDesc>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Binding description in BnF (Paris, Bibliothèque nationale de
                     France, Réserve des livres rares, RES P- YC- 1275)<note>Paris, Bibliothèque
                        nationale de France, Réserve des livres rares, RES P- YC- 1275, accessed
                        January 25, 2022, <ptr target="http://reliures.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cdt9x5x4/"
                        />. The XML is the first example in <ref type="bibl" target="#tei2020">TEI
                           Consortium 2020</ref>, Example: <gi>adminInfo</gi> (administrative
                        information), accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                           target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/examples-adminInfo.html"
                        />.</note></head>
               </figure>

               <p>What emerges from the inquiry is that the need to encode bookbinding structural
                  elements separately is growing, but since there is no agreed structure, the
                  flexibility of the TEI schema permits projects to develop their own alternative
                  solutions. The technique used is the same: projects have added a <att>type</att>
                  attribute either to the <gi>decoNote</gi> element or to phrase-level elements
                  within <gi>p</gi>.</p>
               <p>Beta maṣāḥǝft has also customized the TEI schema to adapt it to the specific needs
                  of research on Ethiopian bookbinding. The customization of the protocol for
                  bookbinding description started with the purpose of hosting the data inherited
                  from the project Ethio-SPaRe<note>The project Ethio-SPaRe (ERC Starting Grant
                     240720) was headed by Denis Nosnitsin of the HLCES from December 2009 to May
                     2015. It was dedicated to the preservation and scientific analysis of
                     manuscripts located in Ethiopian churches and monasteries, with the focus of
                     the activities being in the Tegray region in the north of the country.</note>
                  and has been further developed within the framework of the <title level="u">Torno
                     Subito 2017</title> initiative.<note>The <title level="u">Torno Subito</title>
                     program, promoted by Regione Lazio, financed by the Regional Operational
                     Programme Lazio European Social Fund 2014–2020, aims at increasing the
                     knowledge and the professional skills of young university students or
                     graduates. In 2017 the author was granted funding to participate in the
                     activities of the Hiob Ludolf Centre for Ethiopian and Eritrean Studies and
                     thus contribute to the development of binding description in the Beta maṣāḥǝft
                     project. The second part of the project was carried out at the Italian Central
                     Institute of Cataloging (ICCU) in Rome, within the Manus OnLine project (<ptr
                        target="https://manus.iccu.sbn.it"/>), for which it was possible for the
                     first time to include in the online catalog Ethiopic manuscripts with detailed
                     codicological descriptions (16 mss. from the Exarchic Greek Abbey of St. Mary
                     of Grottaferrata, 1 ms. from the Angelica Library, 2 mss. from the Casanatense
                     Library, 5 mss. from the Library of the Accademia Nazionale dei Licei e
                     Corsiniana, 12 mss. from the Central National Library <title level="u">Vittorio
                        Emanuele II</title>, 12 mss. from the Giovardiana Library, and 19 mss. from
                     the Library of the Abbey of Casamari).</note> Despite TEI Guidelines defining
                  the <gi>decoNote</gi> element as a note describing <quote source="#quoteref3"
                     >either a decorative component of a manuscript or other object, or a fairly
                     homogenous class of such components</quote>,<note><ref xml:id="quoteref3"
                        type="bibl" target="#tei2020">TEI Consortium 2020</ref>, Appendix C:
                     Elements, <gi>decoNote</gi>, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-decoNote.html"
                     />.</note> Beta maṣāḥǝft, like BnF, decided to use it to describe bookbinding
                  structural elements, as well as the decorative elements for which it is designed.
                  The use of <gi>decoNote</gi> elements seemed more appropriate at the semantic
                  level since the content model macro.specialPara defines them as special paragraphs
                  which <quote source="#quoteref4">either contain a series of component-level
                     elements or else have the same structure as a paragraph, containing a series of
                     phrase-level and inter-level elements</quote>.<note>See the definition of the
                     content model macro.specialPara at <ref xml:id="quoteref4" type="bibl"
                        target="#tei2020">TEI Consortium 2020</ref>, Appendix E: Datatypes and Other
                     Macros, macro.specialPara, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-macro.specialPara.html"
                     />.</note></p>
               <p>Therefore, <gi>decoNote</gi> elements have been added where the structural element
                  encoded is specified within a <att>type</att> attribute. The permitted values,
                  related to the main categories of interest listed above, are: binding material,
                  boards, cover, sewing stations, endbands, endleaves, spine, fastenings, slip case,
                  other. The descriptions partly consist of free text and partly are marked up with
                  keywords introduced by using <gi>term</gi> with a <att>key</att> attribute, and
                  choosing one of the values prompted by the schema.</p>
               <p>The <code>decoNote[@type=bindingMaterial"]</code> may contain the child
                     element<gi>material</gi> to specify the materials the binding is made of, with
                  a <att>key</att> attribute equal to one of the values of the corresponding
                  taxonomy from the schema (see <ptr target="#example8" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example8">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <decoNote xml:id="b2" type="bindingMaterial">
                        <material key="wood"/>
                        <material key="textile"/>
                        <material key="silk"/>
                     </decoNote>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Encoding of binding material (Exarchic Greek Abbey of St. Mary
                     of Grottaferrata, Crypt. Aet. 7)</head>
               </figure>
               <p>In the <code>decoNote[@type="Boards"]</code> it is possible to use keywords to
                  specify the wood type—if known—and to encode the presence of a textile inlay or of
                  a mirror (see <ptr target="#example9" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example9">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <decoNote xml:id="b3" type="Boards"> The right board is broken in two halves
                        which are held together by leather strings. The left board is made from
                           <term key="cordiaAfricana">Cordia Africana</term> wood while the right
                        board is made from <term key="ficus">Ficus</term> wood. On the inner part of
                        the left board is pasted a silk <term key="textile">fabric</term>.
                     </decoNote>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Encoding of <term>Boards</term> (Exarchic Greek Abbey of St.
                     Mary of Grottaferrata, Crypt. Aet. 7)</head>
               </figure>
               <p>The cover can be described within the <code>decoNote[@type="Cover"]</code>. The
                  color of the cover can be recorded using the attribute <att>color</att><note>The
                     recording of color can be difficult because of discoloration and degradation of
                     materials over time. As stated in the Ligatus guidelines, the color is recorded
                     from protected areas, such as the turn-ins. See Pickwoad and Gullick (<ref
                        type="bibl" target="#pickwoadGullick2004">2004, 12</ref>).</note> Keywords
                  are used to encode the presence of an additional leather patch and describe the
                  decoration motifs tooled on the cover. Furthermore, it is possible to specify the
                  shape of turn-ins (see <ptr target="#example10" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example10">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <decoNote xml:id="b4" type="Cover"> Light brown leather cover with wide
                        turn-ins (up to 80 mm) and <term key="additionalLeatherPatch">additional
                           leather patch</term>. Among the turn-ins is pasted a <term key="textile"
                        />textile inlay with yellow, red and black vertical lines on a red
                        background. The blind-tooling decoration of the cover is imprecise and
                        asymmetrical. The patterns on the front and back cover differ slightly. The
                        decorative pattern shows a latin cross surrounded by a frame. The cross
                        occupies almost the entire central panel of the cover and is formed by the
                        repetition of <term key="XForm">X-Form</term> motifs within <term
                           key="tripleStraightLine">triple straight lines</term>. The same pattern
                        builds the outer frame. The extant space of the cover is divided in four
                        rectangular panels by the cross. Here, triple straight lines cross each
                        other diagonally. At the corners and intersections are <term
                           key="doubleCircle">double circles</term>, single or in groups of four. On
                        the turn-ins the triple straight lines follow the borders and at the
                        intersections groups of four double circles are found. The spine is not
                        decorated while double circles are found on the board edges. </decoNote>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Encoding of <term>Cover</term> (<ref
                        target="https://betamasaheft.eu/SHOr404">Hamburg, State and University
                        Library Hamburg Carl von Ossietzky, Cod. Orient. 404</ref>)<note>Eliana Dal
                        Sasso, <title level="a">Hamburg, State and University Library Hamburg Carl
                           von Ossietzky, Cod. Orient. 404,</title> in <title level="m">Die
                           Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                           Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</title>, edited by Alessandro Bausi,
                        accessed Janury 25, 2022, <ptr
                           target="https://betamasaheft.eu/manuscripts/SHOr404"/>.</note></head>
               </figure>
               <p>In the <code>decoNote[@type="Endbands"]</code> it is possible to encode the
                     <att>color</att> of the leather straps and specify the endband type using
                  keywords (see <ptr target="#example11" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example11">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <decoNote xml:id="b5" type="Endbands" color="red white"> Narrow <term
                           key="slitBraid">slit-braid</term> endbands and are sewn to the text block
                        using a thread of animal origin. The headband is sewn starting from the
                        upper board while the tailband is sewn starting from the lower board.
                     </decoNote>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Encoding of <term>Endbands</term> (Hamburg, State and
                     University Library Hamburg Carl von Ossietzky, Cod. Orient. 404)</head>
               </figure>
               <p>The <code>decoNote[@type="SewingStations"]</code> requires, by means of a
                  schematron rule in the ODD, that its attribute be a number as attribute, which has
                  to be equal to the number of sewing stations (see <ptr target="#example12"
                     type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example12">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <decoNote xml:id="b6" type="SewingStations">4</decoNote>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Encoding of <term>Sewing Stations</term> (Hamburg, State and
                     University Library Hamburg Carl von Ossietzky, Cod. Orient. 404)</head>
               </figure>

               <p>A further description of the sewing is possible within a general
                  <gi>decoNote</gi>, where one can encode the sewing pattern with keywords—according
                  to Bozzacchi’s classification (<ref type="bibl" target="#bozzacchi2007"
                  >2007</ref>)—and the origin of the sewing thread (see <ptr target="#example13"
                     type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example13">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <decoNote xml:id="b7"> The sewing is a chain-stitch on four sewing stations
                        (two pairs). The sewing follows the <term key="patternA">pattern A</term>
                        defined by G. Bozzacchi. For each sewing station a thread of <term
                           key="animalThread">animal origin</term> has been used. </decoNote>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Further encoding of the sewing (Hamburg, State and University
                     Library Hamburg Carl von Ossietzky, Cod. Orient. 404)</head>
               </figure>
               <p>In the <code>decoNote[@type="Endleaves"]</code> the endleaves—if present— are
                     described.<note>In Ethiopian tradition endleaves are mostly, if not
                     exclusively, sewn to textblock.</note> It is possible to add the attribute
                     <att>pastedown</att>, newly defined in the ODD, and chose up to three values to
                  specify their position in relation to turn-ins. Possible values are <val>L</val>
                  (left), <val>R</val> (right), <val>OTI</val> (over the turn-ins), <val>UTI</val>
                  (under the turn-ins) (see <ptr target="#example14" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example14">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <decoNote xml:id="b11" type="EndLeaves" pastedown="L OTI"> The inner surface of
                        the front board is covered with paper. Traces of paper are found also on the
                        external surface. </decoNote>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Encoding of <term>Endleaves</term> (Hamburg, State and
                     University Library Hamburg Carl von Ossietzky, Cod. Orient. 405).<note>Eliana
                        Dal Sasso, ʻHamburg, State and University Library Hamburg Carl von
                        Ossietzky, Cod. orient. 405ʼ, in <title level="j">Die Schriftkultur des
                           christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                           Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</title>, edited by Alessandro Bausi
                        accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr target="https://betamasaheft.eu/SHOr405"
                        />.</note></head>
               </figure>
               <p>Special characteristics of the spine—for example, a series of holes related to the
                  presence of tackets—can be recorded in the <code>decoNote[@type="Spine"]</code>
                  (see <ptr target="#example15" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example15">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <decoNote xml:id="b9" type="Spine"> Small holes are present close to the head
                        and tail of the quires, probably remains of the tackets. Quires 1, 10 and 11
                        have additional holes, perhaps traces of a previous sewing or errors
                        occurred during the preparation of the quires. </decoNote>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Encoding of <term>Spine</term> (<ref
                        target="https://betamasaheft.eu/SHOr405">Hamburg, State and University
                        Library Hamburg Carl von Ossietzky, Cod. Orient. 405</ref>)</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Within the <code>decoNote[@type="Fastenings"]</code> it is possible to describe
                  fastenings or remaining traces of them, while in the
                     <code>decoNote[@type="SlipCase"]</code> the presence and the shape of the
                  traditional leather case where the codex is kept may be recorded. Lastly, the
                     <code>decoNote[@type="Other"]</code> permits, with keywords, encoding features
                  related to guards—that is, their position in the quire and the technique of
                  attachment—and bookmarks, namely the bookmark type. Furthermore, it is possible
                  using <gi>locus</gi> and <att>target</att> to mark where the bookmarks are
                  found.</p>
               <p>In order to facilitate the work of the catalogers, guidelines for bindings
                  descriptions have been prepared<note>Many catalogers are not binding experts, and
                     the guidelines nevertheless allow them to record features relevant to the study
                     of bindings.</note> and are openly accessible to the research community (<ref
                     type="bibl" target="#liuzzo2018">Liuzzo et al. 2018</ref>).</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="current">
               <head>Current Applications and Future Research Perspectives</head>
               <p>Thanks to the flexibility of the TEI it is now possible to accurately describe
                  bookbinding features and thus gather previously unrecorded data which may enable
                  in-depth studies of the Ethiopian bookbinding tradition. The data encoded
                  according to the protocol presented in this paper are structured data that can be
                  processed and presented in many different ways (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#liuzzo2019">Liuzzo 2019, 4</ref>). Thus, the Beta maṣāḥǝft web
                  application offers the user various options for exploring the data about the
                  bindings.</p>
               <p>For example, in the <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/bindings">bindings’
                     index</ref> it is possible to filter among all cataloged manuscripts those
                  whose binding features have been described.<note>See Beta maṣāḥǝft, accessed
                     January 25, 2022, <ptr target="https://betamasaheft.eu/bindings"/>.</note> As
                     <ptr target="#figure5" type="crossref"/> shows, at the moment the research
                  environment displays several thousands entities, grouped according to their
                  features. Most of them were described by the Ethio-SPaRe project when the protocol
                  for binding description was not fully developed. For this reason, some features
                  are represented more than others in the results. When one selects a feature, the
                  app displays the shelfmarks of the manuscripts in which its description appears,
                  and the shelfmarks point directly to the entire manuscript record. The left
                  sidebar offers several options to further refine the research according to
                  categories and keywords.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure5">
                  <graphic width="1216px" height="789px" url="media/image5.png"/>
                  <head type="legend">Binding-filtered search on Beta maṣāḥǝft web
                     application</head>
               </figure>
               <p>From the results of a search a user can explore various aspects related to the
                  topic of interest—among others bookbinding. A search limited to manuscripts with
                  available images for a given selection allows the user to examine in detail the
                  appearance of selected binding features. For example filtering for
                     <term>manuscripts</term> and the keyword <term>Golden Gospel</term>,<note>See,
                     accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://betamasaheft.eu/newSearch.html?searchType=text&amp;clavistype=&amp;query=&amp;defaultoperator=OR&amp;mode=none&amp;work-types=mss&amp;termkey=GoldenGospel"
                     /></note> the search will retrieve 13 results. It is possible to refine the
                  search by limiting it to manuscripts with available images (6 results) and then
                  filtering for a specific binding material (see <ptr target="#figure6"
                     type="crossref"/>). Thus, the user can directly inspect how the material is
                  used in the manuscripts. Alternatively a view of the results as graphics can allow
                  to directly analyze distributions.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure6">
                  <graphic width="1216px" height="789px" url="media/image6.png"/>
                  <head type="legend">Faceted search for <term>Golden Gospel</term> with available
                     images</head>
               </figure>
               <p>This view of selected items as charts displays, for a group of items, the
                  correlation of the encoded bookbinding features with other manuscript data, such
                  as date and location. In a recent work, Liuzzo introduces this application (<ref
                     target="#liuzzo2019" type="bibl">Liuzzo 2019, 4–10</ref>) and explains how pie
                  or column charts in Beta maṣāḥǝft are created using Google Charts,<note>See Google
                     Charts, accessed January 25, 2022, <ptr
                        target="https://developers.google.com/chart"/>.</note> providing the tool
                  with tables of data extracted from the manuscript records. At present, in the web
                  application, when a group of manuscripts is selected, it is possible to generate
                  bar charts of how the number of sewing stations, the sewing patterns, the thread
                  material, and the binding material vary across time—if these features are encoded.
                  The charts have on the x-axis date ranges and on the y-axis the percentage of
                  manuscripts with that feature. The date ranges are both arbitrary periods of three
                  centuries (1200–1499, 1500–1799, and 1800–2099) and periods taken from the
                  canonical periodization of the project.<note>See PeriodO, accessed January 25,
                     2022, <ptr target="http://n2t.net/ark:/99152/p03tcss4qvv"/>.</note> Bars are
                  created grouping the manuscripts by date, looking at <gi>origDate</gi>. If a
                  manuscript falls within two date ranges, it is counted in both groups. The
                  percentile value allows one to compare the distribution of a feature across
                  different periods regardless of the total number of its attestations (<ref
                     target="#liuzzo2019" type="bibl">Liuzzo 2019, 9</ref>). <ptr target="#figure7"
                     type="crossref"/> shows, for example, how the sewing patterns—<term>pattern
                     A</term> and <term>pattern A3</term>—vary according to the dates of nine
                  manuscripts at the State and University Library Hamburg Carl von Ossietzky.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure7">
                  <graphic width="1216px" height="789px" url="media/image7.png"/>
                  <head type="legend">Bar chart of sewing patterns by date range for nine
                     manuscripts at the State and University Library Hamburg Carl von
                     Ossietzky</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Nevertheless, the data charted in <ptr target="#figure7" type="crossref"/> cannot
                  be taken as representative of the distribution of the sewing patterns in Ethiopian
                  manuscripts since they refer to a sample of only nine manuscripts. More relevant
                  for the representation of a phenomenon is the case when the chart analyzes data
                  from a larger sample. For example, <ptr target="#figure8" type="crossref"/> shows
                  the distribution of binding material across time for 952 manuscripts encoded by
                  the Ethio-SPaRe project.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure8">
                  <graphic width="1216px" height="789px" url="media/image8.png"/>
                  <head type="legend">Bar chart of the binding materials by date range for 952
                     manuscripts encoded by the Ethio-SPaRe project.</head>
               </figure>
               <p> </p>
               <p>The customization of the TEI schema presented here allows catalogers to record
                  accurate and consistent descriptions of Ethiopian bookbinding features. The
                  gathering of this previously unrecorded data offers the opportunity to investigate
                  the possible relationship between specific material features and the time and
                  region in which the manuscripts were produced, thus opening completely new
                  research perspectives in the field of Ethiopian bookbinding studies. Nevertheless,
                  in order for the data to be effectively representative of the Ethiopian
                  bookbinding tradition, they must be derived from a large sample of manuscripts.
                  For this reason, the new protocol for binding description needs to be applied to
                  an increasing number of manuscripts so that more data can be collected.</p>
               <p>In this way it will perhaps be possible to answer unresolved questions relating to
                  the materials and techniques available for bookbinding manufacture and the reasons
                  behind the choices of specific solutions. This study will permit both to
                  understand a specific manuscript’s history and also to shed further light on the
                  development of a craft across time and space.<note>Beta maṣāḥǝft’s bookbinding
                     description keeps developing and improving, and benefits greatly from
                     contributions by the research community.</note> Furthermore, the setup of a
                  good documentation practice, based on standardized terminology and methods, would
                  allow combining bookbinding records from different projects’ databases, thus
                  fostering comparative research.<note>For example, the PhD project on Coptic
                     bookbinding led by the present author, at the Centre for the Study of
                     Manuscript Cultures of the University of Hamburg, will offer interesting data
                     for comparison. For an introduction to Coptic bookbinding, see Szirmai (<ref
                        target="#szirmai1999" type="bibl">1999, 7–43</ref>), and for an overview of
                     Late Antique binding crafts, see Boudalis (<ref type="bibl"
                        target="#boudalis2018">2018</ref>).</note> Hence, an agreement on a standard
                  structure to adopt in binding description in TEI would foster the advance of
                  bookbinding studies.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <!-- the bibliography for the article, organized as a series of <bibl> elements inside <listBibl> -->
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="andrist2013"><author>Andrist, Patrick</author>, <author>Paul
                     Canart</author>, and <author>Marilena Maniaci</author>. <date>2013</date>.
                     <title level="m">La syntaxe du codex: Essai de codicologie structurale</title>.
                  Bibliologia 34. <pubPlace>Turnhout</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>Brepols</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="barbero2014"><author>Barbero, Giliola</author>, and <author>Francesca
                     Trasselli</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">Manus OnLine and the
                     Text Encoding Initiative Schema.</title>
                  <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> 8. <ptr
                     target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1054"/>; doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.4000/jtei.1054</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bausi2015"><author>Bausi, Alessandro</author>, <author>Pier Giorgio
                     Borbone</author>, <author>Françoise Briquel-Chatonnet</author>, <author>Paola
                     Buzi</author>, <author>Jost Gippert</author>, <author>Caroline Macé</author>,
                     <author>Marilena Maniaci</author>, et al. <date>2015</date>. <title level="m"
                     >Comparative Oriental Manuscript Studies: An Introduction</title>. Edited by
                     <editor>Alessandro Bausi</editor>, <editor>Pier Giorgio Borbone</editor>,
                     <editor>Françoise Briquel-Chatonnet</editor>, <editor>Paola Buzi</editor>,
                     <editor>Jost Gippert</editor>, <editor>Caroline Macé</editor>, <editor>Marilena
                     Maniaci</editor>, et al. <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>COMSt</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://www.aai.uni-hamburg.de/en/comst/publications/handbook.html"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="boudalis2018"><author>Boudalis, Georgios</author>. <date>2018</date>.
                     <title level="m">The Codex and Crafts in Late Antiquity</title>. <pubPlace>New
                     York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Bard Graduate</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bozzacchi2000"><author>Bozzacchi, Giampiero</author>.
                  <date>2000</date>. <title level="m">Censimento Dei Dati Materiali Dei Codici
                     Etiopici Della Sezione Orientale Della Biblioteca Dell’Accademia Dei Lincei e
                     Corsiniana.</title> Typewritten. <publisher>Roma</publisher>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bozzacchi2007"><author>Bozzacchi, Giampiero</author>.
                  <date>2007</date>. <title level="m">La Legatura Etiopica.</title>
                  <title level="s">Beni Culturali: Tutela e Valorizzazione</title> 15 (6).</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="burnard2008"><author>Burnard, Lou</author>, ed. <date>2008</date>.
                     <title level="a">The ENRICH Schema — A Reference Guide.</title>
                  <ptr
                     target="http://projects.oucs.ox.ac.uk/ENRICH/Deliverables/referenceManual_en.html"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="campagnolo2015a"><author>Campagnolo, Alberto</author>.
                     <date>2015</date>a. <title level="a">Bit by Bit: Is the Book as an Object
                     Entering the Digital World?</title> In <title level="m">I Beni Bibliografici
                     Nelle Strategie Dei Fondi Europei. Atti Del Convegno. Siracusa, ISISC, 3–4
                     Dicembre 2015</title>, edited by <editor>Alberto Campagnolo</editor>,
                     <editor>Lucia Catalano</editor>, <editor>Rosalia C. Giordano</editor>, and
                     <editor>Gabriele Lo Piccolo</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                  >91–112</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Palermo</pubPlace>: <publisher>Assessorato dei Beni
                     Culturali e dell’Identità siciliana</publisher>; <publisher>Dipartimento B.C. e
                     I.S.</publisher></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="campagnolo2015b"><author>Campagnolo, Alberto</author>.
                     <date>2015</date>b. <title level="u">Transforming Structured Descriptions to
                     Visual Representations: An Automated Visualization of Historical Bookbinding
                     Structures.</title> PhD diss., <publisher>University of the Arts
                     London</publisher>. <ptr target="http://ualresearchonline.arts.ac.uk/8749/"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="campagnolo2017"><author>Campagnolo, Alberto</author>.
                  <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">Bookbinding Information on the Web: Breaking
                     the Circle, from Pixels to Linked Open Data.</title>
                  <title level="j">International Information &amp; Library Review</title> 49 (1):
                     <biblScope unit="page">37–50</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.1080/10572317.2017.1270689</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="campagnolo2020"><author>Campagnolo, Alberto</author>.
                  <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">Conservation and Digitization: A Difficult
                     Balance?</title> In <title level="m">Book Conservation and Digitization: The
                     Challenges of Dialogue and Collaboration</title>, edited by <editor>Alberto
                     Campagnolo</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">49–82</biblScope>. Collection
                  Development, Cultural Heritage, and Digital Humanities.
                  <pubPlace>Leeds</pubPlace>: <publisher>Arc Humanities Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="dibella2014"><author>Di Bella, Marco</author>, and <author>Nikolas
                     Sarris</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">Field Conservation in East
                     Tigray, Ethiopia.</title> In <title level="m">Care and Conservation of
                     Manuscripts 14. Proceedings of the Fourteenth International Seminar Held at the
                     University of Copenhagen 17th-19th October 2012</title>, edited by
                     <editor>Matthew James Driscoll</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >271–307</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Copenhagen</pubPlace>: <publisher>Museum
                     Tusculanum Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="driscoll2010"><author>Driscoll, Matthew James</author>.
                     <date>2010</date>. <title level="a">The ENRICH project: Towards a European
                     Digital Manuscript Library.</title>
                  <title level="j">DigItalia</title> 2: <biblScope unit="page">117–22</biblScope>.
                     <ptr target="http://digitalia.sbn.it/article/view/243"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tafarra2010"><author>Faqāda Śellāsē Tafarrā</author>. AM 2002 /
                     <date>2010</date> CE. ጥንታዊ የብራና መጻሕፍት አዘጋጃጀት (<title level="m">Ṭentāwi
                     yaberānnā</title>
                  <title level="m">maṣāḥeft azzagāǧāǧat</title>, <title level="m">The ancient manner
                     of preparing parchment books</title>). <pubPlace>Addis Ababa</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Addis Ababā Yunivarsiti Prēss</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="lebars2016"><author>Le Bars, Fabienne</author>, <author>Anna
                     Markova</author>, <author>Florence Clavaud</author>, and <author>Lauranne
                     Bertrand</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="m">Encodage des reliures
                     numérisées de la Bibliothèque nationale de France. Manuel et Dictionnaire des
                     balises</title> (version 3). <ptr
                     target="http://bibnum.bnf.fr/reliure_20161025/manuel/bnf_reliure_tei_manuel.html#n2.6"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ligatus2007"><author>Ligatus</author>. <date>2007</date>. <title
                     level="m">Printed Books Survey Schema (version 1.8). XML.</title>
                  <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Ligatus Research Centre</publisher>,
                     <publisher>CCW Graduate School</publisher>, <publisher>University of the Arts
                     London</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="http://www.ligatus.org.uk/stcatherines/sites/ligatus.org.uk.stcatherines/files/basic-1.8_0.xsd"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="liuzzo2019"><author>Liuzzo, Pietro Maria</author>. <date>2019</date>.
                     <title level="m">Digital Approaches to Ethiopian and Eritrean Studies</title>.
                     <title level="s">Supplement to Aethiopica</title> 8.
                     <pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace>: <publisher>Harrassowitz Verlag</publisher>.
                     doi:<idno type="DOI">10.2307/j.ctvrnfr3q</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="liuzzo2018"><author>Liuzzo, Pietro Maria</author>, <author>Dorothea
                     Reule</author>, <author>Eugenia Sokolinski</author>, <author>Solomon
                     Gebreyes</author>, <author>Daria Elagina</author>, <author>Denis
                     Nosnitsin</author>, <author>Eliana Dal Sasso</author>, and <author>Jacopo
                     Gnisci</author>. <date>2018–</date>. <title level="m">Beta Maṣāḥǝft
                     Guidelines.</title>
                  <ptr target="https://betamasaheft.eu/Guidelines/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="mellors2002"><author>Mellors, John</author>, and <author>Anne
                     Parsons</author>. <date>2002</date>. <title level="m">Bookmaking in Rural
                     Ethiopia in the Twenty-First Century: Ethiopian Bookmaking</title>.
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>New Cross Books</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="mersha2011"><author>Mersha Alehegne</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title
                     level="a">Towards a Glossary of Ethiopian Manuscript Culture and
                     Practice.</title>
                  <title level="j">Aethiopica</title> 14: 145–62. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.15460/aethiopica.14.1.417</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="miles2009"><author>Miles, Alistair</author>, and <author>Sean
                     Bechhofer</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="m">SKOS Simple Knowledge
                     Organization System Reference. W3C Recommendation 18 August 2009.</title> W3C.
                  Accessed March 31, 2021. <ptr target="https://www.w3.org/TR/skos-reference/"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="nosnitsin2016"><author>Nosnitsin, Denis</author>. <date>2016</date>.
                     <title level="a">Lesser Known Features of the Ethiopian Codex.</title> In
                     <title level="m">Movements in Ethiopia, Ethiopia in Movement. Proceedings of
                     the 18th International Conference of Ethiopian Studies</title>, edited by
                     <editor>Eloi Ficquet</editor>, <editor>Ahmed Hassen</editor>, and
                     <editor>Thomas Osmond</editor>, 1:75–90. <pubPlace>Addis Ababa</pubPlace> and
                     <pubPlace>Los Angeles</pubPlace>: <publisher>CFEE–IES</publisher> and
                     <publisher>Tsehai Publishers</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pankhurst1984"><author>Pankhurst, Richard</author>. <date>1984</date>.
                     <title level="m">Ethiopian Manuscript Bindings and Their Decoration.</title>
                  <publisher>Abbay</publisher>, <biblScope unit="page">205–57</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pickwoad1995"><author>Pickwoad, Nicholas</author>. <date>1995</date>.
                     <title level="a">The Interpretation of Bookbinding Structure An Examination of
                     Sixteenth-Century Bindings in the Ramey Collection in the Pierpont Morgan
                     Library.</title>
                  <title level="j">The Library</title>, 6th ser., 17 (3): <biblScope unit="page"
                     >209–49</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                  >10.1093/library/s6-17.3.209</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pickwoad2004"><author>Pickwoad, Nicholas</author>. <date>2004</date>.
                     <title level="a">The Condition Survey of the Manuscripts in the Monastery of
                     Saint Catherine on Mount Sinai.</title>
                  <title level="j">The Paper Conservator</title> 28 (1): <biblScope unit="page"
                     >33–61</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                  >10.1080/03094227.2004.9638640</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pickwoad2012"><author>Pickwoad, Nicholas</author>. <date>2012</date>.
                     <title level="a">An Unused Resource: Bringing the Study of Bookbindings out of
                     the Ghetto.</title> In <title level="m">Ambassadors of the Book: Competences
                     and Training for Heritage Librarians</title>, edited by <editor>Raphaële
                     Mouren</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">83–94</biblScope>. IFLA Publications
                  160. <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>: <publisher>De Gruyter Saur</publisher>.
                     doi:<idno type="DOI">10.1515/9783110301502.83</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pickwoad2014"><author>Pickwoad, Nicholas</author>. <date>2014</date>.
                     <title level="a">The Structures and Materials of Commercial Bookbindings in the
                     Arcadian Library</title>. In <title level="m">The Arcadian Library: Bindings
                     and Provenance</title>, edited by <editor>Giles Mandelbrote</editor> and
                     <editor>Willem A. C. de Bruijn</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >233–278</biblScope>. Studies in the Arcadian Library 9.
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Arcadian Library in association with
                     Oxford University Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pickwoadGullick2004"><author>Pickwoad, Nicholas</author>, and
                     <author>Michael Gullick</author>. <date>2004</date>. <title level="m"
                     >Assessment Manual: A Guide to the Survey Forms to Be Used in St Catherine’s
                     Monastery</title>, <ptr
                     target="http://www.ligatus.org.uk/sites/default/files/manual20050110.pdf"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="rousseau2007"><author>Rousseau, Philip</author>. <date>2007</date>.
                     <title level="a">Introduction: From Binding to Burning.</title> In <title
                     level="m">The Early Christian Book</title>, edited by <editor>William E.
                     Klingshirn</editor> and <editor>Linda Safran</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >1–9</biblScope>. CUA Studies in Early Christianity. <pubPlace>Washington,
                     DC</pubPlace>:<publisher> Catholic University of America Press</publisher>.
                     doi:<idno type="DOI">10.2307/j.ctt2853v4.6</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="sergew1981"><author>Sergew Hable Selassie</author>. <date>1981</date>.
                     <title level="m">Bookmaking in Ethiopia</title>. <pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Karstens Drukkers</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="szirmai1999"><author>Szirmai, Janos A.</author>
                  <date>1999</date>. <title level="m">The Archaeology of Medieval
                     Bookbinding</title>. <pubPlace>Aldershot</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Ashgate</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tei2020"><author>TEI Consortium</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title
                     level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                     Interchange</title>. Version 4.1.0. Last updated August 19. <ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tomaszewski2015"><author>Tomaszewski, Jacek</author>, and
                     <author>Michael Gervers</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title level="a"
                     >Technological Aspects of the Monastic Manuscript Collection at May Wäyni,
                     Ethiopia.</title> In <title level="m">From Dust to Digital: Ten Years of the
                     Endangered Archives Programme</title>, edited by <editor>Maja Kominko</editor>,
                     <biblScope unit="page">89–133</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Open Book Publishers</publisher>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.11647/OBP.0052.04</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="velios2005"><author>Velios, Athanasios</author>, and <author>Nicholas
                     Pickwoad</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title level="a">Current Use and Future
                     Development of the Database of the St. Catherine’s Library Conservation
                     Project</title>, <title level="j">The Paper Conservator</title> 29 (1):
                     <biblScope unit="page">39–53</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.1080/03094227.2005.9638486</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="velios2019"><author>Velios, Athanasios</author>, and <author>Nicholas
                     Pickwoad</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title level="a">Versioning Materiality:
                     Documenting Evidence of Past Binding Structures.</title> In <title level="m"
                     >Versioning Cultural Objects: Digital Approaches</title>, edited by
                     <editor>Roman Bleier</editor> and <editor>Sean M. Winslow</editor>, <biblScope
                     unit="page">103–26</biblScope>. Schriften des Instituts für Dokumentologie und
                  Editorik, Bd. 13. <pubPlace>Nordstedt</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>BoD</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="velios2020"><author>Velios, Athanasios</author>, and <author>Nicholas
                     Pickwoad</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">The Development of the
                     Language of Bindings Thesaurus.</title> In <title level="m">Book Conservation
                     and Digitization. The Challenges of Dialogue and Collaboration</title>, edited
                  by <editor>Alberto Campagnolo</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">157–68</biblScope>.
                  Collection Development, Cultural Heritage, and Digital Humanities.
                     <pubPlace>Leeds</pubPlace>: <publisher>Arc Humanities Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="velios2014"><author>Velios, Athanasios</author>, <author>Nicholas
                     Pickwood [sic]</author>, and <author> Aurelie Martin</author>.
                     <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">Multilingual Bookbinding Terms: Complex
                     Conceptual Issues</title>, <title level="j">Newsletter of the ICOM
                     CIDOC</title>: <biblScope unit="page">15–20</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="https://cidoc.mini.icom.museum/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2018/12/CIDOC_Newsletter_2014.pdf"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="winslow2015"><author>Winslow, Sean M</author>. <date>2015</date>.
                     <title level="u">Ethiopian Manuscript Culture: Practices and Contexts.</title>
                  PhD diss., <publisher>University of Toronto</publisher>
                  <ptr target="https://tspace.library.utoronto.ca/handle/1807/71392"/>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
