<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-teilex-207-source.xml 1138 2022-09-13 19:10:33Z pietro.liuzzo $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">TEI Lex-0 Etym: Toward Terse Recommendations for the Encoding of
               Etymological Information</title>
            <!-- author information in separate <author> elements per author -->
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Jack</forename>
                  <surname>Bowers</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Jack Bowers is a <roleName>linguist and language technologist</roleName>
                  with a wide array of interests, including: language documentation, cognitive
                  semantics, diachronic linguistics, digital humanities and corpus linguistics. He
                  received his M.A. in Linguistics from San José State University (San José,
                  California) in 2012. He received his Ph.D. from the Université PSL at the École
                  Pratique des Hauts Études (Paris, France) in 2020 for his dissertation
                     <title>Language Documentation and Standards in Digital Humanities: TEI and the
                     documentation of Mixtepec-Mixtec</title>. Jack has been active in the TEI
                  community since 2014, particularly in the areas of lexical data, annotation, and
                  especially, machine readable dictionaries. He is an Expert in the International
                  Standards Organization (ISO) Technical Committee for Language and Terminology
                  (TC37). He has worked at: Inria (Paris, France), the Austrian Center for Digital
                  Humanities (Vienna, Austria), and currently works at <orgName>Amazon Web
                     Services</orgName> (AWS) in the San Francisco Bay Area (USA).</affiliation>
               <email><!-- this author's email address --></email>
            </author>

            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Axel</forename>
                  <surname>Herold</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Axel Herold is a <roleName>researcher</roleName> at the
                     <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</orgName>. His
                  research centers on the modeling of lexicographic data of digitized as well as
                  born-digital resources. He has worked on several European and German projects such
                  as the German branch of the CLARIN European infrastructure focusing on the reuse
                  and interoperability of lexical resources. He is the coordinator for the lexical
                  resources task area in the German Text+ project (<ptr
                     target="https://www.text-plus.org/"/>). </affiliation>
               <email><!-- this author's email address --></email>
            </author>

            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Toma</forename>
                  <surname>Tasovac</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Toma Tasovac is <roleName>Director</roleName> of the <orgName>Belgrade
                     Center for Digital Humanities</orgName> (BCDH) and Director of the Digital
                  Research Infrastructure for the Arts and Humanities (DARIAH). His areas of
                  interest include lexicography, data modeling, TEI, digital editions and research
                  infrastructures. He is the co-leader of the DARIAH Working Group on Lexical
                  Resources and co-author of TEI Lex-0, a baseline encoding for lexicographic data,
                  which received the 2020 Rahtz Prize for TEI Ingenuity.</affiliation>
               <email><!-- this author's email address --></email>
            </author>

            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Laurent</forename>
                  <surname>Romary</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Laurent Romary is <roleName>Director for scientific information and
                     Culture</roleName> at <orgName>Inria, France</orgName>, and former initiator
                  and director general of the DARIAH European infrastructure. He carries out
                  research on the modeling of semi-structured documents, with a specific emphasis on
                  texts and linguistic resources. He has been active in standardization activities
                  with ISO, as chair of the ISO/TC 37/SC 4 (2002–2014) and ISO/TC 37 (2016–)
                  committees, and with the Text Encoding Initiative, as member (2001–2011) and chair
                  (2008–2011) of its technical council. He has been involved in scientific
                  information (now called open science) policies and corresponding infrastructure
                  deployments (HAL and Episciences) since 2005 within various research-performing
                  organizations.</affiliation>
               <email><!-- this author's email address --></email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>01/10/2022</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor>Tanja Wissik</editor>
            <editor>Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
            <editor>Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
            <editor>Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="rolling">Open Issue</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for
               journals in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking
               to publish full-text articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <!-- a list of keywords, each in its own <term> -->
               <term>Dictionary</term>
               <term>etymology</term>
               <term>TEI</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change><!-- Description of a change to the article; we recommend using @who and @when. --></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p>The present paper describes the specific contribution of the TEI Lex-0 initiative,
               which aims to define a terser subset of the TEI Guidelines for the representation of
               etymological features in dictionary entries. Going beyond the basic provision of
               etymological mechanisms in the TEI Guidelines, TEI Lex-0 Etym proposes a systematic
               representation of etymological and cognate descriptions by means of embedded
               constructs based on the <gi>etym</gi> (for etymologies) and <gi>cit</gi> (for etymons
               and cognates) elements. In particular, given that all the potential contents of
               etymons are highly analogous to those of dictionary entries in general, the contents
               presented herein heavily reuse many of the corresponding features and constraints
               introduced in other components of TEI Lex-0 for the encoding of etymologies and
               etymons. The TEI Lex-0 Etym model is also closely aligned with <ref
                  target="#iso2021a" type="bibl">ISO 24613–3</ref> on modeling etymological data and
               the corresponding TEI serialization available in <ref target="#iso2021b" type="bibl"
                  >ISO 24613–4</ref>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="acknowledgements">
            <p>The work described in this paper has benefited from a lot of interactions with all
               members of the DARIAH Working Group on Lexical Resources<note>Accessed June 17, 2022,
                     <ptr
                     target="https://www.dariah.eu/activities/working-groups/lexical-resources/"
                  />.</note> and various colleagues from the EU project Elexis.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <!-- text divisions, each with an @xml:id and <head> -->
         <div xml:id="intro">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Since the beginning of the Text Encoding Initiative and the first publication of the
               TEI Guidelines, the dictionary chapter has constantly been a reference model for
               representing structured lexical information. Still, as already observed (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#romary2012">Romary and Wegstein 2012</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#romary2015">Romary 2015</ref>), the TEI dictionary chapter lacks
               precision in offering univocal constructs for a given lexical phenomenon or feature.
               The case of etymological descriptions is unique in that it has remained
               underspecified. For instance, in the examples given in the TEI Guidelines (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#tei2022">TEI Consortium 2022, ch. 9: Dictionaries</ref>),<note>
                  <ptr target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/DI.html"
                  />.</note> etymological content is either left untagged or at best lightly
               annotated as mixed content; thus, more elaboration on this topic is needed. To
               address this need, the provisions described in this paper are being presented as the
               TEI Lex-0 Etym extension of the larger TEI Lex-0 initiative.</p>
            <p>Building on recent efforts addressing etymology in TEI (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#bowers2017">Bowers and Romary 2017</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#alt2006">Salmon-Alt 2006</ref>) in combination with the work carried out
               by the ISO (ISO 2021), TEI Lex-0 Etym defines a more restrained set of options for
               encoding any given single etymological phenomenon. The recommendations herein are
               designed to be able to handle born-digital as well as retro-digitized print sources,
               for which more flexible representation mechanisms may be needed. The present proposal
               is named after TEI Lex-0 (<ref type="bibl" target="#romary2018">Romary and Tasovac
                  2018</ref>), an initiative launched in 2016 under the auspices of the DARIAH
               Working Group on Lexical Resources, which aims to define a pivot format for the
               integration and querying of heterogeneous TEI-based lexical resources.<note>See the
                  project’s GitHub repository, accessed June 17, 2022, <ptr
                     target="https://github.com/DARIAH-ERIC/lexicalresources"/>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The scope of our proposal covers the usage of the following concepts central to
               etymological description:</p>
            <list>
               <item>Structuring etymologies through ordering and (optionally) recursivity</item>
               <item>Typology of etymological processes</item>
               <item>Etymons, their forms, senses, and additional characterizing information</item>
               <item>Related forms (cognates, derivatives, and others)</item>
               <item>Temporality of etymological processes</item>
               <item>Bibliographical references in etymologies</item>
               <item>Prose description of etymological process and content</item>
               <item>Provenance, opinion, and conflicting/divergent etymological accounts</item>
            </list>
            <p>As we will demonstrate, inherent in all etymological descriptions are certain
               lexicographic objects, features, and relations. These relations are temporal in the
               case of etymons (representing a stage in the linguistic development of a lexeme),
               and/or spatial in the case of cognates (forms in a related language derived from the
               same etymological origin as given form). In order to concretely improve this
               long-neglected component of the TEI, and to facilitate the encoding and exploitation
               (search and retrieval) of etymological lexicographic data, herein we present a
               systematic representation of all descriptive components associated with these
               lexicographic objects, features, and relations.</p>
            <p>Additionally, where the content is overlapping, the recommendations in this paper are
               intended to reuse those which are defined in other sections of TEI Lex-0. Any
               exceptions to this are due to specific needs of a given feature.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="overview">
            <head>I. Overview of TEI Elements Considered in This Paper</head>
            <p>In this section, we present the basic building blocks of creating structured
               etymological contents in a TEI dictionary. The components discussed are all
               pre-existing within the TEI schema; however, in order to best accommodate the
               concrete lexicographic needs common to both retro-digitized and born-digital
               etymological entries, some elements and attributes have been customized in the TEI
               Lex-0 schema.<note>TEI Lex-0 schema v. 0.9.1, last updated March 25, 2022, <ptr
                     target="https://github.com/DARIAH-ERIC/lexicalresources/tree/master/Schemas/TEILex0"
                  />.</note>
            </p>

            <div xml:id="etym">
               <head><gi>etym</gi></head>
               <p>The basic element within which all etymological content should be described is the
                  etymology element <gi>etym</gi>. With a few modifications which are described
                  below, the basis for the use of the <gi>etym</gi> element is the same as that
                  described by Bowers and Romary (<ref type="bibl" target="#bowers2017">2017</ref>),
                  which features three options for its placement in an entry:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>as a child of <gi>entry</gi>, when describing the history of the lexical
                     entry as a whole</item>
                  <item>as a child of <gi>sense</gi> for sense-based changes, or when such content
                     is present in a legacy print source</item>
                  <item>(in conjunction with one of the above) embedded (0..n) times within another
                        <gi>etym</gi> to represent multiple ordered processes in sequence</item>
               </list>
               <p>Another key feature is that the attribute <att>type</att> can be used on
                     <gi>etym</gi> to specify etymological processes explicitly. If the process has
                  subtypes, <att>subtype</att> can also be used (see section <hi rend="italic"
                     >Nested and Typed Structure</hi>). Finally, the certainty attribute
                     <att>cert</att> can be used in cases where the etymological description may not
                  be certain. The default values of <att>cert</att> are <val>high</val>,
                     <val>medium</val>, <val>low</val>, or <val>unknown</val>; editors could use any
                  combination of these as needed.</p>

            </div>
            <div xml:id="subcompetym">
               <head>Subcomponents of <gi>etym</gi></head>
               <p>Within <gi>etym</gi> the following elements can occur any number of times (some
                  occur within each other):</p>
               <list>
                  <item><gi>cit</gi><note>For a more general discussion on the <gi>cit</gi>
                        element’s semantics and usage scope, see Romary and Wegstein (<ref
                           type="bibl" target="#romary2012">2012</ref>).</note> with <att>type</att>
                     for complex descriptions of linguistic signs and their properties. The two most
                     common usages in the context of etymological representation are etymons
                        (<code>cit[type="etymon"]</code>) and cognates
                        (<code>cit[type="cognate"]</code>).<note>For a complete list of customized
                           <att>type</att> values on <gi>cit</gi> in TEI Lex-0, see <ref type="bibl"
                           target="#tasovac2018">Tasovac et al. 2018, sec. 12.1.19</ref>:
                           <gi>cit</gi>, <ptr
                           target="https://dariah-eric.github.io/lexicalresources/pages/TEILex0/TEILex0.html#TEI.cit"
                        />.</note> We follow here the recent developments related to <ref
                        type="bibl" target="#iso2021a">ISO standard 24613–3</ref>: see Khan and
                     Bowers (<ref type="bibl" target="#khan2020">2020</ref>). The element may carry
                     the appropriate <att>xml:lang</att> attribute to indicate the actual language
                     of the etymon or cognate.</item>
                  <item><gi>lang</gi>, with the attributes <att>expand</att> (full name of language
                     for documentation purpose) and <att>norm</att> (an encoded value according to
                     BCP 47)<note>IANA (Internet Assigned Numbers Authority), Language Subtag
                        Registry, last updated March 2, 2022, <ptr
                           target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/language-subtag-registry/language-subtag-registry"
                        />. BCP 47, <ptr target="https://tools.ietf.org/rfc/bcp/bcp47.txt"/>
                        .</note> for marking up references to languages mentioned in the
                     etymological process.</item>
                  <item><gi>date</gi><note>The elements <gi>date</gi> and <gi>bibl</gi> can also
                        occur within <gi>cit</gi>.</note> for dating information (complementarity to
                        <gi>lang</gi>).</item>
                  <item><gi>bibl</gi> and <gi>biblStruct</gi> for (complete) bibliographical
                     references presented inline.</item>
                  <item><tag>ref type="bibl"</tag> for pointers to bibliographical entries stored
                     elsewhere, which may also contain a <att>target</att> attribute when the
                     bibliographic description is available.</item>
                  <item>As an option depending on editorial practices, <tag>seg type="desc"</tag>
                     for spans of prose that do not represent any of the information types described
                     above.</item>
                  <item><gi>note</gi> for editorial notes that are not part of the actual
                     etymological description (see the previous discussion concerning<tag>seg
                        type="desc"</tag>).</item>
                  <item><gi>lbl</gi> to mark up short intertwining descriptive or connecting
                     markers, particularly in cases of cross references (e.g., <hi rend="italic"
                        >cf.</hi>and<hi rend="italic">see</hi>).</item>
                  <item><gi>xr</gi> (combined with <gi>lbl</gi> and <gi>ref</gi> as specified in TEI
                     Lex-0: see <ref type="bibl" target="#tasovac2018">Tasovac et al. 2018, ch.
                        7</ref>: Cross-references<note>
                        <ptr
                           target="https://dariah-eric.github.io/lexicalresources/pages/TEILex0/TEILex0.html#cross-references"
                        />.</note>) for cross-references to other lexical entries, forms, or senses,
                     typically reflecting lexical-semantic relations.</item>
                  <item>In cases where explicit etymological links have to be expressed, an
                     additional <gi>link</gi> element may be used to link etymons or cognates as
                     described in <ref target="#iso2021a" type="bibl">ISO 24613–3</ref> and <ref
                        target="#iso2021b" type="bibl">ISO 24613–4</ref>.</item>
               </list>

            </div>
            <div xml:id="basicompetym">
               <head>Basic Components of Etymons, Related Forms, and Other Components of
                  Etymologies</head>
               <p>Other than <tag>seg type="desc"</tag>, <gi>bibl</gi>, <gi>date</gi>, and
                     <gi>note</gi>, the rest of the most important components of an etymology, which
                  are described in the following sections, are encoded as children of a typed
                     <gi>cit</gi> element for describing etymons (<code>type="etymon"</code>) or
                  cognates (<code>type="cognate"</code>) , both of which are discussed in detail in
                     <ptr target="#etymons" type="crossref"/>.</p>
               <p>The element <gi>cit</gi> can contain:</p>
               <list>
                  <item><gi>form</gi> for describing the actual form corresponding to the intended
                     etymon or cognate with related constraints (for example, must contain
                        <gi>pron</gi> or <gi>orth</gi>) similar to those that apply in the general
                     TEI Lex-0 specification. In specific cases, when the information is not
                     provided at the etymon level, the element may carry the appropriate
                        <att>xml:lang</att> attribute to indicate the actual language of the
                     form.</item>
                  <item><gi>gramGrp</gi> for providing the grammatical properties associated with
                     the etymon or cognate (as in TEI Lex-0).</item>
                  <item><gi>lang</gi><note>Whereas <gi>lang</gi> is currently not allowed in
                           <gi>cit</gi> in the TEI Guidelines (<ref type="bibl" target="#tei2022"
                           >TEI Consortium 2022, Appendix C: Elements, <gi>cit</gi></ref>, <ptr
                           target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-cit.html"
                        />), TEI Lex-0 introduced the change in its specification. We suggest that
                        the TEI Guidelines integrate the change by making <gi>lang</gi> a member of
                        model.entryPart.</note> for mentioned names of the languages. When both a
                     form and a language are provided, we recommend using <att>norm</att> on
                        <gi>lang</gi> with the same value as the language indication on
                        <code>form/@xml:lang</code> or <code>cit/@xml:lang</code>.</item>
                  <item><gi>date</gi><note>Note that while <gi>date</gi> is not permitted as a
                        direct child element of <gi>cit</gi> in the general TEI Guidelines (<ref
                           type="bibl" target="#tei2022">TEI Consortium 2022, Appendix C: Elements,
                              <gi>cit</gi></ref>, <ptr
                           target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-cit.html"
                        />), it is available in the TEI Lex-0 customization; for further details,
                        see <ref type="bibl" target="#tasovac2018">Tasovac et al. 2018, sec.
                           12.1.19</ref>: <gi>cit</gi>, <ptr
                           target="https://dariah-eric.github.io/lexicalresources/pages/TEILex0/TEILex0.html#TEI.cit"
                        />.</note> for dating information (period of occurrence of the etymon,
                     whether attested or inferred).</item>
                  <item><gi>gloss</gi><note>Note that while <gi>gloss</gi> is not permitted as a
                        direct child element of <gi>cit</gi> in the general TEI Guidelines (<ref
                           type="bibl" target="#tei2022">TEI Consortium 2022, Appendix C: Elements,
                              <gi>cit</gi></ref>, <ptr
                           target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-cit.html"
                        />), it is available in the TEI Lex-0 customization; for further details,
                        see <ref type="bibl" target="#tasovac2018">Tasovac et al. 2018, sec.
                           12.1.19</ref>: <gi>cit</gi>, <ptr
                           target="https://dariah-eric.github.io/lexicalresources/pages/TEILex0/TEILex0.html#TEI.cit"
                        />.</note> in the case of a simple equivalent or paraphrase in the working
                     language of the dictionary.</item>
                  <item><gi>def</gi> for lexicographic definitions of the etymon or cognate.</item>
                  <item><gi>sense</gi> when the description of the etymon or cognate requires a
                     structured semantic description (as in TEI Lex-0).</item>
                  <item><gi>usg</gi> for usage information (as in TEI Lex-0).</item>
                  <item><gi>xr</gi> (combined with <gi>lbl</gi> and <gi>ref</gi>) for additional
                     lexical, etymological, or semantic relations, for example,
                        <soCalled>meronymOf</soCalled>.<note>See Crist (<ref type="bibl"
                           target="#crist2005">2005</ref>) for an in-depth discussion of such
                        possible relations.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item><tag>ref type="bibl"</tag> with a <att>target</att> attribute for references
                     to bibliographic entries described elsewhere in the encompassing document, and
                     possibly <gi>bibl</gi> as an alternative, when no central bibliographical
                     management is anticipated for the current dictionary.</item>
               </list>
               <p>As can be seen already, and in continuity with Bowers and Romary (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#bowers2017">2017</ref>), the TEI Lex-0 recommendation departs
                  significantly from the traditional use of <gi>mentioned</gi> for representing
                  etymons. There are two primary reasons for this. First, we wanted to provide the
                  corresponding forms with the appropriate mechanisms to describe etymological forms
                  (in the lexicographic sense) with a maximal degree of granularity and specificity:
                  that is, it is essential to be able to qualify the nature of their orthographic or
                  phonetic characteristics. Second, from a broader perspective, given that
                  etymological entries may include a wide variety of lexical information (for
                  example, glosses, grammar, and usage), we see etymological constructs (with
                     <gi>cit</gi>) as simplified lexicographic entries<note>In our group
                     discussions, we pondered the idea of also using <gi>entry</gi> elements for
                     etymons, but dropped the idea in order not to introduce too much confusion to
                     future users, and thinking that this would probably be harder to get into the
                     TEI Guidelines later.</note> which need to closely mirror the structure of
                  entries at large.</p>
               <p>It should also be noted here that making a clear-cut decision as to what is to be
                  considered a gloss or definition is not always straightforward, particularly in
                  cases where the meaning is given by a paraphrase in the working language (for
                  example, <q>hin- und herlaufen</q>, which is neither an equivalent lexeme nor a
                  fully-fledged definition). Still, lexicographic practice has led us to keep the
                  two possibilities and require encoders to document precisely the differentiation
                  criteria they have used concerning these two elements. Moreover, in keeping with
                  the general principles of TEI Lex-0, we strongly recommend that any complex
                  semantic description associated with an etymon actually be embedded within a
                  container <gi>sense</gi> element.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="structuring">
            <head>Structuring an Etymology</head>
            <div xml:id="minimal">
               <head>Minimal TEI Lex-0 Etymology Encoding (Flat, Non-typed)</head>
               <p>The most fundamental requirement of any TEI encoding of etymological information
                  should simply be to include this information inside the <gi>etym</gi> element.In
                  marking up an etymological entry, there are several key structural decisions that
                  will be up to the encoder and should conform to the source and target structure of
                  the data itself. Minimal adherence to TEI Lex-0 Etym requires only that the data
                  be encoded using the elements described above: all text content must be wrapped in
                  the particular element(s) specified for their data type, with <tag>seg
                     type="desc"</tag> remaining an option depending on editorial practices.
                  Optionally, users can include multiple layered <gi>etym</gi> elements which may
                  also be typed. In the sections below we describe each basic possibility, their
                  uses, and the specifics of their encoding.</p>
               <p>In <ptr target="#example1" type="crossref"/>, from Kluge’s etymological dictionary
                  of German (<ref type="bibl" target="#kluge1975">Kluge 1975</ref>), we demonstrate
                  the minimal encoding of the entry components.</p>

               <p><quote source="#source1" xml:lang="de">
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="bold">Eingang m</hi>.</p>
                     <p>mhd. īnganc, nnl. ingang, dän. indgang, schwed. ingång: Lehnübersetzung des
                        lat. introitus.</p>
                     <p>Aus dem <q>Hineingehen</q> als Handlung ist die <q>Stelle, an der man ins
                           Haus, in den Saal geht</q> geworden, neuerdings auch die <q>Gesamtheit
                           der eingegangenen Geschäftssachen, Mannschaften</q> usw. Vgl.
                     Zugang.</p></quote> (<ref xml:id="source1" target="#kluge1975" type="bibl"
                     >Kluge 1975, 159</ref>) </p>

               <figure xml:id="example1">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <entry xml:id="Eingang" xml:lang="de">
                        <form type="lemma"><orth>Eingang</orth></form>
                        <gramGrp><gram type="gen">m.</gram></gramGrp>
                        <etym>
                           <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="gmh">
                              <lang expand="Mittelhochdeutsch" norm="gmh">mhd.</lang>
                              <form><orth>īnganc</orth></form>
                           </cit>
                           <cit type="cognate" xml:lang="nl">
                              <lang expand="Neuniederländisch" norm="nl">nnl.</lang>
                              <form><orth>ingang</orth></form>
                           </cit>
                           <cit type="cognate" xml:lang="da">
                              <lang expand="Dänisch" norm="da">dän.</lang>
                              <form><orth>indgang</orth></form>
                           </cit>
                           <cit type="cognate" xml:lang="sv">
                              <lang expand="Schwedisch" norm="sv">schwed.</lang>
                              <form><orth>ingång</orth></form>
                           </cit>
                           <lbl>Lehnübersetzung des</lbl>
                           <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="la">
                              <lang expand="Latein" norm="la">lat.</lang>
                              <form><orth>introitus</orth></form>
                           </cit>
                           <note>Aus dem ‘Hineingehen’ als Handlung ist die ‘Stelle, an der man ins
                              Haus, in den Saal geht’ geworden, neuerdings auch die ‘Gesamtheit der
                              eingegangenen Geschäftssachen, Mannschaften’ usw. Vgl. <xr
                                 type="related">
                                 <ref type="entry">Zugang</ref>. <ref type="bibl">(Kluge, 1975) p.
                                    159</ref></xr></note>
                        </etym>
                     </entry>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Minimal encoding of an etymological description. (Source: <ref
                        target="#kluge1975" type="bibl">Kluge 1975</ref>)</head>

               </figure>

               <p>Note that the use of etymons and cognates will be discussed in detail in <ptr
                     target="#etymons" type="crossref"/>.</p>
               <p>In <ptr target="#example1" type="crossref"/>, all the main data components are
                  tagged in the same relative location as in the printed source. Note also that even
                  though no explicit typology is used here (that is, in the absence of
                     <code>etym/@type</code>, this encoding still contains a significant amount of
                  machine-retrievable information pertaining to the etymological processes involved.
                  For example, in <gi>lbl</gi> there are the words <q>Lehnübersetzung des</q>
                  <hi rend="italic">loan translation of</hi> (also known as <q>calque</q>) and
                     <q>lat. introitus</q>
                  <hi rend="italic">of the Latin introitus</hi> which contains the source language.
                  Additionally, the presence of the Middle High German language
                     (<code>&lt;lang>mhd.&lt;/lang></code>) would enable researchers to infer the
                  process of inheritance into Modern German.</p>
               <p>In any given project where terminology is consistent,<note>In the case of data
                     sets (original or legacy) that do not use consistent terminology, variation in
                     the terminology should be normalized to allow for maximally systematic search
                     and retrieval possibilities.</note> and where the proper references to parent
                  language stages are present, the presence of such information will enable a
                  certain degree of machine-retrievability even without adding any additional
                  structure in the TEI encoding.</p>

            </div>
            <div xml:id="ordering">
               <head>Ordering of Embedded Etymologies to Encode Chronology</head>
               <p>Where an entry has an etymology with multiple stages, the embedded <gi>etym</gi>
                  elements should be ordered so that the element at the highest position in the
                  hierarchy represents the most recent stage and the one at the lowest position
                  represents the oldest stage.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example2">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <etym>Inherited from Middle English X <etym>from Old English Y <etym>which was
                              borrowed from Latin Z <etym>which was from the Proto Italic Q
                                    <etym>from Proto Indo-European Ʊ</etym>
                              </etym>
                           </etym>
                        </etym>
                     </etym>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend"> Embedded <gi>etym</gi> stages: source ordered (most to least
                     recent).</head>
               </figure>
               <p>While the structure of the source in <ptr target="#example2" type="crossref"/> is
                  the ideal case in that the ordering of the contents is also from the most to least
                  recent, there may be data sources or editorial preferences that present the
                  etymology in a reverse, or indirect, order. In such cases, this XML hierarchy
                  structure can nonetheless be maintained, while the information can be presented in
                  an inverse or even nonlinear chronological order while still remaining structured
                  and predictable so that a given XML <gi>etym</gi> layer will correspond
                  programmatically to a relative stage in the chronology. An instance of such a case
                  is shown in <ptr target="#example3" type="crossref"/>:</p>
               <figure xml:id="example3">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <etym>
                        <etym>
                           <etym>
                              <etym>ultimately from Proto Indo-European Ʊ</etym> which was from the
                              Proto Italic Q </etym> borrowed from Latin Z </etym> inherited from
                        Middle English X </etym>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Embedded stages: source ordered (most to least recent).</head>
               </figure>

            </div>
            <div xml:id="nested">
               <head>Nested and Typed Structure</head>
               <p>The nested <gi>etym</gi> structure was introduced by Bowers and Romary (<ref
                     type="bibl" target="#bowers2017">2017</ref>) and allows for the recursion of an
                     <gi>etym</gi> for the purposes of encoding multiple stages of an etymology
                  and/or where an etymological change is complex and is inherently comprised of
                  multiple interacting processes. Typing can of course be done using the
                     <att>type</att> attribute, and if a project’s taxonomy/ontology of etymological
                  processes has subtypes (i.e., if <hi rend="italic">calques</hi> or <hi
                     rend="italic">loan translations</hi> are a subtype of the process <hi
                     rend="italic">borrowing</hi>), the <att>subtype</att> attribute can also be
                  used.</p>
               <p>Re-examining <ptr target="#example1" type="crossref"/> above from Kluge (<ref
                     type="bibl" target="#kluge1975">1975</ref>), we can see that it actually has
                  two potential etymological layers which can be further structured. The entry
                  implicitly states that: a) the word is <hi rend="italic">inherited</hi> from
                  Middle High German <hi rend="italic">īnganc</hi>; and b) a common ancestor of both
                  German <hi rend="italic">Eingang</hi> as well as the cognate forms in other
                  Germanic languages share the same source. The entry explicitly states that the
                  word in each of those languages is a loan translation (<hi rend="italic"
                     >Lehnübersetzung</hi>), that is to say a <hi rend="italic">calque</hi>,from the
                     Latin<hi rend="italic">introitus.</hi>In this alternate encoding of the
                  etymology portion of this entry, the chronological ordering of the etymological
                  processes is represented in the structure as described in the previous section,
                  from most recent (inheritance from Middle High German) on the uppermost
                     <gi>etym</gi> to least recent (loan translation/calque from Latin) on the
                  lowermost (embedded) <gi>etym</gi>.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example4">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <etym type="inheritance">
                        <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="gmh">
                           <lang expand="Mittelhochdeutsch" norm="gmh">mhd.</lang>
                           <form><orth>īnganc</orth></form>
                        </cit>
                        <!-- cognates here -->
                        <etym type="borrowing" subtype="calque">
                           <lbl>Lehnübersetzung des</lbl>
                           <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="la">
                              <lang expand="Latein" norm="la">lat.</lang>
                              <form><orth>introitus</orth></form>
                           </cit>
                        </etym>
                        <note>Aus dem ‘Hineingehen’ als Handlung ist die ‘Stelle, an der man ins
                           Haus, in den Saal geht’ geworden, neuerdings auch die ‘Gesamtheit der
                           eingegangenen Geschäftssachen, Mannschaften’ usw. Vgl. <xr type="related">
                              <ref type="entry">Zugang</ref>. <ref type="bibl">(Kluge, 1975) p.
                                 159</ref></xr></note>
                     </etym>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Alternate encoding of the etymology of <q>Eingang</q> from
                        <ptr target="#example1" type="crossref"/>. (Source: <ref type="bibl"
                        target="#kluge1975">Kluge 1975</ref>)</head>
               </figure>

               <p>This nested structuring is not always possible, especially in cases of
                  retro-digitized print sources where the order in which the forms and data are
                  presented may limit or prohibit the use of nesting in any kind of systematic way.
                  See Bowers and Romary (<ref type="bibl" target="#bowers2017">2017</ref>) for more
                  in-depth discussion of embedding <gi>etym</gi>.</p>

            </div>
            <div xml:id="descprose">
               <head>Descriptions and Prose</head>
               <p>Prose descriptions of the etymological components and processes can be represented
                  in several different ways according to the editorial approach. They could be left
                  alone untagged (text can be placed directly in <gi>etym</gi>); specifically
                  annotated with <gi>lbl</gi> or <gi>note</gi> elements when appropriate; or, when
                  one wants to uniformly embed all linguistic descriptions at the same encoding
                  level in the XML tree, with the systematic use of a <tag>seg type="desc"</tag>
                  element. In some cases the descriptions found in print dictionaries may occur in
                  multiple discontinuous parts interrupted by examples or other structured content.
                  In such cases, where the editors wish, the attribute <att>part</att> can be used
                  with a value of <val>I</val>
                  <hi rend="italic">initial</hi>, <val>M</val>
                  <hi rend="italic">medial</hi>, or <val>F</val>
                  <hi rend="italic">final</hi>,<note>
                     <att>part</att> does also have the option of the values <val>Y</val>
                     <hi rend="italic">yes</hi> and <val>N</val>
                     <hi rend="italic">no</hi>; however, given the options of <hi rend="italic"
                        >initial/medial/final</hi>, <hi rend="italic">yes</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >no</hi> are redundant and serve no additional value. We therefore do not
                     recommend them.</note> where the value <val>M</val> may be used any number of
                  times as needed. <ptr type="crossref" target="#example5"/> shows this and some of
                  the other primary elements we have listed above that are used in etymologies. To
                  the left is the print source with the TEI encoding on the right. Note that, while
                  dating information is indeed conceptually part of a description of the etymology,
                  when possible, it is ideal to keep <gi>date</gi> as a child of <gi>etym</gi>
                  (though <gi>date</gi> is allowed within <gi>seg</gi> where it is too burdensome,
                  or deemed unnecessary to separate it from the prose).</p>
               <p>
                  <quote source="#quote2"><p>Etymologie</p>
                     <p>Seit dem 18. Jh. belegt, auf <hi rend="italic">fickfacken</hi>
                        <q>hin- und herlaufen</q> zurückgeführt: evtl. Auch auf fnhd. <hi
                           rend="italic">Fatzen</hi>
                        <q>spotten, zum Narren halten</q> zurückführbar (vgl. Pfeifer
                     2014:329)</p></quote><ref xml:id="quote2" type="bibl" target="#kluge1975">Kluge
                     1975</ref>
               </p>
               <figure xml:id="example5">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <etym>
                        <lbl>Etymologie</lbl>
                        <date>Seit dem 18. Jh.</date>
                        <seg type="desc" part="I">belegt, auf</seg> ... <seg type="desc" part="M"
                           >zurückgeführt: evtl. Auch auf</seg> ... <seg type="desc" part="F"
                           >zurückführbar</seg>
                        <xr><pc>(</pc><lbl>vgl.</lbl><ref>Pfeifer 2014:329</ref><pc>)</pc></xr>
                     </etym>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Use of <gi>lbl</gi>, <gi>date</gi>, <gi>bibl</gi>, and
                        <tag>seg type="desc"</tag> with discontinuous prose. (Source: <ref
                        type="bibl" target="#kluge1975">Kluge 1975</ref>)</head>
               </figure>

            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="etymons">
            <head>Etymons and Other Forms</head>
            <p>The basic component of an etymology is an <hi rend="italic">etymon</hi>, which is
               often represented by a form and which may include other information typical of any
               lexical entry: for example, a language name, grammatical properties, usage
               descriptions, semantic descriptions, or bibliographic sources. Etymons are encoded in
                  <tag>cit type="etymon"</tag> and are used analogously to the organization of
                  <gi>entry</gi> both conceptually and structurally as shown by the side-by-side
               comparison of Entry structure and contents (<ptr target="#example6" type="crossref"
               />) and basic etymon (<ptr target="#example6a" type="crossref"/>).</p>

            <figure xml:id="example6">

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <entry xml:id="ntuchi" xml:lang="mix">
                     <form type="lemma">
                        <orth>ntuchi</orth>
                        <pron notation="ipa">nduʧí</pron>
                     </form>
                     <gramGrp>
                        <pos>noun</pos>
                     </gramGrp> ... </entry>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Entry structure and contents. (Source: <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#bowers2020">Bowers 2020</ref>)</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="example6a">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="mix">
                     <form>
                        <orth corresp="#ntuchi">ntuchi</orth>
                     </form>
                     <gloss xml:lang="en">bean</gloss>
                     <gloss xml:lang="es">frijol</gloss>
                  </cit>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Basic etymon. (Source: <ref type="bibl" target="#bowers2020"
                     >Bowers 2020</ref>)</head>

            </figure>
            <div xml:id="specific">
               <head>Specific Types of Etymon Structures</head>
               <p>The data structure of etymons can vary in certain ways according to the specifics
                  of the conceptual content, purpose, and/or sources. A few examples of such
                  variation are:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>if the etymon is based in external sources</item>
                  <item>if it expresses a semantic change (but <hi rend="italic">not</hi>a form
                     change)</item>
                  <item>if it expresses provenance while no form attested in the source language is
                     provided</item>
               </list>
               <p>Below we demonstrate such scenarios and their encoding.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="linking">
               <head>Linking Forms to External References</head>
               <p>If an encoder wants to link a form to an existing external resource, it can be
                  done using a <att>corresp</att> attribute on the <gi>form</gi> element.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example7">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="und-x-pie">
                        <form corresp="http://example.org/uekw.htm">
                           <pron>u̯ekʷ-</pron>
                        </form>
                     </cit>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Linking the form associated with an etymon to an external
                     reference.</head>
               </figure>

            </div>
            <div xml:id="ethymonsinsemantic">
               <head>Etymons in Semantic Changes and Polysemy</head>
               <p>In certain cases (such as in an etymology describing a semantic change, resulting
                  in <hi rend="italic">polysemy</hi>), the etymon may consist of only a semantic
                  description with no form. This is possible because in cases of polysemy, the form
                  of the new meaning/lexical item remains the same as the headword of the entry. In
                  the encoding in <ptr target="#example8" type="crossref"/>, the <att>corresp</att>
                  attribute added to the <tag>cit type="etymon"</tag> points to the
                     <att>xml:id</att> value of the source sense. <ptr target="#example8"
                     type="crossref"/> shows the etymon with only sense change; <ptr
                     target="#example8a" type="crossref"/> shows the entry to which the etymon is
                  referring.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example8">

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <entry xml:id="body-face">
                        <form type="lemma">
                           <orth xml:lang="mix">nuu</orth>
                           <pron notation="ipa" xml:lang="mix">nũ̀ṹ</pron>
                        </form> … <sense xml:id="face-PRIME" n="1">
                           <usg type="domain">Anatomical Structure</usg> … <cit type="translation">
                              <form>
                                 <orth xml:lang="en">face</orth>
                              </form>
                           </cit> … <sense xml:id="face-regionOfLM" n="2">
                              <usg type="domain">Space</usg>
                              <usg type="domain">Spatial Relations</usg>
                              <gramGrp>
                                 <pos>relationNoun</pos>
                                 <colloc norm="landmark">LM</colloc>
                              </gramGrp>
                              <def xml:lang="en">The front of (sth).</def> … <cit type="example">
                                 <quote xml:lang="mix">nuu ve'e</quote>
                                 <cit type="translation">
                                    <quote xml:lang="en">the front of the house</quote>
                                 </cit>
                              </cit> … <!-- <etym> goes here -->
                           </sense> … </sense>
                     </entry>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Etymon with only sense change.</head>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="example8a">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <cit type="etymon" corresp="#face-PRIME">
                        <sense>
                           <usg type="domain">Anatomical Structure</usg>
                           <gloss xml:lang="en">face</gloss>
                           <xr type="meronymy">
                              <lbl xml:lang="en">as in:</lbl>
                              <ref type="sense" target="#body-face" xml:lang="en">part of the
                                 body</ref>
                           </xr>
                        </sense>
                     </cit>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Entry to which etymon in <ptr target="#example8"
                        type="crossref"/> is referring.</head>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="etymonswithprov">
               <head>Etymons with Provenance Information</head>
               <p>In other cases, an <gi>etym</gi> may contain only the name of a language,
                  expressing provenance (in a loanword or inheritance), or possibly simply a date
                  corresponding to the time or first attested usage. Note that, as discussed above,
                  typing on <gi>etym</gi> is optional; however, it is shown in <ptr
                     target="#example9" type="crossref"/> and <ptr target="#example9a"
                     type="crossref"/> to complement these particular etymons. The use of the
                     <att>xml:lang</att> attribute on the <gi>cit</gi> level defines the etymon as
                  being from the given language, despite not having a form therein. The inclusion of
                     <att>xml:lang</att> on <gi>lang</gi> therein distinguishes the working language
                  (which is for the reader and is not actually part of the etymon) from the language
                  of the etymon.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example9">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <etym type="borrowing">
                        <lbl>aus</lbl>
                        <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="sl">
                           <lang xml:lang="de" expand="Slowenisch" norm="sl">slow.</lang>
                        </cit>
                     </etym>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Borrowing. Etymon with only provenance, without forms.
                     (Source: <ref type="bibl" target="#kluge1975">Kluge 1975</ref>)</head>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="example9a">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <etym type="inheritance">
                        <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="gmh">
                           <lang xml:lang="de" expand="Mittelhochdeutsch" norm="gmh">mhd.</lang>
                           <ref type="bibl">Lexer Wb. III 324</ref>
                        </cit>
                     </etym>
                  </egXML>

                  <head type="legend">Inheritance. Etymon with only provenance, without forms.
                     (Source: <ref type="bibl" target="#kluge1975">Kluge 1975</ref>)</head>
               </figure>

            </div>
            <div xml:id="etymonswithsimple">
               <head>Etymons with Simple Dating Information</head>
               <p>The information about etymons can sometimes be so reduced as to contain no source
                  form information. This is the case in <ptr target="#example10" type="crossref"/>,
                  in which the author of the etymological description just wanted to record the
                  actual period or date of the first occurrence of the etymon with limited
                  etymological background apart from the temporal information itself (or because the
                  form might be obvious for the reader).</p>
               <p> »ins engl. Nach Trench 24 im 16. Jh. Mit dem hauptbegriffe des geschmückten
                  gekommen; der ursprung ist sehr zweifelhaft« </p>
               <figure xml:id="example10">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <cit type="etymon">ins engl. <xr>
                           <lbl>nach</lbl>
                           <ref type="bibliography">Trench 24</ref>
                        </xr>
                        <date>im 16. Jh.</date>
                        <def>mit dem hauptbegriffe des geschmückten gekommen</def><pc>;</pc> der
                        ursprung ist sehr zweifelhaft <xr>; s.v. /brave/ in Mueller
                        (1878)</xr></cit>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Etymon with date but not form information.</head>
               </figure>

            </div>
            <div xml:id="variantsofety">
               <head>Variants of Etymological Forms</head>
               <p>As mentioned, in encoding any type of forms in etymologies, <gi>form</gi> and its
                  child elements behave the same way as when they occur on the level of the main
                  entry. This structure is necessary for encoders of etymological dictionaries
                  because it is common to find multiple variants and/or inflected forms of the same
                  etymon that cannot be listed separately, as they correspond to the same definition
                  and/or other key pieces of information. Thus variants of etymons or other forms
                  (cognates; see next section) in an etymology should be represented in accordance
                  with the recommendation of the TEI Lex-0 Forms section (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#banski2017">Bański, Bowers, and Erjavec 2017, sec. 2</ref>). <ptr
                     target="example11" type="crossref"/> shows two such occurrences from print
                  dictionaries.</p>
               <p>
                  <quote source="#quote3">
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="bold">Etymologie</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="bold">
                           <hi rend="italic">mhd. vreten, vretten, vraten</hi>
                        </hi>
                        <q>entzünden; wundreiben; herumziehen; quälen; plagen</q> (vgl. Lexer 1878
                        III: 502)</p>
                  </quote>
                  <ref xml:id="quote3" type="bibl" target="#lexer1876">Lexer 1878</ref>) </p>
               <figure xml:id="example11">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <etym>
                        <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="gmh">
                           <lang>mhd.</lang>
                           <form type="variant">
                              <orth>vreten</orth>
                           </form>
                           <form type="variant">
                              <orth>vretten</orth>
                           </form>
                           <form type="variant">
                              <orth>vraten</orth>
                           </form>
                           <gloss>entzünden</gloss>; <gloss>wundreiben</gloss>;
                              <gloss>herumziehen</gloss>; <gloss>quälen</gloss>;
                              <gloss>plagen</gloss>
                        </cit>
                        <bibl><lbl>vgl.</lbl>
                           <title>LEXER</title>
                           <date>1878</date>
                           <edition>III</edition>
                           <citedRange>502</citedRange></bibl>
                     </etym>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Variants of the Middle High German etymon <q>vreten, vretten,
                        vraten</q> (Source: <ref type="bibl" target="#lexer1876">Lexer
                     1878</ref>).</head>

               </figure>


            </div>
            <div xml:id="cognates">
               <head>Cognates</head>
               <p>Cognates are forms asserted as being related in some way to the lexical entry
                  and/or the etymon and are a ubiquitous feature of etymological dictionaries.
                  Cognates are essentially lexical items in a language that share an etymological
                  source. The structure of a basic representation of cognates mirrors that of
                  etymons and uses the same <gi>cit</gi> structure, with the difference that the
                  value of <att>type</att> should be <soCalled>cognate</soCalled>. Note that in <ptr
                     target="#example12" type="crossref"/>, <tag>ref type="bibl"</tag> is used
                  instead of <gi>bibl</gi> because in the project from which the examples are taken
                  all bibliographical sources are listed in the header with <att>xml:id</att>s.</p>

               <figure xml:id="example12">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <cit type="cognate" xml:lang="mig">
                        <lang>Chalcatongo Mixtec</lang>
                        <usg type="geographic">
                           <placeName>San Miguel El Grande</placeName>
                        </usg>
                        <form><pron notation="trans-macaulay-mig">šinì</pron></form>
                        <ref type="bibl" target="#Macaulay-ChalcatongoMixtec-1996">(Macaulay,
                           1996)</ref>
                     </cit>
                     <cit type="cognate" xml:lang="miy">
                        <lang>Ayutla Mixtec</lang>
                        <form><pron notation="trans-hill-1990-miy">shīhih</pron></form>
                        <ref type="bibl" target="#Hills-AyutlaMixtec-1990">(Hills, 1990)</ref>
                     </cit>
                     <cit type="cognate" xml:lang="miz">
                        <lang>Coatzospan Mixtec</lang>
                        <form><pron notation="trans-smll-miz">rkɨ</pron></form>
                        <ref type="bibl" target="#Small-CoatzospanMix-1990">(Small, 1990)</ref>
                     </cit>
                     <cit type="cognate" xml:lang="smd">
                        <lang>San Martín Duraznos</lang>
                        <form><pron notation="ipa">ʃīɲī</pron></form>
                        <ref type="bibl" target="#Padgett-2017">(Padget, 2017)</ref>
                     </cit>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Collection of cognates taken from various external sources.
                     (Source: <ref target="#bowers2020" type="bibl">Bowers 2020</ref>)</head>
               </figure>

            </div>
            <div xml:id="cognateset">
               <head>Cognate Sets from a Common Bibliographic Source</head>
               <p>In some cases there may be a list of cognates in a print or born-digital source
                  that are all from a single bibliographic source, or are at least presented in a
                  source etymology as a set or list. Often these would have some kind of referential
                  function word or abbreviation: for example, <q>cf. …</q> In such cases it may be
                  desirable to present the list of cognates as the source intended and thus group
                  them in a single wrapper <tag>cit type="cognateSet"</tag>.</p>
               <p>In the case of a cognate set where there is a referential function word or
                  abbreviation, it should be tagged with <gi>lbl</gi> and included as a child of
                     <tag>cit type="cognateSet"</tag>, preceding the etymons (see <ptr
                     target="#example13" type="crossref"/>). Where there is a common bibliographic
                  source, <gi>bibl</gi> or <tag>ref type="bibl"</tag> (if the bibliographic sources
                  are already declared elsewhere) should be a child of the <tag>cit
                     type="cognateSet"</tag> and placed after the given forms (see <ptr
                     target="#example13" type="crossref"/>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="example13">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <cit type="cognateSet">
                        <lbl>Cf.</lbl>
                        <cit type="cognate" xml:lang="ffr">
                           <form><orth>...</orth></form> …. </cit>
                        <cit type="cognate" xml:lang="und-x-pom">
                           <form><orth>...</orth></form> …. </cit>
                        <cit type="cognate" xml:lang="und-x-opd">
                           <form><orth>...</orth></form> …. </cit> …… <bibl>Bibl Source Here</bibl>
                     </cit>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Template for a set of cognates (<val>cognateSet</val>) from a
                     single bibliographic source.</head>
               </figure>

            </div>
            <div xml:id="descendantandderivate">
               <head>Descendant and Derivative Forms</head>
               <p>Certain etymological dictionaries may include descendant and/or derivative forms
                  which were derived from the headword.</p>
               <p>In an entry where the lemma is a form which has been derived from another lexical
                  item, in the etymology section, the typology would be
                     <soCalled>derivation</soCalled> and the source term from which it was derived
                  would be the etymon. However, in cases such as the one shown in <ptr
                     target="#example14" type="crossref"/>, in which derivative forms are presented
                  as related entries to the headword prior to the etymology section proper, these
                  should be encoded as embedded <gi>entry</gi> elements according to the TEI Lex-0
                  Guidelines (<ref type="bibl" target="#tasovac2018">Tasovac et al. 2018, ch. 3:
                     Entries</ref>),<note><ptr
                        target="https://dariah-eric.github.io/lexicalresources/pages/TEILex0/TEILex0.html#entries"
                     />.</note> and the value of the <att>type</att> attribute should be
                     <soCalled>derivative</soCalled>.</p>

               <p>
                  <quote source="#quote4">
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="bold">amārus</hi>
                        <q>bitter</q> [adj. ο/ā] (Pl.+)</p>
                     <p>Derivatives: <hi rend="italic">amārilūdō</hi>
                        <q>bitterness</q> (Varro+), <hi rend="italic">amāror</hi>[m.] <q>bitter
                           taste</q> (Lucr.+).</p>
                     <p>PIt. <hi rend="italic">*o/am-?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>PIE *h2h3m-ro-? IE cognates: Skt. <hi rend="italic">amlá-</hi>
                        <q>sour, acid</q>, OIc. <hi rend="italic">apr</hi>
                        <q>sharp, cold</q>, OE <hi rend="italic">ampre</hi>
                        <q>sour one</q>, MDu, <hi rend="italic">amper</hi>
                        <q>bitter, sour</q> &lt; PGm. <hi rend="italic">*am(p)ra-</hi>
                        <q>sour</q>; ? OIr. <hi rend="italic">om</hi>
                        <q>raw</q>, W. of possibly <hi rend="italic">&lt;*h2h3 -emo-,</hi>Skt. āmá-
                        [adj.] <q>raw, uncooked</q>, Gr. ωμός <q>raw</q>, Arm. <hi rend="italic"
                           >howm &lt;*h2eh3mo-*</hi>
                     </p></quote><ref xml:id="quote4" type="bibl" target="#devaan2008">de Vaan
                     2008</ref>
               </p>
               <figure xml:id="example14">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <entry> ... <lbl>Derivatives</lbl><pc>:</pc>
                        <entry type="derivative" xml:lang="la">
                           <form><orth>amārilūdō</orth></form>
                           <sense><gloss>'bitterness'</gloss></sense>
                           <ref type="bibliography">(Varro+)</ref>
                        </entry><pc>,</pc>
                        <entry type="derivative" xml:lang="la">
                           <form><orth>amāror</orth></form>
                           <pc>[</pc><gramGrp><gen>m.</gen></gramGrp><pc>]</pc>
                           <sense><gloss>‘bitter taste'</gloss></sense>
                           <ref type="bibliography">(Lucr.+)</ref>
                        </entry><pc>.</pc>
                     </entry>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend"> Derivatives. (Source: <ref type="bibl" target="#devaan2008"
                        >de Vaan 2008</ref>) </head>
               </figure>


            </div>
            <div xml:id="crossref">
               <head>Cross-referenced Forms</head>
               <p>Often within etymological discussions (as in other portions of a dictionary entry)
                  there are references to forms which are etymons, cognates, or derivatives, but
                  which, in a given specific context, are not actually being posited as such. Where
                  an editor wants to specify the particular etymological relationship to the lemma
                  or other form, that information can be specified using the attributes on the
                  cross-reference <gi>xr</gi> and embedded reference <gi>ref</gi> elements.</p>
               <p>This section overlaps with the TEI Lex-0 section on structured lexical references
                     (<ref target="#tasovac2018" type="bibl">Tasovac et al. 2018, ch. 7:
                     Cross-references</ref>)<note>
                     <ptr
                        target="https://dariah-eric.github.io/lexicalresources/pages/TEILex0/TEILex0.html#cross-references"
                     />.</note> but its application in the context of etymological content requires
                  us to clearly identify the contexts of usage, as well as the conceptual
                  distinctions between the cross-referenced forms and the primary features of
                  etymology markup discussed above.</p>
               <p>In an etymology, the contexts in which a cross-reference form should be used
                  include</p>
               <list>
                  <item>where a reference is made to another lemma or form from a separate
                     entry</item>
                  <item>where a reference is made to the lemma (or another form) in the synchronic
                     entry</item>
                  <item>where a reference is made to an etymon which is not the etymon for the
                     actual lemma</item>
                  <item>where a reference is made to a sense (corresponding to either of the
                     above)</item>
               </list>
               <p>In the examples below we show specific use cases of cross-referenced forms in the
                  context of etymological dictionary entries.</p>
               <p>In this first case, the entry is for the Latin <hi rend="italic">arcessō, -ere /
                     accersō, -ere</hi>; within the etymology section of that entry there are
                  references to the two lemma variants. The cross-references are encoded in <tag>xr
                     type="crossReference" xml:lang="la"</tag>
                  <tag>ref type="entry"</tag>. This format would also apply to external
                  cross-references. In either case, the editors would also have the option of
                  including a pointer to the given internal or external form(s) with the
                     <att>target</att> attribute on <gi>ref</gi>.</p>
               <p>The stem occurs in two variants, <hi rend="bold">
                     <hi rend="italic">accers-</hi>
                  </hi>and<hi rend="bold">
                     <hi rend="italic">arcess-,</hi>
                  </hi>which suggests that...</p>
               <figure xml:id="example15">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> ...<xr type="related"
                        xml:lang="la"><ref type="entry">accers-</ref></xr> ... <xr type="related"
                        xml:lang="la"><ref type="entry">arcess-</ref></xr> …. </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Cross-reference to lemma in etymology section.</head>

               </figure>

               <p>The following example (from the same entry as above) contains a reference to an
                  etymon of the lemma/entry itself, but this is a supplementary instantiation of the
                  given etymon which occurs in the context of a discussion of a particular
                  phenomenon (for example, a phonetic change<note>Note that <att>prev</att> and
                        <att>next</att> can be used to denote temporal sequences of referenced
                     forms.</note>). In such examples as the following, the use of <gi>xr</gi>
                  encodes an important conceptual distinction in the data as it allows <tag>cit
                     type="etymon"</tag> to be reserved for the form(s) in the given entry.</p>
               <p>….Nussbaum 2007b gives two more arguments for regarding <hi rend="italic"
                     >accerso</hi>as original: the noun <hi rend="bold">
                     <hi rend="italic">dorsum → dossum</hi>
                  </hi>shows a phonetic change of...</p>
               <figure xml:id="example16">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> ...the noun <xr type="related"
                        subtype="etymon" xml:id="etym-dorsum" xml:lang="la"><ref type="entry"
                           >dorsum</ref></xr>
                     <lbl>→</lbl>
                     <xr type="related" prev="#etym-dorsum" xml:lang="la"><ref type="entry"
                           >dossum</ref></xr> shows a phonetic change of... </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Cross-referenced forms for etymons not pertaining to the
                     lemma.</head>

               </figure>


               <p>Finally, we have an example in which there is a cross-reference to a sense of an
                  external entry (<ptr target="#example17" type="crossref"/>). This is also encoded
                  as <tag>xr type="crossReference"</tag> but differs in that it is a reference to
                  the sense of a given entry; thus we use <tag>ref @type="sense"</tag> and the
                  embedded <gi>gloss</gi> within, which needs to have the <att>xml:lang</att> to
                  distinguish from the value declared at the <gi>xr</gi> level. In this case there
                  is also a form (included here in a separate <tag>ref type="sense"</tag>); however,
                  it is also possible that a cross-reference to a sense could occur without an
                  accompanying form.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">...</hi> a verb in <hi rend="bold">
                     <hi rend="italic">-cesso</hi>
                  </hi>meaning <hi rend="bold"><q>go get</q></hi>would be favoured by its semantic
                     neighbours<hi rend="bold">...</hi>
               </p>
               <figure xml:id="example17">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> ….a verb in <xr type="related"
                        xml:lang="la"><ref type="sense">-cessō</ref>
                        <lbl>meaning</lbl>
                        <pc>'</pc><gloss xml:lang="en">go get</gloss><pc>'</pc></xr> would be
                     favoured by its semantic neighbours... </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Cross-reference to a sense from an external entry.</head>

               </figure>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="conclusions">
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>In this paper, we have provided a comprehensive view of the core proposals from the
               TEI Lex-0 Etym initiative with the expectation that its powerful and structured
               representations will serve both to provide guidance for the encoding of etymological
               content in TEI, for which little precedent is available, and to facilitate the
               interoperable encoding of a vast variety of potential etymological features found
               both in print (for retro-digitization) and born-digital contents. Still, as we know
               from the TEI Guidelines, this must remain a work in progress, since future users of
               the TEI Lex-0 Guidelines are likely to come up with new issues and change proposals.
               The online management of the whole TEI Lex-0 initiative as an open-source project
               makes it possible for anyone to contribute and help improve the specification and
               documentation, which are already in use in the EU project Elexis as the default pivot
               format for lexical data integration.</p>
            <p>Finally, additional work may indeed be necessary to achieve more precise and stable
               ontologies for typing etymological processes, as well as for qualifying
               cross-references in etymological contexts.</p>
         </div>

         <div xml:id="appendix">
            <head>Appendix: Fully Encoded Examples</head>
            <p>In the following examples, we have tried to illustrate interesting cases of
               etymological processes that show how TEI Lex-0 Etym can seamlessly take into account
               a variety of situations. All examples have been validated and included in the TEI
               Lex-0 GitHub environment.</p>

            <div xml:id="embeddedsenses">
               <head>Embedded Senses, Metaphor, and Compounding</head>
               <p><ptr target="#example18" type="crossref"/> shows a case of an embedded sense from
                  the Mixtepec-Mixtec TEI dictionary (<ref type="bibl" target="#bowers2020">Bowers
                     2020</ref>) in which the lemma form <hi rend="italic">xini ve’e</hi> is a
                  compound with one component that is metaphorical in nature. The portion of the
                  etymology that is metaphorical (<tag>etym type="metaphor"</tag>) is embedded
                  within the <tag>etym type="compounding"</tag>, and as it is relevant to the
                  process of metaphor, within the <tag>etym type="metaphor"</tag> is the domain
                     (<tag>usg type="domain"</tag>).</p>

               <figure xml:id="example18">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <sense>
                        <usg type="domain">Architecture</usg>
                        <cit type="translationEquivalent" xml:lang="en">
                           <form>
                              <orth>ceiling</orth>
                           </form>
                        </cit>
                        <cit type="translationEquivalent" xml:lang="es">
                           <form>
                              <orth>techo</orth>
                           </form>
                        </cit>
                        <etym type="compounding">
                           <etym type="metaphor">
                              <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="mix">
                                 <form type="lemma" corresp="#body-head">
                                    <orth>xiní</orth>
                                 </form>
                                 <gloss xml:lang="en">head</gloss>
                                 <gloss xml:lang="es">cabeza</gloss>
                                 <usg type="domain">Anatomy</usg>
                              </cit>
                           </etym>
                           <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="mix">
                              <form type="lemma" corresp="#house">
                                 <orth>ve'e</orth>
                              </form>
                              <gloss xml:lang="en">house</gloss>
                              <gloss xml:lang="es">casa</gloss>
                           </cit>
                        </etym>
                     </sense>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Embedded senses, metaphor, and compounding. (Source: <ref
                        type="bibl" target="#bowers2020">Bowers 2020</ref>)</head>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="derivationalmorphological">
               <head>Derivational/Morphological Analysis</head>
               <p>In <ptr target="#example19" type="crossref"/>, for the Portuguese entry <hi
                     rend="italic">húmanal,</hi>we have a case of derivation (labeled with a
                     <att>type</att> attribute) in which the suffix <hi rend="italic">-al</hi>is
                  attached to the noun <hi rend="italic">humano</hi>to create the attributive
                  adjective. Given that derivation can occur in a wide variety of morphological
                  ways, the specific type of derivation is labeled with a <att>subtype</att>
                  attribute.</p>
               <figure xml:id="imageexample19">
                  <graphic url="clip_image002_-1109838243.jpg" height="48px" width="369px"/>
                  <head type="legend"/>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="example19">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <entry xml:lang="pt">
                        <form type="lemma">
                           <orth>húmanal</orth>
                           <pron notation="ipa">umɐnáł</pron>
                        </form>
                        <gramGrp>
                           <gram type="pos">adj.</gram>
                           <gram type="gen">m.</gram>
                           <lbl>e</lbl>
                           <gram type="gen">f.</gram>
                        </gramGrp>
                        <etym type="derivation" subtype="suffixalDerivation">
                           <pc>(</pc>
                           <seg type="desc">De</seg>
                           <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="pt">
                              <form>
                                 <orth>humano</orth>
                              </form>
                           </cit>
                           <lbl>+</lbl>
                           <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="pt">
                              <gramGrp>
                                 <gram type="pos" expand="suffix">suf.</gram>
                              </gramGrp>
                              <form>
                                 <orth extent="suff">-al</orth>
                              </form>
                           </cit>
                           <pc>)</pc>
                        </etym>
                        <!--  rest of entry here -->
                     </entry>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Derivational/morphological analysis. (Source: <ref type="bibl"
                        target="#devaan2008">de Vaan 2008</ref>)</head>
               </figure>

            </div>
            <div xml:id="phonological">
               <head>Phonological Changes</head>
               <p>It is very common in etymological dictionaries to have discussions about sequences
                  of sound changes. These most often take place in the context of running prose. As
                  described above, prose can be represented using <tag>seg type="desc"</tag>, and
                  where interrupted with etymons (or other content), the <att>part</att> attribute
                  can be used. The phonetic or phonological units described as having undergone
                  particular changes are represented the same way as full word forms, using <tag>cit
                     type="etymon"</tag>. In order to attribute a unit’s particular place in the
                  sequence of sound changes, the <att>prev</att> and <att>next</att> attributes can
                  be used to point to the <att>xml:id</att> of the previous or next form in the
                  diachrony. <ptr target="#example20" type="crossref"/> illustrates these
                  mechanisms.</p>
               <p>Others have proposed an etymology *<hi rend="italic">ad-arti-</hi> with
                  intervocalic *<hi rend="bold">
                     <hi rend="italic">d</hi>
                  </hi> becoming <hi rend="bold">
                     <hi rend="italic">l</hi>
                  </hi>; the spelling <hi rend="italic">allers</hi>would then be analogical to <hi
                     rend="italic">sollers</hi>
               </p>
               <figure xml:id="example20">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <etym>
                        <seg type="desc" part="I">Others have proposed an etymology</seg>
                        <cit type="etymon" xml:id="ad-arti-" xml:lang="und-x-pie"
                                 ><form><orth>*ad-arti-</orth></form></cit>
                        <etym corresp="#ad-arti-">
                           <seg type="desc" part="I">with intervocalic</seg>
                           <cit type="etymon" xml:id="c1" next="#c2"
                              ><form><orth>d</orth></form></cit>
                           <seg type="desc" part="F">becoming</seg>
                           <cit type="etymon" xml:id="c2" prev="#c1"
                              ><form><orth>l</orth></form></cit>
                           <pc>;</pc>
                        </etym>
                        <seg type="desc" part="F">the spelling <xr type="crossReference"
                              xml:lang="la"><ref type="entry">allers</ref></xr> would then be <xr
                              type="crossReference" xml:lang="la"><lbl>analogical to</lbl>
                              <ref type="entry">sollers</ref></xr><pc>.</pc></seg>
                     </etym>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Phonological changes. (Source: <ref type="bibl"
                        target="#devaan2008">de Vaan 2008</ref>)</head>


               </figure>

               <p>Note also that this entry contains an embedded etymology, and it is distinguished
                  in the data structure according to the portion that belongs directly to the
                  author, and the portion which he is ascribing to <soCalled>others</soCalled>.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="multiple">
               <head>Multiple and/or Conflicting Etymological Accounts</head>
               <p>In many sources there can be multiple, sometimes conflicting, accounts for an
                  etymology. In these cases nested etymologies should be used, the top layer being
                  reserved for the editorial descriptions, and any number of separate <gi>etym</gi>s
                  can be included therein.</p>
               <p>
                  <quote source="#quote5">
                     <p>According to Untermann 2000, Latin <hi rend="italic">*all-</hi>was probably
                        borrowed from Sabellic, since Latin does not have this word in its lexicon.
                        For a word only occurring in glosses, this is of course possible.</p>
                     <p>Others have proposed an etymology <hi rend="italic">*ad-arti-</hi>with
                        intervocalic <hi rend="italic">d</hi> becoming <hi rend="italic">l</hi>; the
                        spelling <hi rend="italic">allers</hi>would then be analogical to <hi
                           rend="italic">sollers.</hi>
                     </p></quote><ref xml:id="quote5" type="bibl" target="#devaan2008">de Vaan
                     2008</ref>
               </p>
               <figure xml:id="example21">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <etym>
                        <!-- PIt, PIE etymons-->
                        <!-- cognates -->
                        <etym cert="medium">
                           <!-- Lat. sollers 
                                 < *soti-arti- to 
                                 sollus 'entire'; 
                                 al(l)ers < *all-arti- 
                                 to O. alio- 'entire'. -->
                           <seg type="desc" part="I">According to <ref type="bibliography">Untermann
                                 2000</ref>, </seg>
                           <xr type="crossReference"><lang>Latin</lang>
                              <ref xml:lang="la">*all-</ref></xr>
                           <seg type="desc" part="M">was probably borrowed from</seg>
                           <cit type="etymon" xml:lang="und-x-sabe1249"><lang norm="und-x-sabe1249"
                                 >Sabellic</lang></cit>, <seg type="desc" part="F">since <lang
                                 norm="la">Latin</lang> does not have this word in its lexicon. For
                              a word only occurring in glosses, this is of course possible.</seg>
                        </etym> <etym cert="medium"><seg type="desc" part="I">Others have proposed
                              an etymology</seg>
                           <cit type="etymon" xml:id="ad-arti-" xml:lang="und-x-pie"
                                    ><form><orth>*ad-arti-</orth></form></cit> <etym
                              corresp="#ad-arti-">
                              <seg type="desc" part="I">with intervocalic </seg><cit type="etymon"
                                 xml:id="c1" next="#c2"><form><orth>d</orth></form></cit> <seg
                                 type="desc" part="F">becoming</seg>
                              <cit type="etymon" xml:id="c2" prev="#c1"
                                 ><form><orth>l</orth></form></cit>
                              <pc>;</pc>
                           </etym> <seg type="desc" part="F">the spelling <xr type="related"><ref
                                    xml:lang="la">allers</ref></xr> would then be <xr
                                 type="crossReference"><lbl>analogical to</lbl>
                                 <ref xml:lang="la">sollers</ref></xr><pc>.</pc></seg></etym>
                     </etym>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Multiple and/or conflicting etymological accounts. (Source:
                        <ref type="bibl" target="#devaan2008">de Vaan 2008</ref>)</head>

               </figure>

            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <!-- the bibliography for the article, organized as a series of <bibl> elements inside <listBibl> -->
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="banski2017"><author>Bański, Piotr</author>, <author>Jack
                     Bowers</author>, and <author>Tomaž Erjavec</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title
                     level="a">TEI-Lex0 Guidelines for the Encoding of Dictionary Information on
                     Written and Spoken Forms</title>. In <title level="m">Electronic Lexicography
                     in the 21st Century: Proceedings of eLex 2017 Conference</title>, edited by
                     <editor>Iztok Kosem</editor>, <editor>Carole Tiberius</editor>, <editor>Miloš
                     Jakubíček</editor>, <editor>Jelena Kallas</editor>, <editor>Simon
                  Krek</editor>, and <editor>Vít Baisa</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >485–94</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Brno</pubPlace>: <publisher>Lexical
                     Computing</publisher>. <ptr target="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01757108"/>; <ptr
                     target="https://elex.link/elex2017/proceedings-download/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bowers2020"><author>Bowers, Jack</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title
                     level="u">Mixtepec-Mixtec Digital Dictionary / Dicionario del Mixteco de
                     Mixtepec</title>. Last updated December 6, 2020. <ptr
                     target="https://github.com/iljackb/Mixtepec_Mixtec/blob/master/MIX-Lexicon-TEI-Dict.xml"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bowers2017"><author>Bowers, Jack</author>, and <author>Laurent
                     Romary</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">Deep Encoding of
                     Etymological Information in TEI</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the Text
                     Encoding Initiative</title> 10. <ptr
                     target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1643"/>; doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.4000/jtei.1643</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="crist2005"><author>Crist, Sean</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title
                     level="a">Toward a Formal Markup Standard for Etymological Data</title>. <title
                     level="m">Paper presented at the LSA Annual Meeting, Oakland, CA, January
                     6–9</title>. Available at <ptr
                     target="http://www.sean-crist.com/professional/publications/crist_etym_markup.pdf"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="iso2021a"><author>ISO (International Organization for
                     Standardization)</author>. <date>2021</date>a. <title level="a">Language
                     Resource Management — Lexical Markup Framework (LMF) — Part 3: Etymological
                     Extension</title>. ISO 24613–3:2021. Geneva: ISO. <ptr
                     target="https://www.iso.org/standard/75410.html"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="iso2021b"><author>ISO (International Organization for
                     Standardization)</author>. <date>2021</date>b. <title level="a">Language
                     Resource Management — Lexical Markup Framework (LMF) — Part 4: TEI
                     Serialization</title>. ISO 24613–4:2021. Geneva: ISO.
                  https://www.iso.org/standard/75411.html.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="khan2020"><author>Khan, Fahad</author>, and <author>Jack
                     Bowers</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">Towards a Lexical Standard
                     for the Representation of Etymological Data</title>. In <title level="m">Atti
                     del IX Convegno Annuale dell’Associazione per l’Informatica Umanistica e la
                     Cultura Digitale (AIUCD). La Svolta Inevitabile: sfide e prospettive per
                     l’Informatica Umanistica [Proceedings of the 9th Annual Conference of the
                     AIUCD...]</title>, edited by <editor>Cristina Marras</editor>, <editor>Marco
                     Passarotti</editor>, <editor>Greta Franzini</editor>, and <editor>Eleonora
                     Litta</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">125–29</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="https://aiucd2020.unicatt.it/aiucd-Khan_Bowers.pdf"/>; doi:<idno
                     type="DOI">10.6092/unibo/amsacta/6316</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="kluge1975"><author>Kluge, Friedrich</author>. <date>1975</date>. <title
                     level="m">Etymologisches Wörterbuch der deutschen Sprache</title>. 21.
                  unveränderte Aufl. <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>: <publisher>De
                  Gruyter</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="lexer1876"><author>Lexer, Matthias von</author>. <title level="m"
                     >Mittelhochdeutsches Handwörterbuch</title>. 3: VF - Z, Nachträge . (<date>1876
                     - 1878</date>).</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="romary2015"><author>Romary, Laurent</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title
                     level="a">TEI and LMF Crosswalks</title>. <title level="j">Journal for Language
                     Technology and Computational Linguistics</title> (JLCL) 30 (1): 47–70. <ptr
                     target="https://jlcl.org/content/2-allissues/6-Heft1-2015/3Romary.pdf"/>.
                  Author’s version available at <ptr target="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00762664"/>.
                  Version published in journal, 2015: <ptr
                     target="https://jlcl.org/content/2-allissues/6-Heft1-2015/3Romary.pdf"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="romary2018"><author>Romary, Laurent</author>, and <author>Toma
                     Tasovac</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">TEI Lex-0: A Target
                     Format for TEI-Encoded Dictionaries and Lexical Resources</title>. Abstract in
                     <title level="u">The 18th Annual TEI Conference and Members’ Meeting: Book of
                     Abstracts</title>, edited by <editor>Tensho Miyazaki</editor>, 274–75.
                     <pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>: <publisher>Center for Evolving Humanities, Graduate
                     School of Humanities and Sociology, The University of Tokyo; International
                     Institute for Digital Humanities</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://tei2018.dhii.asia/AbstractsBook_TEI_0907.pdf"/>. Author’s
                  version of presentation available at <ptr
                     target="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-02265312/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="romary2012"><author>Romary, Laurent</author>, and <author>Werner
                     Wegstein</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">Consistent Modeling of
                     Heterogeneous Lexical Structures</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the Text
                     Encoding Initiative</title> 3. <ptr
                     target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/540"/>; doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.4000/jtei.540</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="alt2006"><author>Salmon-Alt, Susanne</author>. <date>2006</date>.
                     <title level="a">Data Structures for Etymology: Towards an Etymological Lexical
                     Network</title>. <title level="j">Bulletin de Linguistique Appliquée et
                     Générale</title> 31: <biblScope unit="page">101–12</biblScope>. Author’s
                  version available at <ptr target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00110971/"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tei2022"><author>TEI Consortium</author>. <date>2022</date>. <title
                     level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange.
                     Version 4.4.0</title>. Last updated April 19, 2022. <ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tasovac2018"><author>Tasovac, Toma</author>, <author>Laurent
                     Romary</author>, <author>Piotr Banski</author>, <author>Jack Bowers</author>,
                     <author>Jesse de Does</author>, <author>Katrien Depuydt</author>, <author>Tomaž
                     Erjavec</author>, et al. <date>2018</date>. <title level="m">TEI Lex-0: A
                     Baseline Encoding for Lexicographic Data. Version 0.9.1</title>, last updated
                  March 24, 2021. DARIAH Working Group on Lexical Resources. <ptr
                     target="https://dariah-eric.github.io/lexicalresources/pages/TEILex0/TEILex0.html"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="devaan2008"><author>de Vaan, Michiel</author>. <date>2008</date>.
                     <title level="m">Etymological Dictionary of Latin and the Other Italic
                     Languages</title>. Leiden Indo-European Etymological Dictionary Series 7.
                     <pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace>: <publisher>Brill</publisher>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
