<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" 
   schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-oc-ra-schwartz-208-source.xml 1088 2022-01-31 13:54:14Z pietro.liuzzo $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
   rend="jTEI">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Modeling a Born-Digital Factoid Prosopography using the TEI and
               Linked Data</title>
            <author>
               <name xml:id="schwartzd">
                  <forename>Daniel L.</forename>
                  <surname>Schwartz</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Daniel L. Schwartz is <roleName>Associate Professor of
                     History</roleName> and <roleName>Associate Director of the Center of Digital
                     Humanities Research</roleName> at <orgName>Texas A&amp;M University</orgName>.
                  He co-directs (with David A. Michelson) <ref target="http://syriaca.org"
                     >Syriaca.org</ref>, a TEI-encoded linked-open data project dedicated to
                  advancing scholarship in the field of Syriac Studies and to preserving Syriac
                  cultural heritage. He is the general editor of Syriaca.org’s <title level="m"
                     >Syriac Persons, Events, and Relations</title> (<title level="m">SPEAR</title>,
                  an online prosopographical research tool, and the co-editor (with Sergey Minov) of
                     <title level="m">The Syriac Taxonomy</title>, a domain ontology for Syriac
                  Studies.</affiliation>
               <email>daniel.schwartz@tamu.edu</email>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name xml:id="gibsonn">
                  <forename>Nathan P.</forename>
                  <surname>Gibson</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Nathan P. Gibson is a <roleName>Research Associate</roleName> in the
                     <orgName>Institute of Near and Middle Eastern Studies</orgName> at
                     <orgName>Ludwig-Maximilian University of Munich</orgName>. He directs the
                  project Communities of Knowledge (<ref
                     target="https://usaybia.net/exist/apps/usaybia/index.html">Usaybia.net</ref>,
                  funded by the <q>Kleine Fächer – Große Potenziale</q> program of the
                     <orgName>German Federal Ministry of Education and Research</orgName>), which
                  uses TEI factoids to encode and analyze networks of interreligious collaboration
                  in the medieval Middle East. He is a co-editor of the TEI-based clavis <title
                     level="m">New Handbook of Syriac Literature</title> (with David A. Michelson
                  and Jeanne-Nicole Mellon Saint-Laurent at Syriaca.org) and an associate editor of
                  the Bibliography of the Arabic Bible (with Ronny Vollandt, general editor, at <ref
                     target="https://biblia-arabica.com/">Biblia-Arabica.com</ref>).</affiliation>
               <email>nathan.gibson@lmu.de</email>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name xml:id="torabik">
                  <forename>Katayoun</forename>
                  <surname>Torabi</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Katayoun Torabi is an <roleName>Instructional Assistant
                     Professor</roleName> in the <orgName>Department of English at Texas A&amp;M
                     University</orgName> and <roleName>Project Manager</roleName> of the New
                  Variorum Shakespeare at the <roleName>Center of Digital Humanities
                     Research</roleName>. She specializes in Old and Middle English literature, with
                  strong research and teaching interests in the digital humanities. She is currently
                  working on a digital project that investigates connections between purgation and
                  incarceration in pre- and post-mortem punitive spaces in Old and Middle English
                  literature.</affiliation>
               <email>torabik@tamu.edu</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>13/02/2021</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor>Tanja Wissik</editor>
            <editor>Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
            <editor>Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
            <editor>Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="rolling">Open Issue</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for
               journals in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking
               to publish full-text articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>factoids</term>
               <term>Linked Open Data</term>
               <term>prosopography</term>
               <term>stand-off markup</term>
               <term>Syriac studies</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#schwartzd" when="2020-09-10"><name>Dan Schwartz</name> completed encoding of
            article draft for submission to jTEI.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="acknowledgements">
            <p>Nathan P. Gibson’s contributions to this article have been funded by the German
               Federal Ministry of Education and Research in the framework of the Communities of
               Knowledge project.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p>Although the TEI has traditionally been used for encoding text, its combination of
               structured and semi-structured data has made it a compelling choice for born-digital,
               linked-data resources as well. Our intent here is to demonstrate the advantages it
               offers for digital prosopographies along with a model that can be used for them.
                  <title>Syriac Persons, Events, and Relations</title> (<title>SPEAR</title>) is a
               born-digital prosopography project in the field of Syriac studies. Where traditional
               prosopographies focused on prose descriptions of individual persons of significance,
                  <title>SPEAR</title> follows recent developments in research methodologies that
               instead produce prosopographical factoids. Factoids are structured data about persons
               drawn from the analysis of historical texts. Most factoid prosopographies use
               relational databases to model data. Instead, <title>SPEAR</title> uses a customized
               TEI schema to model factoids that can be queried and visualized in an XML database as
               well as serialized in HTML for human viewers and in RDF for data sharing. The TEI’s
               provisions for structured and semi-structured data make it ideal for encoding data
               from heterogeneous historical source material. Moreover, its linking capabilities
               connect <title>SPEAR</title> data to related data sets. By modeling prosopographical
               factoids, and not the source texts themselves, <title>SPEAR</title> offers an example
               of how a born-digital, data-oriented approach to using the TEI can circumvent some of
               the challenges posed by the tree structure of XML. It also disrupts traditional
               understandings of <term>data</term> and <term>stand-off markup</term> through
               combining linked open data approaches with the use of the TEI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="introduction">
            <head>Introduction: <title>SPEAR</title> and the Syriaca.org Data Graph</head>
            <p>The TEI offers multiple ways for humanists to render and engage with text as data.
               Although the TEI was primarily designed to encode text, it also allows the encoding
               of data that lie at a greater distance from the text itself. Many text encoding
               projects use these portions of the TEI to encode stand-off markup containing data
               about aspects of their encoded texts: entities like persons or places, linguistic
               material, or taxonomies.</p>
            <p>Syriaca.org is a linked open data (LOD) project that places this use of the TEI at
               the center of its research agenda. It uses the TEI to encode authority files on
               persons, places, primary source texts, manuscripts, scholarly bibliography, and a
               taxonomy of concept keywords, all of which are related to the cultural heritage of
               the Syriac communities. These communities share the use of the Syriac language, a
               form of Aramaic which flourished in Greater Syria and Mesopotamia throughout the late
               antique and medieval periods and continues to be a part of religious and cultural
               life in parts of the Middle East and in diasporas in India, the U.S., and Europe. As
               Syriac has coexisted variously with Greek, Coptic, Arabic, Latin, and other
               languages, the Syriaca.org project often links its data to digital projects in these
               neighboring fields.<note>For an extended discussion of the Syriaca.org data model,
                  see <ref type="bibl" target="#michelson2021">Michelson 2021</ref>. On Syriac
                  cultural heritage, see, accessed January 31, 2022 <ptr
                     target="https://gallery.library.vanderbilt.edu/exhibits/syriaca"/> and <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#king2018">King 2018</ref>.</note> For each Syriac-related
               entity, Syriaca.org creates a separate XML file, mints a Uniform Resource Identifier
               (URI), collects information about that entity, links to related URIs for other
               Syriaca.org entities, and links out to external resources such as VIAF, Wikidata,
               Pleiades, and others. Moreover, these URIs are so-called cool-URIs that are not only
               unique strings but are also resolvable by a web browser into HTML pages with a
               human-readable version of the data about each entity (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#sauerman2008">Sauerman and Cyganiak 2008</ref>). The extensive pointers
               to URIs for other entities in each file result in a graph of data. Syriaca.org Senior
               Programmer Winona Salesky has also developed the open-source <ref
                  target="https://srophe.app/">Srophé Application</ref>. Built on eXist-DB, it
               renders the TEI data as HTML, facilitates advanced browse and query features, and
               also renders the TEI data into various forms of the Resource Description Framework
                  (RDF).<note>For more on the Srophé Application, see <ptr target="#visualization"
                     type="crossref"/>.</note> On the whole, Syriaca.org can be understood as a
               reference work that leverages the linked open data environment.</p>
            <p><title>Syriac Persons, Events, and Relations</title> (<title>SPEAR</title>) is a
               related project that relies on the Syriaca.org authority files and the data graph
               that results from their linked encoding, but focuses on analyzing primary sources by
               deriving assertions from them rather than providing reference information.
                  <title>SPEAR</title> encoders create a separate born-digital TEI file for each
               primary source text and employ a customized TEI schema to encode prosopographical
               data extracted from texts. Thus the result is not a model of the source texts
               themselves but actually a model of prosopographical factoid data derived from those
               texts.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="facts-factoids">
            <head>Of Facts and Factoids</head>
            <p>The modern historical methodology known as prosopography began in the late nineteenth
               century, flourished throughout the twentieth century, and continues today.
               Definitions of this research methodology are varied, some emphasizing the
               descriptions of individual persons, others emphasizing connections between the
               individuals in a prescribed group. K. S. B. Keats-Rohan discusses this history of
               prosopographical research and offers the following useful definition, <quote
                  source="#quoteref1">Prosopography is about what the analysis of the sum of data
                  about many individuals can tell us about the different types of connection between
                  them, and hence about how they operated within and upon the institutions – social,
                  political, legal, economic, intellectual – of their time</quote> (<ref type="bibl"
                  xml:id="quoteref1" target="#keats-rohan2000">2000, 2</ref>). Initially, this work
               focused on the production of magisterial print volumes containing brief descriptions
               of known persons with a shared characteristic (i.e., occupation) or socio-economic
               status. The chronological focus of the earliest work was ancient and medieval
               Mediterranean history and these works have proven invaluable for historians seeking
               to understand social networks and the political trajectories of elite Greeks and
               Romans (<ref type="bibl" target="#cameron2003">Cameron 2003</ref>). While historians
               have long used structured databases for historical sources such as census data whose
               original form was already a table and thus anticipated database technology, it was
               only very recently that scholars began to work out how to structure prosopographical
               data to leverage the potential of a structured database. Over the last couple of
               decades, a group of scholars at King’s College London, originally part of the Centre
               for Computing in the Humanities but now refashioned into the Department of Digital
               Humanities (CCH/DDH), pioneered a particular approach to prosopographical research
               designed to model prosopography in a relational database. The result has been
               projects such as the Prosopography of the Byzantine World (PBW), the Prosopography of
               Anglo-Saxon England (PASE), and the Clergy of England Database (CCEd).<note>For a
                  list of CCH/DDH prosopographies with brief introductions to each, see, accessed
                  January 31, 2022, <title>Factoid Prosopographies at CCH/DDH KCL</title> at: <ptr
                     target="https://factoid-dighum.kcl.ac.uk/factoid-prosopographies-at-cchddh-kcl/"
                  />.</note> The shift from narrative descriptions to databases required a
               conceptual move from prosopography as textual descriptions of persons to structured
               data about persons. This move was anticipated by print prosopographies such as the
                  <title>Prosopographia Imperii Romani</title> and <title>Prosopographia
                  Ptolemaica</title> (both subsequently digitized) which made use of identifying
               numbers, cross-referencing, and source quotations in individual entries.
               Prosopographical factoids develop this methodology by focusing on small pieces of
               data about persons: name variants, occupations, places of residence, events in which
               they played a role, personal and professional relationships, and possessions. Factoid
               prosopographers then take these discrete pieces of information and put them into a
               relational database that creates a graph of relationships between the pieces.</p>
            <p>Unfortunately, the term <term>factoid</term> can cause confusion. Where facts are
               generally understood to be confirmed truths, the term <term>factoid</term> was
               introduced by Norman Mailer in his biography of Marilyn Monroe to describe pieces of
               information, true or otherwise, that have a life only on account of being repeated by
               the media (<ref type="bibl" target="#marsh2014">Marsh 2014</ref>). This idea is not
               what factoid prosopographers have in mind, however. In adopting the term to describe
               their approach to prosopography, researchers at CCH/DDH instead courted the irony of
               the term (<ref type="bibl" target="#pasin2015">Pasin and Bradley 2015, 89</ref>).
               Rather than asserting that the result of factoid prosopography is a database of
               fabricated or insignificant information, the researchers who applied the term
               intended to emphasize the contingency of information asserted in textual sources.
               Factoids capture assertions made in primary source texts and not necessarily
               confirmed truths about the past. The factoid approach to prosopography thus captures
               the scholar’s interpretation of what a historical source asserts about persons. As a
               result, factoids may or may not be verifiable and in some cases are demonstrably
               false. <ptr target="#notes-descriptions" type="crossref"/> discusses how
                  <title>SPEAR</title> handles these kinds of uncertainties. The scholarly
               interpretation required to understand and reconstruct the source’s assertions is a
               first step toward historical criticism, but factoid prosopographies stand in contrast
               to some prosopographical databases that are intended to contain verified historical
               facts. It might be helpful to think of a factoid prosopography as a sophisticated
               index of the source’s assertions, as understood and annotated by the
                  encoder.<note>However, Bradley and Short (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#bradleyShort2005">2005, 17</ref>) are careful to note that the
                  database is a model of prosopography itself, not a model of the text(s) from which
                  the prosopographical material is drawn. <title>SPEAR</title> seeks to accomplish
                  the same goal using the TEI.</note> The resulting born-digital work provides a
               space situated between the primary source text and the historical-critical evaluation
               of that text where researchers can encode and make publicly available in a linked
               data framework their interpretation of the text. As we will show below, the TEI
               offers an excellent standard for the kind of nuanced interpretive work required to
               meet this purpose.</p>
            <p>The projects using this approach to prosopography have so far focused on relational
               databases for modeling prosopographical factoids. While highlighting this fact back
               in 2005, John Bradley and Harold Short also noted the possibility of using XML for
               factoid-based prosopography, especially given the potential of eXist-DB and XQuery to
               index, search, and browse XML data, thus allowing suitably encoded XML documents to
               produce the kind of data graph generally associated with the tables of a relational
               database (<ref type="bibl" target="#bradleyShort2005">Bradley and Short 2005,
                  15</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#bradley2005">Bradley 2005</ref>; <ref
                  type="bibl" target="#bradley2014">Bradley 2014, 18–19</ref>). <title>SPEAR</title>
               uses these technologies in many of the ways anticipated by Bradley and Short but
               ultimately sidesteps some of the difficulties they discuss with using XML for factoid
               prosopography, particularly the limitations of the XML tree structure. This article
               describes a customization of the TEI that models born-digital prosopographical
               factoids and integrates them with an LOD infrastructure.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="factoids-texts-tei">
            <head>Factoids, Texts, and the TEI</head>
            <p>Syriaca.org adopted the TEI for expressing its data model prior to the inception of
                  <title>SPEAR</title>. Eventually, project members decided that in addition to the
                     <title><ref target="http://syriaca.org/persons">Syriac Biographical Dictionary
                     (SBD)</ref></title>, with each individual XML file containing information on
               one individual, we wanted to pursue a factoid approach to doing prosopography as
               well. Several things made this approach desirable. <title>SBD</title> offers an
               authority file for persons relevant to Syriac studies, including a URI minted on the
               basis of at least one or two references to the person in either primary or secondary
               source material. These URIs can then be used for authority control (such as in
               library catalogues) and as identifiers in digital projects.<note>Syriaca.org data for
                  persons, places, and works meet the criteria for authority files articulated by
                     <ref type="bibl" target="#patton2009">Patton 2009, 83</ref>.</note> In some
               instances, a record on an individual contains many data points while other records
               are quite sparse, serving the purpose of identifying a person and offering relevant
               citations but not necessarily providing extensive data beyond a basis for
               disambiguation. For <title>SBD</title>, encoders are expected to bring their
               knowledge of Syriac studies and scholarly judgment to bear on the accuracy of the
               information contained in <title>SBD</title> entries. <title>SPEAR</title>, on the
               other hand, has different aims and demands a different kind of interpretive work from
               encoders. It does not produce data to be used for authority control, nor does it
               offer its own canonical identifiers for persons. Rather, <title>SPEAR</title> uses
               the system of person URIs established in the <title>SBD</title> authority files and
               employs them in the encoding of prosopographical factoids—factoids which, as noted
               above, may in fact contain false assertions. The difference between the two data sets
               is most clear at the level of workflow. <title>SBD</title> begins from a reference to
               a distinct person relevant to Syriac studies, usually in a reference work or other
               secondary literature, and mints a URI identifying that person, at the same time
               recording information helpful for disambiguation, such as biographical dates and name
               variants. <title>SPEAR</title> works through individual primary source texts and
               employs the URIs from the <title>SBD</title> authority files to label persons with
               unique identifiers while encoding prosopographical data from those texts. To date,
               these primary texts have consisted of late-antique chronicles, letters, and
               hagiographies, but they could theoretically include any Syriac source. Not only the
               process but also the structure of the TEI-encoded XML files differs between
                  <title>SPEAR</title> and <title>SBD</title>: each XML file in <title>SPEAR</title>
               contains prosopographical data about many persons from an individual text rather than
               information about a single person. <ref type="crossref" target="#table1">Table
                  1</ref> summarizes the differences between these two data sets.</p>
            <table xml:id="table1">
               <head type="legend">Comparison of <title>SBD</title> and <title>SPEAR</title> data
                  types</head>
               <row role="label">
                  <cell/>
                  <cell><title>SBD</title></cell>
                  <cell><title>SPEAR</title></cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell role="label">Goal</cell>
                  <cell>Authority control</cell>
                  <cell>Factoid prosopography</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell role="label">Starting Point</cell>
                  <cell>Lists of persons</cell>
                  <cell>Close reading of primary source text</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell role="label">Usage</cell>
                  <cell>Identifying persons</cell>
                  <cell>Creating structured data out of primary-source assertions about
                     persons</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell role="label">Granularity</cell>
                  <cell>Identifying information with primary or secondary bibliography</cell>
                  <cell>Any primary-source assertion about persons</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell role="label">Data Format</cell>
                  <cell>One XML file per person</cell>
                  <cell>One XML file per text or text part</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>Even though <title>SPEAR</title> uses TEI XML and focuses on texts, it does not use
               traditional text encoding to produce its data. The reasons for this are quite
               straightforward. It is extremely difficult to produce highly structured
               prosopographical data through the encoding of texts. Text-encoding projects seeking
               these kinds of data about the persons in their texts usually encode such data in some
               sort of stand-off markup.<note>On some different approaches to TEI stand-off markup
                  see Viglianti (<ref type="bibl" target="#viglianti2016">2016</ref>).</note> The
               work of John Bradley and Harold Short on factoid prosopography and structured data
               has emphasized the benefits of relational database technology over XML for quite some
               time. They argue that a text-encoding approach to prosopography will run up against
               the limitations inherent in the hierarchical tree structure of XML (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#bradleyShort2005">Bradley and Short 2005, 13–15</ref>; see also <ref
                  type="bibl" target="#Jannidis2018">Jannidis and Flanders 2018, 73</ref>). They
               also note the frequent disconnect between the words and phrases employed in a text
               and the meaning that a scholar can derive by reading the text against the grain (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#bradleyShort2005">Bradley and Short 2005, 13–15</ref>). In
               its nascent stages, <title>SPEAR</title> briefly attempted to achieve the kind of
               factoid-based prosopographical data we sought by encoding primary source texts in the
               TEI. We quickly experienced the types of problems discussed by Bradley and Short. It
               proved extremely difficult to get the granularity of data desired given the
               constraints of the hierarchy imposed by XML.</p>
            <p>Though discussions of problems regarding the tree-structure of XML are commonplace,
               it is worth giving a bit more attention to the discussion of Bradley and Short. One
               can read their article as a defense of a relational database (RDB) model for
               prosopographical factoids. Given the textual nature of the source base and strong
               preferences among textual scholars for encoding editions of texts in TEI XML, their
               article aims to make a case for moving from text to database as the preferred
               approach for modeling factoids. They summarize their motivations for using relational
               databases for the factoid projects arising from CCH/DDH as follows: <quote
                  source="#quoteref2">It is exactly because prosopographical projects are involved
                  in the creation of a model of their material that is perhaps not explicitly
                  provided in the texts they work with that a purely textual approach is in the end
                  not sufficient in and of itself. Instead, it is exactly this kind of structuring
                  which makes our projects particularly suitable for the relational database
                  model</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref2" type="bibl" target="#bradley2005">Bradley
                  and Short 2005, 14</ref>). They argue that the structure of text does not
               necessarily lend itself to the kind of data they seek to produce but also that the
               encoding of texts does not offer a robust enough model for their data. The results of
               the CCH/DDH prosopographies clearly demonstrate that rich prosopographical data can
               be modeled in a relational database. However, their argument in favor of RDBs over
               XML only considers one application of XML to the work of collecting factoids.
               Although the use of XML to encode texts is widespread, that is not the only way to
               apply XML in general and TEI in particular to the encoding of prosopographical
               factoids. The TEI can also be used to model the prosopographical factoids
               themselves.</p>
            <p><title>SPEAR</title> combines the TEI encoding of factoids with the LOD
               infrastructure of Syriaca.org and other partner projects to maintain and make
               explicit the close connection between prosopography and the historical source
               providing the material for the prosopography. This begins in the <gi>teiHeader</gi>
               element. The file description for each document contains a title statement with a
                  <gi>title</gi> element indicating the title of the TEI document. The
                  <gi>title</gi> element with a <att>type</att> attribute of <val>main</val>
               reflects the historical work from which the data have been derived. A subtitle
               indicates that it is a prosopography and not an encoding of the document itself.
                  <figure xml:id="example1">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m" type="main">Chronicle of Edessa</title>
                        <title type="sub">A <title>SPEAR</title> Prosopography</title> ...
                     </titleStmt>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Title statement</head>
               </figure> Likewise, the <gi>publicationStmt</gi> contains an <gi>idno</gi> element
               defining the URI for the document. This URI identifies the document as part of
                  <title>SPEAR</title>, but also employs the numerical portion of the corresponding
               Syriaca.org work URI (which takes the form
                  <code>http://syriaca.org/work/{\d+}/tei</code>). <figure xml:id="example2">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <publicationStmt> ... <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/spear/8559/tei</idno>
                        ... </publicationStmt>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Publication statement</head>
               </figure> This same number is also used as the filename for the XML document.</p>
            <p>The intent behind this practice is to maintain a connection between the historical
               source from which researchers encode factoids and the document in which they encode
               the individual factoids. From the perspective of the data themselves, this practice
               is not particularly significant. Each factoid exists on a specific path and the
               document is nothing more than one point on that path. However, from the perspective
               of workflow, textual interpretation, and data entry, the document level collection
               does hold significance. The encoding workflow reinforces the textually oriented
               nature of the data as encoders work document by document to encode the
               prosopographical material contained in that document. The textual orientation of the
               TEI nicely facilitates this workflow even though <title>SPEAR</title> does not
               produce encoded historical texts. This practice is not only followed at the level of
               the <gi>teiHeader</gi>, textual connections are important at the factoid level also,
               as will be demonstrated below. <ptr type="crossref" target="#graphic1"/> shows some
               examples of the kinds of connections between factoids and other related data sets.
               These connections will be explored in the discussion of the factoid modeling that
               follows.</p>
            <figure xml:id="graphic1">
               <graphic url="images/SPEAR_graphic.png" width="2627px" height="1688px"/>
               <head type="legend">Connections between <title>SPEAR</title> and other LOD
                  resources</head>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="prosopographical-factoids-tei">
            <head>Prosopographical Factoids in the TEI</head>
            <p>Encoding a <title>SPEAR</title> factoid entails using the XML structure, the semantic
               value of the TEI elements and attributes, and the linking abilities of Syriaca.org
               URIs to express the encoder’s interpretation of a prosopographical datum derived from
               a historical text in the Syriac literary tradition. While <title>SPEAR</title>
               factoids mostly validate against the TEI P5 schema, the customization significantly
               constrains the document in order to ensure <title>SPEAR</title>’s required formatting
               for factoid data (see <ref
                  target="https://github.com/srophe/syriaca/blob/master/documentation/SPEARschema/SPEAR.odd"
                  >ODD</ref> and <ref
                  target="https://github.com/srophe/syriaca/blob/master/documentation/SPEARschema/out/SPEAR.rng"
                  >RelaxNG</ref>). It also makes extensive use of Schematron rules to validate
               attribute values against the appropriate Syriaca.org URIs for different entities.
               These constraints offer a blueprint for modeling prosopographical data in ways very
               similar to those described by Bradley and Short when expressing their preference for
               the RDB model.</p>
            <p>The <title level="a">Names, Dates, People, and Places</title> module of the TEI
               Guidelines contains a wealth of elements for encoding data about these entities.
               Moreover, the motivation behind this module is the markup of precisely the kind of
               prosopographical data contained in <title>SPEAR</title>: <quote source="#quoteRef2"
                  >The main intended applications for this module are in biographical, historical,
                  or geographical data systems such as gazetteers and biographical databases, where
                  these are to be integrated with encoded texts</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteRef2"
                  type="bibl" target="#teiConsortium2020">TEI Consortium 2020, 13</ref>).
               Nevertheless, modeling a factoid prosopography using the TEI required a lengthy
               iterative process of moving back and forth between Syriac sources in various genres
               and the TEI Guidelines. No prosopography can capture every piece of data from every
               source, nor can it anticipate everything users will want to know about the persons in
               the resulting data set. These challenges would exist even if the TEI Guidelines
               anticipated the encoding of prosopographical factoids.</p>
            <div xml:id="containing-identifying">
               <head>Containing and Identifying Factoids</head>
               <p>Modeling prosopographical factoids required the identification of an element to
                  serve as a container for each factoid. We chose the <gi>ab</gi> element since it
                  offers a generic container for textual material. Each factoid appears in its own
                     <gi>ab</gi> element and must also include a <att>type</att> attribute with a
                  value of <val>factoid</val> indicating how the <gi>ab</gi> element is being used.
                  As described above, Syriaca.org’s linked data model requires that entities receive
                  a cool URI, a unique identifier that is resolvable to a web page containing a
                  human-readable version of the data. The <gi>ab</gi> contains the textual
                  expression of the conceptual entity that is the factoid. <title>SPEAR</title> uses
                  an <att>xml:id</att> on each <gi>ab</gi> element in order to identify this
                  expression of the factoid. However, we also declare the full URI for the factoid
                  by requiring an <gi>idno</gi> element as a child of <gi>ab</gi>. Schematron rules
                  in <title>SPEAR</title>’s customized schema require that the portion of the URI
                  immediately preceding the hyphen match the numerical portion of the <gi>idno</gi>
                  in the <gi>publicationStmt</gi> which in turn must match the file name for the
                  current document.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example3">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <ab type="factoid" subtype="event" xml:id="factoid-5" resp="#jwalters">
                        <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/spear/798-5</idno> ... </ab>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Factoid container and identifier</head>
               </figure>
               <p>The <gi>ab</gi> elements in <title>SPEAR</title> must also include a
                     <att>resp</att> attribute. While the header contains <gi>editor</gi> and
                     <gi>respStmt</gi> elements detailing contributions at the document level, we
                  feel it is important that the intellectual contribution constituted by the
                  interpretation of the text and encoding of the prosopographical data out of that
                  text requires attribution at the factoid level. This information is useful for the
                  encoder in terms of being able to see the number of factoid contributions to the
                  project as well as to the user of the data who might find that information
                  significant for determining the credibility of the way the assertion is
                  interpreted in the factoid. In the process of encoding factoids, the encoders
                  contributing to a given factoid select their personal identifiers from those
                  allowed by <title>SPEAR</title>’s customized schema.</p>
               <p>Each factoid in <title>SPEAR</title> shares the structure described so far; a
                  containing <gi>ab</gi> element, <att>type</att>, <att>xml:id</att>, and
                     <att>resp</att> attributes, along with a child <gi>idno</gi> element indicating
                  the full URI for the factoid. The highest level of divergence has to do with the
                  three basic types of data that <title>SPEAR</title> collects: data on persons,
                  data on events of significance to persons, and data on relationships between
                  persons. A <att>subtype</att> attribute on the factoid <gi>ab</gi> offers the
                  first indication of this divergence. In the previous example, the
                     <att>subtype</att> indicates that this is an event factoid. A relation factoid
                  is indicated by the value <val>relation</val> while the person factoid values
                  specify the type of person data encoded. Those values, mostly derived from TEI
                  element names, include: <val>birthDate</val>, <val>birthPlace</val>,
                     <val>citizenship</val>, <val>deathDate</val>, <val>deathPlace</val>,
                     <val>education</val>, <val>ethnicLabel</val>, <val>gender</val>,
                     <val>langKnown</val>, <val>mentalState</val>, <val>nameVariant</val>,
                     <val>occupation</val>, <val>physicalTrait</val>, <val>residence</val>,
                     <val>sanctity</val>, and <val>socecStatus</val>. The <att>subtype</att> values
                  are not, strictly speaking, necessary as they can be derived from the context of
                  the XML. However, we include these values because it facilitates easier processing
                  of SPEAR’s different data types.</p>
               <p>As the TEI does not allow <gi>person</gi>, <gi>event</gi>, or <gi>relation</gi> to
                  appear as direct children of <gi>ab</gi>, <title>SPEAR</title> uses
                     <gi>listPerson</gi>, <gi>listEvent</gi>, and <gi>listRelation</gi> followed by
                  the respective elements. A factoid is by definition an assertion of personal
                  information sourced to a primary source text and every <gi>ab</gi> must also have
                  one or more <gi>bibl</gi> elements. While not technically necessary for a factoid
                  prosopography, <title>SPEAR</title> also includes the opportunity for encoders to
                  add a <gi>note</gi> element as a child of <gi>ab</gi>. This element may hold a
                  discursive note for an encoder to express additional information about the factoid
                  assertion contained elsewhere. These notes may be used to express uncertainty and
                  doubts about the veracity of the assertions made in the primary source text. We
                  will return to a fuller discussion of the <gi>bibl</gi> and <gi>note</gi> elements
                  after discussing how <title>SPEAR</title> uses the <gi>relation</gi>,
                     <gi>event</gi>, and <gi>person</gi> elements. While all of the data encoded
                  using these elements are prosopographical, we speak in terms of person factoids,
                  event factoids, and relation factoids. This division is based on elements in the
                  TEI used to encode these different types of data. In the following sections we
                  will discuss our methodologies for encoding each of the three types of factoids,
                  moving from the simplest to the most complex.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="relation-factoids">
               <head>Relation Factoids</head>
               <p>Relation factoids encode relationships between people using the <gi>relation</gi>
                  element and attribute values that leverage the same linked data standards seen
                  elsewhere in factoids. Relation factoids can either stand alone or as discussed in
                     <ptr target="#relationshipsInEvents" type="crossref"/>, they can be included in
                  an event factoid using the <gi>relation</gi> element as a child of the
                     <gi>desc</gi> element. Following the lead of the TEI Guidelines (<ref
                     type="bibl" target="#teiConsortium2020">TEI Consortium 2020, 13.3.2.3</ref>),
                  the <gi>relation</gi> element may take either a <att>mutual</att> attribute or
                  both an <att>active</att> and a <att>passive</att> attribute, depending on the
                  type of relationship. The relationship <term>spouse of</term> would take a
                     <att>mutual</att> attribute with two values while the relationship <term>parent
                     of</term> would take the parent in the <att>active</att> attribute and the
                  child in the <att>passive</att> attribute. In all cases, acceptable values for the
                  attributes are Syriaca.org person URIs established in the SBD authority files, as
                  discussed in <ptr target="#factoids-texts-tei" type="crossref"/> and <ptr
                     target="#person-factoids" type="crossref"/>. The <att>type</att> attribute on
                  this <gi>relation</gi> element takes <val>person</val> indicating that this
                  encodes a personal relationship. While this is clear enough from the context of
                  the XML, including this attribute value facilitates processing of the factoid data
                  by distinguishing this from the encoding of a relationship between two events as
                  discussed in <ptr target="#notes-descriptions" type="crossref"/>.
                     <title>SPEAR</title> also encourages encoders to provide date information for
                  the element in a factoid using attributes from the <ident>att.datable</ident>
                  class provided by the TEI Guidelines (<ref type="bibl" target="#teiConsortium2020"
                     >TEI Consortium 2020, 3.5.4 and 13.3.7</ref>).</p>
               <p>A <att>ref</att> attribute on <gi>relation</gi> provides a pointer to a keyword
                  URI in <title>The Syriac Taxonomy</title>, where various identifiers and metadata
                  about the relationship are encoded. <figure xml:id="example4">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ab type="factoid" subtype="relation" xml:id="factoid-15"
                           resp="#ktorabi #dschwartz"> ... <relation type="person"
                              ref="http://syriaca.org/keyword/sibling-of-parent-of"
                              active="http://syriaca.org/person/3056"
                              passive="http://syriaca.org/person/2553">
                              <desc>
                                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3056">Anonymous
                                    3056</persName> was the sibling of the parent of <persName
                                    ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2553">Antoninus</persName>.
                              </desc>
                           </relation> ... </ab>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend"><title>SPEAR</title>
                        <gi>relation</gi> element</head>
                  </figure> The <title>Taxonomy</title> contains fifty-four relationships divided
                  into ten categories: family relationships, personal relationships, professional
                  relationships, clerical relationships, monastic relationships, intellectual
                  relationships dealing with schooling and influence, relationships constituted
                  through legal proceedings, relationships constituted through military service,
                  relationships constituted through slavery, and epistolary relationships dealing
                  with references to third parties and transport of letters. Additionally,
                     <title>SPEAR</title> allows an optional <att>ana</att> attribute that again
                  points to keyword URIs in the <title>Taxonomy</title>. These keywords qualify
                  relationships in the <att>ref</att> attribute, further specifying family
                  relationships as maternal, paternal, in-law, step, adoption, half, foster,
                  claimed, or ritually based (i.e., baptismal godparent). <title>Taxonomy</title>
                  relationships derive from the relationship ontology produced in the
                     <title>SNAP:DRGN</title> project.<note>For more on the <title>SNAP:DRGN</title>
                     project, see <ref type="bibl" target="#bodard2021">Bodard, 2021</ref>.</note>
                  The <title>SNAP</title> ontology was designed to create a data standard for
                  networking ancient prosopographical material. Not only is <title>SNAP</title> a
                  project with which <title>SPEAR</title> has a strong interest in sharing data, but
                     <title>SNAP</title>’s focus on the ancient world means that many of the
                  relationships expressed in <title>SPEAR</title>’s source base are already present
                  in the <title>SNAP</title> ontology. For example, modern relationship ontologies
                  such as Friend of a Friend (FOAF) do not provide robust mechanisms for describing
                  the relationships constituted by the practice of slavery. <title>SPEAR</title>
                  uses most of the relationship types included in the <title>SNAP</title>
                     ontology.<note>For a helpful graph of the <title>SNAP</title> ontology, see
                        <ptr target="http://snap.dighum.kcl.ac.uk/img/OwlVizImage.png"/>.</note>
                  Given the nature of the source base and the expectations of researchers in Syriac
                  studies, <title>SPEAR</title> has also created a number of relationships that can
                  be expressed as subsets of <title>SNAP</title> relationships. In particular,
                     <title>SPEAR</title> captures a range of relationships from within the ranks of
                  Christian clerics and monastic communities. <ref type="crossref"
                     target="#example5">Example 5</ref> shows a type of relationship not included in
                  the <title>SNAP</title> ontology. <figure xml:id="example5">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <relation type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/keyword/ordained"
                           active="http://syriaca.org/person/2562"
                           passive="http://syriaca.org/person/51">
                           <desc>
                              <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2562">Epiphanius</persName>
                              ordained <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of
                                 Antioch</persName>. </desc>
                        </relation>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Ordination</head>
                  </figure> When <title>SPEAR</title> prepares RDF to share with the
                     <title>SNAP</title> project, this clerical relationship can be expressed as a
                     <title>SNAP</title> professional relationship. This practice allows for
                  consistent encoding within <title>SPEAR</title> that can also be serialized as RDF
                  according to the needs of other linked open data projects.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="event-factoids">
               <head>Event Factoids</head>
               <p>Event factoids contain an encoding of any event deemed relevant by the encoder of
                  the file. The <gi>event</gi> element takes an <att>ana</att> attribute with one or
                  more values pointing to the <title>Taxonomy</title>. This keyword tagging creates
                  links between this event and other <title>SPEAR</title> events but also creates
                  links between the event and scholarly bibliography described with the same
                  keywords. The <gi>event</gi> element also contains a <gi>desc</gi> element
                  offering the encoder’s interpretation of the event described in the primary source
                  text. The <title>SPEAR</title> encoding manual encourages encoders to describe
                  events making liberal use of <gi>persName</gi> and <gi>placeName</gi> elements
                  with <att>ref</att> attributes pointing to Syriaca.org person and place URIs.
                  These URIs link different factoids but also link factoids to other Syriaca.org
                  data sets.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example6">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <ab type="factoid" subtype="event" xml:id="factoid-555" resp="#dschwartz">
                        <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/spear/8559-555</idno>
                        <listEvent>
                           <event
                              ana="http://syriaca.org/keyword/emperors http://syriaca.org/keyword/bishops http://syriaca.org/keyword/natural-disasters">
                              <desc> The fourth time the walls of <placeName
                                    ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78"> Edessa </placeName> were
                                 broken down was in the days of the king <persName
                                    ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2268"> Justin </persName> and of
                                 the bishop <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2236">
                                    Asclepius </persName> in <choice>
                                    <reg><date notBefore="0524-10" notAfter="0525-09"
                                          calendar="#gregorian">524/5</date></reg>
                                    <orig><date when-custom="0836" datingMethod="#seleucid">A. Gr.
                                          836</date></orig>
                                 </choice>
                              </desc>
                           </event>
                        </listEvent> ... </ab>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">An event factoid</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Encoders have a great deal of discretion regarding the encoding of events. It is
                  up to the scholarly expertise of the encoders as they engage with the text and
                  draw upon field-specific knowledge to determine what constitutes an event.
                  Different encoders can disagree on the scope of the events they encode and exactly
                  how many factoids they assign to a closely related series of events. Encoding
                  instructions encourage the liberal use of keyword identifiers using the
                     <att>ana</att> attribute but the application of keywords remains a part of the
                  interpretive work of the encoder. <title>SPEAR</title> seeks a rather general
                  application for this data model, but other projects might forgo a more general
                  approach to encoding events and focus instead on encoding only events that serve
                  to address more specific research questions.</p>
               <p>It is important also to recall that the factoid approach offers descriptions of
                  textual assertions on events. The factoid describing a historical event does not
                  function as an authority file of that historical event. Entities like persons,
                  places, and works can be difficult enough to isolate for the purpose of assigning
                  a URI and establishing an authority file.<note>For a discussion of how Syriaca.org
                     handles these challenges in establishing authority files for works, see Gibson,
                     Michelson, and Schwartz (<ref type="bibl" target="#gibson2017"
                     >2017</ref>).</note> These issues become significantly more complicated when it
                  comes to historical events since what constitutes an event can vary so
                  dramatically depending upon the source, the perspective of the encoder, and the
                  research questions motivating the encoding.</p>
               <div xml:id="dates">
                  <head>Dates in Factoids</head>
                  <p>
                     <ref type="crossref" target="#example6">Example 6</ref> demonstrates
                        <title>SPEAR</title>’s preference for applying dates whenever indicated in
                     the source text. In so far as a factoid is an interpretation of a text, the
                     encoder may simply use the <gi>date</gi> element with a properly formatted
                        <att>when</att>, <att>notBefore</att>, or <att>notAfter</att> attribute by
                     itself. However, the <title>SPEAR</title> encoding manual expresses a
                     preference for using the TEI’s ability to capture the calendar system used in
                     the text. <ref type="crossref" target="#example6">Example 6</ref> shows how
                     encoders use <gi>choice</gi> with a child <gi>reg</gi> element indicating
                        <tag>date calendar="#gregorian"</tag> and a child <gi>orig</gi> element with
                     a <gi>date</gi> element pointing to another method of dating. Likewise,
                     encoders can also capture non-calendrical dating systems as shown in <ref
                        type="crossref" target="#example7">example 7</ref>. <figure
                        xml:id="example7">
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                           <choice>
                              <reg><date notBefore="0379-01-19" notAfter="0380-01-18"
                                    calendar="#gregorian">379/80</date>
                                 <note ana="#calculated">This regularized date was calculated by the
                                    SPEAR editor from a non-calendrical dating system such as regnal
                                    years, etc.</note></reg>
                              <orig><date datingMethod="#regnalYear">the year Theodosius the Great
                                    became king</date></orig>
                           </choice>
                        </egXML>
                        <head type="legend">Non-calendrical dating systems</head>
                     </figure> A <gi>note</gi> as child of <gi>reg</gi> allows the HTML
                     serialization of the data to indicate to the user that this date has been
                     calculated by the encoder.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="relationshipsInEvents">
                  <head>Relationships Established through Events</head>
                  <p>An additional complication presents itself when it comes to dealing with the
                     intersection of events and relationships in the <title>SPEAR</title> factoid
                     model. How do we encode events that create relationships? Take, for example, a
                     birth. A birth is an event, but it also creates a parent-child relationship.
                     While a <title>SPEAR</title> encoder can encode these data using two separate
                     factoids, the <title>SPEAR</title> encoding manual prefers inserting the
                     relationship data in a <gi>relation</gi> element as a descendant of the
                        <gi>desc</gi> element. <figure xml:id="example8">
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                           <ab type="factoid" subtype="event" xml:id="factoid-12"
                              resp="#syoung #dschwartz">
                              <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/spear/3045-12</idno>
                              <listEvent>
                                 <event
                                    ana="http://syriaca.org/keyword/ordination http://syriaca.org/keyword/bishops http://syriaca.org/keyword/clergy http://syriaca.org/keyword/letters">
                                    <desc>
                                       <date notBefore="0513" notAfter="0518" calendar="#gregorian"
                                          >Sometime between 513 and 518</date>, <persName
                                          ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName>
                                       wrote a letter to <persName
                                          ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2546">Entrechius</persName>
                                       about the appointment of <persName
                                          ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3064">Anonymous
                                          3064</persName> in <placeName
                                          ref="http://syriaca.org/place/173">Rhosus</placeName>. <listRelation>
                                          <relation type="person"
                                             ref="http://syriaca.org/keyword/sender-of-letter-to"
                                             active="http://syriaca.org/person/51"
                                             passive="http://syriaca.org/person/2546"/>
                                       </listRelation>
                                    </desc>
                                 </event>
                              </listEvent> ... </ab>
                        </egXML>
                        <head type="legend">An event that creates a relationship</head>
                     </figure> This practice maintains the tight connection between event and
                     relationship and has the added benefit of allowing the inclusion of these kinds
                     of events into graphs of the relationships depicted in bodies of literature.
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="person-factoids">
               <head>Person Factoids</head>
               <p><title>SPEAR</title> encodes the following data within the <gi>person</gi>
                  element: birthdate, birthplace, citizenship, death date, death place, education,
                  ethnic label, gender, language, mental state, name variant, occupation, physical
                  trait, place of residence, sanctity, and social rank.<note>Some person factoids
                     (like birth or occupation) might imply that an event occurred to constitute
                     that personal characteristic. Thus, they could alternatively be modeled as
                     events (see <ptr target="#containing-identifying" type="crossref"/>). However,
                     SPEAR encourages encoders to stay close to the text, modeling the assertion as
                     a person factoid when they interpret the source text to be giving a personal
                     description rather than relating an event.</note> Every <gi>person</gi> element
                  must indicate the person about whom the item of data is asserted by the primary
                  source text. <title>SPEAR</title> accomplishes this association with a
                  self-closing <gi>persName</gi> element as the immediate child of <gi>person</gi>,
                  along with a <att>ref</att> attribute pointing to the Syriaca.org URI for that
                  person. There are several important points to be made regarding this connection.
                  To begin with <title>SPEAR</title> does not contain the Syriaca.org authority file
                  for the individual persons. Neither is it the case that some kind of aggregation
                  of <title>SPEAR</title> data points about an individual constitutes such an
                  authority file. <title>SPEAR</title> makes factoid statements indicating what a
                  source asserts about the person entities identified by Syriaca.org authority
                  files. As a consequence, Syriaca.org must have an authority file among its data
                  for any entity an encoder would like to say something about in a
                     <title>SPEAR</title> factoid.<note>Syriaca.org employs webforms that
                        <title>SPEAR</title> encoders can use to create the required entities when
                     they do not already exist in Syriaca.org data. These forms reserve a URI in the
                     proper data set and produce a <soCalled>stub</soCalled> TEI XML record that
                     editors of the relevant data sets can develop and incorporate into the
                     Syriaca.org data graph.</note>
                  <title>SPEAR</title> references Syriaca.org URIs for persons, places, keywords,
                  bibliography, and works.</p>
               <p>Following the <gi>persName</gi> element, a person factoid must have one of the
                  following: <gi>birth</gi>, <gi>death</gi>, <gi>education</gi>,
                     <gi>nationality</gi>, <gi>residence</gi>, <gi>occupation</gi>,
                     <gi>langKnowledge</gi>, <gi>state</gi>, <gi>trait</gi>, or
                  <gi>socecStatus</gi>. The <gi>birth</gi> and <gi>death</gi> elements contain
                  either <gi>date</gi> with a following-sibling <gi>note</gi> or <gi>placeName</gi>
                  with a following-sibling <gi>note</gi>. <figure xml:id="example9">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ab type="factoid" subtype="deathDate" xml:id="factoid-155"
                           resp="#dschwartz">
                           <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/spear/8559-155</idno>
                           <listPerson>
                              <person>
                                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13"/>
                                 <death>
                                    <choice>
                                       <reg><date when="0373-06-09" calendar="#gregorian">9 June
                                             373</date></reg>
                                       <orig><date when-custom="0684-09-09"
                                             datingMethod="#seleucid-SyriacMonths">9 Ḥazirān A. Gr.
                                             684</date></orig>
                                    </choice>
                                    <note type="desc">
                                       <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13"
                                          >Ephrem</persName> died on 9 June 373. </note>
                                 </death>
                              </person>
                           </listPerson> ... </ab>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Person factoid: date of death</head>
                  </figure>
                  <ref type="crossref" target="#example9">Example 9</ref> contains the encoding of a
                  date of death.</p>
               <p>As with the <gi>persName</gi> child of <gi>person</gi> discussed above, the
                     <gi>placeName</gi> in a birth or death element is a self-closing element with a
                     <att>ref</att> attribute pointing to the Syriaca.org URI for that place.
                     <figure xml:id="example10">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ab type="factoid" subtype="birthPlace" xml:id="factoid-7" resp="#ktorabi">
                           <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/spear/796-7</idno>
                           <listPerson>
                              <person>
                                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885"/>
                                 <birth>
                                    <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2804"/>
                                    <note type="desc">
                                       <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885"
                                          >Maro</persName> was born in <placeName
                                          ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2804"
                                       >Kalesh</placeName>.</note>
                                 </birth>
                              </person>
                           </listPerson> ... </ab>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Person factoid: birthplace</head>
                  </figure> Similar to <gi>birth</gi> and <gi>death</gi>,
                     <gi>nationality</gi><note>It is unfortunate that the TEI employs the element
                        <gi>nationality</gi>. For the vast majority of recorded history (even if not
                     for the vast majority of extant texts) there was no such thing as a
                     nation-state. <title>SPEAR</title> uses the <gi>nationality</gi> element even
                     though it allows <gi>nationality</gi> to contain a <gi>placeName</gi> with a
                        <att>ref</att> attribute pointing to any type of place entity of which
                     someone could be a citizen, <q>citizenship</q> being a more meaningful category
                     for the primary source base of <title>SPEAR</title> than is <q>nationality</q>.
                     Factoids of this kind are contained in a <tag>ab subtype="citizenship"</tag>.
                     In this way, <title>SPEAR</title> encoding does not distinguish between a
                     person being a citizen of a state-level entity, for example the Roman or
                     Persian Empire, and a settlement-level entity, for example the city of
                     Antioch.</note> and <gi>residence</gi> both take <gi>placeName</gi> with a
                  following-sibling <gi>note</gi>. Again, this <gi>placeName</gi> element is
                  self-closing and must include a <att>ref</att> attribute pointing to a Syriaca.org
                  place URI. The <tag>note type="desc"</tag> elements in person factoids provide a
                  human-readable version of the data for the HTML serialization of the factoid. From
                  a purely data-oriented perspective, these <gi>note</gi> elements are not strictly
                  necessary. The semantic value of the TEI elements combined with an ISO date and
                  the URIs in <att>ref</att> attributes suffice to produce usable, machine-readable
                  data. The Srophé Application is able to ingest this combination of person, date,
                  and place information and facilitate visualization and queries of the data. We
                  will discuss the use of the <gi>note</gi> element below, after we have seen some
                  of the broader context that makes its significance clearer.</p>
               <p>The remaining types of person factoids collected by <title>SPEAR</title> require a
                  slightly different structure. The <gi>education</gi>, <gi>occupation</gi>,
                     <gi>state</gi>, <gi>trait</gi>, and <gi>socecStatus</gi> elements each have
                  only one child element, a <tag>note type="desc"</tag>. Again in this context, the
                     <gi>note</gi> element offers a more prose-oriented expression of the factoid.
                  However, unlike the situation featuring the elements discussed in the previous
                  paragraph, some additional information is necessary to produce the kind of highly
                  structured data required by <title>SPEAR</title>. Here <title>SPEAR</title> again
                  makes use of <title>The Syriac Taxonomy</title>. The <gi>education</gi>,
                     <gi>occupation</gi>, <gi>state</gi>, <gi>trait</gi>, and <gi>socecStatus</gi>
                  elements all take an <att>ana</att> attribute with a <title>Taxonomy</title>
                  keyword URI as their value. <ref type="crossref" target="#example11">Example
                     11</ref> contains a factoid asserting the occupation of a person who was a
                  Christian bishop. <figure xml:id="example11">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ab type="factoid" subtype="occupation" xml:id="factoid-191"
                           resp="#dschwartz">
                           <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/spear/8559-191</idno>
                           <listPerson>
                              <person>
                                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2251"/>
                                 <occupation ana="http://syriaca.org/keyword/bishops">
                                    <note type="desc">
                                       <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2251"
                                          >Cyrus</persName> was Bishop of <placeName
                                          ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2605"> Edessa
                                       </placeName>.</note>
                                 </occupation>
                              </person>
                           </listPerson> ... </ab>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Person factoid: occupation</head>
                  </figure> The use of the URI for bishops as the value for the <att>ana</att>
                  attribute on the <gi>occupation</gi> element provides a controlled vocabulary for
                  describing the specific occupation but also serves to connect this occupation
                  factoid to 238 scholarly books and articles in the Syriaca.org bibliography that
                  researchers have also described using that keyword URI.</p>
               <p>A similar use of the <att>ana</att> attribute functions the same way on the
                     <gi>education</gi> and <gi>socecStatus</gi> elements. Moreover,
                     <title>SPEAR</title> uses the <gi>state</gi> and <gi>trait</gi> elements in a
                  similar fashion for the purpose of encoding ethnic label, gender, mental state,
                  physical trait, sanctity (used as a general category for people described as
                     <q>saints</q>, <q>martyrs</q>, etc.), and social rank. <title>SPEAR</title>
                  follows the TEI in using the <gi>state</gi> element for qualities more likely to
                  change over time and <gi>trait</gi> for qualities that are more permanent or not a
                  matter of the person’s will (<ref type="bibl" target="#teiConsortium2020">TEI
                     Consortium 2020, 13.3.1</ref>). The <gi>state</gi> element requires a
                     <att>type</att> attribute with one of the following values: <val>mental</val>
                  or <val>sanctity</val>. The <att>type</att> attribute on the <gi>trait</gi>
                  element can be either <val>ethnicLabel</val>, <val>gender</val>, or
                     <val>physical</val>. As with <gi>education</gi>, <gi>occupation</gi>, and
                     <gi>socecStatus</gi> discussed above and shown in <ref type="crossref"
                     target="#example11">example 11</ref>, <gi>state</gi> and <gi>trait</gi> also
                  require an <att>ana</att> attribute pointing to the appropriate keyword.</p>
               <p>Wherever <title>SPEAR</title> employs keyword URIs from the
                     <title>Taxonomy</title>, the customized schema constrains the <att>ana</att>
                  values, pointing encoders to keywords from the relevant subsets of the
                     <title>Taxonomy</title>. Metadata in the encoding of the
                     <title>Taxonomy</title> entities indicates which keywords are relevant to an
                  ethnic label, for example, and which to an occupation. Encoders are directed away
                  from <val>http://syriaca.org/keyword/bishops</val> with an <att>ana</att>
                  attribute in a gender factoid or <val>http://syriaca.org/keyword/sogdians</val>
                  with an <att>ana</att> attribute in an occupation factoid. <ref type="crossref"
                     target="#example12">Example 12</ref> shows a Schematron rule that uses an index
                  of the Taxonomy to constrain the use of keywords for occupations. The Schematron
                  rule uses a warning message for this purpose and provides suggested keywords for
                  encoders. This allows encoders to use keywords not in the Taxonomy in cases where
                  appropriate keywords do not exist. The warning message flags the need for an
                  editor to reassess the decisions made by encoders but it also offers a mechanism
                  for the ongoing development of the Taxonomy by collecting concepts encoders cannot
                  find in the controlled vocabulary.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example12">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <constraintSpec ident="ana-in-occupation" scheme="schematron">
                        <constraint>
                           <sch:rule context="//tei:occupation/@ana">
                              <sch:let name="anaValues" value="tokenize(., ' ')"/>
                              <sch:let name="ti"
                                 value="doc('https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/syriaca/master/documentation/indexes/taxonomyIndex.xml')"/>
                              <sch:let name="occupations"
                                 value="$ti//listURI[@type = 'occupations']/uri"/>
                              <sch:let name="error" value="."/>
                              <sch:assert
                                 test="every $i in (tokenize(., ' ')) satisfies $i = $occupations"
                                 role="warning">
                                 <sch:value-of select="$error"/> is not currently in use. SPEAR has
                                 a strong preference for using established URIs when possible but
                                 appropriate URIs are not always available. Please consult the
                                 Taxonomy. If no appropriate keyword exists in the following list,
                                 please use your own preferred descriptive term: <sch:value-of
                                    select="string-join($occupations, ';  ')"/>.</sch:assert>
                           </sch:rule>
                        </constraint>
                     </constraintSpec>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Schematron rule in <ref
                        target="https://github.com/srophe/syriaca/blob/master/documentation/SPEARschema/SPEAR.odd"
                        >ODD</ref> constraining the use of Taxonomy keywords.</head>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="sources-citations">
               <head>Sources and Citations</head>
               <p>The definition of a factoid discussed earlier focused on the prosopographer’s
                  interpretation of what a historical source asserts about persons. As with other
                  aspects of the project, <title>SPEAR</title> encoding relies heavily on the linked
                  data infrastructure produced by Syriaca.org. Two data sets come into play in this
                  regard, the Syriaca.org bibliography and the <title>New Handbook of Syriac
                     Literature</title> (<title>NHSL</title>). Every <title>SPEAR</title> factoid
                     <gi>ab</gi> element requires one or more <gi>bibl</gi> elements. Each
                     <gi>bibl</gi> element must take a <att>type</att> attribute, showing whether
                  the source referred to is a bibliographic item or a URN in the Canonical Text
                  Services (CTS) system (<ref type="bibl" target="#blackwell2014">Blackwell and
                     Smith 2015</ref>).</p>
               <p>A <tag>bibl type="primary"</tag> indicates a bibliographic reference to a primary
                  source text in the Syriaca.org bibliography. Even though all factoids have a
                  primary source text as the source, the designation distinguishes this source from
                  the URN approach to sourcing factoids. Because Syriaca.org has robust linked data
                  on bibliographic items, a <tag>bibl type="primary"</tag> only contains two
                  elements, <gi>ptr</gi> and <gi>citedRange</gi>. <figure xml:id="example13">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ab type="factoid" subtype="deathDate" xml:id="factoid-155"
                           resp="#dschwartz">
                           <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/spear/8559-155</idno>
                           <listPerson> ... </listPerson>
                           <bibl type="primary">
                              <ptr target="http://syriaca.org/bibl/633"/>
                              <citedRange unit="p">5</citedRange>
                           </bibl>
                        </ab>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Citing the Syriaca.org bibliography</head>
                  </figure> The <gi>ptr</gi> is a self-closing element with a <att>target</att>
                  attribute pointing to a Syriaca.org bibliography URI. Additional information such
                  as author, editor, date, publisher, etc. can be displayed in the HTML
                  serialization of the factoid by drawing on that data from the Syriaca.org
                  bibliography. The factoid does not need to repeat this information in the
                     <gi>bibl</gi> element. The <gi>citedRange</gi> includes a <att>unit</att>
                  attribute and a text node indicating the appropriate place within that source.</p>
               <p>A <tag>bibl type="urn"</tag> indicates that the citation employs the URN system
                  established by the Canonical Text Services (CTS). <note>See <ref
                        target="http://cite-architecture.org/ctsurn/">The CTS URN · The CITE
                        Architecture</ref> and the formal CTS URN specification at <ptr
                        target="https://cite-architecture.github.io/ctsurn_spec/"/>. A related and
                     more recent specification not yet implemented by the <title>Digital Syriac
                        Corpus</title> is <ref
                        target="https://distributed-text-services.github.io/specifications/">(DTS) -
                        Distributed Text Services</ref>. On the relationship between CTS and DTS,
                     see <ptr
                        target="https://distributed-text-services.github.io/specifications/FAQ.html#what-is-the-relationship-between-dts-and-cts-are-they-redundant"
                     />.</note> The URNs used by <title>SPEAR</title> point to the <title>Digital
                     Syriac Corpus</title>, a sister project also using the <ref
                     target="https://srophe.app/">Srophé Application</ref> that encodes the full
                  text of Syriac sources and integrates them with a suite of online lexical tools.
                     <figure xml:id="example14">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ab type="factoid" subtype="event" xml:id="factoid-460" resp="#dschwartz">
                           <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/spear/8559-460</idno>
                           <listEvent>
                              <event
                                 ana="http://syriaca.org/keyword/council-of-chalcedon-451 http://syriaca.org/keyword/deposition-of-clergy">
                                 <desc> In <choice>
                                       <reg><date notBefore="0518-10" notAfter="0519-09"
                                             calendar="#gregorian">518/19</date></reg>
                                       <orig><date when-custom="0830" datingMethod="#seleucid">A.
                                             Gr. 830</date></orig>
                                    </choice>
                                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2268"> Justin
                                    </persName> deposed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51"
                                       > Severus </persName> and <persName
                                       ref="http://syriaca.org/person/44"> Philoxenos </persName>
                                    for refusing to accept the Council of <placeName
                                       ref="http://syriaca.org/place/622"> Chalcedon </placeName> .
                                 </desc>
                              </event>
                           </listEvent> ... <bibl type="urn">
                              <ptr target="urn:cts:syriacLit:nhsl8559.syriacCorpus57:87"/>
                           </bibl>
                        </ab>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">A factoid citing the <title>Digital Syriac
                        Corpus</title></head>
                  </figure> The inclusion of URNs allows the <ref target="https://srophe.app/"
                     >Srophé Application</ref> to make a call to the CTS API and return the piece of
                  text cited in the factoid. This source text is then displayed on each factoid page
                  along with a link that users can follow to see this piece of text in the context
                  of the whole encoded work and to make use of linked lexical tools.</p>
               <figure xml:id="graphic2">
                  <graphic url="images/htmlFactoid.png" height="846px" width="688px"/>
                  <head type="legend">HTML serialization with <title>Digital Syriac Corpus</title>
                     text displayed</head>
               </figure>
               <p>This use of URNs highlights <title>SPEAR</title>’s departure from more traditional
                  practice in using the TEI. Most often, the TEI is used to encode a primary source
                  text. A robust project will generally produce a personography that exists as
                  stand-off markup containing a list of identifiers, names, and personal
                  information. <title>SPEAR</title> uses URNs pointing to externally encoded texts
                  in such a way as to invert the typical practice of TEI encoding. Born digital
                  prosopographical factoids are the <title>SPEAR</title> data and, from the
                  perspective of <title>SPEAR</title>, the historical source encoded in the Syriac
                  Corpus functions as stand-off markup. Of course, from the perspective of the
                  Syriac Corpus, <title>SPEAR</title> and the collection of Syriaca.org authority
                  files function as stand-off markup. Using the TEI along with robust linked data
                  standards allows various semi-independent digital projects to produce rich sets of
                  linked resources using a de-centralized workflow. Each of these resources can
                  maintain their own research agenda and intended audience while also providing data
                  that benefit the others.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="notes-descriptions">
               <head>Notes and Descriptions</head>
               <p>Though they appear in several different contexts within <title>SPEAR</title>, it
                  is best to consider the <gi>note</gi> and <gi>desc</gi> elements in one place. As
                  mentioned earlier, the TEI Guidelines have limitations on which elements can take
                  a child <gi>note</gi> or a child <gi>desc</gi>. From the perspective of the data
                  encoded, <title>SPEAR</title> does not understand a significant difference between
                  these two. We considered the option of customizing the schema to allow one of the
                  two elements to appear in parallel contexts for each type of factoid. Rather than
                  take this course, we decided to conform the data model to the TEI Guidelines but
                  within those parameters strive to be as consistent as possible.
                     <title>SPEAR</title> uses the <gi>note</gi> element inside person factoids
                  because it is allowed in each of the requisite contexts: <gi>birth</gi>,
                     <gi>death</gi>, <gi>education</gi>, <gi>nationality</gi>, <gi>residence</gi>,
                     <gi>occupation</gi>, <gi>langKnown</gi>, <gi>state</gi>, <gi>trait</gi>, and
                     <gi>socecStatus</gi>. The <gi>desc</gi> element is allowed as a child for some
                  of these elements but in order to maintain consistency across the person factoids,
                     <title>SPEAR</title> made the choice to use <tag>note type="desc"</tag>
                  consistently instead of mixing <gi>note</gi> and <gi>desc</gi> elements.
                     <title>SPEAR</title> uses <gi>desc</gi> as a child of <gi>event</gi> and
                     <gi>relation</gi> elements in those factoid types. <title>SPEAR</title> also
                  has a second use for the <gi>note</gi> element. When appearing as a child of
                     <gi>occupation</gi>, <gi>state</gi>, etc. in a person factoid it offers a prose
                  expression of that factoid content; a <gi>note</gi> element can also appear as the
                  child of the factoid <gi>ab</gi>. Here it functions as a discursive note applied
                  to the entire factoid. We will look at these uses in turn.</p>
               <p>The use of <gi>note</gi> or <gi>desc</gi> in the first context mentioned above
                  highlights an important aspect of the decision to use TEI for this factoid
                  prosopography. TEI offers a well-established and widely used standard for encoding
                  texts. As such, it allows users to take heterogeneous corpora of textual material
                  and mark it up in such a way as to make it amenable to computation in a wide
                  variety of ways. As mentioned above, <title>SPEAR</title> briefly attempted to
                  accomplish the kind of highly structured data it sought by encoding texts directly
                  in the TEI. This proved prohibitively difficult and, in some aspects, not
                  possible. The options were either to abandon the TEI in favor of an RDF data set
                  or a relational database, or to model factoids in TEI instead of modeling the
                  texts themselves. The decision to employ the TEI and model the factoids came down
                  to the ability of the TEI to combine structured data via the hierarchy of the tree
                  structure and the extensive use of pointers to linked data with prose descriptions
                  of that data. The use of <gi>note</gi> and <gi>desc</gi> elements play an
                  important role in this regard. <title>SPEAR</title> uses these elements to offer
                  prose descriptions of the data that can capture and display the requisite nuance.
                     <figure xml:id="example15">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <event
                           ana="http://syriaca.org/keyword/council-of-chalcedon-451 http://syriaca.org/keyword/patriarchs">
                           <desc> After <choice>
                                 <reg><date notBefore="0525-06-27" calendar="#gregorian">27 June
                                       525</date></reg>
                                 <orig><date notBefore-custom="0836-09-27"
                                       datingMethod="#seleucid-SyriacMonths">27 Ḥazirān A. Gr.
                                       836</date></orig>
                              </choice>, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2296"> Pawlā
                              </persName> repented of his opposition to the Council of <placeName
                                 ref="http://syriaca.org/place/622"> Chalcedon </placeName>,
                              petitioned <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284"> Justinian
                              </persName> for the return of his episcopal see, and wrote a libellus
                              affirming the council to <persName
                                 ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2278"> Euphrasius the Patriarch
                              </persName>. </desc>
                        </event>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">Event description</head>
                  </figure>
                  <ref type="crossref" target="#example15">Example 15</ref> shows how the various
                  parts of an event factoid come together to produce data out of a reference to an
                  event in a historical source. The encoders have attached keywords on the
                     <gi>event</gi> element, and then offered a rich description of the event that
                  captures the dating system employed in the source document along with references
                  to relevant persons and places. The pointers applied in this factoid as well as
                  elsewhere in the data set create a graph of relationships between these concepts,
                  persons, and places amenable to various forms of computation. These machinable
                  data are at the same time prose descriptions capturing the encoder’s
                  interpretation of the factoid—an interpretation that would be difficult or
                  impossible to represent in a relationship graph alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <title>SPEAR</title> also allows a <gi>note</gi> element to appear as a child of
                     <gi>ab</gi>. In such instances it is used to express the scholarly assessment
                  of the encoder regarding the veracity of the content of the factoid. <figure
                     xml:id="example16">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <note type="errata"> Since the first session of the Council of Chalcedon
                           began on 8 October (Teshri I) of 451, the correct year according to the
                           Greek calendar (A. Gr.) would be 763, not 762. <bibl type="secondary">
                              <ptr target="http://syriaca.org/bibl/660"/>
                              <citedRange unit="p">113</citedRange>
                           </bibl></note>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">A note on the factoid</head>
                  </figure> Recall that factoids contain the encoder’s interpretation of a primary
                  source text. This <gi>note</gi> element requires a <att>type</att> attribute with
                     <val>dubia</val>, <val>errata</val>, or <val>incerta</val> for expressing
                  different types of uncertainty encoders can use to express their position on the
                  prosopographical datum contained in that factoid. A text node contains a prose
                  description of that uncertainty and optional <gi>bibl</gi> elements allow the
                  encoder to indicate a scholarly source discussing the issue.</p>
               <p>Occasionally more than one factoid deals with the same or a closely related event.
                     <title>SPEAR</title> cannot make direct links between events themselves because
                  events do not receive URIs and related authority files. When encoders are aware of
                  another factoid dealing with a related event, they can include a <tag>note
                     type="relatedEvent"</tag>. <figure xml:id="example17">
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ab type="factoid" subtype="event" xml:id="factoid-388" resp="#dschwartz">
                           <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/spear/8559-388</idno>
                           <listEvent>
                              <event ana="http://syriaca.org/keyword/natural-disasters">
                                 <desc> In <choice>
                                       <reg><date notBefore="0498-10" notAfter="0499-09"
                                             calendar="#gregorian">498/9</date></reg>
                                       <orig><date when-custom="0810" datingMethod="#seleucid">A.
                                             Gr. 810</date></orig>
                                    </choice> the city of <placeName
                                       ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2574"> Nicopolis </placeName>
                                    was destroyed by an earthquake. </desc>
                              </event>
                           </listEvent> ... <note type="relatedEvent">
                              <listRelation>
                                 <relation ref="http://syriaca.org/keyword/proximate-event"
                                    type="event"
                                    mutual="http://syriaca.org/spear/8559-388 http://syriaca.org/spear/8559-389 http://syriaca.org/spear/8559-396">
                                    <desc> The following factoids deal with closely related events:
                                          <rs ref="http://syriaca.org/spear/8559-388">8559-388</rs>,
                                          <rs ref="http://syriaca.org/spear/8559-389">8559-389</rs>,
                                          <rs ref="http://syriaca.org/spear/8559-396">8559-396</rs>
                                    </desc>
                                 </relation>
                              </listRelation>
                           </note>
                        </ab>
                     </egXML>
                     <head type="legend">A note indicating multiple factoids encoding related
                        events</head>
                  </figure> This <gi>relation</gi> element must have a <att>mutual</att> attribute
                  with the URIs for two or more factoids. <title>SPEAR</title> uses a <att>ref</att>
                  attribute on <gi>relation</gi> to indicate the type of <gi>relation</gi>. The
                  acceptable values are either <val>http://syriaca.org/keyword/same-event</val> or
                     <val>http://syriaca.org/keyword/proximate-event</val>. The former is reserved
                  for explicit references to the same event encoded in different event factoids
                  while the latter creates a link between factoids that deal with closely related
                  events. This connection would include things like causal connections between
                  events and containing relationships between events.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="visualization">
            <head>Visualizing Factoid Data in the Srophé Application</head>
            <p>Structuring factoids and embedding URIs in them as described above makes it possible
               to visualize and query the resulting data graph in a variety of ways. The scope of
               this paper does not allow a full discussion of these issues, but a demonstration of
               the utility of using the TEI requires at least a brief discussion of how the <ref
                  target="https://srophe.app/">Srophé Application</ref> uses eXist-DB to display
               SPEAR data. Factoids can be viewed individually with links to related data as shown
               above in <ptr target="#graphic2" type="crossref"/>, but they can also be aggregated
               by source text or across multiple source texts according to person, keyword, or place
               URIs. <ptr target="#graphic3" type="crossref"/> shows the aggregation of factoids
               about one individual. The events associated with this person are displayed on a
               timeline. Related persons, places, and keywords are also displayed in a force graph
               (shown), sankey graph, or a list. The <ref target="https://srophe.app/">Srophé
                  Application</ref> also facilitates faceted browse of factoid data and search by
               multiple fields. Thus, TEI-encoded factoids can not only capture nuanced
               interpretations in structured, transparent assertions containing linked-data
               pointers; they can also benefit from the same kinds of aggregate, dynamic
               visualizations that relational databases provide.</p>
            <figure xml:id="graphic3">
               <graphic url="images/aggregation.png" height="2030px" width="3824px"/>
               <head type="legend">Aggregation of factoid data about a person showing force graph
                  and event timeline</head>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="conclusion">
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p><title>SPEAR</title> demonstrates the value of bringing the TEI to the task of
               modeling prosopographical factoids. While this may not fit the process all factoid
               prosopography projects use, it is a viable alternative to RDBs and one that fits the
               ethos of the TEI, that is, open and well-documented community-based encoding. The
               ability of the user to view the native TEI data, combined with the use of a
               customized TEI schema for validation and documentation, enhances the transparency of
               the data. Applying linked data standards to the modeling of prosopographical data in
               the TEI allows for the integration of structured data about persons and
               semi-structured, marked-up prose interpretations of the historical sources from which
               they are derived. These prose interpretations enrich the resulting data graph and
               easily display a human-readable version of the data with hyperlinks that connect the
               user to additional linked data. Using the TEI brings transparency to the model by
               maintaining a close connection between each factoid datum and the text from which the
               encoder derives it. Each factoid makes a prosopographical assertion about a text,
               indicates the scholar responsible for that textual interpretation, and points the
               user to the text. In this way, <title>SPEAR</title> uses the TEI both to model
               prosopographical factoids and to model the scholarly process by which the factoids
               are produced.</p>
            <p>Combining this approach with the LOD infrastructure of Syriaca.org further enhances
               the data-oriented approach to the textual interpretation of <title>SPEAR</title>.
               Pointers in <att>ref</att> attributes do not point to project-specific
                  <att>xml:id</att> attributes in a stand-off markup file but to linked data that
               have an independent purpose. These URIs are also used by other projects: digital
               research projects, encoded reference works, etc. The <title>Taxonomy</title> URIs
                  <title>SPEAR</title> applies to events, occupations, etc. are the same URIs used
               to catalog and describe bibliography, thus creating links between these and other
               data sets. This approach demonstrates a way that autonomous and semi-autonomous
               research projects can maintain their distinctive research agendas and methodologies
               while providing critical metadata for general use. This level of linking results in a
               different kind of born-digital application for the TEI, one in which the encoding of
               primary source texts remains important but can also be transcended through the
               encoding of born-digital interpretations of those texts.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="blackwell2014">
                  <author>Blackwell, Christopher</author> and <author>Neel Smith</author>.
                     <date>2014</date>. <title level="u">The Canonical Text Services URN Protocol
                     Specification</title>. <ptr
                     target="https://cite-architecture.github.io/ctsurn_spec/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bodard2021">
                  <author>Bodard, Gabriel</author>. <date>2021</date>. <title level="a">Linked Open
                     Data for Ancient Names and People</title>. In <title>Linked Open Data for the
                     Ancient Mediterranean: Structures, Practices, Prospects</title>, edited by
                     <editor>Sarah E. Bond</editor>, <editor>Paul Dilley</editor>, and <editor>Ryan
                     Horne</editor>. <series>
                     <title level="s">ISAW Papers</title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>.</series><ptr
                     target="http://hdl.handle.net/2333.1/zs7h4fs8"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bradley2005">
                  <author>Bradley, John</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title level="a">Documents and
                     Data: Modelling Materials for Humanities Research in XML and Relational
                     Databases</title>. <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>, no. <biblScope unit="issue"
                  >1</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">133–51</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqh048"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bradley2014">
                  <author>Bradley, John</author>. <date>2014</date>
                  <title level="a">Silk Purses and Sow’s Ears: Can Structured Data Deal with
                     Historical Sources?</title>
                  <title level="j">International Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts Computing: A
                     Journal of Digital Humanities</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>, no. <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>:
                     <biblScope unit="page">13–27</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="https://doi.org/10.3366/ijhac.2014.0117"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bradleyShort2005">
                  <author>Bradley, John</author> and <author>Harold Short</author>.
                     <date>2005</date>. <title level="a">Texts into Databases: The Evolving Field of
                     New-style Prosopography</title>. <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic
                     Computing</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>, no. <biblScope unit="issue"
                  >1</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">3–24</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqi022"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="cameron2003">
                  <editor>Cameron, Averil</editor>. <date>2003</date>. <title level="m">Fifty Years
                     of Prosopography: The Later Roman Empire, Byzantium and Beyond</title>. <title
                     level="s">Proceedings of the British Academy</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Oxford University
                  Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="gibson2017">
                  <author>Gibson, Nathan P.</author>, <author>David A. Michelson</author>, and
                     <author>Daniel L. Schwartz</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">From
                     Manuscript Catalogues to a Handbook of Syriac Literature: Modeling an
                     Infrastructure for Syriaca.org</title>. <title level="j">Journal of Data Mining
                     and Digital Humanities</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">Special Issue on Computer-Aided Processing of
                     Intertextuality in Ancient Languages</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                     >1–15</biblScope>. <ptr target="https://jdmdh.episciences.org/1395"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Jannidis2018">
                  <author>Jannidis, Fotis</author> and <author>Julia Flanders</author>.
                     <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">A Gentle Introduction to Data
                     Modeling</title>. In <title level="m">The Shape of Data in Digital Humanities:
                     Modeling Texts and Text-Based Resources</title>, edited by <editor>Jannidis
                     Fotis</editor> and <editor>Julia Flanders</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >26–95</biblScope>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Routledge</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="keats-rohan2000">
                  <author>Keats-Rohan, K. S. B.</author>
                  <date>2000</date>. <title level="a">Prosopography and Computing: A Marriage Made
                     in Heaven?</title>
                  <title level="j">History and Computing</title>. <biblScope unit="volume"
                     >12</biblScope>, no. <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>: <biblScope
                     unit="page">1–11</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="https://doi.org/10.3366/hac.2000.12.1.1"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="king2018">
                  <editor>King, Daniel</editor>. <date>2018-12-14</date><title level="m">The Syriac
                     World</title>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Routledge</publisher>.
                     <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4324/9781315708195"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="marsh2014">
                  <author>Marsh, David</author>. <date>2014–01–17</date>. <title level="a">A Factoid
                     is not a Small Fact</title>. <title level="j">The Guardian</title>. <title
                     level="s">Mind Your Language</title>. <ptr
                     target="https://www.theguardian.com/media/mind-your-language/2014/jan/17/mind-your-language-factoids"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="michelson2021">
                  <author>Michelson, David A.</author>
                  <date>2021</date>. <title level="a">Using Linked Open Data to Model Cultural
                     Heritage Information: The Research Questions and Data Structures of the
                     Syriaca.org Knowledge Graph</title>. In <title>Linked Open Data for the Ancient
                     Mediterranean: Structures, Practices, Prospects</title>, edited by
                     <editor>Sarah E. Bond</editor>, <editor>Paul Dilley</editor>, and <editor>Ryan
                     Horne</editor>. <series>
                     <title level="s">ISAW Papers</title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>.</series>
                  <ptr target="http://hdl.handle.net/2333.1/69p8d8cc"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pasin2015">
                  <author>Pasin, Michele</author> and <author>John Bradley</author>.
                     <date>2015</date>. <title level="a">Factoid-based Prosopography and Computer
                     Ontologies: Towards an Integrated Approach</title>. <title level="j">Digital
                     Scholarship in the Humanities</title>. <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>,
                  no. <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                     >86–97</biblScope>. <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqt037"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="patton2009">
                  <author>Patton, Glenn E.</author>
                  <date>2009</date>. <title level="m">Functional Requirements for Authority Data: A
                     Conceptual Model</title>. <pubPlace>Berlin and Boston</pubPlace>: <publisher>De
                     Gruyter</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="sauerman2008">
                  <author>Sauerman, Leo</author> and <author>Richard Cyganiak</author>. <title
                     level="u">Cool URIs for the Semantic Web</title>. <title level="s">W3C Interest
                     Group Note</title>. <ptr
                     target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2008/NOTE-cooluris-20081203/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="teiConsortium2020">
                  <author>TEI Consortium</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="m">TEI P5:
                     Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>. Version 4.1.0.
                  Last updated August 19. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>: <publisher>TEI
                     Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="viglianti2016">
                  <author>Viglianti, Raffaele</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">Why TEI
                     Stand-off Markup Authoring Needs Simplification</title>. <title level="j"
                     >Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>. <biblScope unit="volume"
                     >10</biblScope>. <ptr target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1838"
                  />.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
