<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                    <title type="main">Visualizing Mouvance: Towards an Alignment of Medieval Vernacular Text Traditions</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Jänicke</surname>
                        <forename>Stefan</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Institut für Informatik, Universität Leipzig, Leipzig, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>stjaenicke@informatik.uni-leipzig.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wrisley</surname>
                        <forename>David Joseph</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>American University of Beirut, Lebanon (Lebanese Republic)</affiliation>
                    <email>dwrisley@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016-03-04T14:52:33.252588735</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Maciej Eder, Pedagogical University in Krakow</publisher>
                <publisher>Jan Rybicki, Jagiellonian University</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Institute of Polish Studies</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Pedagogical University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ul. Podchorazych 2</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>30-084 Krakow, Poland</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>maciej.eder@ijp-pan.krakow.pl</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from an OASIS Open Document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.21">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>text alignment</term>
                    <term>visualization</term>
                    <term>textual variance</term>
                    <term>medieval French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>literary studies</term>
                    <term>medieval studies</term>
                    <term>french studies</term>
                    <term>philology</term>
                    <term>visualisation</term>
                    <term>folklore and oral history</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Poetry in the Middle Ages changed as it was recopied, recited and passed along. 
                <hi rend="italic">Mouvance</hi> is a term used by late Swiss medievalist Paul Zumthor to designate the high degree of instability in medieval text traditions. Zumthor qualifies this instability as an “interplay between variant readings and reworkings,” balancing both the textual, literary elements of written works with oral, performative ones (Zumthor, 1992; p.44). Twentieth-century text editing came to grips with this instability in large text traditions in different ways. For complex text traditions with a high degree of variance in medieval French, editors sometimes compiled one edition containing all the witnesses in successive chapters, as in the cases of 
                <hi rend="italic">La vie de sainte Marie l’Egyptienne</hi> (Dembowski, 1977) and 
                <hi rend="italic">L’Evangile de Nicodème</hi> (Ford, 1973) or they arranged them in a synoptic-style parallel edition as in the case of the <hi rend="italic">fabliaux</hi> (Rychner, 1960). The alignment of such synoptic editions, although not discussed explicitly by the editors, was no doubt hand-ordered and its page layout was based on rough narrative equivalence of passages.
            </p>
            <p>Cerquiglini has argued that, faced with such variance, the medievalist’s “analysis must be comparative, not archeological” (Cerquiglini, 1999; p.44). Such parallel print editions provide readers with a visual frame for comparative reading of variant texts, inviting exploration and giving insight into processes of textual change. There are a number of problems in text traditions with oral influence. There are not only different kinds of variance (single word/string variance, half-line or hemistich variance, transposition and reorganization of rhyming verse lines or interpolation of entirely new lines), but patterns of variance are also not uniform across a text, making the desired comparative visualization of texts difficult. Alignments can also mix and confuse kinds of variance. What are ways of visualizing textual variation in a digital environment? This is the question our paper intends to explore.</p>
            <p>Visualization strategies for historical text reuse vary according to the scale of the phenomenon and the nature of the texts involved (Franzini et al., 2015). Sophisticated visualizations for alignment exist at the micro-level, that is, at the level of the word such as the graph visualizations of TRAViz (Jänicke et al., 2015). They facilitate comparative readings of word-level variance in manuscript witnesses or translations. The text in such alignments is fully legible. A clean example of this can be found in the TRAViz alignments of English translations of the Bible (Figure 1), a textual use case in which units and sub-units of text are already commonly agreed upon by tradition (e.g. book, chapter, verse). On the other hand, solutions exist for macro-level text reuse, such as fingerprinting techniques (Jänicke and Geßner, 2015), creating distant patterns of textual similarity without showing the text (Figure 2).</p>
            <p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="275/10000000000006400000010E6F6B0156047D0DD6.png"/>
                    <head>Figure 1: Micro-level alignment of 24 English translations of Genesis 1:1 (Jänicke et al., 2015)</head>
                </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="275/10000000000004E20000034E57377D9A62E9DF27.png"/>
                    <head>Figure 2: Macro-level fingerprint illustrates similarity between 24 English Bible translations (Jänicke and Geßner, 2015)</head>
                </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">A critical discussion of the description and design of meso-level visualization of complex text traditions is missing. Not only are these text traditions large, but they are highly influenced by orality, that is, in Zumthor's words, they present a combination of textual and performative variance. Textual reworking at multiple scales (whole chunks of text, groups of lines, individual lines, sub-line strings) are challenges for both alignment and visualization. Our design attempts to translate the insights of Zumthor and Cerquiglini into an environment for visual exploration using two medieval text traditions: a tradition of short baudy tales known as the </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">fabliaux</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">,</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> and in versions of the well-known epic the </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Chanson de Roland</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">.</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)italic"> </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">These two traditions have been chosen for the kinds of complex variance they exhibit. Our paper focuses on so-called meso-level alignments that visualize patterns of textual variance higher than the word and verse line level, and stress both legibility and human interaction in visualizing patterns.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Existing methods for text alignment in digital environments, generally speaking, favor relatively stable texts with small variance. The Versioning Machine accepts texts encoded “according to TEI's Parallel Segmentation method” and “interprets the encoding, parsing out the text into its constituent parts” (Versioning Machine, 2015). The authors of the Versioning Machine offer a sample alignment of a medieval “Prophecy of Merlin” (Figure 3). The line-to-line alignment has been encoded by the textual scholar. Similar lines are visually connected using customary mouse behavior, however, variance within the line or across lines is not visualized.</p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="275/100000000000034F000000FC327D18466BD2829B.png"/>
                        <head>Figure 3: Two versions of the Prophecy of Merlin visualized in Versioning Machine</head>
                    </figure>
                </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">Another environment for the collation of raw text and visualization of textual differences is JuxtaCommons (Wheeles and Jensen, 2013). The example in Figure 4 uses two editions of Chretien de Troyes’ medieval romance </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Perceval</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">,</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> one based on BnF, ms. français 12576 (Roach, 1959) at left, and the other Bern, Burgerbibliothek ms. 354 (Méla, 1990) at right. There is basic alignment of the verse line and minor lexical or dialectal variance, and mouse over in JuxtaCommons allows basic comparative reading of word- and string-level variants. In their out-of-the-box implementation, both tools allow </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">for easy </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">comparison of two versions of the text, although the Versioning Machine has been implemented for larger comparison sets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="275/10000000000005010000021C80C4C88CD7ED0954.png"/>
                        <head>Figure 4: Two editions of Chretien de Troyes’ Perceval visualized in JuxtaCommons</head>
                    </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">When complex text traditions containing more than just variant readings, but also interpolations, extra or missing lines or a significant amount of orthographic variance are collated automatically in JuxtaCommons, their results, however, are nearly illegible. Figure 5 shows two </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">witnesses</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> of </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">the same</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> old French </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">fabliau</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">;</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> the visual alignment, however, does an insufficient job at expressing the performative element of their </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">mouvance</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="275/10000000000004FD000001F4B88CFDAD106D5143.png"/>
                        <head>Figure 5: Two versions of a fabliau visualized in JuxtaCommons</head>
                    </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">Our design for a sufficient representation of </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">variance in</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> the</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">fabliaux</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> is shown in Figure 6. We use the intuitive quality of stream graphs (Byron et al., 2008) in order to support the analysis of aligned verses and to illustrate the transmission of one </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">fabliau</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">in four versions. The text editions are juxtaposed in columns in order to minimize edge crossings, in other words, we order the editions according to their similarity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="275/10000000000004D200000396D171FF1B4FAB2C40.png"/>
                        <head>Figure 6: Four versions of a fabliau in our design</head>
                    </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
                <anchor xml:id="id_docs-internal-guid-c13027de-4252-f2aa-16ae-1759b2647bb4"/>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">The visualization is available at</hi>
                <ref target="http://informatik.uni-leipzig.de:8080/Fabliaux/">
                    <hi rend="color(#1155cc)"> </hi>
                </ref>
                <ptr target="http://informatik.uni-leipzig.de:8080/Fabliaux/"/>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">. </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">Clicking on a specific verse line produces a TRAViz micro-view of the line-level variance (Jänicke et al., 2015), whereas the larger meso-view of this portion of the </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">fabliau</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">allows patterns between and across verse lines to be clearly ascertained. </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">V</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">ariance </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">in this genre </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">maintains prosody and avoids hypermeter; </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">mouvance</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">is characterized </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">here </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">by the interpolation of larger narrative multi-line fragments of text. The exception to this general rule is manuscript Harley 2253 in the column at far right where the narrative is reconstituted almost completely around sparse line re-use, illustrating what Rychner calls in the subtitle of his book “deteriorization” </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">[dégradation] </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">(Rychner, 1960). </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Mouvance</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">occurs in multi-line “chunks,” visible in </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">highly legible streams of text re-use. This provides much more insight into textual transformation than reading Rychner’s hand-aligned synoptic edition, with the streams </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">here </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">drawing our attention to patterns of re-used text. In his edition, blank spaces and horizontal lines in the page layout effect a more uncertain alignment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">Another example of what we are calling meso-level alignment is the visualization of one stanza from the </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Chanson de Roland</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">tradition contained in six manuscripts. </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">Figure 7 illustrates</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">laisse</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">1 of the Lavergne fragment, absent from Oxford, Bodleian Library manuscript Digby, 23. An interactive version of the alignment is available at</hi>
                <ref target="http://informatik.uni-leipzig.de:8080/roland/index2.html?ftsize=11">
                    <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                </ref>
                <ptr target="http://informatik.uni-leipzig.de:8080/roland/index2.html?ftsize=11"/>
                <hi rend="color(#1155cc)underline">.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <anchor xml:id="id_docs-internal-guid-c13027de-4253-a9f9-d546-e3b8c763bc67"/>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="275/10000201000005C5000002FE08346E7609AD2FCC.png"/>
                        <head>Figure 7: Six editions and one fragment of the Chanson de Roland in our design</head>
                    </figure>
                </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <anchor xml:id="id_docs-internal-guid-c13027de-4254-48b8-72bb-849f0195e26e"/>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">To indicate how often lines recur across the whole manuscript tradition, we use streams colored </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">with</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> varying saturation. Highly saturated colors indicate frequently repeated passages, whereas less saturated colors indicate less repeated ones. Such a feature allows for a “consensus” visualization of the tradition at this meso scale. It is easy to see the more complex, transpositional variance of lines in the </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Chanson de</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic"> Roland</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">.</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> This compositional feature of French epic visualized here needs to be studied across the entire corpus of seven manuscripts and three fragments. It is perhaps on this point, however, that a principle of visualization clashes with the visual expectations of a medieval textual scholar. As in the above example, we ordered the </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">editions to reduce the number of crossing streams and to maximize legibility. This is potentially at odds with readers who expect to see temporality of manuscript dating represented in the visualization. More thinking needs to be done about the visual semantics of such a large tradition. In such a case, a perfect order that produces less clutter might be hard to determine, and we will be required to extend our proposed design.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">We began with the alignment of the </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">fabliaux</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">and </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Chanson de Roland</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">since they are traditions where editors have indexed alignment manually, either using page layout or by </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">numerical </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">cross referencing </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">of the stanzas</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">.</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">As the example shown in Figure 8 illustrates, </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">lin</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">es are not identical word for word, but rather our alignment has asserted basic diegetical equivalence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <anchor xml:id="id_docs-internal-guid-c13027de-4254-a979-5799-5c8c612441bb"/>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="275/10000000000004B3000001F98C8F70B7E5AD807C.png"/>
                    <head>Figure 8: Visualization of an aligned verse line in three versions of a fabliau</head>
                </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
                <anchor xml:id="id_docs-internal-guid-c13027de-4254-fcf3-5a99-8679adf6ead0"/>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="275/100002010000046E0000024C5FE649DE32830886.png"/>
                        <head>Figure 9: Alignment of an aligned verse among seven Chanson de Roland editions</head>
                    </figure>
                </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <anchor xml:id="id_docs-internal-guid-c13027de-4255-7162-e175-023e1728ab02"/>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">In the example portrayed in Figure 9, performative </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">mouvance</hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">is reflected in the recombination of words in the line.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In developing our research on this topic, we intend to pursue more granular alignment using computational means, down to the line and perhaps the hemistich. Based on the Relative Edit Distance of strings (Jänicke et al., 2015), we aim to determine spelling variants and rhyme sets automatically. Combined with an n-gram analysis, we will support the discovery and alignment of similar text passages. Due to the high degree of orthographic variance of the medieval French language, a purely computational approach might lead to a high number of false positive alignments. Therefore, we will design a visual analytics system that includes the human in the alignment process in order to configure appropriate settings that maximize the alignment of re-used text passages. This visual analytics process includes the supervised training of a classifier that supplies the parameters steering the alignment. Iteratively, computationally aligned text fragments are scored by the textual scholar according to their relevance. After each scoring session, the alignment will be recomputed taking the scholar's justifications into account.</p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">In contrast to the manual alignment illustrated in the visualizations above (Figures 6-9), such a semi-automated process will potentially yield a very different picture in particular with respect to the degree of difference the human allows in string matching and the presence of shared n-grams required to align certain text passages. A further opportunity of this generic visual analytics approach is its straightforward adaptability to editions in other languages than medieval French. With </hi>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">such a user-centered approach, alignment is not to be understood as a final product, but rather a process, for understanding variant text traditions, exploring their intricacies and supporting generation of hypotheses about textual behavior.</hi>
            </p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <anchor xml:id="id_docs-internal-guid-c13027de-4256-65cf-3c19-6d800e1d885c"/>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Anonymous (2005).</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">La Chanson de Roland / The Song of Roland: The French Corpus</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> Ed. J. Duggan. Geneva: Droz.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Byron, L., and Wattenberg, M.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">(2008). Stacked graphs–geometry &amp; aesthetics. In </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Visualization and Computer Graphics, IEEE Transactions.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">14.6 (2008): 1245-1252.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Cerquiglini, B.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">(1999). </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">In Praise of the Variant: A Critical History of Philology</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Baltimore/London: The Johns Hopkins Press.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Dembowski, P.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">(1977). </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">La vie de sainte Marie l’Egyptienne, versions en ancien et en moyen français</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Geneva: Droz.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Ford, A.E.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">(1973). </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">L’Evangile de Nicodème: les versions courtes en ancien français et en prose</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Geneva: Droz.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Franzini, G., Franzini, E., Büchler, M.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">(2015). Historical Text Reuse: What Is It?. Available at: </hi>
                        <ref target="http://http//etrap.gcdh.de/?page_id=332">
                            <hi rend="color(#1155cc)underline">http://etrap.gcdh.de/?page_id=332</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">[accessed 3 March 2016].</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Jänicke, S. and Geßner, A.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">(2015). A Distant Reading Visualization for Variant Graphs. In </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Proceedings of the Digital Humanities 2015</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Jänicke, S., Geßner, A., Franzini, G., Terras, M., Mahony, S. and Scheuermann, G. (2015). TRAViz: A Visualization for Variant Graphs. In </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">, 30(suppl.1): i83–i99. </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Available at:</hi>
                        <ref target="http://www.informatik.uni-leipzig.de/~stjaenicke/TRAViz.pdf">
                            <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        </ref>
                        <ptr target="http://www.informatik.uni-leipzig.de/~stjaenicke/TRAViz.pdf"/>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">[accessed 27 October 2015]</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Méla, C. (1990). </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Le Roman de Perceval. Édition du ms. 354 de Berne, traduction critique, présentation et notes</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> By Chrétien de Troyes. Paris, Librairie générale française.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Moffat, M. (2014). </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">The Châteauroux Version of the “Chanson de Roland”: A Fully Annotated Critical Text</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Berlin/Boston: De Gruyter.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Roach, W.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">(1959). </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Le roman de Perceval ou le Conte du Graal</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">publié d'après le ms. fr. 12576 de la Bibliothèque nationale</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> By Chrétien de Troyes.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Geneva, Droz.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Rychner, J.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">(1960). </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Contribution à l’étude des fabliaux: variantes, remaniement, dégradations</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Geneva: Droz.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Versioning Machine.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">(2015).</hi>
                        <ref target="http://v-machine.org/samples/prophecy_of_merlin.html">
                            <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        </ref>
                        <ptr target="http://v-machine.org/samples/prophecy_of_merlin.html"/>
                        <hi rend="color(#1155cc)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">[accessed 27 October 2015]</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Wheeles, D. and Jensen, K.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">(2013). Juxta Commons. In </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Proceedings of the Digital Humanities 2013</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Zumthor, P. (1992). </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Toward a Medieval Poetics</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic">.</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)italic"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="color(#000000)">Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
