<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Change, Transition and Governance: Lessons from a Long-Term, Large Scale DH Collaboration</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Siemens</surname>
                        <forename>Lynne</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Victoria, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>siemensl@uvic.ca</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016-03-02T17:48:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Maciej Eder, Pedagogical University in Krakow</publisher>
                <publisher>Jan Rybicki, Jagiellonian University</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Institute of Polish Studies</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Pedagogical University</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>ul. Podchorazych 2</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>30-084 Krakow, Poland</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>maciej.eder@ijp-pan.krakow.pl</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.20">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>collaboration</term>
                    <term>project management</term>
                    <term>INKE</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>digital humanities - institutional support</term>
                    <term>project design, organization, management</term>
                    <term>interdisciplinary collaboration</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Digital Humanities (DH) is becoming increasingly a collaborative community of practice, a move encouraged both by the scale, scope and complexity of projects (L. Siemens and Burr, 2013) and by granting agencies with programs such as Digging into Data (2013), the new Bilateral Digital Humanities Program between the National Endowment for the Humanities’ Office of Digital Humanities and the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, Germany’s research office (2014), Canada’s Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council’s Partnership Grants (2013), and many others. This trend is further supported through efforts such as Fair Cite (2012) and the Collaborators’ Bill of Rights (Off the Tracks, 2011) to more fully recognize project contributions through multi-authorship citation practices, University of Virginia’s Praxis Program which provides collaborative project experience for graduate students (The Praxis Program at the Scholars' Lab, 2011a, 2011b, 2012, nd), and individual DH project charters outlining guidelines for team work (Hjartarson, Fast, and Hasenbank, 2011; Ruecker and Radzikowska, 2007).</p>
            <p>These are all exciting developments that will reap long-term contributions at the individual, project, and DH as a community of practice levels and beyond. At the same, more work is needed to understand how these teams function and the types of supports which are needed to coordinate the research, people and tasks to ensure successful outcomes at these levels (Dombrowski, 2013; Lyall, Bruce, Marsden, and Meagher, 2013). With this knowledge, DH teams will be better able to anticipate benefits and challenges associated with collaborations and develop processes to maximize benefits while minimizing associated challenges. </p>
            <p>At present, much of the body of knowledge about academic team functioning and best practice guidelines has been developed through a reflection process at a project’s completion (For example, see Bracken and Oughton, 2006; Bryan, Negretti, Christensen, and Stokes, 2002; Kishchuk, 2005; Lawrence, 2006; National Endowment for the Humanities Office of Digital Humanities, 2010). These reviews often focus on the actual research work accomplished with little discussion of associated processes that supported the work, communication patterns, and other factors that supported (or not) successful outcomes. As a result, some hard-earned lessons are forgotten or minimized through the passage of time, but might be captured if this type of reflection occurs during a project’s life. </p>
            <p>As a large project in terms of team membership, budget, scope, disciplinary perspectives, and project length and research integration, Implementing New Knowledge Environments (INKE) provides a unique perspective to explore the nature of collaboration (INKE, 2012a). INKE’s primary research focus is the exploration of e-books and their potential from a variety of perspectives, including interface design, modeling and prototyping, user studies, and textual studies (INKE, 2012b). Further, this collaboration is examining the “understanding, creating, and evaluating research structures that will allow academic and non-academic (including industry partner) members of our research team to work together in ways that meet the needs of the research and development cycles of the entire INKE group” (R. G. Siemens, Siemens, Cunningham, Galey, Ruecker, and Warwick, 2012, p. 7)
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">See R. G. Siemens et al. (2009) for the full grant application.</note>. To that end, INKE has undergone yearly reflections on the nature of collaboration within the project with an objective to better understand the ways to support large-scale research collaborations as they unfold and communicate these lessons to other projects for consideration. 
            </p>
            <p>This paper contributes to our understanding of how research teams function by reviewing INKE’s six years of experience in collaboration and with a view to articulate best practice guidelines (L. Siemens and INKE Research Group, 2010, 2012b, 2012c, 2012d, 2012e, 2013).</p>
            <p>Members of the administrative team, researchers, graduate research assistants and others are asked about their experiences collaborating within INKE on an annual basis in order to understand the nature of collaboration and ways that it may change over a grant’s long-term life. The interview questions focus on understanding the nature of collaboration, advantages and challenges associated with it within INKE’s context. These interviews allow the researcher to explore topics more fully and deeply with probing and follow up questions while participants reflect on their own experiences and emphasis those issues which are important to them (Marshall and Rossman, 1999; McCracken, 1988; Newell and Swan, 2000; Rubin and Rubin, 1995). This paper focuses on a summary of the first 5 years of the grant-funded work.</p>
            <p>At the time of writing this proposal, final data analysis is being completed, but clear patterns are emerging and, after final analysis, these will form the basis of my presentation.</p>
            <p>While the grant application suggested a stable team of active researchers and partners, the reality has been very different. Due to a variety of reasons (L. Siemens and INKE Research Group, 2012a, 2013), change and transition have been constant within INKE, which has led to sub-research group re-organizations and the creation of new ones. Concurrently, new researchers, administrative leads and partners joined the team. And as is always the case when working with student research assistants and post-doctoral fellows, sub-research areas were continually recruiting and training new ones as others moved on to other opportunities. </p>
            <p>Grounding this change has been several constants that have ensured the research has been able to continue effectively and efficiently despite the transitions. First, the governance documents outlined clear articulation of roles and responsibilities which became especially important for ensuring that new researchers, partners, and administrative understood and enacted the nature of collaboration and accountability within INKE. At the same time, these documents provided guidance for ensuring that processes for change, transition, planning and reporting, and decision making were considered and thoughtful while remaining responsive to changing circumstances (L. Siemens and INKE Research Group, 2012c). The use of basecamp, an online project space, and an updated project website further reinforced these processes by providing an ongoing repository for messages, documents, data, and publications, all important knowledge for current and new researchers and partners. Second, multiple communication channels, such as annual birds-of-a-feather gatherings, attendance at other conferences, both formal and in-formal face-to-face administrative and sub-research area group meetings, conference calls, and online project spaces, ensured that team members met on a regular basis to exchange information about and participate in research projects with the other sub-research areas, ensuring highly collaborative work.</p>
            <p>As INKE nears the end of its 7 years of funded research, the team is anticipating both winding down this focused work on e-books and exploring next research steps, building from its successes (INKE, 2014). While the research has been intellectually challenging and not without its administrative issues, INKE team members report positive experiences in terms of the collaboration, associated outcomes, and connections to the DH and traditional humanities communities. As measures of this positive spirit and connections, they are extending their collaboration into associated research areas as well as contemplating another large-scale research project. </p>
            <p>This research will make several contributions to the knowledge base about the nature of collaboration within the DH community of practice. First, this research contributes to efforts to make work patterns and relationships more explicit and understand those factors that tend to predispose them to success, and perhaps, more importantly, to avoid those which may lead to problematic interactions. Already, lessons from INKE are informing other projects’ collaborations (Nowviskie, 2011; The Praxis Program at the Scholars’ Lab, nd). Second, INKE’s experience demonstrates that these types of team research projects require skills not typically taught in graduate school, including project management and collaboration within a targeted and integrative research environment, which differs from that of curiosity-based one. This reinforces the call to enlarge graduate training beyond purely disciplinary to these larger collaborative skills to ensure that students are prepared for both academic and alternative academic posts (Berman, 2011; Carr, 2012; Leon, 2011; Nowviskie, 2010; Powell, Bouchard, Dalgleish, Keenan, McLeod, and Thomson, 2013; L. Siemens, 2013; Spiro, 2010). </p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_1"/>Berman, R. A. (2011). Reforming Doctoral Programs: The Sooner, the Better. Retrieved from
                        <ref target="http://www.mla.org/blog?topic=143"> http://www.mla.org/blog?topic=143</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_2"/>Bracken, L. J., and Oughton, E. A. (2006). 'What do you mean?' The importance of language in developing interdisciplinary research. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Institute of British Geographers, 31</hi>(3), 371-382.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_3"/>Bryan, L., Negretti, M., Christensen, F. B., and Stokes, S. (2002). Processing the process: One research team's experience of a collaborative research project 
                        <hi rend="italic">Contemporary Family Therapy, 24</hi>(2), 333-353.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_4"/>Carr, G. (2012). Graduate students need preparation for life outside the university, November 1, 2012, from 
                        <ref target="http://m.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/graduate-students-need-preparation-for-life-outside-university/article4699319/?service=mobile">http://m.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/graduate-students-need-preparation-for-life-outside-university/article4699319/?service=mobile</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_5"/>Digging into Data Challenge. (2013). Digging into data challenge, October 28, 2013, from 
                        <ref target="http://www.diggingintodata.org">http://www.diggingintodata.org</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_6"/>Dombrowski, Q. (2013). 
                        <hi rend="italic">What ever happened to Project Bamboo?</hi> Paper presented at the DH 2013, Lincoln, Nebraska. 
                        <ref target="http://dh2013.unl.edu/abstracts/ab-287.html">http://dh2013.unl.edu/abstracts/ab-287.html</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_7"/>Fair Cite. (2012). Fair cite: Towards a fairer culture of citation in academia Retrieved March 5, 2012, from 
                        <ref target="http://faircite.wordpress.com/">http://faircite.wordpress.com/</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_8"/>Hjartarson, P., Fast, K., and Hasenbank, A. (2011). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Modelling collaboration in digital humanities scholarship: Foundational concepts of an EMIC UA project charter</hi>. Paper presented at the Space/Place/Play, Toronto, ON. 
                        <ref target="http://www.cwrc.ca/events/final-ryerson-conference-program/">http://www.cwrc.ca/events/final-ryerson-conference-program/</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_9"/>INKE. (2012a). About, October 29, 2012, from 
                        <ref target="http://inke.uvic.ca/projects/about/">http://inke.uvic.ca/projects/about/</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_10"/>INKE. (2012b). Publications, August 28, 2013, from 
                        <ref target="http://inke.ca/projects/publications/">http://inke.ca/projects/publications/</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_11"/>INKE. (2014). Future directions, November 3, 2014, from 
                        <ref target="http://inke.ca/projects/future-directions/">http://inke.ca/projects/future-directions/</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_12"/>Kishchuk, N. (2005). Performance report: SSHRC's major collaborative research initiatives (MCRI) program. Ottawa, ON: SSHRC.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_13"/>Lawrence, K. A. (2006). Walking the tightrope: The balancing acts of a large e-research project. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Computer Supported Cooperative Work: The Journal of Collaborative Computing, 15</hi>(4), 385-411.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_14"/>Leon, S. M. (2011). Project management for humanists: Preparing future primary investigators Retrieved June 24, 2011, from 
                        <ref target="http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/alt-ac/pieces/project-management-humanists">http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/alt-ac/pieces/project-management-humanists</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_15"/>Lyall, C., Bruce, A., Marsden, W., and Meagher, L. (2013). The role of funding agencies in creating interdisciplinary knowledge. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Science and Public Policy, 40</hi>(1), 62-71.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_16"/>Marshall, C., and Rossman, G. B. (1999). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Designing qualitative research</hi> (3rd ed.). Thousand Oaks, CA: SAGE.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_17"/>McCracken, G. (1988). 
                        <hi rend="italic">The long interview</hi> (Vol. 13). Newbury Park, California: SAGE Publications.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_18"/>National Endowment for the Humanities Office of Digital Humanities. (2010). Summary findings of NEH digital humanities start-up grants (2007-2010). Washington, D.C.: National Endowment for the Humanities,.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_19"/>Newell, S., and Swan, J. (2000). Trust and inter-organizational networking. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Human Relations, 53</hi>(10), 1287-1328.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_20"/>Nowviskie, B. (2010). #alt-ac: Alternate academic careers for humanities scholars. Retrieved from 
                        <ref target="http://nowviskie.org/2010/alt-ac/">http://nowviskie.org/2010/alt-ac/</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_21"/>Nowviskie, B. (2011). Where credit is due: Preconditions for the evaluation of collaborative digital scholarship. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Profession, 13</hi>, 169–181.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_22"/>Off the Tracks. (2011). Recommendations Retrieved May 26, 2011, from 
                        <ref target="http://mith.umd.edu/offthetracks/recommendations/">http://mith.umd.edu/offthetracks/recommendations/</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_23"/>Office of Digital Humanities. (2014). NHE/DFG 2014 bilateral digital humanities program, October 31, 3014, from 
                        <ref target="http://www.neh.gov/divisions/odh/grant-news/nehdfg-2014-bilateral-digital-humanities-program">http://www.neh.gov/divisions/odh/grant-news/nehdfg-2014-bilateral-digital-humanities-program</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_24"/>Powell, D., Bouchard, M., Dalgleish, M., Keenan, A., McLeod, A., and Thomson, T. (2013). Conversation, collaboration, credit: The graduate researcher in the digital scholarly environment. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Studies/Le champ numerique, 4</hi>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_25"/>Rubin, H. J., and Rubin, I. S. (1995). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Qualitative interviewing: The art of hearing data</hi>. Thousand Oaks, CA: SAGE Publications.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_26"/>Ruecker, S., and Radzikowska, M. (2007). 
                        <hi rend="italic">The iterative design of a project charter for interdisciplinary research</hi>. Paper presented at the DIS 2007, Cape Town, South Africa. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_27"/>Siemens, L. (2013). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Meta-methodologies and the DH methodological commons: Potential contribution of management and entrepreneurship to DH skill development</hi>. Paper presented at the DH 2013, Lincoln, Nebraska. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_28"/>Siemens, L., and Burr, E. (2013). A trip around the world: Accommodating geographical, linguistic and cultural diversity in academic research teams. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Linguistic and Literary Computing, 28</hi>(2), 331-343.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_29"/>Siemens, L., and INKE Research Group. (2010). 
                        <hi rend="italic">The e-paper anniversary: Lessons from the first year of INKE</hi>. Paper presented at the SDH/SEMI 2010, Montreal, Quebec. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_30"/>Siemens, L., and INKE Research Group. (2012a). Firing on all cylinders: Progress and transition in INKE's year 2. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Scholarly and Research Communication, 3</hi>(4), 1-16.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_31"/>Siemens, L., and INKE Research Group. (2012b). From writing the grant to working the grant: An exploration of processes and procedures in transition. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Scholarly and Research Communication, 3</hi>(1).
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_32"/>Siemens, L., and INKE Research Group. (2012c). INKE administrative structure: Omnibus document. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Scholarly and Research Communication, 3</hi>(1).
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_33"/>Siemens, L., and INKE Research Group. (2012d). 
                        <hi rend="italic">INKE at the midterm review</hi>. Paper presented at the Research Foundations for Understanding Books and Reading in the Digital Age: E/Merging Reading, Writing, and Research Practices, Havana, Cuba. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_34"/>Siemens, L., and INKE Research Group. (2012e). Understanding long-term collaboration: Reflections on year 1 and before. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Scholarly and Research Communication, 3</hi>(1), 1-4.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_35"/>Siemens, L., and INKE Research Group. (2013). Responding to change and transition in INKE’s year three. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Scholarly and Research Communication, 4</hi>(3), 12 pp.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_36"/>Siemens, R. G., Siemens, L., Cunningham, R., Galey, A., Ruecker, S., and Warwick, C. (2012). Implementing new knowledge environments: Year one research foundations. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Scholarly and Research Communication, 3</hi>(1).
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_37"/>Siemens, R. G., Warwick, C., Cunningham, R., Dobson, T., Galey, A., Ruecker, S., Schreibman, S., and INKE Research Group. (2009). Codex ultor: Toward a conceptual and theoretical foundation for new research on books and knowledge environments. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Studies/Le champ numerique, 1</hi>(2).
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_38"/>Spiro, L. (2010). Opening up digital humanities education. Retrieved from 
                        <ref target="http://digitalscholarship.wordpress.com/2010/09/08/opening-up-digital-humanities-education/">http://digitalscholarship.wordpress.com/2010/09/08/opening-up-digital-humanities-education/</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_39"/>SSHRC. (2013). Partnership grants: An overview, December 9, 2013, from 
                        <ref target="http://www.sshrc-crsh.gc.ca/about-au_sujet/partnerships-partenariats/partnership_grants-bourses_partenariats-eng.aspx">http://www.sshrc-crsh.gc.ca/about-au_sujet/partnerships-partenariats/partnership_grants-bourses_partenariats-eng.aspx</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_40"/>The Praxis Program at the Scholars' Lab. (2011a). 2011-12 praxis program charter, September 19, 2012, from 
                        <ref target="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/charter.html">http://praxis.scholarslab.org/charter.html</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_41"/>The Praxis Program at the Scholars' Lab. (2011b). 2011-12 praxis program charter Retrieved February 11, 2012, from 
                        <ref target="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/charter.html">http://praxis.scholarslab.org/charter.html</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_42"/>The Praxis Program at the Scholars' Lab. (2012). About praxis, October 17, 2012, from 
                        <ref target="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/about.html">http://praxis.scholarslab.org/about.html</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="EndNote Bibliography">
                        <anchor xml:id="ENREF_43"/>The Praxis Program at the Scholars' Lab. (nd). Toward a project charter, September 11, 2013, from 
                        <ref target="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/topics/toward-a-project-charter/">http://praxis.scholarslab.org/topics/toward-a-project-charter/</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
