<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:53+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Access to DH Pedagogy as the Norm: Introducing Students to DH Methods Across the Curriculum and at a Distance</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dan</forename><surname>Tracy</surname></persName>
							<email>dtracy@illinois.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename><forename type="middle">Massa</forename><surname>Hoiem</surname></persName>
							<email>hoiem@illinois.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Access to DH Pedagogy as the Norm: Introducing Students to DH Methods Across the Curriculum and at a Distance</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign United States of America United States of America</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>This poster presents research into integration and assessment of digital humanities pedagogy in a distance course on the History of Children&apos;s Literature, and provokes conversation about pedagogical approaches that expand student access to DH methods, tools, and dispositions. Much of the existing literature on DH pedagogy addresses methods courses or multi-modal writing courses rather than integration of DH practices in particular topical contexts, or advanced topics courses that explore a narrow slice of disciplinary content through extended engagements with digital projects (Ball 2012; Mostern &amp; Gainor 2013; Fyfe 2016; Nyhan, Mahony, and Terras 2016). This literature provides valuable lessons but raises questions about the feasibility of engaging with DH across the curriculum in small-to-medium scale engagements with new methods and technologies. Amy E. Earhart and Toniesha L. Taylor (2016), for example, respond to this situation by rejecting the idea that DH should be limited to advanced courses and propose broader integration of &quot;embedded [DH] skills development&quot; that students can take out of the environment of a specific institution. Similarly, we suggest that allowing for repeated and diverse engagement by students across methods-intensive and topic-intensive courses (as is now common for writing) is necessary for teaching deeper DH dispositions like collaboration, openness to failure, and creativity with technology.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
