<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:39+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Network analysis of the manuscript context of Old Icelandic literature</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Anna</forename><surname>Katarzyna</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Kapitan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Network analysis of the manuscript context of Old Icelandic literature</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Questions</head><p>Hrómundar saga Gripssonar traditionally belongs in the corpus of legendary sagas (fornaldarsö gur); it was included in the second volume of Rafn's (1829) Fornaldarsögur Norðrlanda, and in Bjö rner's (1737) Nordiska kämpa dater. The saga as it is known today, however, is a post-medieval re-working of a metrical version of the story known as rı́murrı́mur <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Brown, 1946)</ref>, and is probably not much older than seventeenth century. Therefore it does not necessarily fit well with the other texts included the corpus of legendary sagas, as they usually date from the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries <ref type="bibr">(Driscoll, 2005:207)</ref>. This makes Hrómundar saga Gripssonar an interesting case study for investigations of the text's genre affiliation in the extant manuscripts preserving the saga. Does it appear frequently in manuscripts with the older legendary sagas or with younger rı́murrı́mur-based narratives? To answer this question, I first examine the manuscript context of legendary sagas as a corpus, based on collaborative research with Rowbotham and Wills ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Kapitan et al., 2017)</ref>; second, I examine the position of Hrómundar saga Gripssonar within the corpus and its relationships with other texts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>State of the Art</head><p>Much discussion in the field of Old Norse studies centers on whether the legendary sagas deserve to be considered a separate literary genre, or should instead be analyzed as chivalric literature <ref type="bibr">(Quinn, 2006</ref>). One of the main reasons for these considerations seems to be the fact that the term fornaldarsö gur is not attested in the medieval texts; it was introduced in the early nineteenth century by C.C. Rafn, who published a collection of texts under the title Fornaldarsögur Norðrlanda (Rafn, 1829). Rafn's selection of texts and the definition of fornaldarsö gur as a corpus of texts dealing with events taking place in Scandinavia before the settlement of Iceland, however, was not detached from pervious scholarship of early eighteenth century <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Lavender, 2015)</ref>. The current discussion on the legendary sagas as a corpus (or a genre) is polarized around contradicting opinions. Some scholars suggest that the legendary sagas had to be considered a separate category in pre-modern period, because they are frequently bound together in the manuscripts <ref type="bibr">(GuðmundsdóttirGuðmundsdóttir, 2001:cxlvii;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mitchell, 1991:21)</ref> while others, using the same argument, emphasize strong connections between the legendary sagas and the chivalric sagas ( <ref type="bibr">Driscoll, 2005:193</ref>). Additional problems arise when classifying the generic hybrids <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Rowe 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">2004</ref>) appearing within the corpus, or distinguishing between the legendary sagas (fornaldarsö gur) and the late legendary sagas (fornaldarsö gur sı́ðarisı́ðari tı́matı́ma; Driscoll 2005). Even though scholars eagerly turn towards the manuscript context to support their claims regarding the genre classification, no comprehensive overview of the legendary sagas' codicological context has yet been presented. This gave rise to the project Stories for all times conducted at the University of Copenhagen, which created a complete catalogue of manuscripts preserving legendary sagas. The catalogue contains 818 TEI-conformant XML-based manuscript descriptions with over 8000 items, 1764 of which are classified as legendary sagas and 920 as chivalric sagas. This amount of data is much too large to be analyzed manually, therefore it is necessary to apply computer-assisted analysis in order to draw some general conclusions regarding this corpus and the relationships between these texts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p>The first part of my paper, which aims to establish the position of Hrómundar saga Gripssonar within the wider context of the manuscript, draws on the network analysis of the corpus, conducted in collaboration with <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Rowbotham and Wills (Kapitan et al., 2017)</ref>. There, the codicological context of a text was considered as a system of relationships between texts, and following <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Hall's (2013)</ref> approach in his network of chivalric sagas, texts were represented as nodes, manuscripts as edges, both visualized with the free visualization software Gephi. The second part is based on database queries aimed at obtaining detailed information about particular manuscripts and their contents. The main focus of the analysis was to examine the manuscripts preserving the complete texts of Hrómundar saga Gripssonar in Icelandic, therefore the manuscripts containing excerpts and translations were ignored. The distribution of texts appearing frequently alongside Hrómundar saga Gripssonar by century has been obtained using XPath queries of the online catalogue Stories for all times.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Main Findings</head><p>As a result of this research, the hypothesis can be confirmed: generally, texts belonging to one genre appear most frequently in manuscripts with other texts belonging to the same genre. However, an interesting transmission history of Hrómundar saga Gripssonar suggests a close association of this saga with the late legendary sagas, and in particular Bragða-Ölvis saga. Both Bragða-Ölvis saga and Hrómundar saga Gripssonar are post-medieval reworkings of older metric versions of the stories (rı́murrı́mur), and for both texts the manuscript AM 601 b 4to (Aj rni MagnússonMagnússon Institute, Reykjavı́kReykjavı́k) was suggested as the witness carrying the best text of the saga <ref type="bibr">(Andrews, 1911;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Brown, 1946;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Hooper, 1934;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Hooper, 1932)</ref>. Even though Hrómundar saga Gripssonar appears most frequently with texts classified as late legendary sagas in pre-1800 manuscripts, after 1800 the texts classified as (traditional) fornaldarsö gur start to dominate. The late Bragða-Ölvis saga dominates the pre-1800 setting, but the distribution changes in the nineteenth century when Þorsteins saga Víkingssonar, Starkaðar saga gamla, Friðþjófs saga ins fraekna, and Hálfs saga Hálfsreka appear more frequently (as presented on figure below). Starkaðar saga gamla is a lateeighteenth century saga written by Snorri Bjö rnson (1710-1803), utilizing traditional legendary motifs of Saxo's Gesta Danorum and legendary sagas <ref type="bibr">(Driscoll, 2009:209;</ref><ref type="bibr">Simek and Hermann Paísson, 1987:331)</ref>, so its co-occurrence with other legendary sagas starting from the eighteenth century onwards is not surprising. The three remaining texts that started to appear more frequently alongside Hrómundar saga Gripssonar in nineteenth-century manuscripts were all published in the same volume of Rafn's Fornaldarsögur Norðrlanda, in which Hrómundar saga Gripssonar was published (volume II); likewise FriðþjófsFriðþjófs saga ins fraekna, and Hálfs saga Hálfsreka appeared in Bjö rner's edition from 1737 together with Hrómundar saga Gripssonar. This shows how printed editions influenced the saga's transmission in the manuscript form. A text, which once showed strong connections to another rı́murrı́mur-based narrative, became detached from its previous setting and gained new, print-influenced context after becoming part of printed editions. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Relevance</head><p>The topic of this paper fits in the advertised panel "Quantitative stylistics and philology, including big data and text mining studies," as it employs database quarrying and network analysis of significant amount of data.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Texts appearing frequently with Hrómundar saga Gripssonar in manuscripts by century</figDesc><graphic url="image-1.png" coords="2,316.86,232.38,241.20,100.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The author of this paper owes a great debt to Tarrin Wills for merging the data from various databases (fasnl.ku.dk, skaldic.abdn.ac.uk, handrit.is, onpweb.nfi.sc.ku.dk) to obtain the input data for the network analysis, and to Tim Rowbotham, who worked on standardizing the uniform titles and genre classifications in the XML-files in the Stories for all times catalogue.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nordiska kämpa dater i en sagoflock samlade om forna kongar och hjältar</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Björner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://books.google.com/books?id=9nZUAAAAYAAJ" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Volumen historicum, continens variorum in orbe hyperboreo antiquo regum, heroum et pugilum res praeclare et mirabiliter gestas. Accessit, praeter conspectum genealogicum Svethicorum regum et reginarum accuratissimum etiam praefatio. Stockholmiae: typis J.L., Horrn</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1737-01" />
			<biblScope unit="page">28</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The saga of HrómundHrómund Gripsson and Þorgilssaga</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1946" />
			<publisher>Saga-Book</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="77" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Late prose fiction (lygisö gur). A Companion to Old Norse-Icelandic Literature and Culture</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Driscoll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="204" />
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Editing the Fornaldarsö gur Norðurlanda. Á Austrvega, Saga and East Scandinavia, Preprints of the 14th International Saga Conference Uppsala 9th -15th</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Driscoll</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Gä vle: University of Gä vle</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="219" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Gephi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://gephi.org" />
		<title level="m">Gephi: The open graph viz platform</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Making stemmas with small samples, and digital approaches to publishing them: testing the stemma of KonráðsKonráðs saga keisarasonar</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Parsons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://handrit.org" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Online catalogue handrit</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genre in the saga literature: A Squib</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scandinavian Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="427" to="463" />
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bragða-Ǫlvis saga&quot; now first edited</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leeds Studies in English</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="42" to="54" />
			<date type="published" when="1932" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HrómundarHrómundar saga Gripssonar and the Griplur</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leeds Studies in English</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="1934" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualising genre relationships in Icelandic manuscripts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kapitan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Rowbotham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wills</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Conference Abstracts. Gothenburg: The University of Gothenburg</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="62" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Secret Prehistory of the Fornaldarsö gur</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lavender</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of English and Germanic Philology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="526" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Heroic Sagas and Ballads</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<publisher>Cornell University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Ithaca and London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The &quot;Stories for all time</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nordisk</forename><surname>Forskningsinstitut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://fasnl.ku.dk/Quinn" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Interrogating Genre in the Fornaldarsö gur: Round-Table Discussion&apos;. Viking and Medieval Scandinavia</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="276" to="96" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fornaldarsögur Norðrlanda. Kaupmannahö fn</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Rafn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1829" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generic Hybrids: Norwegian &apos;Family&apos; Sagas and Icelandic &apos;Mythic-Heroic&apos; Sagas</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scandinavian Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="54" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Þorsteins þáttrþáttr uxafótsuxafóts, Helga þáttrþáttr ÞórissonarÞórissonar,&apos; and the Conversion &apos;þaettir&apos;</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scandinavian Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Lexikon Der Altnordischen Literatur, Die Mittelalterliche Literatur Norwegens Und Islands. (Krö ners Taschenausgabe 490)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Simek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pálsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<publisher>Krö ner</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Stuttgart</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
				<ptr target="http://onpweb.nfi.sc.ku.dk/mscoll_d_menu.html" />
		<title level="m">? University of Copenhagen (n.d.) Ordbog over det norrøne prosasprog Registre</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Skaldic Project Academy Body. (n.d.) Skaldic project</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
