<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:51+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Natural Language Processing for the Long Tail</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Banman</surname></persName>
							<email>dbamman@berkeley.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<region>UC</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Natural Language Processing for the Long Tail</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>Many thanks to the anonymous reviewers for helpful feedback. This work is supported by a grant by the Digital Humanities at Berkeley initiative. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bibliography</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proceedings of the 2006 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing, EMNLP '06, pages 120-128, Stroudsburg, PA, USA, 2006. Association for</head><p>Computational Linguistics.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S., Štěpánek, J., et al. (2009) The CoNLL-2009 shared task: Syntactic and semantic dependencies in multiple languages. In Proceedings of the Thirteenth Conference</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Parsers and part-of-speech taggers trained on the WSJ expect newswire syntax. Automatically parsed syntactic dependency graph with part-of-speech tags for Long is the way and hard, that out of Hell leads up to light. Errors in part-of-speech tags and dependency arcs are shown in red. Part-of-speech errors snowball into major syntactic errors.</figDesc><graphic url="image-1.png" coords="1,317.14,294.10,241.44,62.16" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Out-of-domain performance for several NLP tasks, including POS tagging, phrase structure (PS) parsing, dependency parsing and named entity recognition. Accuracies are reported in percentages; phrase structure parsing and NER are reported in F1 measure.</figDesc><graphic url="image-2.png" coords="2,54.58,72.58,241.44,258.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Out-of-domain performance for several NLP tasks, including POS tagging, phrase structure (PS) parsing, dependency parsing and named entity recognition. Accuracies are reported in percentages; phrase structure parsing and NER are reported in F1 measure.</figDesc><graphic url="image-3.png" coords="3,54.58,72.58,241.44,258.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Andor, D.</head><label></label><figDesc>, Alberti, C., Weiss, D., Severyn, A., Presta, A., Ganchev, K., Petrov, S., and Collins, M. (2016). Glob- ally normalized transition-based neural networks. In Proceedings of the 54th Annual Meeting of the Associa- tion for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Pa- pers), pages 2442-2452, Berlin, Germany, August 2016. Association for Computational Linguistics. Bamman, D., and Crane, G. (2011) The ancient Greek and Latin dependency treebanks. In Language Technology for Cultural Heritage, pages 79-98. Springer, 2011. Benne, D. C. (2014). Marrying the benefits of print and dig- ital: Algorithmically selecting context for a key word. In Digital Humanities 2014, 2014. Blitzer, J., McDonald, R., and Pereira, F. (2006) Domain adaptation with structural correspondence learning. In</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Burga, A., Codina, J., Ferraro, G., Saggion, H., and Wan- ner, L. ( 2013 )., L., Ritter, A., Clark, S., and Bontcheva, K., C., Teehan, A., and Keating, J., K., Schneider, N., O'Connor, B., Das, D., Mills, D., Eisenstein, J., Heilman, M., Yogatama, D., Flanigan, J., and Smith, N. A. ( 2011 ), J., Ciaramita, M., Johansson, R., Kawahara, D., Martí, M. A., Màrquez, L., Meyers, A., Nivre, J., Padó,</head><label>20132011</label><figDesc>The challenge of syntactic dependency parsing adaptation for the patent domain. In ESSLLI-13 Workshop on Extrinsic Parse Improvement, 2013. Chelba, C., and Acero, A. (2006). Adaptation of maximum entropy capitalizer: Little data can help a lot. Computer Speech &amp; Language, 20 (4): 382-399, 2006. Daumé, H. (2009) Frustratingly easy domain adaptation. arXiv preprint arXiv:0907.1815. Derczynski, L., Maynard, D., Aswani, N., and Bontcheva, K. (2013a) Microblog-genre noise and impact on se- mantic annotation accuracy. In Proceedings of the 24th ACM Conference on Hypertext and Social Media, pages 21-30. ACM, 2013.DerczynskiTwitter part-of-speech tagging for all: Overcoming sparse and noisy data. In RANLP, pages 198-206, 2013b.Derven(2014). Mapping and unmapping Joyce: Geoparsing wandering rocks. In Digital Humanities 2014, 2014. Galves, C., and Faria, P. (2010). Tycho Brahe Parsed Cor- pus of Historical Portuguese. http://www.tycho.iel.uni- camp.br/corpus/en/index.html . Gildea, D. (2001) Corpus variation and parser perfor- mance. In Proceedings of the 2001 Conference on Empiri- cal Methods in Natural Language Processing, pages 167- 202, 2001.GimpelPart-of-speech tagging for Twitter: Annotation, features, and experiments. In Pro- ceedings of the Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, companion volume, Portland, OR, June 2011. Glorot, X., Bordes, A., and Bengio, Y. (2011). Domain ad- aptation for large-scale sentiment classification: A deep learning approach. In Proceedings of the 28th Interna- tional Conference on Machine Learning (ICML-11), pages 513-520, 2011.Hajič</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Taylor, A., and Kroch, A.S. (2000) The Penn-Helsinki</head><p>Parsed Corpus of Middle English. University of <ref type="bibr">Pennsyl- vania, 2000</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Taylor, A., Nurmi, A., Warner, A., Pintzuk, S., and Nevalainen, T. (2006). Parsed Corpus of Early English Cor</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
