<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:47+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Cultural (Re-)formations: Structuring a Linked Data Ontology for Intersectional Identities</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Susan</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
							<email>sbrown@uoguelph.ca</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">alemak@uoguelph.ca</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Guelph</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Abigel</forename><surname>Lemak</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Guelph</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Colin</forename><surname>Faulkner</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Guelph</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kim</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Guelph</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rob</forename><surname>Warren</surname></persName>
							<email>rwarren@math.carleton.ca</email>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Carleton University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Cultural (Re-)formations: Structuring a Linked Data Ontology for Intersectional Identities</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Cultural diversity has been an increasing source of debate within the digital humanities community. The concentration within the Debates in Digital Humanities series <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Gold, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Gold and Klein, 2016)</ref> of pieces reflecting the increasing prominence of matters related to race, gender, cultural diversity and difference is but one marker of the extent to which diversity matters. The Orlando Project in feminist literary history incorporated an intersectional understanding of identity categories from the outset <ref type="bibr">(Brown, Clements and</ref><ref type="bibr">Grundy, 2006-2017)</ref>. Translating Orlando's Extensible Markup Language (XML) data into linked open data (LOD) to make it accessible, interoperable, and amenable to a range of analytical approaches (Simpson and Brown) requires an ontology that will serve both Orlando and the broader research community hosted by the Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory (CWRC). This paper outlines the CWRC ontology design and the challenges of shifting from semi-structured to structured data <ref type="bibr">(Smith, 2016: 273)</ref>.</p><p>Much work on digital diversity expresses skepticism of the ability of systematized knowledge structures to capture the performative, processual, and contingent nature of lived subjectivities. Tara McPherson stresses that "computers are themselves encoders of culture" and calls for more attention to be paid to the interconnectedness of the structures of code and the management of race socially: "Just as the relational database works by normalizing data-that is, by stripping it of meaningful, idiosyncratic context, creating a system of interchangeable equivalencies-our own scholarly practices tend to exist in relatively hermetically sealed boxes or nodes." <ref type="bibr">Scholars including Lisa Nakamura (2002: 120)</ref> and Moya Bailey (2011) see value in "messiness" as a way to push against and redefine the contours of a digital humanities scholarship that remains rooted in predominantly white epistemology.</p><p>At the same time, relegating representations of difference to narrative rather than structured data will produce gaps within big data that are both impoverishing for humanities inquiry and dangerous in their political implications <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Lerman, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Trevinarus, 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">"Use";</ref><ref type="bibr">Brown and Simpson, 2013)</ref>. Adriel DeanHall and Robert <ref type="bibr">Warren (2013)</ref> have advocated approaches that respect the privacy and preferences of lived human subjects while improving the responsiveness of online systems to diversity and complexity. Within a LOD context, what are finally findable, processable, and reusable on the global graph are things, not strings, so the challenge is the extent to which nuance, context, and indeed messiness can be incorporated into a LOD ontology.</p><p>The Orlando Project <ref type="bibr">(Brown, et al., 2006</ref><ref type="bibr">(Brown, et al., -2017</ref>) charted a middle ground between narrative and structure for its bespoke XML tagset. The team struggled with the hierarchical nature of XML particularly in relation to identity categories, torn between knowledge that readers would turn to Orlando to find writers associated with particular cultural identities and recognition that such categories are discursive rather than essential <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Fuss, 2013)</ref>. It devised a "Cultural Formation" tagset to depict identity as neither unitary nor immutable, and as much related to representational acts as to the lived experiences into which those representations blur. Precisely because constituted through discursive and social practices, vocabularies associated with subjectivities and identities can shift over time and place, and throughout an individual's lifetime.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cultural formation tagset</head><p>The Cultural Formation (CF) tagset recognizes categorization as endemic to social experience, while incorporating variation in terminology and contextualization of identity categories by employing tags at different discursive levels. CF tags describe the subject positions of individuals through 1) contextual tags that encode substantial discussions: class; language; nationality; race and ethnicity; religion; and sexuality; and 2) granular tags that describe, in a word or short phrase, class; ethnicity; gender; geographical heritage; language; nationality; national heritage; political affiliation; race or colour; religious denomination, and sexual identity. With the exception of gender and social class, the Orlando schema eschewed fixed attribute values for the granular tags, allowing the prose to employ the most appropriate language for the context. The structure was not entirely logical or parallel, and we are making the ontology more consistent. The granular tags possess attributes regarding forebears and whether a subject self-identified with a particular term. The tagset aimed to highlight the extent to which social classification is culturally produced and discursively embedded. Rather than disambiguating leaky cultural categories, it considered them as mutually constitutive with historically specific discursive frameworks, including our tagging structures.</p><p>CF encoding pointed users towards a framework for raising and debating complex matters for cultural investigation rather than standardized classifications, refusing to neatly group writers into distinct and fixed categories, since those categories were neither stable nor mutually exclusive (Algee-Hewitt, Porter, Walser, forthcoming). It can represent quite complex identities, as in the case of Anna Leonowens, the writer whose story of life as governess to the royal Siamese harem was popularized in The King and I. Partial markup for the first paragraph of her CF description is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. The CF component of Orlando's knowledge representation is thus crucial to its intersectional approach to identity <ref type="bibr">(Brown et al., 2006</ref>). Creating a LOD ontology that was not self-referential, however, requires translating the strings or literal values from CF tags, to link Orlando's semantic structures to other semantic web communities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LOD ontology creation</head><p>An ontology "is a formal naming and definition of the types, properties, and interrelationships of the entities that really or fundamentally exist for a particular domain of discourse" (Wikipedia, Ontology -Information Science). Using a standard ontology language such as OWL allows others to interact and exchange with a particular view of the world through a computational process of mediation. As a representation of that understanding, an ontology can be referenced, (dis)agreed with, extended, and used operationally. The coexistence of different representations provides the foundation for translations between LOD concepts.</p><p>Ontology creation in our case, as in many others, was driven by the idiosyncrasies and limitations of an existing data set. The information architectures of application databases or XML stores are not always reconcilable to a consistent information system. The CF tagset represents a major challenge in that its structure was designed to eschew disambiguation. Even the major tags were difficult to relate within a concise ontology <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 2</ref>). For example, nationality and national heritage are not employed as commensurate with citizenship, a well-defined legal concept related to an organized state. They can also be related to a geographical area, which may or may not coincide with a state. Finally, nationhood can reference socio-political constructs such as Lesbian Nation <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Johnston, 1973;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Ross, 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Munt, 1998)</ref> or disavowals of nationality such as Virginia <ref type="bibr">Woolf's (1938: 197)</ref>, which Orlando quotes alongside assigning Woolf an English nationality, a contradiction that requires contextual evidence to make sense.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Linked into context</head><p>We decided to make all human-readable annotations within the dataset instances of contextual notes to which the ontological classes are directly tied <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Fig- ure 3)</ref>. classificatory labels relate to predicates and external ontologies. Skos:narrower/broader relationships are also used, but omitted here to improve legibility Thus we model the discursive context within a Race[or]EthnicityContext class. The note instance links to instances of granular category labels, here RaceColour; it provides the provenance and the basis for links to source information. Linking to the provenance of the LOD is particularly important for disputed or contradictory information, as in our example. We are modeling the original Orlando narrative as a source document for our LOD provenance using the the Web Annotation Data Model's subproperty instances. We aim to link every triple to the prose from which it is derived, providing provenance information and contains citations to the sources on which identity assertions are based.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Relating cultural formations</head><p>Cultural formation for Orlando is understood primarily as representational, which is not to say that cultural formation is not real or that it has no material effects. The complex signifiers of cultural identities float across Orlando tags as cdata or free text in a semistructured representation of cultural identities and categories. For the CWRC ontology, we strategized to relate this ontological perspective to that of external vocabularies without conflating our truth with theirs. Our architecture does not import other ontologies wholesale, but adopts components of major vocabularies such as BIBO, FOAF, and FRBR, and relates to large vocabularies in defined ways. As indicated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig- ure 3</ref>, the instances of cwrc:whiteRaceColour and cwrc:whiteEthnicity within the CWRC ontology are subclasses of the cwrc:whiteLabel. This retains the ambiguity of terms such as "white" or "Jewish" precisely as labels that draw together particular types of identity categories, as well as subClasses of those labels. As indicated, those subClasses can be linked to terms in external vocabularies, but both internal and external terms are understood within the CWRC ontology as labels. Indeed, constructing this ontology has brought home to us the need for the LOD community to think through with greater care the relationship between representation and "reality" in LOD ontologies. A further complication is that identity categories are not only historically contingent but often also change over a particular individual's lifetime. The Orlando dataset supports such nuance in only a few cases, so we have not started with this gnarly problem, but we aim to build into the ontology the capacity to represent such cultural formation dynamics in order to accommodate more temporally precise data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>The CWRC ontology design avoids representing RDF extractions from Orlando data as positivist assertions, and yet produces machine-readable OWL/RDFcompliant graph structures. It allows references to, without endorsing, external ontological vocabularies that are nevertheless part of documenting intersectional cultural processes and identities.</p><p>We will present CWRC ontology as built around the CF design described here, and we will demonstrate its implications through several practical examples. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig- ure 4</ref> shows schematically the intersectionality of multiple identity categories associated with Leonowens, including the ways that instances are related by subclass relationships in accordance with OWL principles. This importantly allows us to reference components of other ontologies (here the Muninn Appearances ontology, Library of Congress Subject Headings, Getty Art and Architecture Thesaurus, and DBpedia) without adopting them wholesale.   the edge between Elizabeth Sarah Gooch and cwrc:jewishReligion is hasReligion) Our live presentation will demonstrate the ontology in action using the interactive HuViz (Humanities Visualizer) interface with a larger dataset. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Adapted from Brown, Clements and Grundy, "Anna Leonowens", Life tab, Show Markup option</figDesc><graphic url="image-1.png" coords="2,54.58,575.14,247.20,83.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Schematic representation of the granular Cultural Formation tags from Orlando (Please note that these representations are simplified in order to make them legible to the reader.)</figDesc><graphic url="image-2.png" coords="2,317.14,416.98,245.76,87.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Schematic representation of how the discursive context (note) links to the classificatory structure, and how classificatory labels relate to predicates and external ontologies. Skos:narrower/broader relationships are also used, but omitted here to improve legibility</figDesc><graphic url="image-3.png" coords="3,54.58,152.50,235.92,180.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Cultural Formation triples related to Anna Leonowens, with corresponding XML-encoded context notes</figDesc><graphic url="image-4.png" coords="4,54.58,72.58,246.00,242.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 indicates</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5 indicates the ability to see patterns and outliers related to different categorizations of Jewishness in a small subset of Orlando authors.</figDesc><graphic url="image-5.png" coords="4,57.22,391.06,235.92,111.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Subset of CF triples related to a subset of writers, with sample context annotations and external links; predicates linking individuals to subclasses are inferred (e.g. the edge between Elizabeth Sarah Gooch and cwrc:jewishReligion is hasReligion)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>CWRC sparql end point: http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ • Orlando Biography schema containing Cultural For- mation tagset: https://github.com/cwrc/CWRC-</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Essentially Speaking: Feminism, Nature &amp; Difference</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fuss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>
		<editor>Gold, M. K., and Klein, L. F.</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Minnesota; Minnesota</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Minnesota Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Lesbian Nation: The Feminist Solution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Johnston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
			<publisher>Simon and Schuster</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Big data and its exclusions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.hei-nonline.org.subzero.lib.uoguelph.ca/HOL/Page?han-dle=hein.journals/slro66&amp;start_page=55&amp;collec-tion=journals&amp;id=66" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">66 Stanford Law Review Online</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-04-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why are the Digital Humanities so white? Or thinking the histories of race and computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mcpherson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>
		<editor>M. Gold</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Minnesota</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Minnesota Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="160" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Appearances Ontology Specification -0.1</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Muninn</forename><surname>Project</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://rdf.muninn-project.org/ontolo-gies/appearances.html" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sisters in exile: the lesbian nation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Munt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bodies and Gender. London: Routledge</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>New Frontiers of Space</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Nakamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Cybertypes: Race, Ethnicity, and Identity on the Internet. London: Routledge</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The House that Jill Built: A Lesbian Nation in Formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>University of Toronto Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Working with the Semantic Web</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Doing Digital Humanities: Practice, training, research. London: Routledge</title>
		<editor>C. Crompton, R. J. Lane, and R. Siemens</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="88" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The value of the statistically insignificant</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Treviranus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://er.educause.edu/arti-cles/2014/1/the-value-of-the-statistically-insignificant" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-04" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Web Annotation Data Model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W3c</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.w3.org/TR/annotation-model/(ac-cessed:7" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-02-23" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ontology (information science),&quot; Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia</title>
		<ptr target="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Ontol-" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ogy_(information_science)&amp;oldid=772391479 (accessed</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-04-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Three Guineas</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Woolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1938" />
			<publisher>Hogarth Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
