<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:53+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Word Vectors in the Eighteenth Century</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ryan</forename><surname>James Heuser</surname></persName>
							<email>heuser@stanford.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>United States of America</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Word Vectors in the Eighteenth Century</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>This talk explores how new vector-based approaches to computational semantics both afford new methods to digital humanities research, and raise interesting questions for eighteenth-century literary studies in particular. New semantic models known as "word embedding models" have generated excitement recently in the natural language processing and machine learning communities, due to their ability to represent and predict semantic relationships as complex as analogy. "Man" is to "woman" as "king" is to what?, one can ask of the model; "queen," it will most likely reply. These models formulate analogical and other semantic relationships by computing mathematical vectors for words, such that, if V(x) denotes the vector for the word x, then the above analogy can be expressed as V(woman) - V(man) + V(king) ≈ V(queen). Although these models have a longer history- vector space semantics dates from the '70s, having been first developed for the SMART information retrieval system <ref type="bibr">(Sal- ton, 1971)</ref> by Gerard Salton and his colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Salton et al, 1975</ref>)" <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Turney and Pantel, 2010)</ref>- new innovations in their speed and accuracy (see Note <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref>) have renewed researchers' interests-a development begun, in part, by Google, when researchers there unveiled newly efficient algorithms in 2013, packaged in software they released called word2vec. (The word2vec algorithm was originally described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Mikolov et al, 2013</ref>. It introduced the neural network to vector space semantics, providing an efficient means by which to compute word vectors. The GloVe algorithm from the Stanford NLP Group eschews the neural network approach, instead performing a novel method of dimensionality reduction on word collocation counts).</p><p>"Word vectors," as these new methods are sometimes informally called, have already enabled published research into questions relevant to humanistic research, such as a recent landmark paper from researchers in the Stanford NLP Group into patterns of semantic change across centuries of discourse (Hamilton et al). However, unfortunately, word vectors have so far rarely appeared in research from the digital humanities community itself. Moreover, what work that does exist has so far been primarily circulated through blogs, rather than through published proceedings or articles. Ben Schmidt, for instance, has written an influential introduction to word vectors in his blog post "Vector Space Models for the Digital Humanities" (2015a), which also includes a documented R package for computing them. Also notable is his post, "Rejecting the gender binary" <ref type="bibr">(Schmidt, 2015b)</ref>, which uses word vectors to dissect the polysemy of words; as well as Michael Gavin's post, "The Arithmetic of Concepts" (2015), which explores the conceptual implications of adding and subtracting word vectors.</p><p>On the whole, the current research landscape of word vectors in the digital humanities resembles the landscape of topic modeling years ago, when the original LDA algorithm (published in 2003 <ref type="bibr">[Blei et al]</ref>), before appearing in landmark published DH studies such as Matt Jockers' Macroanalysis (2013), was employed for humanistic research as early as 2006 by researchers working outside or tangentially to the digital humanities (Newman and Block).</p><p>Given this scarcity of digital-humanities research on word vectors, work that seeks equally to explain, interpret, and demonstrate their potential seems particularly useful. With these goals in mind, this paper attempts first to unpack for a digital-humanities audience how word vectors work, with reference to the canonical analogy cited above: "man is to woman as king is to queen." Second, in order to interpret word vectors' conceptual implications for eighteenth-century literature, I move away from this canonical analogy to one central to a particularly influential argument in the period: "Learning is to Genius as Riches are to Virtue." Lastly, I turn from this close reading of word vectors to methods of distant-reading analogies that lie implicit in eighteenth-century literature.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Explaining Word Vectors</head><p>How do word vectors work? In the interests of space, I have omitted this section of my talk from the abstract. Readers curious about the mechanics of word vectors can read more on my blog, which also links to a number of other explanatory resources (Heuser, "Methods").</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Close-reading Word Vectors</head><p>Word vectors provide a persuasive computational means for the semantic representation and analysis of analogies. They combine a mathematical elegance with an intuitive interpretability to yield what is, potentially, a method useful not only for large-scale semantic analysis, but also for smaller-scale explorations of particular analogies in literature, and their specific forms of analogical argumentation. For instance, analogy lies at the heart of Edward Young's essay Conjectures on Original Composition (1759), which argued for the superior aesthetic interest of modern, "original" composition over the neoclassical imitation of the ancients. Crucially, Young makes his argument through analogy, identifying several other conceptual contrasts as analogues to his central one between original and imitative composition: "I would compare Genius to Virtue, and Learning to Riches," Young writes; "[a]s Riches are most wanted where there is least Virtue; so Learning where there is least Genius." In this way, Young's valuation of "Genius" over "Learning," and of original over imitative composition, become ethically justified through their analogy with another, more obviously moral contrast between "Virtue" and "Riches."</p><p>But what is the logic behind this analogy? Here, word vectors provide the close reader with a framework, language, and method of exploring the semantic implications at work in an analogy. In terms of vectors, we can ask, what does V(Virtue)-V(Riches) (Also sometimes expressed here, in a shorthand, as V(VirtueRiches) mean, and is it in fact correlated with V(Genius)-V(Learning) in the broader discourse of the period? Asking this question of a word2vec model trained on the 80 million words of eighteenth-century literature in the ECCO-TCP corpus, we find that "Riches" are to "Virtue" as "Learning" is to... "Genius" is the sixth closest word vector, or the sixth most likely solution, to this analogy. How to test the significance of this result is not immediately clear, but, out of tens of thousands of possibilities, it's certainly provocative: it raises the possibility that word vectors might provide computational assistance to close readings. Indeed, the other words in this list amplify the semantic profile of this analogy in a way that might help to clarify its underlying implications. For instance, the contrast between the intrinsic form of value in "Virtue" and the extrinsic form of value in "Riches" seems underscored for me by the contrast here between the extrinsic writerly attribute of "Learning," associated with an Oxbridge education, and the intrinsic attributes of morality, genius, and wisdom.</p><p>Ultimately, however, what does it mean to closeread word vectors? This is a question raised by Gabriel Recchia in a blogpost responding to my interpretation above as it first appeared on my blog (Recchia; Heuser, "Concepts"). Recchia's post explores other vector operations that even more reliably yield "genius," namely V(learning)+V(virtue) and V(talents)+V(abilities)+V(erudition). To me, however, these alternative "paths" to genius do not exclude one another; instead, each contributes to our understanding of the semantics of genius in the period. My goal with this interpretation is not to "prove" Young's analogy, but rather to suggest that, by "amplifying" a particular analogy through its semantic associations across a corpus, word vectors help contextualize our interpretations of particular analogies in literature. As Recchia writes, "the computational exercise has helped us focus our search."</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Distant-reading Word Vectors</head><p>If, then, vectors help us explore this micro-analytic scale of interpretation, they also help us scale those same interpretive models up to the level of macroanalysis. For instance, inspired by the foregoing closereading of Young's complex web of analogies <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">(Table 1)</ref>, we might continue Young's project of obsessive analogization by way of a distant reading. By defining vectors for a range of common eighteenth-century contrasts <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">(Table 2)</ref>, and then measuring the correlation between them, we can in fact construct another complex web of analogies-this time gleaned computationally, from a large-scale archive of the period's discourse.  <ref type="formula">(1748)</ref>, as well as a number of essays from the period; they are not meant to be exhaustive. This is an admittedly unsatisfactory method; I am currently exploring ways to discover conceptual contrasts computationally.</p><p>Looking at a particularly strong correlation among the contrasts in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>, between V(Simplicity-Refinement) and V(Virtue-Vice), we can see how their correlation emerges from the way in which both contrasts carry similar semantic associations across the same set of words <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Figure 3</ref>). . 1,000 most frequent nouns in the ECCO-TCP corpus. On the x-axis is their cosine similarity with the V(Simplicity-Refinement) vector: if above 0, then associated more with refinement; if below, more with simplicity. Conversely, on the y-axis, above 0 means associated more with Vice; below 0, more with Virtue.</p><p>In other words, this graph shows that there are more words for simple virtues (e.g. "graces") than refined virtues (e.g. "science"), and more words for refined vices (e.g. "corruption") than simple vices (e.g. "murder"). This correlation between their semantic associations (R^2 = 0.41) reveals, then, an analogy emerging from the period's broader discursive practices-Simplicity is to Refinement as Virtue is to Vice-even as that analogy might appear only implicitly in particular essays, such as in Hume's "Of Simplicity and Refinement in Writing" (1742), when Hume loosely associates refinement with the moral decline of post-Augustan Rome.</p><p>This macro-analytic approach to discovering implicit discursive analogies allows us to visualize the ways in which the frequent conceptual contrasts in eighteenth-century literature are implicitly analogized in the discourse, and how those implicit analogical relationships may have helped to structure what Peter De Bolla has called the "conceptual architecture" of the period <ref type="figure">(Figure 4</ref>). the R^2 value of their correlation, across the 1,000 most frequent nouns (as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>), is greater than 0.1. Blue lines read in the natural order (e.g. Simplicity is to Refinement as Woman is to Man); red lines read in reverse order (e.g. Simplicity is to Refinement as the King is to Parliament). Nodes are sized by betweenness centrality, and colored by network community. Edges are sized by the R^2 value.</p><p>From this network of correlated contrasts, we can see which of them, for instance, are implicitly gendered in the period's discourse. "Woman" is to "man," for instance, as "queen" is to "king"-but also as the beautiful is to the sublime, as simplicity is to refinement, and as passion is to reason. Similarly, we can see which contrasts are moralized in the period: "virtue" is to "vice" as wisdom is to folly, as pity is to fear, as the mind is to the body. Moreover, the contrasts of virtue and vice, and simplicity and refinement, might actually play a central role in such a conceptual architecture of analogies, as seen from their centrality within the network.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>I hope to have demonstrated some of the ways in which word vectors might be useful for the digital humanities, and particularly for eighteenth-century literary studies, both by demonstrating how they might help us to close-read specific analogical maneuvers, as well as distant-read analogies as they emerge from patterns in their usage across a literary discourse.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Notes</head><p>[1] According to statistics provided in the original paper for the Stanford NLP group's "GloVe," a competing algorithm to word2vec, a word2vec model trained on a large English-language corpus can accurately solve 65% of analogies in a test dataset, and GloVe 75% (Pennington et al, <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>). As a rough comparison to the accuracy we would expect from human subjects, we might look to the Miller Analogy Test from Pearson-an admittedly unrelated analogy test, which is given to some graduate student applicants. In the MAT of 2002-3, to accurately solve 65% or more of its 100 analogies places a student above the 80th percentile (Pearson). Although not directly comparable, these statistics make more probable the assessment that word vectors are capable of capturing semantic relationships at a level competitive with human subjects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bibliography</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. "Riches" are to "Virtue" as "Learning" is to what?, asked of a word2vec model trained on 80 million words of eighteenth-century literature (the ECCO-TCP corpus).</figDesc><graphic url="image-2.png" coords="2,321.18,72.30,232.80,95.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. 1,000 most frequent nouns in the ECCO-TCP corpus. On the x-axis is their cosine similarity with the V(Simplicity-Refinement) vector: if above 0, then associated more with refinement; if below, more with simplicity. Conversely, on the y-axis, above 0 means associated more with Vice; below 0, more with Virtue.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Semantic contrasts are connected in this network if the R^2 value of their correlation, across the 1,000 most frequent nouns (as in Figure 3), is greater than 0.1. Blue lines read in the natural order (e.g. Simplicity is to Refinement as Woman is to Man); red lines read in reverse order (e.g. Simplicity is to Refinement as the King is to Parliament). Nodes are sized by betweenness centrality, and colored by network community. Edges are sized by the R^2 value.</figDesc><graphic url="image-5.png" coords="3,316.86,404.94,229.68,178.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Table of conceptual analogies leveraged by Edward Young to argue for original over imitative composition (Conjectures on Original Composition, 1759).</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Common eighteenth-century contrasts, each expressed as a vector contrast. For instance, Virtue &lt;&gt; Vice denotes the vector V(Vice-Virtue). Contrasts were gleaned manually while reading Fielding's Tom Jones</figDesc><table></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Latent Dirichlet allocation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Blei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jordan</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Machine Learning Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="993" to="1022" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Architecture of Concepts: The Historical Formation of Human Rights</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bolla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<pubPlace>Fordham UP</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic topic decomposition of an eighteenth-century American newspaper</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Newman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Block</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="753" to="767" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Arithmetic of Concepts: a response to Peter de Bolla</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gavin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Web. Accessed</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-09-19" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Modeling Literary History</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diachronic Word Embeddings Reveal Statistical Laws of Semantic Change</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hamilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leskovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jurafsky</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1605.09096</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Web. Accessed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016-05-30" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
	<note>Submitted</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Word Vectors in the Eighteenth Century, Episode 1: Concepts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Heuser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adventures of the Virtual</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Word Vectors in the Eighteenth Century</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Heuser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="&lt;http://ryan-heuser.org/word-vectors-2&gt;" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-04-07" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Adventures of the Virtual</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jockers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Macroanalysis: Digital Methods and Literary History. U of Illinois P</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Distributed representations of words and phrases and their compositionality</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mikolov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="page">26</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Advances in neural information processing systems</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Candidate Information Booklet</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Pearson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="&lt;http://im-ages.pearsonclinical.com/images/pdf/milleranalo-gies/matcib2002_03.pdf&gt;" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Miller Analogies Test. Web. Accessed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glove: Global Vectors for Word Representation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pennington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Socher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Manning</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2014 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing</title>
		<meeting>the 2014 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1532" to="1543" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Numberless Degrees Of Similitude&apos;: A Response To Ryan Heuser&apos;s &apos;Word Vectors In The Eighteenth Century, Part 1</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Recchia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="&lt;http://www.twonewthings.com/gabrielrec-chia/2016/06/11/numberless-degrees-of-similitude-word-vectors/&gt;" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-04-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Gabriel Recchia&apos;s Blog. 11</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">models.word2vec - Deep learning with word2vec</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Řehůřek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="&lt;https://radimrehurek.com/gensim/mod-els/word2vec.html&gt;" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">gensim. Web. Accessed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The SMART retrieval system: Experiments in automatic document processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Salton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1971" />
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A vector space model for automatic indexing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Salton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yang</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="613" to="620" />
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vector Space Models for the Digital Humanities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Web. Accessed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Bookworm.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rejecting the gender binary: a vectorspace operation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Web. Accessed</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-10-30" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Bookworm.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From Frequency to Meaning: Vector Space Models of Semantics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Turney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pantel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
