<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Bridging the Gap: Greater Usability for TEI encoding</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Stefan</forename>
            <surname>Dumont</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Stefan Dumont is a <roleName>research associate</roleName> in the TELOTA
            working group for digital humanities at the <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of
              Sciences and Humanities</orgName>.</affiliation>
          <email>dumont@bbaw.de</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Martin</forename>
            <surname>Fechner</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Martin Fechner is a <roleName>research associate</roleName> in the TELOTA
            working group for digital humanities at the <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of
              Sciences and Humanities</orgName>.</affiliation>
          <email>fechner@bbaw.de</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>09/06/2015</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Arianna Ciula</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Fabio Ciotti</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Martin Holmes</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="8">Selected Papers from the 2013 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Revues.org -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>tools</term>
          <term>usability</term>
          <term>bottom up</term>
          <term>usability</term>
          <term>graphical user interface</term>
          <term>ediarum</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change/>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>This article shows how, with a focus on user-friendliness and a bottom-up approach, the
          digital work environment ediarum was successfully developed. With ediarum, researchers can
          comfortably encode and edit in TEI, as well as publish their results in an online or print
          edition. This solution, developed by the TELOTA initiative of Berlin-Brandenburg Academy
          of Sciences and Humanities, is based on three software components: eXistdb, Oxygen XML
          Author, and ConTeXt. These components are combined, supplemented with additional
          functions, and tailored to fit a project’s needs. After a pilot run, ediarum has been
          implemented for multiple internal and external research projects. The experience that was
          gained and our self developed program components are available to the Digital Humanities
          community.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="situation">
        <head>The Situation</head>
        <div xml:id="gap">
          <head>A Gap Between User and Possibility</head>
          <p>For a reader of <title level="j">jTEI</title> it might be self-evident that in this day
            and age a historical-critical edition should be created with established technologies
            (e.g., XML). The benefits are well known: texts encoded in TEI-XML can be used to
            produce both Web and print publications and at the same time ensure long-term
            accessibility and reusability. Furthermore, both XML and TEI are well-established
            technologies—the TEI Guidelines having been in use for over 25 years. Nevertheless, in
            Germany as well as internationally, edition projects continue to use programs such as
            Microsoft Word to edit their texts. These texts are used to create print editions and
            may be digitized in a simple form such as PDF.</p>
          <p>There is thus a gap between the available, useful technologies and their actual
            adoption. The cause of this is in many cases economic circumstances. Academic
            institutions and publishing houses are reluctant to alter their
              <soCalled>tried-and-true</soCalled> workflows, in part because any changes cost time
            and money. Moreover, the know-how is often not available to correctly encode
            transcriptions into TEI. An important additional factor is that despite the many
            advantages of a Web publication, the printed edition—especially for veteran edition
            projects—remains the bar of what serious results should look like. Thus a new technology
            must justify itself not only economically, but academically as well (see <ref
              type="bibl" target="#sahle13">Sahle 2013, 109–10</ref>).</p>
          <p>Another cause of this gap is the dearth of programs to help researchers who lack the
            technical knowledge to transcribe and annotate their texts in TEI. While other prevalent
            text-editing programs offer an intuitive user interface, this is not the case for most
            XML editors.<note>In the TEI community one can find multiple tools. However, almost all
              of them support only the publication of TEI documents and not their creation (see,
              e.g., <ref type="bibl" target="#pape12">Pape, Schöch, and Wegner 2012</ref>). Tools
              that aim to support the actual transcription and editing of texts are less common. One
              such tool is from the Teuchos project, which provides a basic user interface for
              certain parts of the manuscript description (<ref type="bibl" target="#vertan12"
                >Vertan and Reimers 2012</ref>). In this case the data is not edited directly in XML
              but saved in a text format. In addition, it is not possible to enter inline markup. A
              more functional solution is the CWRCWriter, which still requires the user to have a
              good knowledge of TEI (<ref type="bibl" target="#rockwell12">Rockwell et al.
                2012</ref> or <ptr target="http://cwrctc.artsrn.ualberta.ca/"/>).</note> A factor
            contributing to the lack of such a user interface could be the high complexity of a
            TEI-encoded edition.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="bridge">
          <head>The Bridge: Greater Usability</head>
          <p>The solution that is repeatedly suggested—that researchers should learn TEI-XML or even
            learn how to program—does not seem viable, and in any case simply shifts the problem to
            the side of the user.<note>This point calls for a more thorough discussion that does not
              fit within the parameters of this article. It can nevertheless be determined that the
              lack of user-friendly tools is an obstacle for new TEI users (<ref type="bibl"
                target="#burghart12">Burghart and Rehbein 2012, § 32</ref>).</note> The lack of
            knowledge of how to encode a manuscript in TEI should not hinder the use of TEI. On the
            contrary, an easy method to adopt TEI for using should be made available. The center of
            editorial work should remain the evaluation and examination of manuscripts.<note>Of
              course the creation of a TEI-conformant XML schema is also an editorial process and is
              thus done in collaboration with the editors, when not done by them
            directly.</note></p>
          <p>When one considers the developments in graphical user interfaces over the last few
            years, one observes that programs are offering simpler and more intuitive
            interfaces—even with sometimes more complex program tasks and functions behind them. It
            is not without reason that there are now entire fields that concern themselves with the
              <soCalled>ergonomics</soCalled> of software.</p>
          <p>In our opinion, the Digital Humanities community should not avoid such developments but
            instead should take advantage of them. A simple and intuitive user interface would help
            reduce the fear and frustration that often meets new technologies (<ref type="bibl"
              target="#nielsen93">Nielsen 1993, 24–25</ref>).<note> Sahle (<ref type="bibl"
                target="#sahle13">2013, 111</ref>) notes that editors are often afraid of the
              technical challenges of digital editions.</note> User-friendly programs create a
            positive user experience and would increase interest in using TEI for the transcription
            and annotation of manuscripts.</p>
          <p>A fundamental part of user-friendly software is providing the user with visual feedback
            for an executed action (<ref type="bibl" target="#nielsen93">Nielsen 1993, 134</ref>).
            For example, after the appropriate markup for a crossed-out piece of text is entered,
            this text can then be displayed as crossed out. Although this type of feedback might
            seem trivial, another type certainly is not: print output. As mentioned above, the
            printed edition is still the main goal for most scholarly edition projects, even when it
            is supplemented with a Web publication (<ref type="bibl" target="#sahle13">Sahle 2013,
              111–112</ref>). When the formatting process begins after the encoding is completed,
            the researcher can only check their work in an abstract manner. When the publication and
            creation of the edition is not separated, but happens simultaneously in one work
            environment, the researcher has the benefit of being able to see his or her markup with
            one click displayed properly in the desired medium. This not only improves the
            supervision of the work in progress, but also increases trust in and satisfaction with
            the technology—in this case the TEI encoding of manuscripts.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="pilot">
        <head>The Pilot Project</head>
        <p><ref target="http://www.bbaw.de/en/telota">TELOTA</ref>,<note><ptr
              target="http://www.bbaw.de/en/telota"/>.</note> the digital humanities initiative at
          the <ref target="http://www.bbaw.de/en">Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and
            Humanities</ref> (BBAW),<note>
            <ptr target="http://www.bbaw.de/en"/>.</note> had to confront these issues as they were
          given the task to develop a digital work environment for the edition project <ref
            target="http://www.bbaw.de/en/research/schleiermacherII">Schleiermacher in Berlin
            1808–1834</ref>.<note>
            <ptr target="http://www.bbaw.de/en/research/schleiermacherII"/>.</note> This environment
          was intended to assist the researchers in transcribing, encoding, and annotating the
          letters, lectures, and daily calendar of the Protestant theologian Friedrich
          Schleiermacher. In addition to creating a user interface for transcribing and editing, the
          environment had to be able to produce both a Web and a print edition from the TEI-XML
          data. Ideally this would happen automatically, so that the editors would be able to see
          their results immediately.</p>
        <p>To develop such a solution from scratch requires significant resources. To reduce time
          and effort of development it is preferable to build on existing software. After evaluating
          the available software, the team chose the following programs: <list rend="bulleted">
            <item><ref target="http://exist-db.org/">eXistdb</ref><note><ptr
                  target="http://exist-db.org/"/>.</note> for the database in which the TEI files
              would be stored. A decisive factor was the ability to retrieve and run XQuery and XSLT
              scripts from within the eXistdb and not just externally.</item>
            <item><ref target="http://www.oxygenxml.com/xml_author.html">Oxygen XML Author</ref><note>
                <ptr target="http://www.oxygenxml.com/xml_author.html"/>.</note> as the user
              interface for entering and editing the centrally stored TEI files. Decisive were the
              extensive functions of Oxygen XML Author that allowed visual editing of XML for
              persons without technical knowledge.</item>
            <item><ref target="http://wiki.contextgarden.net/Main_Page">ConTeXt</ref><note>
                <ptr target="http://wiki.contextgarden.net/Main_Page"/>.</note> for the formatting
              language to generate an automatic print-ready proof from the XML files. Among its
              benefits were its use of the long-established formatting language TeX, the possibility
              of processing XML directly, and the option to add one’s own functions with the help of
              the programming language Lua.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>Although eXistdb and ConTexT are open source software, this is not the case for Oxygen
          XML Author. A completely open-source solution would have been preferable, but there is no
          software currently available that offers such extensive functions for end users.</p>
        <p>Because of the solution’s modular organization, the software components can be replaced
          if necessary (for example when a tool is no longer supported by the community or a
          company). Essentially every piece of software can and will become outdated at some point;
          what is important is that the data is in a format that can still be reopened and
          reused.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure1">
          <graphic url="images/jtei-8-084-dumont_fig_01.jpg" width="1024px" height="666px"/>
          <head type="legend">Workflow in the digital work environment</head>
        </figure>
        <p>The three selected software components were combined, and scripts and additional
          functions were written. The goal was to create a software solution that was not just
          generally suitable for the research project, but customized to increase the
          user-friendliness of the work environment despite the complexity behind a critical
          edition. Besides the creation of multiple TEI P5–compatible schemata, the functions and
          toolbar of the Oxygen XML Author were also configured and supplemented with additional
          custom functions. XQuery and XSLT scripts were written for the Web publication and its
          presentation was designed in HTML and CSS. The automatic generation of the print edition
          was programmed with the formatting language ConTeXt.</p>
        <div xml:id="database">
          <head>A Central Database Enables Collaborative Work</head>
          <p>The digital work environment uses the open-source XML database eXistdb as its central
            repository for the TEI documents. The database is installed on a server and available
            online. This gives all the researchers on the project access to the same data
            collection, allowing them to work collaboratively. The contents of the database are
            directly available and searchable for users as a collection of files in Oxygen XML
            Author. Collaborative access is made possible through the WebDAV protocol, which locks
            files that are in use to avoid conflicts and unintended overwrites.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="environment">
          <head>A User-Friendly Environment with Oxygen XML Author</head>
          <p>Oxygen XML Author was chosen to create the user interface with which the editors
            transcribe and edit in the work environment.<note>To this end we used <soCalled>Oxygen
                Frameworks</soCalled>: that is to say, we developed additional frameworks within the
              context offered by the program. Oxygen XML delivers a standard framework for TEI
              documents that provides a toolbar with a few basic TEI elements. However, because of
              the large number of TEI elements and attributes, the development of an all-inclusive
              TEI Framework would not be practical. The editor would be overwhelmed with such a
              large number of superfluous functions.</note> While using this program, the editors
            usually do not see the code, but instead are in a user-friendly <soCalled>author
              view</soCalled> that is styled with CSS. More than one sub-view was made for the
            project within this author view, so that editors can choose the one most fitting for
            their current phase of work. In the various views, only certain TEI markup is shown or
            highlighted in the transcription. For example, when an editor only wants to examine the
            indexed passages of a text, then he or she can choose the view which only highlights the
              <gi>index</gi> elements.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure2">
            <graphic url="images/jtei-8-084-dumont_fig_02.jpg" width="1024px" height="298px"/>
            <head type="legend">Toolbar for the Schleiermacher edition with functions for inserting
              TEI markup</head>
          </figure>
          <p>Above all, however, the end user can enter markup into the manuscript or into the TEI
            Header with one click in the toolbar. In this way, text phenomena like struck-out text
            can be documented, editorial comments can be added, and the creation date of a
            manuscript can be noted. For every type of editorial markup there is a special button
            that enters the appropriate valid XML. If needed not only single elements but complex
            XML fragments will be inserted. Furthermore, the buttons for the metadata insert proper
            elements in the correct place of the <gi>teiHeader</gi>. If necessary, the editor is
            asked via an extra dialog box for the value of an attribute. The editor is thus not
            concerned with the name of the actual TEI element, whether it needs an attribute, or
            whether in this context there are structural variations to be considered. The entire
            text can thus be quickly and simply marked up with TEI
            <!-- [RvdB] changed 'conformant' to 'conformant' -->conformant XML. The researcher can
            also, if desired, view the XML code at any time for more precise editing or simply to
            follow the process more closely.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="indexes">
          <head>Central Indexes</head>
          <p>Besides the transcription of the text, the database can also include central indexes
            (for persons, places, works, etc.) in the form of XML files. These can be edited and
            linked through the texts. If, for example, one wishes to mark up a person’s name, one
            selects the word in the text to be indexed, and a dropdown list appears with all the
            names from the person index, from which the editor can choose the appropriate one.
            Selecting the name causes both the correct element <gi>persName</gi> and the correct ID
            of the person (as an attribute) to be entered. The index with the actual references to
            the correct text passages is then automatically created for both the print and Web
            publications from the marked-up TEI document. This index function is created through a
            specially-programmed Java operation for Oxygen XML Author and with various XQuery
            scripts in the database. When programming the Java operation, we used parameters and not
            constants in the source code. Thus, the parameter values could be comfortably entered in
            Oxygen XML Author and changed if necessary.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure3">
            <graphic url="images/jtei-8-084-dumont_fig_03.jpg" width="1235px" height="926px"/>
            <head type="legend">Customized Oxygen XML Author with the index function’s dialogue box
              opened</head>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="website">
          <head>Website</head>
          <p>In addition to the work environment in Oxygen XML Author, we also created a website for
            the project. On this website the researchers can easily browse through or search the
            current data collection through a live connection with the database. Access to the
            website can be either limited to the project team or open to the public.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure4">
            <graphic url="images/jtei-8-084-dumont_fig_04.jpg" width="1672px" height="1042px"/>
            <head type="legend">Website for the Schleiermacher edition</head>
          </figure>
          <p>From a technical viewpoint, the website consists primarily of XQuery scripts, whose
            request results are presented as HTML5, through an XSL transformation. The scripts and
            transformations are requested from eXist through a REST interface and processed with the
            eXistdb internal parser—a great advantage of this database. The website is thus
            generated completely server-side.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="printedition">
          <head>Print Edition</head>
          <p>A further output option is the print edition, implemented with the help of ConTeXt,
            which automatically generates a PDF (at any point in the workflow) from a TEI document.
            With the correct configuration, the format and presentation of the PDF can meet the
            research project’s exact needs for printed editions. Each TEI element is given a
            specific formatting command through a configuration file. In this way the different
            apparatuses can, for example, appear as footnotes that refer to the main text with the
            help of line numbers and lemmata. The print edition can also provide the correct index
            for each transcription and resolve any cross-references between manuscripts.</p>
          <figure xml:id="figure5">
            <graphic url="images/jtei-8-084-dumont_fig_05.jpg" width="800px" height="580px"/>
            <head type="legend">Print edition for the Schleiermacher edition generated via
              ConTeXt</head>
          </figure>
          <p>The print edition helps the researchers to check their TEI-encoded transcriptions;
            additionally, it obviates the need for a separate typesetting process.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="feedback">
          <head>Feedback</head>
          <p>The researchers of <title level="m">Schleiermacher in Berlin 1808–1834</title> had a
            two-hour training session introducing them to the work environment. They were also given
            an extensive handbook, a quick start guide, and a <soCalled>cheat sheet</soCalled> with
            an overview of all the available functions.<note><ptr
                target="http://www.bbaw.de/en/telota/software/ediarum"/>.</note></p>
          <p>After working with the environment for two months, the researchers were asked to share
            their opinions. The feedback was overwhelmingly positive, and they confirmed that the
            environment eased their work on the edition and saved them time. The ability to check
            their work immediately on the website or in the print edition was seen as a great
            advantage. The researchers were also thankful that they were not expected to work
            directly in the XML code, but instead could mark up the texts with TEI
            <!-- [RvdB] conformant? -->conform XML in a simple graphical user interface. At the same
            time, some researchers had familiarized themselves with the TEI XML behind the interface
            and did sometimes edit directly in the XML, especially in the beginning when some
            functions were not yet available.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="bottomup">
        <head>From the Bottom Up</head>
        <p>In the end the pilot run was so successful that other projects within the
          Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of the Sciences and Humanities expressed interest. In the
          spring of 2013 the work environment was implemented for the Academy’s project <ref
            target="http://www.bbaw.de/en/research/cagb">Commentaria in Aristotelem Graeca et
            Byzantina</ref> (CAGB)<note><ptr target="http://www.bbaw.de/en/research/cagb"/>.</note>
          and in the summer of 2013 for <ref target="http://www.bbaw.de/forschung/regestaimperii"
            >Regesta Imperii</ref>—<ref
            target="http://www.regesta-imperii.de/unternehmen/abteilungen/xiii-friedrich-iii.html"
            >Friedrich III</ref>.<note><ptr target="http://www.bbaw.de/forschung/regestaimperii"/>
            and <ptr
              target="http://www.regesta-imperii.de/unternehmen/abteilungen/xiii-friedrich-iii.html"
            />.</note> This was done using the same technical concept, but with customized functions
          for each project for the text entry and for the publication (Web and print). This was due
          to the fact that the TEI schemata were in both cases very different from the pilot
          project. For example, CAGB is not an edition of manuscript transcriptions but of
          manuscript descriptions. In contrast, the time and effort for implementation would be
          minimal if one were using a schema from a project for which the work environment is
          already implemented. The amount of work does not depend on the software or technology, but
          on the complexity and diversity of TEI-encoded editions.</p>
        <p>With every new implementation, the work environment developed further and was
          supplemented with new functions. This applied not just to the Java operations but also to
          the XQuery scripts, which are responsible for various fundamental tasks such as making the
          index file available for the Java operations. For these frequently used XQuery and XSLT
          scripts and for further configurations, an eXistdb application<note>For further
            information about apps in eXistdb, see <title level="a">Getting Started with Web
              Application Development</title>, <ptr
              target="http://exist-db.org/exist/apps/doc/development-starter.xml"/>.</note> was
          developed in 2013 that allows for a simple and fast installation into the database.<note>
            This eXistdb app will soon be available online.</note> New functions are then, when
          suitable, integrated into the already existing work environment so that after the launch
          of the work environment the operability continually improves.</p>
        <p>After we published a <ref
            target="http://digiversity.net/2012/digitale-arbeitsumgebung-fur-das-editionsvorhaben-schleiermacher-in-berlin-1808-1834/"
            >report about ediarum</ref>,<note><bibl><author>Stefan Dumont</author> and
                <author>Martin Fechner</author>, <title level="a">Digitale Arbeitsumgebung für das
                Editionsvorhaben <q>Schleiermacher in Berlin 1808–1834</q></title>, <title level="j"
                >digiversity: Webmagazin für Informationstechnologie in den
                Geisteswissenschaften</title> (October 11, <date>2012</date>), <ptr
                target="http://digiversity.net/2012/digitale-arbeitsumgebung-fur-das-editionsvorhaben-schleiermacher-in-berlin-1808-1834/"
              />.</bibl></note> it caught the attention of other research institutions. During this
          time TELOTA introduced and explained the environment to interested institutions in various
          presentations. As a result, for example, the Academy of Science and Literature Mainz
          adopted the concept of ediarum and built their own digital work environment based on it.
          Other interested persons can read about the concept in a series of blog entries that are
          written as tutorials.<note><bibl><author>Stefan Dumont</author>, <title level="a"
                >Tutorial: Wie baue ich ein eigenes Framework für Oxygen XML?</title>, <title
                level="m">digiversity: Webmagazin für Informationstechnologie in den
                Geisteswissenschaften</title> (October 30, <date>2013</date>), <ptr
                target="http://digiversity.net/2013/tutorial-wie-baue-ich-ein-oxygen-xml-framework/"
              /></bibl>, and <bibl><author>Stefan Dumont</author>, <title level="a">Tutorial:
                Indexfunktionen für Oxygen XML Frameworks</title>, <title level="m">digiversity:
                Webmagazin für Informationstechnologie in den Geisteswissenschaften</title>(December
              16, <date>2013</date>), <ptr
                target="http://digiversity.net/2013/tutorial-indexfunktionen-fuer-oxygen-xml-frameworks/"
              />.</bibl></note> In addition, the custom Java functions were made available by TELOTA
          on <ref target="https://github.com/telota/ediarum/tree/master/oxygen_java">GitHub</ref>
          for the TEI community.<note><ptr
              target="https://github.com/telota/ediarum/tree/master/oxygen_java"/>; for
            documentation, see <ptr
              target="https://github.com/telota/ediarum/wiki/Documentation-ediarum.jar-(english)"
            />.</note> There the functions can be downloaded and used directly in Oxygen Frameworks
          or, if necessary, changed in accordance with theGNU LGPL (Lesser General Public
          License).</p>
        <p>At the end of 2013, TELOTA began implementing ediarum for the <ref
            target="http://www.gotthelf.unibe.ch/content/index_ger.html">historical-critical edition
            of Jeremias Gotthelf</ref>.<note><title level="m">Jeremias Gotthelf:
              Historisch-kritische Gesamtausgabe (HKG)</title>, Forschungsstelle Jeremias Gotthelf,
            Universität Bern, <ptr target="http://www.gotthelf.unibe.ch/content/index_ger.html"
            />.</note> In this collaboration with Bern University, new functions are being developed
          and existing ones improved. For instance, we plan to build a function to allow end users
          to insert overlapping markup (using, e.g., <gi>anchor</gi> elements and <att>spanTo</att>)
          in Oxygen XML Author.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="summary">
        <head>Summary and Prospects</head>
        <p>The bottom-up development of ediarum with its strong focus on user-friendliness brings
          with it certain implications.</p>
        <p>It has required a lot of work during the initial implementation and customization of the
          environment, especially to generate the website and print edition. TELOTA is now
          considering simplifying the creation of the Web and print editions, so that less time is
          needed for programming. The goal, however, will be not to develop a complete plug-and-play
          solution. That would be impossible, considering the complexity and diversity of critical
          editions. The aim for a future version of ediarum will be rather to create a solution for
          encoding editions in TEI which involves the lowest possible amount of time and effort for
          programming while being customized to the specific needs of a project. </p>
        <p>The concept of ediarum’s development with its tailored solution has various advantages:
            <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>Time and effort for programming is spared through the consistent use of existing
              software and the elimination of extraneous functionality not required by a particular
              project. In this way a functional software solution is reached more quickly and
              practically.</item>
            <item>The work environment is customized to the exact needs of the project. Due to the
              user-friendly interface, researchers enjoy operating it and use it in their daily
              work.</item>
            <item>The automatic generation of the Web and print edition from the XML file allows the
              researcher to immediately check their TEI encoding. This eases the publication
              process, leaving more time for the actual editorial work.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>Thus, through addressing the needs of a specific project, we found a solution that can be
          used by many: ediarum helps bridge the gap between hesitant users and the many
          possibilities and advantages of TEI encoding.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burghart12"><author>Burghart, Marjorie</author>, and <author>Malte
              Rehbein</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">The Present and Future of the
              TEI Community for Manuscript Encoding</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the Text
              Encoding Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope> (February). <ptr
              target="http://jtei.revues.org/372"/>. doi:<idno type="doi"
            >10.4000/jtei.372</idno></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="nielsen93"><author>Nielsen, Jakob</author>. <date>1993</date>. <title
              level="m">Usability Engineering</title>. <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Academic Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pape12"><author>Pape, Sebastian</author>, <author>Christof Schöch</author>,
            and <author>Lutz Wegner</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">TEICHI and the
              Tools Paradox</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding
              Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope> (February). <ptr
              target="http://jtei.revues.org/432"/>. doi:<idno type="doi"
            >10.4000/jtei.432</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rockwell12"><author>Rockwell, Geoffrey</author>, <author>Susan
              Brown</author>, <author>James Chartrand</author>, and <author>Susan
            Hesemeier</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">CWRC-Writer: An In-Browser XML
              Editor</title>. In <title level="m">Digital Humanities 2012: Conference
              Abstracts</title>, edited by <editor>Jan Christoph Meister</editor>, <biblScope
              unit="page">508–11</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>: <publisher>Hamburg
              University Press</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/HamburgUP_dh2012_BoA.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sahle13"><author>Sahle, Patrick</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
              level="m">Digitale Editionsformen. Zum Umgang mit der Überlieferung unter den
              Bedingungen des Medienwandels. Teil 2: Befunde, Theorie und Methodik.</title>
            <series>Schriften des Instituts für Dokumentologie und Editorik</series>, <biblScope
              unit="issue">8</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Norderstedt</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>BoD</publisher>. <ptr target="http://kups.ub.uni-koeln.de/id/eprint/5352"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="vertan12"><author>Vertan, Cristina</author>, and <author>Stefanie
              Reimers</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">A TEI-based Application for
              Editing Manuscript Descriptions</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding
              Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope> (February). <ptr
              target="http://jtei.revues.org/392"/>. doi:<idno type="doi"
            >10.4000/jtei.392</idno>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
