<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">TEI4LdoD: Textual Encoding and Social Editing in Web 2.0
          Environments</title>
        <author>
          <name><forename>António</forename>
            <surname>Rito Silva</surname></name>
          <affiliation>António Rito Silva is <roleName>associate professor</roleName> in the
            Department of Computer Science and Engineering, <orgName>University of Lisbon</orgName>,
            and <roleName>researcher</roleName> at the <orgName><ref
                target="http://www.inesc-id.pt/">INESC-ID</ref></orgName>. He has worked in the
            field of collaborative systems and social software, particularly in the domain of
            business processes tools that blend the roles of producer and consumer. In this project
            he intends to apply some of these techniques for connecting the roles of producer and
            reader of the literary work.</affiliation>
          <email>rito.silva@tecnico.ulisboa.pt</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name><forename>Manuel</forename>
            <surname>Portela</surname></name>
          <affiliation>Manuel Portela is <roleName>assistant professor</roleName> with Habilitation
            in the Department of Languages, Literatures and Cultures, <orgName>University of
              Coimbra</orgName>, Portugal, where he directs the Doctoral Program in <ref
              target="http://matlit.wordpress.com/">Advanced Studies in the Materialities of
              Literature</ref>. He is also a <roleName>researcher</roleName> at the <ref
              target="http://www.uc.pt/fluc/clp/apr/clping">Centre for Portuguese Literature</ref>
            at the <orgName>University of Coimbra</orgName>, and the principal investigator of the
            project <ref target="http://matlit.wordpress.com/projectos/">No Problem Has a Solution:
              A Digital Archive of the Book of <emph>Disquiet</emph></ref> (2012–15). His latest
            book is <title level="m">Scripting Reading Motions: The Codex and the Computer as
              Self-Reflexive Machines</title> (MIT Press, 2013).</affiliation>
          <email>mportela@fl.uc.pt</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>09/04/2015</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Arianna Ciula</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Fabio Ciotti</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Martin Holmes</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="8">Selected Papers from the 2013 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Revues.org -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>Fernando Pessoa</term>
          <term>Book of Disquiet</term>
          <term>digital archive</term>
          <term>Web 2.0</term>
          <term>collaborative archive</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>In this article we describe how textual encoding is used in our current project of
          constructing a digital archive of Fernando Pessoa’s <title level="m">Livro do Desassossego
            [LdoD]</title>. Our model for virtualizing the authorial and editorial forms of this
          unfinished work aims to create a dynamic archive that is open to user interaction and
          collaboration. A brief introduction to the theoretical rationale of the archive is
          followed by a description of our technical solution for TEI XML encoding that is
          responsive to dynamic changes over time. With our software architecture proposal for
          processing TEI markup, the Collaborative Digital Archive of the Book of Disquiet will be
          able to instantiate the cooperative and social editing functionalities of Web 2.0
          environments.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="acknowledgements">
        <p>We would like to thank Timothy Thompson for his contributions to the TEI template for
            <title level="m">LdoD</title>.</p>
        <p>This work was supported by Portuguese national funds through FCT – Fundação para a
          Ciência e a Tecnologia, under projects <idno>PTDC/CLE-LLI/118713/2010</idno> and
            <idno>UID/CEC/50021/2013</idno>.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="intro">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>Fernando Pessoa’s <title level="m">Book of Disquiet</title> (<title level="m">Livro do
            Desassossego</title>, abbreviated <title level="m">LdoD</title>) is an unfinished book
          project. Pessoa wrote more than five hundred texts meant for this work between 1913 and
          1935, the year of his death. The first edition of <title level="m">LdoD</title> was not
          published until 1982, and another three major versions have been published since then
            (<ref target="#cunha90" type="bibl">1990</ref>, <ref target="#zenith98" type="bibl"
            >1998</ref>, <ref target="#pizarro10" type="bibl">2010</ref>), most of which have been
          further revised. As it exists today, <title level="m">LdoD</title> may be characterized as
            <list rend="ordered inline">
            <item>a set of autograph (manuscript and typescript) fragments,</item>
            <item>mostly unpublished at the time of Pessoa’s death, which have been</item>
            <item>transcribed, selected, and organized into four different editions, implying</item>
            <item>various interpretations of what constitutes this book according to the extant
              print editions.</item>
          </list> Editions show four major types of variation: in readings of particular passages,
          in selection of fragments, in their ordering, and also in heteronym attribution. <note>The
            concept <soCalled>heteronym</soCalled> was developed by Fernando Pessoa himself –
            heteronyms are fictional authors who have a specific writing style and a unique
            psychology. Many of Pessoa’s works have been written by a heteronym. In the case of the
              <title level="m">Book of Disquiet</title>, the work was assigned by Pessoa to
            heteronym Vicente Guedes during the first stage of writing, and to Bernardo Soares
            during the later stage. One editor has assigned this work to both Vicente Guedes and
            Bernardo Soares; two editors have assigned it to Bernardo Soares; and one editor has
            assigned it to Fernando Pessoa.</note></p>
        <p>The goal of the <title level="m">LdoD Archive</title><note><title level="u">No Problem
              Has a Solution: A Digital Archive of the <title level="m">Book of
              Disquiet</title></title>, a research project of the Centre for Portuguese Literature
            at the University of Coimbra, Portugal, is funded by FCT (Foundation for Science and
            Technology). Principal investigator: Manuel Portela. Reference:
              <idno>PTDC/CLE-LLI/118713/2010</idno>. Co-funded by FEDER (European Regional
            Development Fund), through Axis 1 of the Operational Competitiveness Program (POFC) of
            the National Strategic Framework (QREN). COMPETE:
              <idno>FCOMP-01-0124-FEDER-019715</idno>.</note> is twofold: on the one hand, we want
          to provide a <soCalled>standard</soCalled> archive where experts can study and compare
            <title level="m">LdoD</title>’s authorial witnesses to their different editions, and
          each one of these to each other; on the other hand, we want to design a virtual archive
          that allows both experts and non-experts to experiment with the production of different
          editions of <title level="m">LdoD</title>, and also with the writing of their own
          fragments based on <title level="m">LdoD</title>’s original fragments. Therefore, this
          latter goal, which is built on top of the genetic and critical archival goal, extends a
          scholarly understanding of <title level="m">LdoD</title> as both authorial project and
          editorial construct to a new perspective of <title level="m">LdoD</title> as an
          exploratory environment for individual and/or community editing and writing based on
          authorial witnesses and editorial versions.</p>
        <p>The rationale for allowing experts and non-experts to experiment with re-editing and
          rewriting this work originates in social editing theories and in the increasing appeal of
          the <title level="m">Book of Disquiet</title> for a general and global
            audience.<note>During the last three decades, the <title level="m">Livro do
              Desassossego</title> has been translated several times, and new translations continue
            to appear in Spanish, French, English, Italian, German, Dutch, Swedish, Polish, and
            several other languages. <title level="m">LdoD</title> is now regarded by many critics
            as one of the major achievements of Fernando Pessoa and one of the major works of
            European modernism. In Portugal, two new revised editions (<ref target="#cunha13"
              type="bibl">Sobral Cunha 2013</ref>; <ref target="#pizarro13" type="bibl">Pizarro
              2013</ref>) were published in 2013, and excerpts from <title level="m">LdoD</title>
            were recently selected for inclusion in the secondary school syllabus. Pessoa’s
            heteronyms, such as Álvaro de Campos, Alberto Caeiro, Ricardo Reis, and Bernardo Soares,
            are among the most quoted authors in Brazilian and Portuguese blogs. A feature film
            based on this unfinished book, <title level="m">Filme do Desassossego</title>, directed
            by João Botelho, was released to critical acclaim in 2010.</note> We want to explore the
          collaborative dimension of the Web as a reading and writing space in the context of a
          digital archive in ways that enhance its scholarly, pedagogical, ludic, and expressive
          uses. Through this double strategy, we also expect to build a tool for investigating the
          relation between writing processes and material and conceptual notions of the book. By
          allowing users to perform various roles within the <title level="m">LdoD Archive</title>,
          we suggest that one-way flow of text from the expert edition to the novice-remixed digital
          edition can be one way of handling questions of authority concerning the work’s textual
          form. We argue that it is possible to create a textual environment where professional and
          general readers can interact, and that such an environment extends theories about the
          social nature of textual production to current social media technologies.</p>
        <p>The novelty of this project is built on the possibility of dynamically interacting with
          the repository. Therefore, we intend to provide to end users, either TEI experts or
          non-experts, a web interface through which they can interact with the <title level="m"
            >LdoD</title> repository to create their own interpretations of Pessoa’s work. To
          achieve the project’s goal we designed and implemented a collaborative archive where
          experts and non-experts can interact, while preserving the relative autonomy of their
          interventions. The archive enables the coexistence of three different dimensions of <title
            level="m">LdoD</title>: genetic, social, and virtual. This coexistence is supported by a
          Web 2.0 environment that integrates an object-oriented database with a file repository for
          TEI-encoded files. Web 2.0 interactions are done through the object-oriented database
          while experts continue to use their TEI XML editor of choice—which stores TEI files in the
          file repository—to interact with the environment.</p>
        <p>In this article we focus on two aspects: <list rend="inline ordered">
            <item>how to encode <title level="m">LdoD</title>, and</item>
            <item>how to support a dynamic environment.</item>
          </list> For (1) we will show how the existing witnesses, both authorial and editorial, can
          be encoded in TEI markup and how the proposed encoding structure will support dynamic
          interactions with the book, such as, for instance, the creation of further
            editions.<note>Our XML encoding of what we refer to as <soCalled>authorial</soCalled>
            and <soCalled>editorial</soCalled> witnesses is in itself a new edition of <title
              level="m">LdoD</title>. The distinction that we make in this article between
              <soCalled>authorial</soCalled> and <soCalled>editorial</soCalled> serves the
            rhetorical purpose of showing two types of relation between our XML encoding and its
            source texts: in the case of <soCalled>authorial</soCalled> witnesses we are referring
            to our topographic transcription of autograph documents, which will also be accessible
            as digital image facsimiles; in the case of <soCalled>editorial</soCalled> witnesses we
            are referring to our textual transcription of <title level="m">LdoD</title> texts as
            they have been transcribed and organized in four major editions published between 1982
            and 2013. It can be argued that our XML topographic transcription of the
              <soCalled>authorial</soCalled> witnesses is of course a fifth editorial witness of the
              <title level="m">LdoD</title>, since it cannot be considered an authorial source. It
            must always be a particular reading and representation of that source, even if we intend
            to give readers a less mediated text by placing it in the context of the document
            facsimiles. It should, however, be noted that, at this level, we are not proposing a
            specific selection or organization for the fragments other than the semi-arbitrary shelf
            marks of the National Library. In fact, the fragments included for representation in the
            archive equal the total sum of the fragments included in those four editions. Our
            topographic transcription could be described as a new implicit edition by the research
            team focused on representing revision layers and describing material details of the
            source documents. An explicit edition by the research team, with its own selection and
            organization rationale, will take place only at the virtual level of the archive.</note>
          Regarding (2), we will propose a software architecture that supports the traditional
          process of TEI encoding (<ref target="#vanhoutte06" type="bibl">Vanhoutte 2006</ref>; <ref
            target="#tei12" type="bibl">TEI Consortium 2012</ref>; <ref target="#barney12"
            type="bibl">Barney 2012</ref>; <ref target="#earhart12" type="bibl">Earhart 2012</ref>)
          with the possibility of dynamically extending the interpretations of <title level="m"
            >LdoD</title> on top of a TEI representation.</p>
        <p>In <ptr target="#relatedWork" type="crossref"/> we briefly refer to related work. <ptr
            target="#project" type="crossref"/> presents the aims and rationale of the project. <ptr
            target="#problem" type="crossref"/> states the problem, and in <ptr target="#solution"
            type="crossref"/> we present our solution strategy. <ptr
            target="#encoding #architecture" type="crossref"/> describe our approach as far as,
          respectively, the TEI encoding and the software architecture are concerned.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="relatedWork">
        <head>Related Work</head>
        <p>Our proposal explores current approaches to editing in electronic environments and
          attempts to integrate them with TEI conceptual and processing models.</p>
        <p>In a recent article on the theory of digital editions, Peter Robinson shows how printed
          editions have traditionally focused on the relationship of text to work, while digital
          editions have been more focused on the relationship of text to document. He suggests that
            <quote source="#quoteRef1">a scholarly edition must, so far as it can, illuminate both
            aspects of the text, both text-as-work and text-as-document</quote> (<ref
            target="#robinson13" xml:id="quoteRef1" type="bibl">Robinson 2013, 123</ref>), and he
          calls attention to the presence of reading in any production of text through acts of
          transcription. The <title level="m">LdoD Archive</title> embodies a similar understanding
          of the nature of textual semiosis as a process involving self and object in a continuous
          and co-dependent process of meaning production through acts of reading. Editing Pessoa’s
          centrifugal and reticular body of unpublished work—a work that is constantly relocating
          its centre in a network of ever-expanding writing projects—is an especially acute
          experience of the productive function of reading in activating the material and
          interpretative fields that allow us to move back and forth from document to text to book
          to work. To the extent that each text of each edition is contextualizable in an archive of
          authorial and editorial witnesses, it is the very process of construction of text from
          document and edition from text that the genetic and social dimensions of the <title
            level="m">LdoD Archive</title> place in evidence. Our conceptual model reframes
          established digital archive practices by using the dynamic and social affordances of
          electronic space itself for simulating literary processes.</p>
        <p>The object representation of transcriptions is related to the work on data structure for
          representing multi-version objects (<ref target="#schmidt09" type="bibl">Schmidt and
            Colomb 2009</ref>) because we also parse the TEI files into a customized data structure,
          in our case a persistent object model that is manipulated in memory to avoid round trips
          to the databases. We emphasize the need identified by Schlitz and Bodine (<ref
            target="#schlitz09" type="bibl">2009</ref>) to have a clear separation between content
          and presentation in order to simplify and empower presentation tools. With regard to a Web
          2.0 for digital humanities, we are indebted to proposals on cooperative annotations by
          Tummarello, Morbidoni, and Pierazzo (<ref target="#tummarello05" type="bibl">2005</ref>)
          and the advantages and vision of Web 2.0 and collaboration discussed in Benel and Lejeune
            (<ref target="#benel09" type="bibl">2009</ref>), Fraistat and Jones (<ref
            target="#fraistat09" type="bibl">2009</ref>), and Siemens et al. (<ref
            target="#siemens10" type="bibl">2010</ref>). More recent research work raises the need
          to have several views of the encoding (<ref target="#brüning13" type="bibl">Brüning,
            Henzel, and Pravida 2013</ref>). In our approach, different views are also helpful for
          interoperability (interchange) and to simplify the implementation of user interfaces. The
          work of Wittern (<ref target="#wittern13" type="bibl">2013</ref>) stresses the need to
          allow dynamic edition of texts and management of versions, while Muñoz, Viglianti, and
          Fraistat (<ref target="#muñoz13" type="bibl">2013</ref>) highlight the challenges of
          participatory and distributed encoding in the context of the recently launched
          Shelley-Godwin Archive.</p>
        <p>One of the differences related to other existing TEI projects is that in the <title
            level="m">LdoD</title> project, TEI is envisioned more as an interchange mechanism (<ref
            target="#bauman11" type="bibl">Bauman 2011</ref>), through the export functionalities,
          than as the standard for a fully interoperable service-oriented architecture. As a
          consequence, we can experiment with technologies that are not usually used in TEI
          environments. To do this we had to implement TEI import and export functionalities to
          allow the manipulation of the TEI-encoded information in an object-oriented database.
          Additionally, the export functionality allows backup in a safe repository in a
          human-readable format. On the other hand, there is information in the object-oriented
          database that is specific to a Web 2.0 environment, like the information required to
          support access control policies, and which is not explicitly encoded using TEI because it
          depends on the dynamic aspects of the Web 2.0 tools.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="project">
        <head><title level="m">LdoD</title> Project</head>
        <p>The main goal of the project is to create a dynamic literary archive: <title level="m"
            >LdoD Archive—Collaborative Digital Archive of the Book of Disquiet</title>. This
          archive will aggregate digital facsimiles of all documentary materials of the <title
            level="m">Livro do Desassossego</title> and loosely topographic textual transcriptions
          of these materials. Our topographic transcription represents four types of spatial marks
          in the autographs: line breaks (using the <gi>lb</gi> element), spacing between paragraphs
          (using the <gi>space</gi> element), dividing rulers (using the <gi>pb</gi> element), and
          revision sites (using the <att>place</att> attribute on <gi>add</gi>). The main goal of
          the topographic transcription is to facilitate the side-by-side reading of the facsimile
          and its transcription. The archive will also include textual representations of the four
          major Portuguese editions published between 1982 and 2013, respectively by Jacinto do
          Prado Coelho (<ref target="#coelho82" type="bibl">1982</ref>), Teresa Sobral Cunha (<ref
            target="#cunha90" type="bibl">[1990–91]</ref>
          <ref target="#cunha08" type="bibl">2008</ref>), Richard Zenith (<ref target="#zenith98"
            type="bibl">[1998] 2012</ref>), and Jerónimo Pizarro (<ref target="#pizarro10"
            type="bibl">[2010]</ref>
          <ref target="#pizarro13" type="bibl">2013</ref>). At this level the archive combines a
          genetic edition with a social text edition of <title level="m">LdoD</title>, showing this
          work both as a network of multiple authorial intentions and as a conjectural construction
          of its successive editors. Readers will engage with the genetic edition when they see
          Pessoa’s acts of revision in each fragment as well as his different partial plans for the
            <title level="m">Book of Disquiet</title>. Future annotations will also mark
          intertextual relations of fragments to Pessoa’s readings, including references to
          passages, authors, and marginalia in his own personal library. Readers will engage with
          the social text edition in two ways: first, by seeing actual historical instances of the
            <title level="m">Book of Disquiet</title> as it has been edited in the four versions
          selected for inclusion in the archive, and in our own XML-encoded topographic
          transcription; and second, by creating new virtual instances of the <title level="m">Book
            of Disquiet</title> understood as a particular selection and organization of fragments.
          Tools for textual analysis, collation, and annotation will represent the dynamics of the
          acts of writing and editing in the production and reproduction of <title level="m"
            >LdoD</title>.</p>
        <p>Although the extension and detail of the critical apparatus varies considerably in
          Coelho, Cunha, Zenith, and Pizarro, all of those editions make explicit the interpretative
          criteria used for selecting and ordering the pieces of text. Our digital representation of
          the dynamics of textual and bibliographic variation depends on both XML encoding of
          variation sites (deletions, additions, substitutions, etc.) and metatextual information
          concerning authorial and editorial witnesses (such as date, order, or heteronym). While
          TEI markup may be considered as a particular kind of critical apparatus on its own, it is
          through visualization tools that users will be able to critically engage with the dynamics
          of variation in authorial and editorial witnesses. They will be able to examine not only
          the differences between autograph sources or between manuscripts and print editions, but
          also the differences among the various print editions.</p>
        <p>Besides using TEI XML encoding and programming to recreate the history of the authorial
          and editorial dynamics, the <title level="m">LdoD Archive</title> also explores the
          simulative potential of the digital medium as a space for virtualizing the <title
            level="m">Book of Disquiet</title> in ways that will enable users to experiment with the
          processes of editing and writing in relation to this work. Expert and non-expert users
          will be able to collaborate by making their own editions and by adding further textual
          fragments to the archive. Interventions can take two forms: selecting, ordering, and
          annotating fragments as part of a user-defined virtual edition; or selecting fragments or
          parts of fragments as textual seeds for creating variations and extensions based on <title
            level="m">LdoD</title> as part of a user-defined virtual writing process. This
          interactive feature of the archive is further enhanced by search and navigation functions
          that will allow a strong integration between the initial closed set of scholarly materials
          and the open virtual editing and writing additions.</p>
        <p>The participatory affordance of the digital medium has two major aspects: an environment
          for collaboration and social interaction, on the one hand, and the possibility of marking
          material changes at the level of code, on the other. Material changes can be marked up in
          the XML encoding, but also as new data and metadata generated by the users’ interaction
          with the archive, which are stored in the database. We believe that these features of
          networked computational media can be used to redesign the digital archive as a dynamic
          environment for different kinds of practice, not limited to research and teaching. A
          scholarly remediation of <title level="m">LdoD</title> according to tested principles of
          electronic philology would be part of a larger interactive environment where reading and
          writing practices around the <title level="m">Book of Disquiet</title> could be socialized
          within the digital medium itself.<note>A second stage of development of this project
            (2016–2018) will add a corpus of reception texts (reviews and essays) that will be fully
            integrated with the <title level="m">Book of Disquiet</title> fragments. This new stage
            will also develop software tools—including text editors, textual generators and other
            e-lit tools—for enabling writing interactions with the archive’s textual database. Six
            applications for mobile media, called <soCalled>Machines of Disquiet</soCalled>, are
            currently being tested.</note> Aggregation of genetic and editorial witnesses according
          to criteria defined by readers could also occur within a virtual space that allows users
          to make critical annotations and write variations based on the fragments. Thus knowledge
          of textual form and textual transmission would be complemented by experiments with writing
          processes and bibliographic structures.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="problem">
        <head>Problem: The LdoD Archive Model</head>
        <p>In this section we offer a synthesis of the four functions and three dimensions of our
          model for a virtual <title level="m">LdoD</title>, as described in Portela and Silva (<ref
            target="#portela14" type="bibl">2014</ref>). This description has been diagrammed in
            <ptr target="#figure1" type="crossref"/>. Our virtual model for <title level="m"
            >LdoD</title> establishes a framework of interactions distributed across four functions:
          reader-function, editor-function, book-function, and author-function. These functions
          contain a model of the ecosystem of literary inscriptions. With regard to facsimile
          surrogates and textual transcriptions, seen here as digital objects available for
          interaction with expert and non-expert users, we may say that the archive contains three
          related dimensions: a genetic dimension that allows users to create a narrative of
          authorial composition; a social dimension that allows users to create a narrative of
          scholarly editing and textual reception; and a virtual dimension that enables users to
          explore the possibilities of both writing and editing while interacting with the <title
            level="m">Book of Disquiet</title>.</p>
        <p>We should clarify here that <soCalled>social dimension</soCalled> is used in this article
          to refer to the socialization of texts embodied in particular textual and bibliographic
          forms in the historical archive—a notion derived from social editing theories (<ref
            target="#mcgann06" type="bibl">McGann 2006</ref>). The <soCalled>virtual
            dimension</soCalled> refers to the collaborative additions and interactive
          transformations of the archive in a web environment. Thus the <soCalled>virtual
            dimension</soCalled> should be understood as a particular expression of the
            <soCalled>social dimension</soCalled> in this constructed electronic reading, editing,
          and writing space, which can be freely used by either Pessoa experts or non-experts. The
          final relevance of each virtual edition will result from its popularity—how often it is
          accessed and used in the construction of other virtual editions. <soCalled>Social
            editing</soCalled> in the title of this article subsumes both processes of textual
          socialization, that is, our digital representation of the historical socialization of
          Pessoa’s <title level="m">LdoD</title> in a set of expert editions (<soCalled>social
            dimension</soCalled>), and our design of a digital platform for furthering textual
          collaborations (<soCalled>virtual dimension</soCalled>). The social/virtual distinction is
          pertinent from both a design and a theoretical perspective, since we need to distinguish
          the static and dynamic layers of the archive. On the other hand, we also want to emphasize
          the social nature of editing processes through a series of built-in affordances in our
          digital archive.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure1">
          <graphic url="images/72-425-1-SP.jpg" height="720px" width="540px"/>
          <head type="legend">A functional model of the <title level="m">LdoD Archive</title></head>
        </figure>
        <p>The reader-function supports a contextualized reading of the <title level="m"
            >LdoD</title> fragments. It enables readers to visualize and compare fragments and
          variations according to several authorial and editorial witnesses. The book-function
          enables the construction and reconstruction of <title level="m">LdoD</title> based on
          textual and metatextual information in the archive. The output of these flexible remakings
          of the <title level="m">LdoD</title> can be either a given form that already exists in the
          work’s archive, such as the Coelho 1982 or the Pizarro 2010 edition, or a virtual
          reorganization of the book. The editor-function, in its turn, is meant to provide
          interpretations of <title level="m">LdoD</title> as a book project based on a pre-existing
          (but variable and unstable) corpus of documents. This function allows users to produce
          textual sequences and textual aggregations according to user-defined criteria. It also
          enables users to add annotations and tags to particular passages. Finally, the
          author-function enables the extension of <title level="m">LdoD</title> with new texts
          based on original fragments from <title level="m">LdoD</title>. Thus, a reader of <title
            level="m">LdoD</title> is able to write a new text derived from fragments of <title
            level="m">LdoD</title>, becoming an author in the context of a virtual edition. These
          newly authored fragments can result both from textual remixes of the archive’s content,
          and from textual additions of user-created content.</p>
        <p>We can conclude that what is needed is <list rend="inline ordered">
            <item>a scholarly archive where experts can study and compare <title level="m"
                >LdoD</title>’s authorial witnesses with their critical editions; and</item>
            <item>a virtual archive that allows experts and non-experts to experiment with the
              production of different editions of <title level="m">LdoD</title>, by means of <list
                rend="inline ordered">
                <item>editing (aggregating, sequencing, annotating, tagging) and</item>
                <item>writing (extensions and variations based on Pessoa’s texts).</item>
              </list></item>
          </list></p>
        <p>Given the above set of goals, the <title level="m">LdoD Archive</title> has to
          accommodate scholarly standards and requirements concerning digital archives, for instance
          the use of TEI as a specification to encode literary texts, and the virtual communities
          and social software features to support the social edition of <title level="m"
            >LdoD</title> by both other experts and non-experts. This aspect implies additional
          constraints on how to coordinate the interactions within the archive. Therefore, there is
          the need for a dynamic archive where users can edit their own versions of <title level="m"
            >LdoD</title>, and write extensions of the original fragments, while the archive’s
          initial set of experts’ interpretations and analyses of <title level="m">LdoD</title> are
          kept <soCalled>unchanged</soCalled> and clearly separated from the socialized virtual
          editions and writings (<ref target="#silva13" type="bibl">Silva and Portela 2013</ref>).
          This constraint will actually shape the formulation of the solution strategy.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="solution">
        <head>Solution Strategy: A Collaborative Archive Framework</head>
        <p>To address the separation of the experts’ interpretations from the socialized virtual
          editions and writings we establish the following principles:</p>
        <list>
          <item><p>Definition of Expert and Virtual (Social) Editions,<note>Although we refer to
                expert and virtual editions, the latter may also be constructed by Pessoa experts.
                  <soCalled>Expert editions</soCalled> refers to the four printed editions published
                prior to the existence of the <title level="m">LdoD Archive</title>, and also to the
                project’s topographic transcription.</note> to explicitly separate the experts’
              interpretations, represented in expert editions, from the socializations of the book,
              represented as virtual editions;</p></item>
          <item>Coexistence and Separation of Editions, to enable users to use the experts’ editions
            to build their virtual editions without interfering with expert interpretations. This is
            achieved by imposing a set of restrictions: <list>
              <item>Virtual editions are built on top of other expert and virtual editions, and thus
                use their interpretations;</item>
              <item>Expert editions do not refer to virtual editions, in order to keep these
                experts’ interpretations separate from the virtual editions’ extensions;</item>
              <item>By default only the expert editions are presented, so as to preserve an
                  <soCalled>official</soCalled> experts’ archive, which means that users have to
                explicitly access the virtual editions. This explicit access makes them aware of the
                existence, and separation, of experts’ and socialized virtual
                interpretations.</item>
            </list>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>These principles are illustrated in <ptr target="#figure2" type="crossref"/>. In the
          center we show how the archive repository is built using three layers (the three
          aforementioned dimensions), and their recursive construction. The original set of expert
          editions (that is, our own topographic transcription and the editions by Coelho, Cunha,
          Zenith, and Pizarro) instantiate the genetic and social dimensions while virtual editions
          are built on them and on other virtual editions. As we can see, although the virtual level
          of the archive is separate from its scholarly level, the virtual dimension is built on the
          genetic and on the social dimensions. For instance, when reading takes place, it is
          necessary to show what kind of edition is being read: the project’s topographic
          transcription of an authorial document (genetic view), one of the four expert editorial
          versions that are pre-encoded in the archive (social view), or one of an open set of
          virtual editions (virtual view). Each textual unit of any virtual edition, in its turn,
          will contain the stemma of its sources, including authorial witnesses, critical editions,
          and other virtual editions.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure2">
          <graphic url="images/72-426-1-SP.jpg" width="720px" height="540px"/>
          <head type="legend">Dynamic and static aspects in the <title level="m">LdoD
              Archive</title>.</head>
        </figure>
        <p>Additionally, <ptr target="#figure2" type="crossref"/> also enriches the representation
          of the four functions in <ptr target="#figure1" type="crossref"/> by describing to what
          extent they support static and dynamic manipulations of the archive repository. In
          contrast with most digital literary archives, which are built using XSLT technology to
          transform TEI representations into HTML for visualization, and where only the reader- and
          book-functions are dynamic, in the <title level="m">LdoD Archive</title> we allow users to
          create their own editorial interpretations of the <title level="m">LdoD</title>, and
          extend <title level="m">LdoD</title> written fragments using a web interface. Therefore,
          users can dynamically change the archive repository through its virtual dimension.
          However, we still continue to support the traditional scholarly work on the genetic and
          social dimensions where the project editors do static offline TEI encoding of the <title
            level="m">LdoD</title> using their XML editor of choice.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="encoding">
        <head>TEI Encoding</head>
        <p>Because of the dynamic requirements of <title level="m">LdoD</title> project, and the
          strategy to create a collaborative archive as described above, the TEI encoding needs to
          address the three dimensions. Actually, while the description of the TEI encoding of the
          genetic and social dimensions is driven by how TEI can be used to express the authorial
          witnesses and their expert interpretations through the concept of edition, the encoding of
          the virtual dimension focuses on how the TEI encoding chosen for the genetic and social
          dimensions can be used to support the creation of a non-predefined number of virtual
          editions.</p>
        <p>In Portela and Silva (<ref target="#portela14" type="bibl">2014</ref>) we describe a UML
          (Unified Modeling Language) model for a virtual <title level="m">LdoD</title> that
          supports the project requirements. In this section we show how this model is encoded in
          TEI.</p>
        <div xml:id="genetic-social">
          <head>Genetic and Social Dimensions</head>
          <figure xml:id="figure3">
            <graphic url="images/72-427-1-SP.jpg" width="783px" height="309px"/>
            <head type="legend">Model of the genetic and social interpretations of <title level="m"
                >LdoD</title>.</head>
          </figure>
          <p><ptr target="#figure3" type="crossref"/> shows a UML model of the genetic and social
            interpretations of <title level="m">LdoD</title>. The root concept, which has a single
            instance, is <title level="m">LdoD</title>, and it contains a set of Fragment instances
            and several interpretations (<ident>FragInter</ident> instances) for each fragment.
            Interpretation is the name we give in the model to refer to a textual instance of a
            fragment according to one of the sources, authorial or editorial, thus stressing
            transcription as an interpretive act. These interpretations are encoded in TEI using the
              <gi>app</gi> element with an <gi>rdg</gi> element for each different transcription.
            There are two types of interpretations, authorial and editorial. Authorial
            interpretations, instances of <ident>SourceInter</ident>, refer to their Source
            instance, which can be a <ident>PrintedSource</ident>, <ident>Typescript</ident>, or
              <ident>Manuscript</ident>. On the other hand, editorial interpretations,
              <ident>ExpertEditionInter</ident> instances, are contained, and ordered, in the
            context of expert editions (<ident>ExpertEdition</ident> instances). Currently, the
            project is encoding four <ident>ExpertEdition</ident> instances. Finally, an
            interpretation contains several <ident>TextPortions</ident> that represent the use of
            TEI elements in the fragments’ transcriptions. <ident>TextPortions</ident> abstract
            elements which constitute the transcription with the objective of capturing their
            variations.</p>
          <p>To encode this model in TEI we use the <gi>teiCorpus</gi> element to contain all the
            fragments and aggregate in its header the entities that are common, and can be reused,
            in each of the fragments. The encoding below shows a part of the TEI Corpus header where
            the different editions are encoded inside a <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element as a list of
              <gi>bibl</gi> elements. The TEI encoding of Pessoa’s heteronyms is done within
              <gi>profileDesc</gi> and <gi>particDesc</gi> elements as a list of <gi>person</gi>
            elements with attribute <att>type</att> set to the <val>heteronyms</val> value. In the
            example, the four experts’ editions and the two heteronyms assigned by experts to the
              <title level="m">LdoD</title> are declared. <egXML
              xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <teiHeader type="corpus">
                <fileDesc>
                  <titleStmt>...</titleStmt>
                  <sourceDesc>
                    <listBibl xml:id="ED.CRIT">
                      <bibl xml:id="ED.CRIT.C">…</bibl>
                      <bibl xml:id="ED.CRIT.SC">…</bibl>
                      <bibl xml:id="ED.CRIT.Z">…</bibl>
                      <bibl xml:id="ED.CRIT.P">…</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                  </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                  <particDesc>
                    <person xml:id="FP">
                      <persName type="orthonym">…</persName>
                    </person>
                    <listPerson type="heteronyms" xml:id="HT">
                      <person xml:id="HT.BS">…</person>
                      <person xml:id="HT.VG">…</person>
                    </listPerson>
                  </particDesc>
                </profileDesc>
              </teiHeader>
            </egXML></p>
          <p>For each fragment we use a <gi>TEI</gi> element inside the global <title level="m"
              >LdoD</title>
            <gi>teiCorpus</gi> element. This <gi>TEI</gi> element contains a <tag>teiHeader
              type="text"</tag> element where the different interpretations are declared; several
              <gi>facsimile</gi> elements to declare the fragment’s facsimiles; and a <gi>text</gi>
            element which contains the interpretations’ transcriptions, represented in <ptr
              target="#figure3" type="crossref"/> by <ident>TextPortion</ident> instances. The
            encoding example below presents part of the structure of the header for a fragment
            selected for the four expert editions that has two manuscripts and one printed source.
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <teiHeader type="text">
                <fileDesc>
                  <titleStmt>…</titleStmt>
                  <publicationStmt>…</publicationStmt>
                  <sourceDesc>
                    <listBibl xml:id="Fr1.SRC">
                      <listBibl xml:id="Fr1.SRC.MS">
                        <msDesc xml:id="Fr1.SRC.MS.Fr1a">…</msDesc>
                        <msDesc xml:id="Fr1.SRC.MS.Fr1b">…</msDesc>
                      </listBibl>
                      <listBibl xml:id="Fr1.SRC.ED">
                        <bibl xml:id="Fr1.SRC.ED.Fr1c">…</bibl>
                      </listBibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <listWit xml:id="Fr1.WIT">
                      <listWit xml:id="Fr1.WIT.MS">
                        <witness xml:id="Fr1.WIT.MS.Fr1a.274">
                          <ref target="#Fr1.SRC.MS.Fr1a"/>
                        </witness>
                        <witness xml:id="Fr1.WIT.MS.Fr1b.273">
                          <ref target="#Fr1.SRC.MS.Fr1b"/>
                        </witness>
                      </listWit>
                      <listWit xml:id="Fr1.WIT.ED">
                        <listWit xml:id="Fr1.WIT.ED.ORIG">
                          <witness xml:id="Fr1.WIT.ED.ORIG.Fr1c.405">
                            <ref target="#Fr1.SRC.ED.Fr1c"/>
                            <!-- Bibliographic info about the edition -->
                          </witness>
                        </listWit>
                        <listWit xml:id="Fr1.WIT.ED.CRIT">
                          <witness xml:id="Fr1.WIT.ED.CRIT.C">
                            <ref target="#ED.CRIT.C"/>
                            <!--Info about the edition interpretation -->
                          </witness>
                          <witness xml:id="Fr1.WIT.ED.CRIT.SC">
                            <ref target="#ED.CRIT.SC"/>
                            <!--Info about the edition interpretation -->
                          </witness>
                          <witness xml:id="Fr1.WIT.ED.CRIT.Z">
                            <ref target="#ED.CRIT.Z"/>
                            <!--Info about the edition interpretation -->
                          </witness>
                          <witness xml:id="Fr1.WIT.ED.CRIT.P">
                            <ref target="#ED.CRIT.P"/>
                            <!--Info about the edition interpretation -->
                          </witness>
                        </listWit>
                      </listWit>
                    </listWit>
                  </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
              </teiHeader>
            </egXML></p>
          <p>The Source concept is implemented within the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element and the
            distinction between <ident>Manuscript</ident>, <ident>Typescript</ident>, and
              <ident>PrintedSource</ident> is indicated by convention through the structure of the
              <att>xml:id</att> attribute value. Note that <ident>Manuscript</ident> and
              <ident>Typescript</ident> are implemented within the <gi>msDesc</gi> element, while
              <ident>PrintedSource</ident> is used in the <gi>bibl</gi> element. On the other hand,
            the <ident>FragInter</ident> concept is implemented by the <gi>witness</gi> element and
            the distinction between editorial (<ident>ExpertEditionInter</ident>) and authorial
              (<ident>SourceInter</ident>) witnesses is also indicated by convention through the
            structure of the <att>xml:id</att> attribute value. A <gi>ref</gi> element is used to
            associate the witness with its source, for <ident>SourceInter</ident> witnesses, or with
            its edition, for <ident>ExpertEditionInter</ident> witnesses. The editions are declared
            in the corpus header. The editorial contextual information of the fragment (metatextual
            information) is encoded within the <gi>witness</gi> element. Finally, the
              <ident>TextPortion</ident> instances depicted in <ptr target="#figure3"
              type="crossref"/> are represented within the <gi>text</gi> element and refer to their
            respective <ident>FragInter</ident> through the <att>wit</att> attribute of <gi>rdg</gi>
            elements, which contain the witness identifier declared in the fragment
              header.<note>Although we are not, at this stage of the project, creating a critical
              apparatus for variants for these major four editions, the possibility remains open for
              such a representation in the future, if resources permit. Except for Prado Coelho,
              whose 1982 edition was not reedited (he died soon after publication), the other three
              editors have never reissued <title level="m">LdoD</title> under the exact same form.
              Every new publication becomes an occasion for revision. There are now more than
              fifteen editions that may be considered variations of those three sets. Our copyright
              agreement with the <title level="m">LdoD</title> editors is that we encode in the
              archive the most recent version at the time of work.</note> As mentioned above, an
            apparatus is used to distinguish the different readings of the fragments. The
              <gi>rdg</gi> element is useful in the context of the editions to represent variations
            in their readings of the source documents. </p>
          <p>This approach allows us to associate interpretation metadata in the context of each
            witness. Users will be able to compare digital facsimile representations of authorial
            documents (and topographic transcriptions of those documents) to editorial
            transcriptions. The latter can also be compared against each other in order to highlight
            their interpretations of the source.</p>
          <p>When a TEI-encoded file for a <title level="m">LdoD</title> fragment is uploaded to the
            system, it is parsed, and if it does not contain any errors, a new Fragment instance is
            created associated with a new instance of <ident>FragInter</ident> for each different
            transcription of the text. In addition to the verification of the TEI syntax, the parser
            does a semantic verification of the encoded fragment. For instance, it verifies the
            existence of the entities referenced by <att>xml:id</att> attributes. This supports the
            encoding work because it allows the early detection of errors.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="virtual">
          <head>Virtual Dimension</head>
          <figure xml:id="figure4">
            <graphic url="images/72-428-1-SP.jpg" width="523px" height="338px"/>
            <head type="legend">Model of the virtual interpretations of <title level="m"
                >LdoD</title>.</head>
          </figure>
          <p><ptr target="#figure4" type="crossref"/> describes how the model for the genetic and
            social interpretations is enriched to support virtual interpretations. Three new
            concepts are introduced: <ident>VirtualEdition</ident>, which represents virtual
            editions; <ident>VirtualEditionInter</ident>, which represents the interpretations of
            fragments in the context of virtual editions; and <ident>VirtualHeteronym</ident>, which
            represents the new heteronyms that end users may create.</p>
          <p>These three new concepts implement the principle of the separation of expert and
            virtual editions. To support the coexistence of expert and virtual editions, we define
            an optional association between a <ident>VirtualEdition</ident> and an
              <ident>Edition</ident> and a mandatory association between a
              <ident>VirtualEditionInter</ident> and a <ident>FragInter</ident>. The former
            association means that all the interpretations of the virtual edition use the
            interpretations of the source edition. Therefore, this association is optional at the
            edition level because we allow the creation of a virtual edition that uses
            interpretations of fragments from different source editions. The association between a
              <ident>VirtualEditionInter</ident> and a <ident>FragInter</ident> is mandatory because
            virtual interpretations of fragments should be based on an existing
            interpretation—either another virtual interpretation or an authorial or editorial
            interpretation. Ultimately, the transcriptions in a virtual interpretation are identical
            to either an authorial or an editorial transcription. Note that a virtual interpretation
            comprises one transcription, either authorial or editorial, and a set of tags and
            annotations on it.</p>
          <p>The semantics of this relationship is defined by the <att>usePolicy</att> attribute
            that can take two values: <val>import</val> and <val>inherit</val>. When the
              <val>import</val> value is used, the virtual interpretation of the fragment is built
            on top of the source interpretation and can change it. Any further change done in the
            source interpretation does not impact on the virtual interpretation. The source
            interpretation is copied, at virtual interpretation creation time, to the virtual
            interpretation context and can be freely changed by the user. When the
              <val>inherit</val> policy is used, the source interpretation is extended in the
            virtual interpretation and cannot be changed. For example, if the source interpretation
            is changed by the source community, then the changes are propagated to its virtual
            interpretations. These policies only apply to the tags and annotations associated with
            the virtual edition, because, currently, the archive does not allow any changes to the
            authorial and editorial transcriptions.</p>
          <p>The TEI encoding of the genetic and social interpretations is extended to support the
            virtual interpretations. Therefore, the virtual editions are declared in the corpus
            header as a new <gi>listBibl</gi> element containing a <gi>bibl</gi> element for each
            new virtual edition. However, the distinction between the set of critical editions and
            the set of virtual editions is done by convention through the <att>xml:id</att>
            attribute value. Virtual heteronyms are similarly declared in the corpus header. As
            regards virtual interpretations, they are encoded in the fragment header using
              <gi>witness</gi> elements and a convention based on the <att>xml:id</att> attribute
            value to distinguish them from the other editorial interpretations, namely the experts’
            interpretations. Additionally, the editorial contextual information (metatextual
            information) of the virtual fragment contains, among other information, a reference to
            the source interpretation and the fragment order in the virtual edition.</p>
          <p>Following the proposed TEI encoding we are able to implement the solution principles
            for the <title level="m">LdoD</title> project identified in <ptr target="#problem"
              type="crossref"/>. However, some of the distinctions associated with the separation
            principle, or the references between virtual interpretations and their source
            interpretations, are set by convention and require automatic tools to be aware of them.
            On the other hand, TEI does not support the encoding of some information that is
            required in a Web 2.0 application, namely access control information. For instance, we
            cannot express in TEI whether a virtual edition is private or public, and which specific
            users may access the virtual edition. We intend, as one of the final results of the
            project, to define a TEI customization that accommodates all the identified aspects that
            cannot be expressed using the TEI core.</p>
          <p>There are some other open issues. The main problem is related to the dynamic evolution
            of the archive in terms of Web 2.0 requirements: how can TEI code be changed as a result
            of users’ interactions with the archive? Note that the traditional approach to encoding
            in TEI is done statically, through tools like oXygen. However, we want to support the
            evolution of <title level="m">LdoD</title> as a continuously reeditable and rewritable
            book. This means that it is necessary to enable the dynamic addition of new virtual
            editions and heteronyms in the Corpus and the addition of new fragments that extend the
            original ones. Additionally, users can define their own interpretation of any of <title
              level="m">LdoD</title>’s fragments, for instance by using tags, which results in the
            generation of new editions of the book through the execution of a categorization
            algorithm. This open issue is addressed by the software architecture we propose in the
              <ref target="#architecture" type="crossref">next section</ref>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="architecture">
        <head>Architecture</head>
        <p>Most digital scholarly archives are static. By static we mean that the construction of
          the archive is separated from its use. The former is done using TEI and XML editors, and
          the latter is supported by XSLT transformations. This software architectural approach is
          not feasible if we want to provide Web 2.0 functionality to the archive. Since we do not
          want to disregard the existing practice of encoding in TEI by expert users, the
          architecture needs to support the traditional encoding in TEI by the experts while
          enabling dynamic user interactions with the platform, as highlighted in the static and
          dynamic aspects of <ptr target="#figure2" type="crossref"/>.</p>
        <p><ptr target="#figure5" type="crossref"/> presents a component-and-connector view of the
            <title level="m">LdoD Archive</title> software architecture using the repository and the
          client-server architectural styles. Components are depicted using UML component instances;
          connectors are represented by linking UML component ports. The port roles are labelled
          according to the architectural style that the connector implements: that is, the roles
          between the <ident>:Browser</ident> and <ident>:LdoD Application Server</ident> components
          denote the client-server architectural style.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure5">
          <graphic url="images/72-429-1-SP.jpg" width="762px" height="323px"/>
          <head type="legend"><title level="m">LdoD Archive</title> Software Architecture.</head>
        </figure>
        <p>Traditional TEI encoding, where scholars use an XML editor of choice statically, is
          represented in <ptr target="#figure5" type="crossref"/> by the interactions between
          components <ident>:TEI Editor Tool</ident> and <ident>:LdoD TEI File Repository</ident>.
          However, instead of supporting the presentation through XSLT transformation of files in
          the repository, we provide an importer component (<ident>:LdoD TEI File Importer</ident>)
          that loads the TEI-encoded files into an object-oriented database (<ident>:LdoD
            Object-Oriented Repository</ident>). This database contains the object model described
          in Portela and Silva (<ref type="bibl" target="#portela14">2014</ref>). For the support of
          Web 2.0 interactions, the <ident>:LdoD Application Server</ident> component provides a web
          client-server interface that users, experts and non-experts alike, use to interact with
          the object-oriented repository.<note>The interactions with the repository are done on top
            of the object model described in <ptr target="#figure3 #figure4" type="crossref"/>. It
            is possible to generate TEI-encoded files from the repository. On the other hand, the
            system allows tagging and annotation of transcriptions but does not allow them to be
            changed.</note> Therefore, the changes occur on the object-oriented representation of
          the TEI-encoded files. Finally, in order to preserve the TEI interchange qualities of the
          archive, the <ident>:LdoD TEI File Export</ident> component allows the regeneration of
          TEI-encoded files from the object-oriented repository. Note that this component allows the
          selection of which parts of the repository to generate and the strategy of the encoding.
          For instance, it is possible to choose only a subset of the interpretations, and decide
          between different methods for linking critical apparatus to the text. Since the dynamic
          write interactions can only occur in the context of a virtual edition, it is possible to
          export the original TEI-encoded files as they were imported, except for their formatting,
          which is not stored when files are uploaded and parsed.</p>
        <p>When comparing the software architecture in <ptr target="#figure5" type="crossref"/> with
            <ptr target="#figure2" type="crossref"/>, we see that the static aspects of the author
          and editor functions occur through the <ident>:TEI Editor Tool</ident> component and all
          the other dynamic aspects occur through the <ident>:Browser</ident> component.</p>
        <p>The key point of the proposed architecture is the use of an object domain model to
          represent the <title level="m">LdoD</title> archive. Using this approach we, at first,
          transform <title level="m">LdoD</title> encoded in TEI to the object model, and allow the
          visualization and editing of this object model through a web user interface. Additionally,
          TEI files can be regenerated from the object model. This approach has several advantages:
            <list rend="inline ordered">
            <item>the archives’ experts continue using editor tools like oXygen to do their
              work;</item>
            <item>users (experts and non-experts) can create their virtual editions and fragment
              extensions through the web user interface;</item>
            <item>the object model preserves a semantically consistent <title level="m">LdoD</title>
              archive by checking the consistency of users’ operations;</item>
            <item>interoperability (interchange) can be supported by exporting the regenerated TEI
              files;</item>
            <item>it is possible to customize the generation of TEI files.</item>
          </list></p>
        <p>This architecture is implemented by a full-fledged prototype that the <title level="m"
            >LdoD </title>encoders use on a daily basis to see the result of their static encoding.
          Additionally, we are starting to plan experiments to study how users interact with the
          repository using the dynamic Web 2.0 features. The prototype is implemented in the JAVA
          programming language, using the <ref target="http://spring.io/">Spring MVC
            framework</ref><note>Spring MVC framework: <ptr target="http://spring.io/"/>.</note> for
          server-side interaction, <ref target="http://getbootstrap.com/"
            >Bootstrap</ref><note>Bootstrap: <ptr target="http://getbootstrap.com/"/>.</note> and
            <ref target="http://jquery.com/">JQuery</ref><note>JQuery: <ptr
              target="http://jquery.com/"/>.</note> for client-side interactions, and the <ref
            target="http://fenix-framework.github.io/">Fénix Framework</ref><note>Fénix Framework:
              <ptr target="http://fenix-framework.github.io/"/>.</note> to support a transactional
          and persistent domain model.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="conclusion">
        <head>Conclusion</head>
        <p>The specific correlation of static and dynamic goals in the <title level="m">LdoD</title>
          Digital Archive means that our emphasis falls on open changes that feed back into the
          archive. The TEI encoding and software design implications of this project make us address
          both the conceptual aspects of TEI schemas for modeling texts and documents, and the
          processing problems posed by user-oriented virtualization of Pessoa’s writing and
          bibliographic imagination.</p>
        <p>In this article we have presented how to encode <title level="m">LdoD</title> editions
          and fragments using TEI,<note>A complete example of an encoded fragment is included in
              <ref target="http://jtei.revues.org/1180?file=1">appendix 1</ref>.</note> and also the
          software architecture of a Web 2.0 environment through which the encoded fragments are
          fed. These two approaches create an environment where experts and non-experts can
          collaborate in four roles: reader, book, editor, and author. The environment separates the
          different contributions while allowing certain levels of information-sharing that enhance
          collaboration and the continuous enrichment of the repository.</p>
        <p>In this phase we have already implemented a full-fledged prototype that is used on a
          daily basis by the TEI encoders. Currently we are extending the architecture and prototype
          with more affordances for the editor and author functions. Meanwhile we intend to start
          experiments with end users to assess the dynamic aspects of the environment and study how
          to foster the creation of communities around a virtual <title level="m">LdoD</title>.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="barney12"><author>Barney, Brett</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title
              level="a">Digital Editing with the TEI Yesterday, Today, and Tomorrow</title>. <title
              level="j">Textual Cultures</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">29–41</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bauman11"><author>Bauman, Syd</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title level="a"
              >Interchange vs. Interoperability</title>. In <title level="m">Proceedings of
              Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</title>. <series>Balisage Series on Markup
              Technologies</series>, vol. <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>. doi:<idno
              type="doi">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Bauman01</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="benel09"><author>Benel, Aurelien</author>, and <author>Christophe
              Lejeune</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">Humanities 2.0: Documents,
              Interpretation and Intersubjectivity in the Digital Age</title>. <title level="j"
              >International Journal of Web Based Communities</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">562–76</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1504/ijwbc.2009.028090</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="brüning13"><author>Brüning, Gerrit</author>, <author>Katrin Henzel</author>,
            and <author>Dietmar Pravida</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a">Multiple
              Encoding in Genetic Editions: The Case of <soCalled>Faust</soCalled></title>. <title
              level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Intiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4 (March)</biblScope>. <ptr target="http://jtei.revues.org/697"
            />. doi:<idno type="doi">10.4000/jtei.697</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="coelho82"><editor>Coelho, Jacinto do Prado</editor>, ed. <date>1982</date>.
              <author>Fernando Pessoa</author>, <title level="m">Livro do Desassossego</title>. 2
            vols. <pubPlace>Lisboa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Ática</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cunha90"><editor>Cunha, Teresa Sobral</editor>, ed. <date>1990–91</date>.
              <author>Fernando Pessoa</author>, <title level="m">Livro do Desassossego</title>. 2
            vols. <pubPlace>Lisboa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Relógio d’Água</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cunha08"><editor>Cunha, Teresa Sobral</editor>, ed. <date>2008</date>.
              <author>Fernando Pessoa</author>, <title level="m">Livro do Desassossego</title>.
              <pubPlace>Lisboa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Relógio d’Água</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cunha13"><editor>Cunha, Teresa Sobral</editor>, ed. <date>2013</date>.
              <author>Fernando Pessoa</author>, <title level="m">Livro do Desassossego</title>.
              <pubPlace>Lisboa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Relógio d’Água</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="earhart12"><author>Earhart, Amy E.</author>
            <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">The Digital Edition and the Digital
              Humanities</title>. <title level="j">Textual Cultures</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">18–28</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fraistat09"><author>Fraistat, Neil</author>, and <author>Steven E.
              Jones</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">Editing Environments: The
              Architecture of Electronic Texts</title>. <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic
              Computing</title> <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue"
              >1</biblScope>): <biblScope unit="page">9–18</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1093/llc/fqn032</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mcgann06"><author>McGann, Jerome</author>. <date>2006</date>. <title
              level="a">From Text to Work: Digital Tools and the Emergence of the Social
              Text</title>. <title level="j">Text</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">49–62</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="muñoz13"><author>Muñoz, Trevor</author>, <author>Raffaele
            Viglianti</author>, and <author>Neil Fraistat</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
              level="a">Texts and Documents: New Challenges for TEI Interchange and the
              Possibilities for Participatory Archives</title>. <title level="m">The Linked TEI:
              Text Encoding in the Web. Book of Abstracts. Abstracts of the TEI Conference and
              Members Meeting 2013</title>, edited by <editor>Fabio Ciotti</editor> and
              <editor>Arianna Ciula</editor>, 91–96. <pubPlace>Rome</pubPlace>: <publisher>DIGILAB
              Sapienza University</publisher> and <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://digilab2.let.uniroma1.it/teiconf2013/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/book-abstracts.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pizarro10"><editor>Pizarro, Jerónimo</editor>, ed. <date>2010</date>.
              <author>Fernando Pessoa</author>, <title level="m">Livro do Desasocego</title>. Edited
            by Jerónimo Pizarro. 2 vols. <pubPlace>Lisboa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Imprensa
              Nacional-Casa da Moeda</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pizarro13"><editor>Pizarro, Jerónimo</editor>, ed. <date>2013</date>.
              <author>Fernando Pessoa</author>, <title level="m">Livro do Desassossego</title>.
              <pubPlace>Lisboa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Tinta-da-China</publisher>.</bibl>
          <!--          MDH: Commenting this out since it's not mentioned. Authors say it's OK to do that. -->
          <!--<bibl xml:id="portela13"><author>Portela, Manuel</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a">Nenhum Problema Tem Solução: Um Arquivo Digital do Livro do Desassossego</title>. <title level="j">MatLit</title> <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>): <biblScope unit="page">9–33</biblScope>. <ptr target="http://iduc.uc.pt/index.php/matlit/article/view/1618"/>.</bibl> -->
          <bibl xml:id="portela14"><author>Portela, Manuel</author>, and <author>António Rito
              Silva</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">A Model for a Virtual
            LdoD</title>. <title level="j">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">March 2014</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1093/llc/fqu004</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="robinson13"><author>Robinson, Peter</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
              level="a">Towards a Theory of Digital Editions</title>. <title level="j"
              >Variants</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
            >105–31</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="schlitz09"><author>Schlitz, Stephanie A.</author>, and <author>Garrick S.
              Bodine</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">The TEIViewer: Facilitating the
              Transition from XML to Web Display</title>. <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic
              Computing</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">339–46</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1093/llc/fqp022</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="schmidt09"><author>Schmidt, Desmond</author>, and <author>Robert
              Colomb</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">A Data Structure for Representing
              Multi-version Texts Online</title>. <title level="j">International Journal of
              Human-Computer Studies</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">497–514</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1016/j.ijhcs.2009.02.001</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="siemens10"><author>Siemens, Ray</author>, <author>Mike Elkink</author>,
              <author>Alastair McColl</author>, <author>Karin Armstrong</author>, <author>James
              Dixon</author>, <author>Angelsea Saby</author>, <author>Brett D. Hirsch</author>,
              <author>Cara Leitch</author>, et al. <date>2010</date>. <title level="a">Underpinnings
              of the Social Edition? A Narrative, 2004–9, for the Renaissance English Knowledgebase
              (REKn) and Professional Reading Environment (PReE) Projects</title>. <title level="m"
              >Online Humanities Scholarship: The Shape of Things to Come. Proceedings of the Mellon
              Foundation Online Humanities Conference at the University of Virginia, March 26–28,
              2010</title>, edited by <editor>Jerome McGann</editor>, <editor>Andrew M.
              Stauffer</editor>, <editor>Dana Wheeles</editor>, and <editor>Michael
            Pickard</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">401–60</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Houston,
              TX</pubPlace>: <publisher>Rice University Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="silva13"><author>Silva, António Rito</author>, and <author>Manuel
              Portela</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a">Social Edition 4 <title
                level="m">The Book of Disquiet</title>: The Disquiet of Experts with Common
              Users</title>. In <title level="m">ECSCW 2013 Adjunct Proceedings: The 13th
              European Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work</title>, edited by
              <editor>Matthias Korn</editor>, <editor>Tommaso Colombino</editor>, and <editor>Myriam
              Lewkowicz</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">45–50</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Aarhus,
              Denmark</pubPlace>: <publisher>Department of Computer Science, Aarhus
              University</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://cs.au.dk/~mkorn/ECSCW_2013_Adjunct_Proceedings-web.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tei12"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2012</date>. <title
              level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>.
              <edition>Version 2.5.0</edition>. Last updated October 25. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/2.2.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tummarello05"><author>Tummarello, Giovanni</author>, <author>Christian
              Morbidoni</author>, and <author>Elena Pierazzo</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title
              level="a">Toward Textual Encoding Based on RDF</title>. In <title level="m">From
              Author to Reader: Challenges for the Digital Content Chain: Proceedings of the 9th
              ICCC International Conference on Electronic Publishing</title>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >57–63</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Leuven-Heverlee, Belgium</pubPlace>: <publisher>Peeters
              Publishing Leuven</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://elpub.scix.net/data/works/att/206elpub2005.content.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="vanhoutte06"><author>Vanhoutte, Edward</author>. <date>2006</date>. <title
              level="a">Prose Fiction and Modern Manuscripts: Limitations and Possibilities of
              Text-Encoding for Electronic Editions</title>. In <title level="m">Electronic Textual
              Editing</title>, edited by <editor>Lou Burnard</editor>, <editor>Katherine O’Brien
              O’Keeffe</editor>, and <editor>John Unsworth</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >161–80</biblScope>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Modern Language
              Association of America</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="wittern13"><author>Wittern, Christian</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
              level="a">Beyond TEI: Returning the Text to the Reader</title>. <title level="j"
              >Journal of the Text Encoding Intiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope> (March). <ptr target="http://jtei.revues.org/691"
            />. doi:<idno type="doi">10.4000/jtei.691</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="zenith98"><author>Zenith, Richard </author>, ed. [<date>1998</date>]
              <date>2012</date>. <author>Fernando Pessoa</author>, <title level="m">Livro do
              Desassossego</title>. <pubPlace>Lisboa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Assírio &amp;
              Alvim</publisher>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
