<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Manus OnLine and the Text Encoding Initiative Schema</title>
        <author>
          <name><forename>Giliola</forename>
            <surname>Barbero</surname></name>
          <affiliation>Giliola Barbero, Ph.D. in Italian literature (humanistic philology), has been
            a <roleName>lecturer in Library Sciences and IT for cultural heritage</roleName> at the
              <orgName>Università Cattolica</orgName>, Milan, since 2001, and is the technical
            coordinator of Manus OnLine.</affiliation>
          <email>giliola.barbero@unicatt.it</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name><forename>Francesca</forename>
            <surname>Trasselli</surname></name>
          <affiliation>Francesca Trasselli is <roleName>head of the Activity Area for Manuscript
              Bibliography, Research and Census</roleName> of the <orgName>Central Institute of
              Cataloguing</orgName> and a specialist in an archival approach to manuscripts. She is
            the author of <title level="m">Manoscritti della Biblioteca Sessoriana di Roma:
              segnature, inventari, cataloghi</title> (Casamari: Edizione Casamari,
            2011).</affiliation>
          <email/>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>29/12/2014</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Arianna Ciula</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Fabio Ciotti</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Martin Holmes</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="8">Selected Papers from the 2013 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Revues.org -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <tagsDecl> </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>manuscripts</term>
          <term>original handwritten letters</term>
          <term>manuscripts cataloguing</term>
          <term>bibliographical standards</term>
          <term>interchange</term>
          <term>letter cataloguing</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>The Italian Central Institute of Cataloguing (ICCU) has developed a web application to
          export manuscript descriptions from Manus OnLine (MOL), the Italian national catalogue of
          manuscripts, into TEI XML documents. As of June 2013, single descriptions can be
          downloaded from the MOL Online Public Access Catalogue (OPAC) as TEI XML documents by any
          user. The aim of the first tool is to supply manuscript descriptions to the institutions
          which produced them using MOL, because libraries and research organizations need to use
          their own data, outside the MOL project. The aim of the second service – exporting
          manuscript catalogues of entire collections as TEI XML files - is to promote exchange of
          data with other national and international projects. For these purposes, the ICCU needs a
          rich schema, not only a partial set of metadata, in order to be able to export complete
          structured manuscript descriptions. As bibliographical standards (MARC, Unimarc) cannot
          represent the entire structure of MOL descriptions adequately, ICCU adopted the TEI schema
          as an interchange standard. This paper describes solutions adopted by ICCU in encoding MOL
          contents within the TEI <gi>msDesc</gi> element and problems they encountered in
          performing this work. The encoding of information about material (<gi>material</gi>),
          number of folios and physical dimensions of manuscripts (<gi>extent</gi>) are discussed as
          well as a list of data pertaining to original letter cataloguing.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="mol">
        <head>Manus OnLine and ICCU Activity</head>
        <p>The Activity Area for Manuscript Bibliography, Research and Census (Area di attività per
          la bibliografia, la documentazione e il censimento dei manoscritti) is a branch of the
            <ref target="http://www.iccu.sbn.it/opencms/opencms/it/">Central Institute of
            Cataloguing (ICCU)</ref> belonging to the Italian Ministry of Heritage and
              Culture.<note><p>ICCU’s full name is <soCalled>Istituto centrale per il catalogo unico
                delle biblioteche italiane e per le informazioni bibliografiche</soCalled>, <ptr
                target="http://www.iccu.sbn.it/opencms/opencms/it/"/>.</p></note> The goal of this
          office is to take the census and to catalogue manuscripts held by Italian institutions:
          medieval manuscripts, early modern and modern manuscripts, literary and private papers of
          the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, and original handwritten letters.</p>
        <p>The main achievements of this office are: <list rend="bulleted">
            <item><p><ref target="http://manus.iccu.sbn.it/">Manus OnLine</ref>, the Italian
                national catalogue of manuscripts,<note><p>MOL, <ptr
                      target="http://manus.iccu.sbn.it/"/></p></note> and</p></item>
            <item><p><ref target="http://bibman.iccu.sbn.it/">BibMan</ref>, the national
                bibliography of manuscripts.<note><p>BibMan, <ptr
                      target="http://bibman.iccu.sbn.it/"/>.</p></note></p></item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>Manus OnLine (MOL) is a project managing a relational database accessible through a
          web-based application. In 2007, this was the first national web-based application devoted
          to manuscript cataloguing. Italian librarians and researchers can produce manuscript
          descriptions and publish digital images through MOL using personal computers connected
          through the Internet to the ICCU main server. Within MOL, manuscript descriptions can be
          linked to images stored in any digital repository. Moreover, cataloguers share the same
          authority list of names (<ref type="bibl" target="#maruccio10">Marcuccio 2010</ref>; <ref
            type="bibl" target="#bagnato09">Bagnato, Barbero, and Menna 2009</ref>).</p>
        <p>Since all the manuscript descriptions are stored directly in the same central repository,
          as soon as a description is marked as <soCalled>published</soCalled> by the cataloguer, it
          becomes immediately accessible and searchable through the OPAC.</p>
        <p>At the time of writing (January 2014), MOL contains about 141,000 manuscript descriptions
          from 270 different libraries and 470 cataloguers are involved in the project. The
          catalogue will be continuously updated and extended. As the Italian manuscript collections
          preserve the majority of European manuscripts, MOL contains material of outstanding
          research importance for all periods and disciplines. Greek manuscripts are catalogued as
          well, for example those belonging to the Biblioteca Trivulziana of Milan, the Biblioteca
          Riccardiana in Florence, the Biblioteca Angelica, and the Biblioteca Nazionale Centrale
          (National Central Library) in Rome. Having been created and developed by the Ministry of
          Heritage and Culture, MOL is free: cataloguers need only a username and a password to
          begin their work.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="mol-tei">
        <head>MOL and the TEI Schema: the Same Logical Model</head>
        <p>MOL and the TEI schema share a logical model which is typical of European scientific
          manuscript cataloguing practices (<ref type="bibl" target="#petrucci01">Petrucci
            2001</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#rehbein09">Rehbein, Sahle, and Schassan
          2009</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#fischer10">Fischer, Fritze, and Vogeler 2010</ref>).
          Data considered in paleographical and codicological environments, and as a consequence in
          manuscript cataloguing, are <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>the manuscript identifier;</item>
            <item>the physical description;</item>
            <item>history;</item>
            <item>the contents (texts);</item>
            <item>the bibliography; and</item>
            <item>names of people and corporations who have any responsibility for the manuscript
              curation and for texts, and names of places where manuscripts were written.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>In European manuscript cataloguing practice, the manuscript identifier—composed of the
          name of the place and library where the manuscript is preserved and by an official
          shelfmark—is necessary to define every single manuscript. This identifier is linked to a
          single physical description when the manuscript consists of one unit, or to multiple
          physical descriptions when the manuscript is composite. Each area devoted to the physical
          description is linked to one or more texts, because several texts can be copied in the
          same manuscript or part of a manuscript. Names can be linked both to the physical
          description (to represent, e.g., owners or copyists) and to texts (to represent, e.g.,
          authors or translators). This traditional conceptual data model inspired the organization
          of data storage in the MOL database in which the identifier and the physical descriptions
          are considered as two separate entities while texts and names are considered different
          types of entities. The relationship between the identifier and the physical descriptions
          in MOL is one-to-n (one-to-many); the relationship between physical descriptions and texts
          is also one-to-n. The relationship between names (which populate the MOL authority file)
          and physical descriptions and between names and texts is n-to-n.</p>
        <p>The TEI schema has the same logical structure as MOL. In fact, following the TEI P5
          Guidelines (<ref type="bibl" target="#tei13">TEI Consortium 2013</ref>: <ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/2.5.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html#msdesc">10.2
            The Manuscript Description Element</ref>), within an element <gi>msDesc</gi>
          <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>the manuscript identifier is marked with <gi>msIdentifier</gi>, which is mandatory
              in any description;</item>
            <item>the physical description is marked with <gi>physDesc</gi>—optional;</item>
            <item>history is marked with <gi>history</gi>—optional;</item>
            <item>the contents (texts) are marked with <gi>msContents</gi>—optional;</item>
            <item>the bibliography is marked with <gi>msBibl</gi> within
              <gi>additional</gi>—optional; and</item>
            <item>names can be inserted at different levels within several other elements.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>Moreover, at deep levels the TEI schema contains an almost complete set of tags devoted
          to manuscript description and cataloguing (<ref type="bibl" target="#barbero00">Barbero
            and Smaldone 2000</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#burnard01">Burnard 2001</ref>; <ref
            type="bibl" target="#milanese07">Milanese 2007</ref>). This is why on several occasions
          and with different aims the ICCU adopted the TEI schema to exchange data between different
          electronic repositories.</p>
        <p>In the past, between 2004 and 2007, when Manus was still a standalone application, the
          ICCU was able to export TEI XML files from local Manus databases, which were not
          accessible through the web, and import them into the online public catalogue (<ref
            type="bibl" target="#barbero04">Barbero 2004</ref>). In 2003, Manus was adopted by the
          European project <ref target="http://palin.iccu.sbn.it/">Rinascimento
                Virtuale</ref>,<note><p><ptr target="http://palin.iccu.sbn.it/"/></p></note> devoted
          to the digital publication of Greek palimpsests; on that occasion, the TEI schema was
          adopted to share manuscript descriptions of palimpsests among all the European partners
            (<ref type="bibl" target="#magrini05">Magrini, Pasini, and Arduini 2005</ref>). Later,
          starting in 2007, the ICCU planned and performed harvesting between the <ref
            target="http://www.cerl.org/resources/cerl_portal">CERL Portal</ref>, a meta search
          interface developed by the Consortium of European Research Libraries, and MOL: the ICCU
          exposes MOL contents on the web, providing OAI-PMH records with light TEI metadata inside,
          and CERL harvests them.<note><p><ptr target="http://www.cerl.org/resources/cerl_portal"
              /></p></note></p>
        <p>At present, the TEI schema is used in MOL with another very important aim. The ICCU wants
          to supply data to the institutions which produced them. In fact libraries and research
          organizations also need to use their own data outside MOL. For example, they need complete
          data to manage their own online public access catalogues (OPACs) or to populate their
          local digital libraries.<note><p><ptr target="http://www.manoscrittilombardia.it/"/> is an
              example of an OPAC edited by Regione Lombardia, whose contents derive from
            MOL.</p></note> Since institutions produce data on their own, they have the right to
          access all the data they produce; that is why the ICCU needs a suitably rich schema, not
          only a partial set of metadata. Bibliographical standards are not adequate for structuring
          manuscript descriptions in their entirety, because they have a quite different logical
          structure (<ref type="bibl" target="#daines12">Daines and Nimer 2012</ref>; <ref
            type="bibl" target="#barbero13">Barbero 2013</ref>).</p>
        <p>In 2012, an export application was developed to export catalogues of manuscript
          collections from MOL as TEI XML files; moreover, users can download each description from
          the OPAC in TEI format: <figure xml:id="figure1">
            <graphic url="img/image1.jpg" width="550px" height="371px"/>
            <head type="legend">The OPAC of Manus OnLine with the download button</head>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="tei-export">
        <head>TEI XML Documents Exported from MOL</head>
        <p>The aim of this paper is to discuss how the ICCU exports the contents of MOL fields into
          TEI elements to create valid XML files. An example of a TEI XML file exported from MOL is
          shown in <ptr type="crossref" target="#appendix1"/>, while a complete list of MOL fields
          and the corresponding TEI elements follows in <ptr type="crossref" target="#appendix2"
          />.</p>
        <p>According to TEI P5 Guidelines (<ref type="bibl" target="#tei13">TEI Consortium
            2013</ref>: <ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/2.5.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html">2. The TEI
            Header</ref>), at the beginning of each XML file, a <gi>teiHeader</gi> is automatically
          produced, where a title (<foreign xml:lang="it">Catalogo di manoscritti</foreign>), the
          name of the publisher (ICCU), the date of the creation of the XML file, and the name of
          the person or institution or project which is considered responsible for the intellectual
          content of the file are inserted. In the <gi>body</gi> of the TEI XML document, a
            <gi>listBibl</gi> element is nested, in which each manuscript description is encoded
          within an <gi>msDesc</gi> element. For each <gi>msDesc</gi> an <att>xml:id</att> attribute
          is create, whose value corresponds to the CNMD,<note><p>Censimento Nazionale dei
              Manoscritti—Descrizione.</p></note> the unique code number identifying each
          description published by the Italian National Census of Manuscripts.</p>
        <p>The first-child-level elements of <gi>msDesc</gi> defined by the TEI schema,
            <gi>msIdentifier</gi>, <gi>msContents</gi>, <gi>physDesc</gi>, <gi>history</gi>, and
            <gi>additional</gi>, appear whenever the MOL database contains the corresponding
          information. If a manuscript is defined as composite and its parts are described
          separately in MOL, then the TEI XML document contains as many <gi>msPart</gi> elements as
          there are codicological sections.</p>
        <p>Within these elements, many other TEI elements are used to create a deeply structured XML
          manuscript description. In several cases, during the design of the export application, it
          was clear which TEI elements had to be used in encoding MOL original information. For
          example, there is no doubt that the name of the library holding a manuscript must be
          encoded through a <gi>repository</gi> element within <gi>msIdentifier</gi>; the field
          containing the history of the manuscript, which can be very long in MOL, can be encoded in
          a <gi>summary</gi> element within the element <gi>history</gi>; the author’s name is
          inserted in the <gi>author</gi> tag within an <gi>msItem</gi>.</p>
        <p>Several specific highly formalized data have also been encoded as TEI attribute values.
          For example, the international code identifying libraries, composed of two letters
          representing a city and four numbers, is encoded as the value of the canonical
            <att>key</att> attribute within <gi>institution</gi>, because this code can associate
          each library with the records of the national database <ref
            target="http://anagrafe.iccu.sbn.it/opencms/opencms/">Anagrafe delle biblioteche
            italiane</ref>:<note><p><ptr target="http://anagrafe.iccu.sbn.it/opencms/opencms/"
            /></p></note>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <institution key="LO0020">Biblioteca comunale Laudense</institution>
          </egXML>
        </p>
        <p>The code identifying a single record inside the MOL authority file of names (composed of
            <mentioned>CNMN</mentioned> and a number) is encoded as the value of the <att>key</att>
          attribute within <gi>name</gi>: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <name key="CNMN0000014152">Alighieri, Dante</name>
          </egXML>
        </p>
        <p>The global <att>n</att> attribute has been used in <gi>msPart</gi> and <gi>msItem</gi> to
          encode the numbers of the codicological units and of the texts. These are numbers which
          are automatically recorded in MOL to order codicological parts and texts in the same
          sequence as they appear within the original codex: <egXML
            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <msItem n="01"> ... <title type="elaborato">Divina Commedia. Inferno</title> ... </msItem>
            <msItem n="02"> ... <title type="elaborato">Divina Commedia. Purgatorio</title> ... </msItem>
            <msItem n="03"> ... <title type="elaborato">Divina Commedia. Paradiso</title> ...
            </msItem>
          </egXML>
        </p>
        <p>The <att>type</att> attribute has been used on <gi>title</gi>, and four values have been
          defined to express whether the title is <soCalled>attested</soCalled> in the manuscript by
          the copyist, <soCalled>added</soCalled> by a hand different from the main copyist’s hand,
            <soCalled>elaborated</soCalled> by the cataloguer, or <soCalled>identified</soCalled> as
          a published work: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <title type="elaborato">Divina Commedia. Paradiso</title>
            <title type="presente"> Seguita la terça Comedia di Dante chiamata Paradiso et capitolo
              primo</title> ... </egXML>
        </p>
        <p>The <att>type</att> attribute is also used on <gi>incipit</gi> and <gi>explicit</gi> to
          distinguish which part of the text begins or ends with those words: the dedication letter,
          the preface, the first poem of an anthology, the main text, and any other significant part
          of the text. The ICCU also uses the <att>defective</att> attribute on the elements
            <gi>incipit</gi> and <gi>explicit</gi> to specify whether incipit or explicit belongs to
          an acephal text or if the text is lacking its end: <egXML
            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <incipit type="prefazione" defective="false"> Apuleius Plato ad cives suos Ex pluribus
              paucas vires herbarum</incipit>
            <incipit type="primoTesto" defective="false"> Herba nomine plantago a Graecis
              dicitur</incipit>
          </egXML>
        </p>
        <p>In some other cases, the XML encoding of information stored in MOL needs to be discussed,
          because different solutions can be adopted in the export process to create valid TEI
          documents. Astonishingly, this is the case in the encoding of three types of codicological
          data which are very common in manuscript descriptions: material, number of folios, and
          dimensions of the manuscripts.</p>
        <p>In fact there is no consensus on the values of the <att>material</att> attribute that can
          be used in the element <gi>supportDesc</gi>. Even if papyrus, parchment, and paper can
          absolutely be considered the most common materials, together with mixed material
          manuscript, different solutions have been chosen to express these data through the
            <att>material</att> attribute. The TEI P5 Guidelines (<ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/2.5.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/REF-ELEMENTS.html"
            >Appendix C</ref>) suggests <val>paper</val>, <val>parch</val>, and <val>mixed</val> as
          values of this attribute, but ultimately the ICCU decided to follow the important European
          cataloguing projects <title level="m"><ref target="http://www.manuscriptorium.com/"
              >Manuscriptorium</ref></title><note><p><ptr target="http://www.manuscriptorium.com/"
              /></p></note> and <title level="m"><ref target="http://www.e-codices.unifr.ch/"
              >e-Codices</ref></title><note><p><ptr target="http://www.e-codices.unifr.ch/"
            /></p></note> in using <val>chart</val> (paper), <val>perg</val>, (parchment) and
            <val>mixed</val>.</p>
        <p>In describing the number of folios, cataloguers usually need to encode the quantity of
          guard leaves bound at the beginning of the volume, of folios which constitute the volume
          proper, and of guard leaves at the end of the volume. These are three simple numbers, but
          TEI P5 Guidelines (<ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/2.5.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html#msph1ext"
            >10.7.1.2 Extent</ref>) proposes different solutions and different projects have adopted
          different encoding methods which, of course, will not help them in sharing data.</p>
        <p>The project <title level="m">Manuscriptorium</title>, which describes itself as a
            <q>European digital library of written cultural heritage</q>, uses arabic numerals
          directly within the <gi>extent</gi> element; if the codex has guard leaves, their number
          is distinguished through a <mentioned>+</mentioned> (plus sign):
            <code>&lt;extent>2+30+2&lt;/extent></code>. As all three numerals (separated by plus
          signs) are expressed only if a manuscript has guard-leaves at both the beginning and the
          end, and sometimes manuscripts have guard-leaves only at the beginning or only at the end,
          an automatic procedure cannot distinguish the semantic value of numerals expressed.</p>
        <p><title level="m">e-Codices</title>, the virtual manuscript library of Switzerland,
          encodes the quantity of folios through non-structured information within a
            <gi>measure</gi> element contained in the element <gi>extent</gi>; at the same time a
          structured version of the same information is given as value of the <att>n</att>
          attribute:
            <code><![CDATA[<extent><measure type="leavesCount" n="114 + 3">114 Bll. + 2 Vor- und 1 Nachsatzbl.</measure></extent>]]></code>.
          As <att>n</att> is a global attribute which should number the element, not express any
          number contained within the element, probably this solution is not to be recommended.</p>
        <p>As the ICCU needs to preserve the structure of the MOL data model as far as possible, and
          also the semantic distinction among initial and final guard leaves, in the export process
          the following solution has been adopted: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <extent>
              <measure type="Guardieiniziali" unit="carte">2</measure>
              <measure type="Corpo" unit="carte">30</measure>
              <measure type="Guardiefinali" unit="carte">2</measure>
            </extent>
          </egXML>
        </p>
        <p>As with material and number of folios, the size of leaves can also be marked with
          different elements following the TEI P5 Guidelines (<ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/2.5.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html#msph1ext"
            >10.7.1.2 Extent</ref>): with the elements <gi>dimensions</gi>, <gi>height</gi>, and
            <gi>width</gi>, or with the element <gi>measure</gi>. Manuscriptorium adopts the first
          solution: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <extent> ... <dimensions>
                <height>21 cm</height><width>15 cm</width>
              </dimensions>
            </extent>
          </egXML> while e-Codices uses an empty <gi>measure</gi> element and, again, an
            <att>n</att> attribute:
            <code><![CDATA[<measure type="pageDimensions" n="24.0 x 17.5 cm / 23.3 x 16.5 cm / 24 x 18 cm"/>]]></code>.
          As in MOL, several measurements can be recorded and each of them must be related to a
          folio number from which size was assessed; in the export application the following
          solution has been adopted: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <extent>
              <measure n="1" type="height" unit="mm">234</measure> x <measure n="2" type="width"
                unit="mm">123</measure>
              <locus>c. 1</locus>
            </extent>
          </egXML>
        </p>
        <p>Other problems to be discussed are due to MOL contents and data structure. First, each
          cataloguing area, for example those devoted to material, date, number of folios, and many
          others, contains a generic field called <soCalled>Note</soCalled>, where cataloguers can
          register annotations in prose about that area. The ICCU decided not to encode all the MOL
            <soCalled>Note</soCalled> fields in XML with the same <gi>note</gi> element, without
          introducing any distinction, and tried to distinguish the original MOL field represented
          in each <gi>note</gi> element. For this reason each <gi>note</gi> uses the <att>n</att>
          attribute to number the element and the <att>type</att> attribute to encode the subject of
          the original <soCalled>Note</soCalled> field. For example, annotations about the first
          area of MOL, devoted to the identification of the manuscript, are marked as <tag>note
            n="1" type="sez01"</tag>, while annotations about the second area, devoted to the form
          of the manuscript, are marked as <tag>note n="2" type="sez02"</tag>.</p>
        <p>The <gi>note</gi> element with <att>n</att> and <att>type</att> attributes is also used
          to encode those contents which have an appropriate field in MOL but do not have an
          appropriate tag in the TEI schema. For example, in MOL there is a specific area devoted to
          the description of palimpsest folios, which is not considered in the TEI P5 Guidelines; in
          the TEI XML document, this information is encoded through a <gi>note</gi> element with
            <val>palimpsest</val> as the value of <att>type</att>: <tag>note n="3"
            type="palinsesto"</tag>. A similar solution has been adopted by the ICCU to encode data
          about many other subjects: description of missing folios (<tag>note n="9"
            type="mancanze"</tag>), fragments of manuscripts (<tag>note n="10"
            type="frammenti"</tag>), folios derived from printed books (<tag>note n="11"
            type="partistampa"</tag>), pricking (<tag>note n="14" type="foratura"</tag>), ruling
            (<tag>note n="15" type="rigatura"</tag>),<note><p>According to the TEI schema, pricking
              and ruling can be encoded in <gi>layout</gi> together with other information. As the
              MOL project needs to encode pricking, ruling, lines, columns, and justification
              separately, specific notes were inserted in <gi>layoutDesc</gi> and
            <gi>p</gi>.</p></note> ruled frame (<tag>note n="16" type="specchiorigato"</tag>), lines
            (<tag>note n="17" type="righe"</tag>), columns (<tag>note n="18"
            type="disposizionetesto"</tag>),<note><p>According to the TEI schema, lines and columns
              can be described through numbers (<ident>data.count</ident>) using the attributes
                <att>columns</att>, <att>ruledLines</att>, and <att>writtenLines</att> of
                <gi>layout</gi>; the MOL project cannot use such markup because these data can also
              be represented in MOL through prose, not only through numbers.</p></note> and ink
            (<tag>note n="20" type="inchiostro"</tag>). However, even if these data can be encoded
          in a TEI XML document by creating specific combinations of a generic <gi>note</gi> element
          with specific attribute values, at least for the data that are commonly recorded in
          manuscript cataloguing practice (for example pricking, ruling, and ink), the ICCU would
          recommend the introduction in the TEI schema of new specific elements.</p>
        <p>Other codicological data pertaining to manuscript decoration, music notation, and
          binding, which are analytically recorded in several MOL fields and are expressed through a
          specialized lexicon, are exported in TEI XML files within a generic <gi>term</gi> element.
          As with our use of the <gi>note</gi> element, this encoding also uses <att>n</att> and
            <att>type</att> attributes to mark data derived from different MOL fields and to express
          in this way the specific semantic area of each <gi>term</gi>. For example, a cataloguer
          can point out the presence of neumes in a manuscript by putting a flag
            (<mentioned>yes</mentioned> in the database) in the MOL field <soCalled>Neumatic
            notation</soCalled>; such information is exported in the TEI XML document as
            <code><![CDATA[<term n="4" type="notazione">neumatica</term>]]></code>. The presence of
          clasps can be recorded by putting a flag in the MOL field <soCalled>Clasps</soCalled>,
          which causes an element <code><![CDATA[<term n="14">fermagli</term>]]></code> to be
          created in the TEI XML document.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="letters">
        <head>Letters</head>
        <p>The Italian standard for manuscripts adopted by MOL also includes original letters. The
          information about original letters in MOL consists of the following fields related to the
          physical description: <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>type of letter (letter, postcard, picture postcard, business card…),</item>
            <item>presence of envelope,</item>
            <item>presence of typescript part,</item>
            <item>presence of a printed letterhead,</item>
            <item>presence of original signature,</item>
            <item>presence of manuscript notes.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>Such data should be encoded in a <gi>physDesc</gi>, but at present, there are no TEI
          elements which could be used for this purpose.</p>
        <p>The information about the text of original letters recorded in MOL consists of <list
            rend="bulleted">
            <item>folios,</item>
            <item>name of sender,</item>
            <item>name of addressee,</item>
            <item>stage of the text (draft, original, copy),</item>
            <item>place,</item>
            <item>date,</item>
            <item>summary.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>Such data should be encoded through an <gi>msItem</gi> within <gi>msContents</gi>. The
          number of folios can be marked with <gi>locus</gi>; the sender can be encoded as an
            <gi>author</gi> and the addressee as a name with a specific <gi>respStmt</gi>; but at
          present the ICCU does not know which elements could be used for other fields. Close
          collaboration among different projects and the TEI Consortium would be essential in order
          to develop an encoding system for original letters compatible with TEI <gi>msDesc</gi>
          encoding; for example a new set of tags to be used in the header of correspondence
          editions could be studied in collaboration by the <ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/SIG/Manuscript/index.xml">TEI Manuscripts
            SIG</ref><note><p><ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/SIG/Manuscript/index.xml"
              /></p></note> and the <ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/SIG/Correspondence/">TEI Correspondence
            SIG</ref>.<note><p><ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/SIG/Correspondence/"
              /></p></note></p>
        <p>Discussing the solutions found by the ICCU with the TEI Consortium could help not only to
          verify the encoding developed by the ICCU, but also to spread the use of this standard to
          meet the needs of European manuscript cataloguing.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix1">
        <head>A TEI XML File Exported from Manus OnLine</head>
        <p><ref target="http://jtei.revues.org/1068?file=1"
            >Milano_Archivio_storico_civico_e_Biblioteca_Trivulziana_Trivulziano_Triv_80.xml</ref></p>
      </div>
      <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix2">
        <head>Manus Online / <gi>msDesc</gi> mapping</head>
        <p><ref target="http://jtei.revues.org/1069?file=1">Mapping.xls</ref></p>
      </div>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bagnato09"><author>Bagnato, Gian Paolo</author>, <author>Giliola
              Barbero</author>, and <author>Massimo Menna</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title
              level="a">ManusOnLine: un’applicazione web per il patrimonio manoscritto</title>. In
              <title level="m">Convegno AICA 2009</title>. <ptr
              target="http://manus.iccu.sbn.it/AICA2009_Menna.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="barbero00"><author>Barbero, Giliola</author>, and <author>Stefania
              Smaldone</author>. <date>2000</date>. <title level="a">Il linguaggio SGML/XML e la
              descrizione di manoscritti</title>. <title level="j">Bollettino AIB</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>)
              (<date>June</date>): <biblScope unit="page">159–79</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="barbero04"><author>Barbero, Giliola</author>. <date>2004</date>. <title
              level="a">Archivi elettronici dei manoscritti delle biblioteche d’Italia</title>.
              <title level="j">Biblioteche Oggi</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>)
              (<date>March</date>): <biblScope unit="page">90–91</biblScope>. Accessed January 1
            2014. <ptr target="http://www.bibliotecheoggi.it/2004/20040209001.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="barbero13"><author>Barbero, Giliola</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
              level="a">Manoscritti e standard</title>. <title level="j">DigItalia</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">43–65</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="http://digitalia.sbn.it/article/view/824"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burnard01"><editor>Burnard, Lou</editor>, ed. <date>2001</date>. <title
              level="u">Reference Manual for the MASTER Document Type Definition</title>. Discussion
            Draft. Revised Jan. 6, 2001. <ptr
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/About/Archive_new/Master/Reference/oldindex.html"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="daines12"><author>Daines, J. Gordon</author>, and <author>Cory L.
              Nimer</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">U. S. Descriptive Standards for
              Archives, Historical Manuscripts, and Rare Books</title>. In <title level="m">IFLA
              World Library and Information Congress. 78th IFLA General Conference and Assembly,
              11–17 August 2012, Helsinki, Finland</title>. Accessed January 1 2014. <ptr
              target="http://conference.ifla.org/past/2012/212-danies-en.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fischer10"><editor>Franz Fischer</editor>, <editor>Christiane
              Fritze</editor>, and <editor>Georg Vogeler</editor>, eds. <date>2010</date>. <title
              level="m">Kodikologie und Paläographie im digitalen Zeitalter 2 (Codicology and
              Palaeography in the Digital Age 2)</title>. <pubPlace>Norderstedt</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Books on Demand</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="magrini05"><author>Magrini, Sabina</author>, <author>Cesare Pasini</author>,
            and <author>Franca Arduini</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title level="a">L’Italia e
              Rinascimento virtuale</title>. <title level="j">Biblioteche Oggi</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>)
              (<date>May</date>): <biblScope unit="page">23–33</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="http://www.bibliotecheoggi.it/2005/20050402301.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="maruccio10"><author>Marcuccio, Roberto</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title
              level="a">Catalogare e fare ricerca con Manus Online</title>. <title level="j"
              >Biblioteche Oggi</title> (<date>July–August</date>): <biblScope unit="page"
              >33–49</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="http://manus.iccu.sbn.it/BibliotecheOggi_Marcuccio2010.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="milanese07"><author>Milanese, Guido</author>. <date>2007</date>. <title
              level="a">XML e lo studio dei manoscritti. Linee di orientamento e un esempio di
              applicazione.</title> In <title level="m">From Manuscript to Digital Text:Problems of
              Interpretation and Markup. Proceedings of the Colloquium (Bologna, June 12,
              2003)</title>, edited by <editor>Francesco Citti</editor> and <editor>Tommaso Del
              Vecchio</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">71–91</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Rome</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Herder</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="petrucci01"><author>Petrucci, Armando</author>. <date>2001</date>. <title
              level="m">La descrizione del manoscritto: Storia, problemi, modelli</title>.
              <pubPlace>Rome</pubPlace>: <publisher>Carocci</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rehbein09"><editor>Rehbein, Malte</editor>, <editor>Patrick Sahle</editor>,
            and <editor>Torsten Schassan</editor>, eds. <date>2009</date>. <title level="m"
              >Kodikologie und Paläographie im digitalen Zeitalter (Codicology and Palaeography in
              the Digital Age)</title>. <pubPlace>Norderstedt</pubPlace>: <publisher>Books on
              Demand</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tei13"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2013</date>. <title
              level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>.
              <edition>Version 2.5.0</edition>. Last updated July 26. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/2.5.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
