<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- [RvdB] general remarks:
  -are the escaped XPath characters in the URL identifiers intentional? Wouldn't it be nicer to use unescaped XPath characters: "http://data.perseus.org/citations/urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0008.tlg001.perseus-grc1:3.6@0Ἴστρος[1]-συκοφάνται[1]"
   instead of
"http://data.perseus.org/citations/urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0008.tlg001.perseus-grc1:3.6%40Ἴστρος%5B1%5D-συκοφάνται%5B1%5D"
-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Linked Fragment: TEI and the Encoding of Text Reuses of Lost
          Authors</title>
        <author>
          <name><forename>Monica</forename>
            <surname>Berti</surname></name>
          <affiliation>Monica Berti is <roleName>Assistant Professor at the Humboldt Chair of
              Digital Humanities</roleName> at the <orgName>University of Leipzig</orgName>, where
            she teaches courses on digital philology. Since 2008 she has been working with the
            Perseus Digital Library at <orgName>Tufts University</orgName>, where she has been
              <roleName>visiting professor in the Department of Classics</roleName>. Her current
            research work is focused on representing quotations and text reuses of ancient lost
            works.</affiliation>
          <email>monica.berti@uni-leipzig.de</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name><forename>Bridget</forename>
            <surname>Almas</surname></name>
          <affiliation>Bridget Almas is the <roleName>lead software developer for the Perseus
              Digital Library</roleName> at <orgName>Tufts University</orgName>. She has been
            working in software development since 1994, and for Perseus since 2010. She also
            currently serves as a member of the Technical Advisory Board of the Research Data
            Alliance.</affiliation>
          <email>bridget.almas@tufts.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name><forename>David</forename>
            <surname>Dubin</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>David Dubin is a <roleName>research associate professor</roleName> at the
              <orgName>University of Illinois</orgName> Graduate School of Library and Information
            Science. His research areas are the foundations of information representation and
            description, and issues of expression and encoding in documents and digital information
            resources.</affiliation>
          <email>ddubin@illinois.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name><forename>Greta</forename>
            <surname>Franzini</surname></name>
          <affiliation>Greta Franzini completed her Classics BA and Digital Humanities MA degrees at
            King’s College London. Greta is currently doing a PhD at the UCL Centre for Digital
            Humanities, where she conducts research in the fields of Classical Philology, Manuscript
            Studies and Literary Criticism. She is also currently working as a
              <roleName>Researcher</roleName> at the <orgName>Göttingen Centre for Digital
              Humanities</orgName>. Previously, she worked as a Research Associate at the Humboldt
            Chair of Digital Humanities at the University of Leipzig.</affiliation>
          <email>gfranzini@gcdh.de</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name><forename>Simona</forename>
            <surname>Stoyanova</surname></name>
          <affiliation>Simona Stoyanova is a classicist who specializes in epigraphy, and a digital
            humanist. She works as a <roleName>research associate for the Open Philology
              Project</roleName> at the <orgName>University of Leipzig</orgName>. She is also a PhD
            candidate in Digital Classics at King’s College London. Her research is focused on the
            Greek and Latin epigraphic traditions in the mixed-language population of the province
            of Thrace, with particular interest on palaeographical issues and their possible
            investigation through the DigiPal framework.</affiliation>
          <email>simona.stoyanova@informatik.uni-leipzig.de</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name><forename>Gregory R.</forename>
            <surname>Crane</surname></name>
          <affiliation>Gregory R. Crane is the <roleName>editor-in-chief of the Perseus
              Project</roleName> at <orgName>Tufts University</orgName>, where he is
              <roleName>professor of Classics</roleName> and holds the Winnick Family Chair of
            Technology and Entrepreneurship. He is also <roleName>Alexander von Humboldt Professor
              of Digital Humanities</roleName> at the <orgName>University of
            Leipzig</orgName>.</affiliation>
          <email>gregory.crane@tufts.edu</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>09/06/2015</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Arianna Ciula</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Fabio Ciotti</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Martin Holmes</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="8">Selected Papers from the 2013 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Revues.org -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>fragmentary text</term>
          <term>digital edition</term>
          <term>Classics</term>
          <term>CTS</term>
          <term>SAM</term>
          <term>PROV</term>
          <term>EpiDoc</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>This paper presents a joint project of the Humboldt Chair of Digital Humanities at the
          University of Leipzig, the Perseus Digital Library at Tufts University, and the Harvard
          Center for Hellenic Studies to produce a new open series of Greek and Latin fragmentary
          authors. Such authors are lost and their works are preserved only thanks to quotations and
          text reuses in later texts. The project is undertaking two tasks: <list
            rend="inline ordered">
            <item>the digitization of paper editions of fragmentary works with links to the source
              texts from which the fragments have been extracted;</item>
            <item>the production of born-digital editions of fragmentary works</item>
          </list>. The ultimate goals are the creation of open, linked, machine-actionable texts for
          the study and advancement of the field of Classical textual fragmentary heritage and the
          development of a collaborative environment for crowdsourced annotations. These goals are
          being achieved by implementing the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R1"
            target="#perseidsplatform"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R1">Perseids Platform</rs> and by
          encoding the <title level="m">Fragmenta Historicorum Graecorum</title>, one of the most
          important and comprehensive collections of fragmentary authors.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="intro">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>This paper presents the research work of the Humboldt Chair of Digital Humanities at the
          University of Leipzig to establish a new <ref
            target="http://www.dh.uni-leipzig.de/wo/projects/open-greek-and-latin-project/the-leipzig-open-fragmentary-texts-series-lofts/"
            >Leipzig Open Fragmentary Texts Series</ref> (LOFTS).<note><ptr
              target="http://www.dh.uni-leipzig.de/wo/projects/open-greek-and-latin-project/the-leipzig-open-fragmentary-texts-series-lofts/"
            />.</note> The project is developed in conjunction with the Perseus Digital Library at
          Tufts University and the Harvard University Center for Hellenic Studies. LOFTS produces
          open editions of ancient classical works that survive through quotations and text reuses
          in later texts (i.e., textual fragments). These fragments include many formats that range
          from quotations to allusions and translations, which are only a shadowy image of the
          original depending on their distance from a literal citation (for a definition of
          fragmentary texts, see <ref type="bibl" target="#berti12">Berti 2012</ref> and <ref
            type="bibl" target="#berti13">Berti 2013</ref>). Generations of scholars have looked for
          information about lost authors and have created huge print collections of fragmentary
          works that cover almost every literary genre in prose and verse, allowing for the
          rediscovery of authors otherwise lost and forgotten (<ref type="bibl" target="#most97"
            >Most 1997</ref>). As far as Greek literature from the eighth century BCE to the third
          century CE is concerned, we know that the works of about sixty percent of known authors
          are preserved only in textual fragments, thus showing the importance of this form of
          evidence (<ref type="bibl" target="#berti09">Berti et al. 2009</ref>).</p>
        <p>Print editions of fragmentary works are indexed collections of excerpts extracted from
          their contexts and from the textual data about those contexts. Editions of fragmentary
          works are fundamentally hypertexts and the goal of this project is to produce a dynamic
          infrastructure for a full representation of the complex relationships between sources,
          quotations, and annotations about them. In a digital edition, fragments are linked
          directly to the source text from which they are drawn and can be accurately aligned to
          multiple editions (<ref type="bibl" target="#berti09">Berti et al. 2009</ref>).
          Accordingly, digital fragments are contextualized annotations about reused authors and
          works. As new versions of, or scholarship on, the source texts emerge in a standard,
          machine-actionable form, these new findings are automatically linked to the digital
          fragments. Such a representation allows us to go beyond the limits of print collections of
          fragmentary authors, where quotations and text reuses are snippets of text completely
          isolated from their original context. Fragmentary texts also include quotations and reuses
          of surviving sources (e.g., Herodotus quoted by Athenaeus). In these cases it is possible
          to compare the original text with its reuses and, therefore, to produce different textual
          alignments that help scholars to infer the quotation habits of ancient authors.</p>
        <p>The first step for rethinking the significance of text reuses of lost works is to
          represent them inside their preserving context. This entails the selection of the string
          of words that belong to the portion of text classifiable as reuse and to encode all those
          elements that signal the presence of the text reuse itself (i.e., named entities such as
          the onomastics of reused authors, titles of reused works and descriptions of their
          content, <term>verba dicendi</term>, syntax, etc.). The second step is to encode all the
          information pertaining to other sources that reuse the same original text with different
          words or a different syntax (witnesses), or that deal with the same topic of the text
          reuse (parallel texts), as well as alternative editions and translations of both the
          source and the derived texts (<ref type="bibl" target="#almas13b">Almas and Berti
            2013</ref>).</p>
        <p>LOFTS has two main objectives: <list rend="inline ordered">
            <item>to digitize paper editions of fragmentary works and link them to source texts,
              and</item>
            <item>to produce born-digital editions of fragmentary works</item>
          </list>. In order to achieve these goals, LOFTS is implementing a <ptr type="software"
            xml:id="R2" target="#fragmentarytextseditor"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R2">Fragmentary
            Texts Editor</rs> within the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R3" target="#perseidsplatform"
            /><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R3">Perseids Platform</rs><note>For a prototype interface,
            see <rs type="soft.url" ref="#R2"><ptr target="http://perseids.org/sites/berti_demo/"
              /></rs>.</note> (<rs type="soft.bib.ref" ref="#R2"><ref type="bibl" target="#almas13b"
              >Almas and Berti 2013</ref></rs>) and is producing a digital edition of the <title
            level="m">Fragmenta Historicorum Graecorum</title> edited by Karl Müller in the
          nineteenth century (<ref type="bibl" target="#müller85">Müller 1878–85</ref>; DFHG
            Project).<note>On this project, see below, <ptr type="crossref" target="#DFHG"/>.</note>
          Alongside the DFHG project, LOFTS is working on two other subprojects: <list
            rend="inline ordered">
            <item>the <ref
                target="http://www.dh.uni-leipzig.de/wo/projects/open-greek-and-latin-project/digital-athenaeus/"
                >Digital Athenaeus</ref>, whose goal is to produce a digital edition of the <title
                level="m">Deipnosophists</title>, with a complete survey of quotations of both lost
              and surviving sources preserved by Athenaeus of Naucratis;<note>Digital Athenaeus,
                Universität Leipzig, <ptr
                  target="http://www.dh.uni-leipzig.de/wo/projects/open-greek-and-latin-project/digital-athenaeus/"
                />.</note> and</item>
            <item>the <ref
                target="http://www.dh.uni-leipzig.de/wo/projects/open-greek-and-latin-project/digital-marmor-parium/"
                >Digital Marmor Parium</ref>, which seeks to create a digital edition of the
              so-called Parian Marble, a Hellenistic chronicle on marble from the Greek island of
                Paros<note>Digital Marmor Parium, Universität Leipzig, <ptr
                  target="http://www.dh.uni-leipzig.de/wo/projects/open-greek-and-latin-project/digital-marmor-parium/"
                />.</note></item>
          </list>. The latter is the work of a fragmentary author whose name is lost and the project
          serves as a test case to build a model that works with both fragmentary texts and physical
          fragments of ancient works such as inscriptions and papyri (<ref type="bibl"
            target="#berti14">Berti and Stoyanova 2014</ref>).</p>
        <!-- HIER WEITER: -->
        <p>The present paper is divided into two parts. The first part (<ptr type="crossref"
            target="#perseids"/>) describes the implementation of a fragmentary texts editor within
          Perseids, the editorial platform developed by the Perseus Project for collaborative
          annotation of classical source documents. Perseids facilitates the annotation of text
          reuses, the production of syntactic annotations, the alignment of multiple texts, and the
          production of digital commentaries on fragmentary works. This section also elaborates on
          the complex nature of fragmentary texts and how different technologies need to be combined
          to reach our goals.</p>
        <p>The second part (<ptr type="crossref" target="#DFHG"/>) describes the Digital Fragmenta
          Historicorum Graecorum, a synergetic effort which is currently encoding print collections
          of fragmentary texts and creating a directory of fragmentary authors which feeds into the
          Perseus catalog.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="perseids">
        <head>Perseids Platform</head>
        <p>The <ref target="http://perseids.org/">Perseids Platform</ref> supports collaborative
          editing, annotation, and publication of born-digital editions of source documents in the
              classics.<note><ptr target="http://perseids.org/"/>.</note> Perseids is not one single
          application but an integrated environment built from a loose coupling of heterogeneous
          tools and services from a variety of sources. The development of the Perseids platform was
          inspired and motivated by the work of several pre-existing projects: the <ref
            target="http://www.library.tufts.edu/tisch/ematlocalstorage/miscellany_collection/home.html"
            >Tufts Miscellany Collection</ref> at Tufts University,<note><ptr
              target="http://www.library.tufts.edu/tisch/ematlocalstorage/miscellany_collection/home.html"
            />.</note> the <ref target="http://www.homermultitext.org/">Homer Multitext
            Project</ref> at the Harvard’s Center for Hellenic Studies,<note><ptr
              target="http://www.homermultitext.org/"/>.</note> and the <ref
            target="http://www.papyri.info/">Papyri.info</ref> project<note><ptr
              target="http://www.papyri.info/"/>.</note> (<ref type="bibl" target="#almas13">Almas
            and Beaulieu 2013</ref>). The Son of SUDA Online (SoSOL) application sits at the core of
          the Perseids platform. SoSOL is a <ref target="http://rubyonrails.org/">Ruby on
            Rails</ref><note><ptr target="http://rubyonrails.org/"/>.</note> application, originally
          developed by the Papyri.info project, that serves as front end for a <ref
            target="http://git-scm.com/">Git</ref><note><ptr target="http://git-scm.com/"/>.</note>
          repository of documents, metadata, and annotations. It includes a workflow engine that
          enables documents and data of different types to pass through flexible review and approval
          processes. The SoSOL application includes user interfaces for editing XML documents,
          metadata, and annotations. While it does not include a full-featured XML editor, it
          supports alternative text-based input of XML markup, and can enforce XML schema validation
          rules on the documents being edited.</p>
        <p>A key goal behind the initial development of the platform was to enable original
          undergraduate research in the field of Classics.<note>This work was supported by grants
            from Tufts University, the National Endowment for the Humanities (grant
              <idno>HD-51548-12</idno>), and the Institute from Museum and Library Services. Funding
            from the Mellon Foundation is now allowing us to expand the platform to support
            classroom-based collaboration on digital editions, beginning-to-end scholarly workflows,
            and the development of dynamic syllabi using the resources managed by the
            platform.</note> The workflows related to the encoding of text reuses and lost authors
          represent core use cases for the current phase of work on the platform (<ref type="bibl"
            target="#almas13b">Almas and Berti 2013</ref>).<note>For the prototype functionality
            used by students of the Digital Philology course at the University of Leipzig in the
            fall of 2013, see <ptr
              target="http://sites.tufts.edu/perseids/workflows/fragmentary-author-workflows/fragmentary-text-prototype-fall-2013/"
            />.</note> In developing features of the Perseids Platform to support these workflows,
          we are focusing first and foremost on the data. We expect that techniques for visually
          representing digital editions will change rapidly with technology. So, while our work
          includes prototype representations of digital editions suitable for publication on the
          web, our first priority is to enable scholars to create data about the authors, texts and
          related commentaries, annotations, links, and translations in a way that encourages and
          facilitates their preservation and reuse. We have identified the following core
          requirements to meet this goal: <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>The ability to represent the texts themselves, links between them, and annotations
              and commentaries on them, in semantically and structurally meaningful ways that adhere
              to well-accepted and documented standard formats.</item>
            <item>Stable and resolvable identifiers for all relevant data points, including: <list
                rend="bulleted">
                <item>the lost authors and their works</item>
                <item>the authors and extant texts that preserve quotations and text reuses of the
                  lost works</item>
                <item>different editions and translations of the lost and extant texts</item>
                <item>named entities (e.g., persons, places, and events) mentioned within the
                  texts</item>
                <item>commentaries and annotations on the texts, from ancient times through the
                  present</item>
              </list>
            </item>
            <item>The ability to group any of the data points into collections representing
              different contextual views of the data.</item>
            <item>The ability to accurately represent provenance information for data and
              workflows.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <div xml:id="dataformats">
          <head>Data Formats</head>
          <div xml:id="texts">
            <head>Texts</head>
            <p>We use TEI encoding to represent the source texts and textual fragments preserved
              within them.<note>The texts will adhere to the EpiDoc subset of the TEI standard, as
                discussed further below.</note> TEI provides the markup syntax and vocabulary needed
              to produce XML that enables citable passages of text to be unambiguously identified
              and linked to <emph>within their preserving context</emph>, a key requirement of the
              representation of text reuses as discussed above. For example, the following excerpt
              from Athenaeus’ <title level="m">Deipnosophists</title> 3.6 uses the TEI <gi>div</gi>
              element to demarcate the book and chapter: <egXML
                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="3"> ... <div type="textpart"
                    subtype="chapter" n="6">
                    <p> ...Ἴστρος δ᾽ ἐν τοῖς Ἀττικοῖς οὐδ᾽ ἐξάγεσθαί φησι τῆς Ἀττικῆς τὰς ἀπ᾽ αὐτῶν
                      γινομένας ἰσχάδας, ἵνα μόνοι ἀπολαύοιεν οἱ κατοικοῦντες: καὶ ἐπεὶ πολλοὶ
                      ἐνεφανίζοντο διακλέπτοντες, οἱ τούτους μηνύοντες τοῖς δικασταῖς ἐκλήθησαν τότε
                      πρῶτον συκοφάνται. ... </p>
                  </div>
                </div>
              </egXML>
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="identifiers">
            <head>Identifiers</head>
            <p>The CITE Architecture developed by the <ref
                target="http://www.homermultitext.org/hmt-doc/cite/index.html">Homer Multitext
                Project</ref><note>Documentation: <ptr
                  target="http://www.homermultitext.org/hmt-doc/cite/index.html"/>.</note> provides
              us with a standard identifier syntax for texts, passages, and related objects and with
              APIs for services which can retrieve objects identified via these protocols. CITE
              defines Canonical Text Services (CTS) URNs for creating semantically meaningful unique
              identifiers for texts and passages within texts. CITE also defines an alternate URN
              syntax for data objects that are not citable text notes, such as images, annotations,
              and the lost texts themselves. As URNs, these identifiers are not web-resolvable on
              their own. By combining them with a URL prefix and deploying CTS and CITE services to
              serve the identified resources at those addresses, we have resolvable, stable
              identifiers for our texts, data objects, and annotations (<ref type="bibl"
                target="#smith12">Smith and Blackwell 2012</ref>). One of our key motivations for
              using CTS URNs is that they give us a robust means of targeting annotations at
              specific substrings of text within a canonical work. The pointers to the text are
              specific to the location of these strings within their canonical citation structure,
              and not to the XML markup of any particular digital edition of the text. Further, the
              URN syntax degrades gracefully to allow us to reference either the notional work or a
              very specific edition of that work. Our goal in using this syntax, together with RDF
              and stand-off markup techniques as discussed below, is to enable the assertions we are
              making to stand on their own as data, independent of the encoding techniques used to
              digitize the text.</p>
            <p>For example, the following set of identifiers might be used to represent a reuse of a
              lost work of Istros at book 3, chapter 6 in Athenaeus’ <title level="m"
                >Deipnosophists</title> (<ref type="bibl" target="#almas13b">Almas and Berti
                2013</ref>):
                <eg>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0008.tlg001.perseus-grc1:3.6@Ἴστρος%5B1%5D-συκοφάνται%5B1%5D</eg>
            </p>
            <p>This is a CTS URN for a subset of passage <ident>3.6</ident> in the
                <ident>perseus-grc1</ident> edition of the work identified by <ident>tlg001</ident>
              in the group of texts associated with Athenaeus, identified by <ident>tlg0008</ident>.
              The URN further specifies a string of text in that passage, starting at the first
              instance of the word <mentioned>Ἴστρος</mentioned> and ending at the first instance of
              the word <mentioned>συκοφάνται</mentioned>.</p>
            <p>
              <eg>urn:cite:perseus:lci.2</eg> is a CITE URN identifier for the instance of lost text
              being reused. This URN identifies an object whose name <ident>2</ident> is unique
              within the Perseus Collection of Lost Content Items (<ident>lci</ident>). Every item
              in this collection points to a specific text reuse of a lost author as it is
              represented in a modern edition (see below for further discussion of CITE
              Collections).</p>
            <p>These URNs represent distinct technology-independent identifiers for the two cited
              objects, and by prefixing them with the <ident>http://data.perseus.org</ident> URL
              prefix (representing the web address at which they can be resolved) we create stable
              web identifiers for them, making them compatible with linked data best
                  practices:<note><title level="a">Perseus Stable URIs</title>, Perseus Digital
                Library Updates, <ptr
                  target="http://sites.tufts.edu/perseusupdates/beta-features/perseus-stable-uris/"
                />.</note>
              <list rend="simple">
                <item><code>http://data.perseus.org/citations/urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0008.tlg001.perseus-grc1:3.6%40Ἴστρος%5B1%5D-συκοφάνται%5B1%5D</code><note>At
                    the time of this writing, complete implementation of the CTS standard for
                    resolution of passage subreferences at the <ident>data.perseus.org</ident>
                    address is still pending.</note></item>
                <item><code>http://data.perseus.org/collections/urn:cite:perseus:lci.2</code></item>
              </list>
            </p>
            <p>The RDF data model also gives us more precision than XML with respect to targets of
              annotations and subjects of assertions. A human reader can usually tell from context
              whether an assertion concerns the wording of a sentence, the writing of a sentence as
              an event, the author of a sentence, or another scholar’s assertion about the sentence.
              XML has no standardized semantics, and interpretations of relationships among elements
              and attributes are often underspecified in XML vocabularies (<ref type="bibl"
                target="#renear02">Renear et al. 2002</ref>). In RDF, subject, predicate, and object
              roles in a statement are explicit at the data structure level. Distinctions among
              domain entities (such as author vs. authorship event, or morpheme vs. sentence) are
              encoded as a class identity for the resource.</p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="annotations">
            <head>Annotations</head>
            <p>The term <soCalled>Annotations</soCalled> covers a potentially wide variety of data
              types. We can have simple annotations in the form of typed links between data points,
              such as: a textual fragment and a proposed author of that fragment; detailed textual
              commentaries making an assertion about a text; a complex morphosyntactic analysis of a
              section of text; an alignment between editions or translations of a text. The Open
              Annotation (OA) data model <q>specifies an interoperable framework for creating
                associations between related resources, annotations, using a methodology that
                conforms to the Architecture of the World Wide Web</q>.<note>Open Annotation Data
                Model, February 8, 2013, <ptr
                  target="http://www.openannotation.org/spec/core/20130208/index.html"/>.</note> The
              OA model enables us to serialize every annotation in its most simple form, as a link
              between one or more <term>target</term> items being annotated, and one or more
                <term>bodies</term> representing the contents of the annotation. OA also gives us a
              standard vocabulary for categorizing the motivation for the annotations. URIs are used
              to specify both the target and the body of the annotation. We use the OA data model
              both as the primary representation of an annotation, in cases where the annotations
              are created by linking two identifiers (such as a link between a passage in a text and
              an identifier for a named entity or event), and also as a serialization method for
              more complex annotations, where the annotation process involves the creation of
              complex documents as the annotation bodies which we can then reference by their URI
              identifiers. In the latter case, we use a variety of standard formats for the actual
              annotation bodies, including: <list rend="bulleted">
                <item>The <ref
                    target="http://nlp.perseus.tufts.edu/syntax/treebank/agdt/1.7/data/treebank-1.5.xsd"
                    >Perseus Ancient Greek and Latin Treebank Schema</ref><note><ptr
                      target="http://nlp.perseus.tufts.edu/syntax/treebank/agdt/1.7/data/treebank-1.5.xsd"
                    />.</note> for morphosyntactic analyses.</item>
                <item>The <ref
                    target="https://svn.code.sf.net/p/alpheios/code/xml_ctl_files/schemas/trunk/aligned-text.xsd"
                    >Alpheios Translation Alignment Schema</ref><note><ptr
                      target="https://svn.code.sf.net/p/alpheios/code/xml_ctl_files/schemas/trunk/aligned-text.xsd"
                    />.</note> for text alignments.</item>
                <item><ref target="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax">Markdown
                    Syntax</ref><note><bibl><author>John Gruber</author>, <title level="a">Markdown:
                        Syntax</title>, <ptr
                        target="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax"/>.</bibl></note>
                  for short textual commentaries.</item>
                <item>TEI XML for primary and secondary source texts.</item>
              </list>
            </p>
            <p>The annotation representing the assertion (discussed above) that text at Athen.,
                <title level="m">Deipn</title>. 3.6 describes a reuse of a lost work of Istros
              identified by <ident>urn:cite:perseus:lci.2</ident>, serialized in OA using the
                JSON-LD<note>JSON for Linking Data, <ptr target="http://json-ld.org/"/>.</note>
              format, might be formalized as follows (<ref type="bibl" target="#almas13b">Almas and
                Berti 2013</ref>): <!-- [RvdB] 
                    -corrected "http://data.perseus.org.org" to "http://data.perseus.org" for "hasTarget"
                -->
              <eg> { "@context": "http://www.w3.org/ns/oa-context-20130208.json", "@id":
                "http://perseids.org/annotations/urn:cite:perseus:annsimp.2.1", "@type":
                "oa:Annotation", "annotatedAt": "2013-03-05T07:57:00", "annotatedBy": { "@id":
                "http://data.perseus.org/sosol/users/Monica Berti", "@type": "foaf:Person", "name":
                "Monica Berti" }, "hasBody":
                "http://data.perseus.org/collections/urn:cite:perseus:lci.2", "hasTarget":
                "http://data.perseus.org/citations/urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0008.tlg001.perseus-grc1:3.6%40Ἴστρος%5B1%5D-συκοφάνται%5B1%5D",
                "oa:motivatedBy":"oa:linking" } </eg>
            </p>
            <p><ptr type="crossref" target="#figure1"/> shows a possible visual representation of
              the same annotation: <figure xml:id="figure1">
                <graphic url="images/jtei-088-almas_figure_01.png" width="935px" height="430px"/>
                <head type="legend">Visual representation of an OA annotation of a text reuse in
                  Athen., <title level="m">Deipn</title>. 3.6</head>
              </figure>
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="collections">
          <head>Collections</head>
          <p>We need to be able to organize text reuses into various types of collections of data,
            including those represented in a given traditional print edition which comprises: reuses
            from one or many authors; all text reuses attributed to a specific author; all text
            reuses quoted by a specific author; all text reuses referencing a specific topic; all
            text reuses attributed to a specific time period. CITE Collection Services define a
            protocol for identifying and retrieving digital representations of objects identified by
            CITE URNs. CITE URNs uniquely identify objects in a set of objects of a similar kind:
            for example, images, manuscripts, and entries in commentaries. (CITE stands for
            Collections, Indices, Texts, and Extensions.) Examples of CITE collections used to
            support the encoding of text reuses for our project include the abstract lost text
            entities themselves, digital images of manuscripts of the extant source texts that quote
            those lost texts, commentaries on instances of text reuse, and linguistic annotations of
            the quoted text.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="provenance">
          <head>Provenance</head>
          <p>Scholars produce data through a variety of activities, observations, and other events.
            Some data is created, other data discovered. The <emph>provenance</emph> of a digital
            object is an account of its origin and change over time. Documenting and preserving data
            provenance in a structured, machine-readable format enables us to more precisely track
            and document shared resources, ultimately improving data quality and encouraging further
            sharing. Specifically, we intend our retrieval, editorial annotation, and communication
            tools to create records of the research transactions in which they are used. These
            records are expressed in RDF vocabularies that are based on abstract provenance
            models.</p>
          <p>According to Groth et al. (<ref type="bibl" target="#groth06">2006</ref>), two key
            principles for provenance data are that <list rend="inline ordered">
              <item>actors must only record propositions that they know to be true, through
                statements of what they observe; and</item>
              <item>each statement of provenance must be attributable to a particular actor.</item>
            </list></p>
          <p>In our use case, we need to be able to <list rend="inline ordered">
              <item>reference ancient data that can be identified but that did not literally come
                into existence as the result of any modern computational interaction (and which may
                in fact no longer be extant in any preserved source); and</item>
              <item>identify the role a data item, such as an ancient scholarly assertion, plays as
                the vehicle for the modern scholarly claims.</item>
            </list> A third requirement, which results from the second, is that we need to be able
            to represent the assertions of the ancient scholars, on which our modern assertions
            depend, in a format that can be included computationally in a common data set with the
            modern claims.</p>
          <p>Although our usual workflow discourse describes domain entities coming into existence
            and undergoing genuine change, that understanding poses problems for tracking identity
            and other semantic relationships. For example, if a text is enriched by adding TEI
            markup, what exactly is preserved in the derivation of the newer version from the older?
            On what basis do we identify the same original work in each reuse despite the
            superficial differences between them? And how do we represent assertions concerning
            works that have no physical exemplars? Our solution to dilemmas like these is to employ
            complementary data provenance models: one with a transformational view and another with
            a semiotic view of the same research events.</p>
          <p>The W3 Consortium’s <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/prov-dm/">PROV</ref> is a
            specification for expressing provenance records with descriptions of the entities and
            activities involved in producing and delivering or otherwise influencing a given digital
              object.<note>PROV-DM: The PROV Data Model, W3C Recommendation, April 30, 2013, <ptr
                target="http://www.w3.org/TR/prov-dm/"/>.</note> A PROV <term>activity</term> is an
            event through which entities come into existence and/or change to become new entities.
            Activities are dynamic aspects of the world, such as actions and processes. For example,
            a PROV account of the OA annotation shown in the previous section would document its
            coming into existence at a particular time through a researcher’s use of annotation
            software.</p>
          <p>In contrast to PROV, the Systematic Assertion Model (SAM) treats events in scholarship
            as linguistic acts (<ref type="bibl" target="#wickett12">Wickett et al. 2012</ref>). SAM
            is concerned not with mutable data structures that change from one form to another, but
            with unchanging abstract objects that come to stand in new contingent relationships
            during a project. A SAM account of the OA annotation, for example, would be concerned
            with its role as a vehicle for the scholar’s claim of a proposition’s truth (that is,
            the proposition that Athen., <title level="m">Deipn</title>. 3.6, quotes LCI 2). A SAM
            description links an annotation expression to the act of annotation, the claim advanced
            at that time and place, the annotator’s justification for the claim, and to interpretive
            contexts necessary for understanding the annotation. In the present example these
            contexts would include the OA vocabulary and the JSON-LD serialization syntax.</p>
          <p>SAM’s formal account of research data and its content supplies contextual information
            that PROV lacks, but PROV can record functional relationships that SAM hides: because
            SAM’s abstract symbol structures and propositions are immutable, their roles in a
            project are incompletely specified without the PROV view of their use as inputs and
            outputs to activities.</p>
          <p>In the scenario discussed in this paper, a scholar wants to annotate what she thinks is
            a reuse of a lost text attributed to Istros in an extant source text by Plutarch (<title
              level="m">Sol</title>. 24.1), where Istros is not named.<note>To substantiate her
              argument, the scholar must also identify corroborating material, including instances
              of Istros’ text in other primary sources—in this example that of Athenaeus, <title
                level="m">Deipn</title>. 3.6, who does name Istros as the source.</note> The
            scholar, using the Perseids annotation tools to produce a concrete representation of
            this assertion, <emph>indicates</emph> the text that represents the reuse. An example of
            an RDF triple documenting this action—the selection of the string starting with the
            first instance of <mentioned>ἐξαγωγὴ </mentioned>to the first instance of
              <mentioned>συκοφαντεῖν</mentioned> according to the SAM data model—is: <eg>
              &lt;system:actions/berti/textsel1> sam:indicates [ xsd:string
              "ἐξαγωγὴ1,συκοφαντεῖν1"]; event:agent &lt;perseids:users/berti>; event:time
              [xsd:dateTime "2013-05-20T09:01:00"]; a sam:Indication. </eg>
          </p>
          <p>Although we could represent this action as an <term>activity</term> involving the
            scholar’s physical interaction with the system, we would lose the significance of the
            linguistic force behind the scholar’s identification of the text.</p>
          <p>In reaction to her selection of text, the system computes a URI identifier for that
            text. This event can be represented as a SAM <term>computation</term>, but in order to
            represent the fact that the URI <emph>came into being</emph> as a result of a
            user-system interaction, it is also appropriate to describe this as a PROV
              <term>activity</term> that was <hi rend="italic">informed by</hi> the scholar’s
            previous action of selecting a string of text (<ref type="bibl" target="#almas13c">Almas
              et al. 2013</ref>): <eg> &lt;system:urncompute1&gt; sam:indicates
              &lt;data:citations/urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007.perseus-grc1:24.1%40ἐξαγωγὴ%5B1%5D-συκοφαντεῖν%5B1%5D&gt;;
              event:agent &lt;system:installation1&gt;; event:time [xsd:dateTime
              &quot;2013-05-20T09:01:01&quot;]; a sam:Computation, prov:Activity; prov:wasInformedBy
              &lt;system:actions/berti/textsel1&gt;. </eg>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="dissemination">
          <head>Dissemination and Presentation</head>
          <p>As discussed above, our primary focus thus far has been on capturing the data about the
            authors, texts and related commentaries, annotations, links, and translations in a way
            that is accurate and also encourages and facilitates its preservation and reuse. Visual
            representation of the data is one type of reuse, and the data format selections have
            been made with the need to support disseminations for online presentation in mind. The
            JSON-LD syntax recommended by OA allows us to easily build a dynamic display interface
            in Javascript which navigates the JSON-LD data object and retrieves the datasets
            identified as the targets and bodies of the annotations at their addressable URIs, as
            served by supporting CTS and CITE services. Our <ref
              target="http://perseids.org/sites/berti_demo/index.html">prototype
                interface</ref><note><ptr target="http://perseids.org/sites/berti_demo/index.html"/>
              (source code at <ptr target="https://github.com/PerseusDL/lci-demo"/>).</note>
            provides a demonstration of one possible approach to a digital representation of text
            reuse data. Similarly, although we hope eventually to be able to represent the rich
            provenance metadata discussed above in the visual representation of our digital
            editions, we are above all concerned with capturing the data in a way that ensures they
            can be preserved and serve as the basis for further research.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="DFHG">
        <head>The Digital Fragmenta Historicorum Graecorum (DFHG) Project</head>
        <p>As mentioned before, one of the goals of LOFTS is to digitize paper editions of
          fragmentary works and link them to the source texts from which the fragments have been
          excerpted. Such a work aims both at preserving a philological heritage and at providing a
          methodological foundation for implementing a new generation of born-digital editions of
          fragmentary texts. Accordingly, LOFTS is encoding the <title level="m">Fragmenta
            Historicorum Graecorum</title> (<title level="m">FHG</title>), which is one of the most
          important collections of textual fragments of Classical authors.</p>
        <div xml:id="FHG">
          <head>The <title level="m">FHG</title> Texts</head>
          <p>The five volumes of the <title level="m">FHG</title> edited by Karl Müller (1878–85)
            comprise the first big collection of fragments of Greek historians’ work ever realized.
            The work collects excerpts from textual sources pertaining to more than six hundred
            fragmentary authors. Excluding the first volume, these authors are chronologically
            distributed and range from the sixth century BCE to the seventh century CE. Under each
            author the fragments are numbered sequentially and arranged according to works and book
            numbers (when such information is available), and every fragment is translated into
            Latin. The first volume also includes the text of the inscription of the <title
              level="m">Marmor Parium</title> with a Latin translation, a chronological table, and a
            commentary, and the Greek text of the Rosetta Stone with a French literal translation,
            as well as a critical, historical, and archaeological commentary. The fifth volume
            includes fragments of the writings of Greek and Syriac historians preserved in Armenian
            sources.</p>
          <p>The basic structure of the <title level="m">FHG</title> has introductions to the
            volumes with discussions of the content, citations of sources, and references to
            bibliographical records. Sometimes short introductions precede the fragments of the
            fragmentary authors with biographical information and related textual evidence. The
            Greek fragments are arranged into two columns and the Latin translations are printed at
            the bottom of the page below a horizontal line. The <title level="m">FHG</title> does
            not include a critical apparatus for the Greek text.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="project">
          <head>The DFHG Project</head>
          <p>LOFTS is producing the first digital edition of the <title level="m">FHG</title> as a
            means of providing an open, linked, machine-actionable text for the study and
            advancement of Greek fragmentary literature.<note>Digital Fragmenta Historicorum
              Graecorum (DFHG) Project, Universität Leipzig, <ptr
                target="http://www.dh.uni-leipzig.de/wo/projects/open-greek-and-latin-project/digital-fragmenta-historicorum-graecorum-dfhg-project/"
              />.</note> The text is encoded in accordance with the latest TEI <ref
              target="http://sourceforge.net/p/epidoc/wiki/Home/">EpiDoc
              standards</ref>.<note>EpiDoc: Epigraphic Documents in TEI XML, <ptr
                target="http://sourceforge.net/p/epidoc/wiki/Home/"/>.</note> The decision to adopt
            the EpiDoc subset was dictated by two factors: <list rend="inline ordered">
              <item>EpiDoc markup lends itself well to ancient texts, be these papyri, inscriptions,
                manuscripts, or editions, allowing for various levels of detail;</item>
              <item>encoding in EpiDoc ensures compatibility with existing papyrological and
                epigraphic resources, with the <ref target="http://www.eagle-network.eu/"
                  >EAGLE-Europeana network</ref>,<note><ptr target="http://www.eagle-network.eu/"
                  />.</note> and with the forthcoming EpiDoc-compliant Perseus 5.0
                <!-- [RvdB]: 'database'? -->databank.</item>
            </list></p>
          <p>The Leipzig Humboldt Chair and Perseus Digital Library partnership entails a synergetic
            effort not only to enrich the <ref target="http://catalog.perseus.org/">Perseus
              Catalog</ref><note><ptr target="http://catalog.perseus.org/"/>.</note> but also to
            provide new testing material for the continuous development of the Perseids Platform,
            where the first EpiDoc version of the <title level="m">FHG</title> will be placed for
            further annotation. This undertaking is proving to be invaluable not only for the growth
            of partner resources but also for the development of the EpiDoc schema
              itself.<note>There is little room or intention in this article to elaborate further on
              the topic. Let it suffice to say this endeavor has contributed to the new release of
              the schema (published in February 2014) which now allows, among other additions, the
              following: <list rend="inline ordered">
                <item>the <att>rend</att> attribute of <gi>hi</gi> can now have <val>stacked</val>
                  as a value to encode stacked symbols or characters (such features are often found
                  in manuscripts);</item>
                <item>the <gi>anchor</gi> element is no longer omitted.</item>
              </list> All this has been explained in version 8.20 of the EpiDoc Guidelines
                  (<bibl><author>Tom Elliott</author>, <author>Gabriel Bodard</author>, <author>Elli
                  Mylonas</author>, <author>Simona Stoyanova</author>, <author>Charlotte
                  Tupman</author>, <author>Scott Vanderbilt</author>, et al., <title level="m"
                  >EpiDoc Guidelines: Ancient Documents in TEI XML</title>, <date>December 4,
                  2014</date>, <ptr target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/"
            /></bibl>).</note></p>
          <p>The project team is also working on the text of the so-called <title level="m">Marmor
              Parium</title> (<title level="m">IG</title> 12.5.444), which is a fragmentary
            inscription from the island of Paros that preserves a Hellenistic chronicle from the
            reign of Cecrops (1581/1580 BCE) to the archonship of Euctemon (299/298 BCE).<note><ptr
                target="http://www.dh.uni-leipzig.de/wo/projects/open-greek-and-latin-project/digital-marmor-parium/"
              /></note> The epigraphical text was edited in the first volume of the <title level="m"
              >FHG</title> because of its historiographical value (Müller 1878–85, 1:533–90). The
            author of the text is unknown, but the content reflects his choices and it consists of a
            list of historical events mainly based on the Athenian history. In this respect, this
            evidence is a perfect example of a fragmentary author, whose work is preserved not
            through quotations in later texts, but in a fragmented original form. The text of the
            inscription is also being encoded in EpiDoc. An important part of the project is the
            identification of named entities mentioned in the inscription (such as names of kings
            and magistrates, personal names, and place names). The <ref
              target="http://pleiades.stoa.org/">Pleiades gazetteer</ref> has been referenced for
            the place names.<note><ptr target="http://pleiades.stoa.org/"/>.</note> The
            identification of individuals will make use of and feed into the <ref
              target="http://snapdrgn.net/">Standards for Networking Ancient Prosopographies project
              (SNAP)</ref>.<note><ptr target="http://snapdrgn.net/"/>.</note> The team is also
            producing a visualization of the chronology preserved by the <title level="m">Marmor
              Parium</title> with the open source tool <ref target="http://timeline.knightlab.com/"
              >TimelineJS</ref>, which allows the comparison of the text not only with other ancient
            chronologies but also with different chronological interpretations of the content of the
            inscription made by modern scholars (<ref type="bibl" target="#berti14">Berti and
              Stoyanova 2014</ref>).<note><ptr target="http://timeline.knightlab.com/"/>.</note>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="EpiDoc">
          <head>The EpiDoc Guidelines and Encoding Process</head>
          <p>The digital text of the <title level="m">FHG</title> was obtained by feeding the volume
            scans available at the Internet Archive<note><ptr
                target="https://archive.org/details/fragmentahistori01mueluoft"/>.</note> to an
            Optical Character Recognition (OCR) engine, which transformed the printed text into
            digital form. The error-laden Greek output was corrected semi-automatically and stored
            in text files. Any remaining errors are manually rectified during the encoding
            process.</p>
          <p>LOFTS has drawn up an EpiDoc template that is compatible with the Perseus Digital
            Library corpus and applicable to all types of texts produced by the University of
            Leipzig <ref
              target="http://www.dh.uni-leipzig.de/wo/projects/open-greek-and-latin-project/">Open
              Greek and Latin (OGL) Project</ref>, which is producing a comprehensive open
            collection of Classical sources.<note><ptr
                target="http://www.dh.uni-leipzig.de/wo/projects/open-greek-and-latin-project/"
              />.</note> The template covers basic layout and citation structures with room for
            alteration and improvement and it is integrated with encoding guidelines, produced not
            only to document the LOFTS editorial choices but also to help external individuals
            contribute to the encoding process. The project production line consists of two stages:
              <list rend="inline ordered">
              <item>the encoding process is implemented by LOFTS and tackles layout, citation
                elements, and philological issues;</item>
              <item>the initial editorial endeavor and the guidelines are made available for
                crowdsourcing, where contributors are encouraged to further tag the EpiDoc files
                with information regarding places, personal names, and any other relevant
                entities.</item>
            </list></p>
          <div xml:id="stage1">
            <head>Stage One: First Level of Encoding by LOFTS</head>
            <p>The editorial team of LOFTS creates one XML file per fragmentary author. Every file
              contains a <gi>teiHeader</gi> with specific information about the author, volume, or
              book in question. As for the <gi>text</gi>, Müller’s layout is not kept since the
              Greek text is separated from its Latin translation. The structure within <gi>text</gi>
              reflects the structure of each volume, using the <tag>div type="textpart"</tag> with
              different <att>subtype</att> values, whenever needed. Müller’s Latin translations of
              the fragments are encoded in a separate XML file to facilitate text alignment.</p>
            <p>For example, fragment 6 of Ion of Chios will be encoded as follows (<ptr
                type="crossref" target="#figure2 #figure3 #figure4"/>): <figure xml:id="figure2">
                <graphic url="images/jtei-088-almas_figure_02.png" height="635px" width="457px"/>
                <head type="legend">Page image from FHG 2:48: Greek text of fragment 6 (outlined in
                  red) and Latin translation (outlined in yellow)</head>
              </figure>
            </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure3">
              <graphic url="images/jtei-088-almas_figure_03.png" width="782px" height="129px"/>
              <head type="legend">Image from the XML file for the Greek translation</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="figure4">
              <graphic url="images/jtei-088-almas_figure_04.png" width="782px" height="79px"/>
              <head type="legend">Image from the XML file for the Latin translation</head>
            </figure>
            <p>While retaining the same number (6), the Greek is encoded in a <gi>cit</gi> and the
              Latin translation in a <gi>p</gi>. The <gi>cit</gi> is broken down into <gi>bibl</gi>,
              which contains the source <gi>author</gi> (Plutarch) and work, and a <gi>quote</gi>,
              containing the Greek text. Whenever there is a note, the <gi>note</gi> element is also
              placed within <gi>cit</gi>. Any information that does not strictly pertain to the
              fragment is encoded in a <gi>p</gi>. This initial editorial stage also involves
              replacing special characters, such as the <mentioned>æ</mentioned> diphthong, with
              their Unicode entities (see the Latin translation, where <mentioned>æ</mentioned> is
              displayed as <code>&amp;#230;</code>) in order to avoid font and potential display
              issues and confusion between graphically similar but semantically different characters
              (e.g., capital Latin c and Greek capital lunate sigma). Numbers, including ordinal,
              are also tagged. Footnotes are given arabic numbers (Müller uses asterisks) for
              clarity.</p>
            <p>An <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt">XSL transformation</ref><note><ptr
                  target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt"/>.</note> is used to help the encoder better
              visualize the marked-up text and links the main body to the footnotes. All references
              to other works (often abbreviated by Müller) are tagged as <gi>bibl</gi> and will
              eventually point to a master bibliography file. Work titles appearing in the Greek and
              Latin texts are wrapped in a <gi>title</gi> element. Where we have both the Greek and
              the Latin titles of a work, the two titles are enclosed in another <gi>title</gi> tag:
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <title><title xml:lang="grc">Περὶ τελετῶν</title> sive <title type="alt"
                    xml:lang="la">De mysteriis</title></title>
              </egXML>
            </p>
            <p>The <title level="m">FHG</title> does not include a critical apparatus, but sometimes
              Müller signals variant readings in the text, and these are tagged as <gi>rdg</gi>
              elements inside an <gi>app</gi>
              <emph>within</emph> the main text. Personal names are simply tagged as
                <gi>persName</gi>. Names often carry additional information, such as patronymics and
              epithets or clues about an individual’s profession. Encoding such specificity is not a
              stage one priority but a stage two expectation.</p>
            <p>Another problematic feature when working with editions of fragmentary works is how to
              encode specific editorial decisions concerning the attribution of a quotation or a
              text reuse to an author whose original works are lost. Müller sometimes adds different
              marks (parentheses, square brackets, or question marks) to the fragment number in
              order to signal uncertainty about the attribution of that fragment.<note>See, for
                example, <ref type="bibl" target="#müller85">Müller 1878–85</ref>, 1:1, frr. 5 and
                7; 1:56, fr. 83; 2:29, fr. 2.</note> In these cases the uncertainty is encoded using
              the <att>ana</att> attribute to the <gi>cit</gi> element, with one of the following
              values: <val>#dubia</val>, <val>#incerta</val>, and <val>#anonyma</val>. These values
              are defined in the <gi>classDecl</gi> element in <gi>encodingDesc</gi> in the header.
              The reason for this choice depends on the fact that when the project was started not
              all relevant elements had the <att>cert</att> attribute. Even if they did, Müller
              reasons for marking something as uncertain vary a lot, and he is also inconsistent in
              his use of these sigla. The use of the <gi>certainty</gi> element also proved
              problematic, because of this inconsistency, since it was at times difficult to
              determine whether the uncertainty was the content of the citation, the attribution to
              an author, or the extent of the quotation. So it was decided to roughly map Müller’s
              three sigla to what seemed the most frequent and probable uncertainty categories
              across the collection, and rather than have <att>cert</att> or <gi>certainty</gi>
              sometimes in <gi>cit</gi> sometimes in <gi>bibl</gi> sometimes in <gi>quote</gi>, to
              have three different values of the <att>ana</att> attribute in <gi>cit</gi>.</p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="stage2">
            <head>Stage Two: Crowdsourced Annotation</head>
            <p>Once complete, these basic XML files are deposited in the Perseids Platform for
              further annotation by third parties. While still in testing mode, this second stage
              encourages annotators to tag any additional information, including—but not limited
              to—the following: <list rend="bulleted">
                <item>Names (person).<note>For example, Κάδμος Ἀρχελάου Μιλήσιος, where we have the
                    name of the author (Κάδμος), the name of the father (Ἀρχελάου), and the ethnicon
                    (Μιλήσιος). Further details on, and matching of, name components will be part of
                    a later, spin-off prosopography project.</note></item>
                <item>Names (place).<note>GeoNames geographical database, <ptr
                      target="http://www.geonames.org/"/>.</note></item>
                <item>Bibliographic references: expansion of bibliographic references and linking to
                  bibliography file.</item>
                <item>Numbers.</item>
                <item>Titles within Greek and Latin text.</item>
                <item>Stage 2 encoding of the Latin translations (after initial encoding at stage
                  one).</item>
              </list>
            </p>
            <p>The editorial board provides the final review for each file. EpiDoc-encoded DFHG
              files are being progressively added to the <ref
                target="https://github.com/OpenGreekAndLatin/dfhg-dev/wiki">DFHG <ptr
                  type="software" xml:id="GitHub" target="#GitHub"/><rs type="soft.name"
                  ref="#GitHub">GitHub</rs> repository</ref><note><ptr
                  target="https://github.com/OpenGreekAndLatin/dfhg-dev/wiki"/>.</note> for everyone
              to download, improve, and share in accordance with our <ref
                target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">CC BY-SA 4.0 International
                License</ref>.<note><ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                />.</note></p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="conclusions">
        <head> Conclusions</head>
        <p>The Leipzig Open Fragmentary Texts Series (LOFTS) aims not only at producing an open
          series of Greek and Latin fragmentary authors, but also at building a model for
          representing quotations and text reuses of lost works in a digital environment. In order
          to achieve these goals, different technologies are being used and implemented beyond the
          TEI XML standard. The final outcome is the production of dynamic excerpts from source
          texts. In the case of digitized print editions of fragmentary works, this means linking
          the fragments directly to the source text and annotating their metadata within it. In the
          case of new-born digital editions of fragmentary texts, fragments become multilayered
          annotations of information concerning fragmentary authors and reuses of their lost works.
          These dynamic excerpts contribute to the production of a real
            <soCalled>multitext</soCalled>, where each version of the same text embodies a different
          step in its transmission and a reconstruction of philological conjectures (on the concept
          of multitext see <ref type="bibl" target="#blackwell09">Blackwell and Crane 2009</ref>).
          The ultimate goals are the creation of open, linked, machine-actionable texts for the
          study of textual reuses of Classical works and the development of a collaborative
          environment for crowdsourced annotations that involve both scholars and students.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="almas13"><author>Almas, Bridget</author>, and <author>Marie-Claire
              Beaulieu</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a">Developing a New Integrated
              Editing Platform for Source Documents in Classics</title>. <title level="j">Literary
              &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">493–503</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1093/llc/fqt046</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="almas13b"><ptr type="software" xml:id="R4" target="#fragmentarytextseditor"
              /><rs type="soft.bib.ref" ref="#R4"><rs type="soft.agent" ref="#R4"><author>Almas,
                  Bridget</author></rs>, and <rs type="soft.agent" ref="#R4"><author>Monica
                  Berti</author></rs>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a">Perseids Collaborative
                Platform for Annotating Text Re-uses of Fragmentary Authors</title>. In <title
                level="m">DH-Case 2013. Proceedings of the 1st International Workshop on
                Collaborative Annotations in Shared Environments: Metadata, Vocabularies and
                Techniques in the Digital Humanities</title>, edited by <editor>Francesca
                Tomasi</editor> and <editor>Fabio Vitali</editor>, article no. 7. <pubPlace>New
                York, NY</pubPlace>: <publisher>ACM Digital Library</publisher>. doi:<idno
                type="doi">10.1145/2517978.2517986</idno>.</rs></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="almas13c"><author>Almas, Bridget</author>, <author>Monica Berti</author>,
              <author>Sayeed Choudhury</author>, <author>David Dubin</author>, <author>Megan
              Senseney</author>, and <author>Karen M. Wickett</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
              level="u">Representing Humanities Research Data Using Complementary Provenance
              Models</title>. Poster presented at Building Global Partnerships—RDA Second Plenary
            Meeting, Washington, DC, September 16–18, 2013.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="berti12"><author>Berti, Monica</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a"
              >Citazioni e dinamiche testuali. L’intertestualità e la storiografia greca
              frammentaria</title>. In <title level="m">Tradizione e Trasmissione degli Storici
              Greci Frammentari II. Atti del Terzo Workshop Internazionale. Roma, 24–26 febbraio
              2011</title>, edited by <editor>Virgilio Costa</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >439–58</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Tivoli</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edizioni
              Tored</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.monicaberti.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/CitazioniDinamicheTestuali.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="berti13"><author>Berti, Monica</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a"
              >Collecting Quotations by Topic: Degrees of Preservation and Transtextual Relations
              among Genres</title>. <title level="j">Ancient Society</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">43</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">269–88</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="http://poj.peeters-leuven.be/content.php?url=article&amp;id=2992614&amp;journal_code=AS"
            />. doi: <idno type="doi">10.2143/AS.43.0.2992614</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="berti14"><author>Berti, Monica</author>, and <author>Simona
              Stoyanova</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">Digital Marmor Parium. For a
              Digital Edition of a Greek Chronicle</title>. In <title level="m">Information
              Technologies for Epigraphy and Cultural Heritage. Proceedings of the First EAGLE
              International Conference</title>, edited by <editor>Silvia Orlandi</editor>,
              <editor>Raffaella Santucci</editor>, <editor>Vittore Casarosa</editor>, <editor>Pietro
              Maria Liuzzo</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">319–24</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Roma</pubPlace>: <publisher>Sapienza Università Editrice</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.eagle-network.eu/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/Paris-Conference-Proceedings.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="berti09"><author>Berti, Monica</author>, <author>Matteo Romanello</author>,
              <author>Alison Babeu</author>, and <author>Gregory R. Crane</author>.
              <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">Collecting Fragmentary Authors in a Digital
              Library</title>. In <title level="m">JCDL ’09: Proceedings of the 9th ACM/IEEE-CS
              Joint Conference on Digital Libraries</title>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >259–62</biblScope>. <pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>: <publisher>ACM Digital
              Library</publisher>. doi:<idno type="doi">10.1145/1555400.1555442</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="blackwell09"><author>Blackwell, Christopher</author>, and <author>Gregory R.
              Crane</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">Conclusion: Cyberinfrastructure,
              the Scaife Digital Library and Classics in a Digital Age</title>. <title level="j"
              >Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>). <ptr
              target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/1/000035/000035.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="groth06"><author>Groth, Paul</author>, <author>Simon Miles</author>, and
              <author>Steve Munroe</author>. <date>2006</date>. <title level="a">Principles of High
              Quality Documentation for Provenance: A Philosophical Discussion</title>. <title
              level="m">Lectures Notes in Computer Science</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4145</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">278–86</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.1007/11890850_28</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="most97"><editor>Most, Glenn W.</editor>, ed. <date>1997</date>. <title
              level="m">Collecting Fragments. Fragmente sammeln</title>.
              <pubPlace>Göttingen</pubPlace>: <publisher>Vandenhoeck &amp;
            Ruprecht</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="müller85"><editor>Müller, Karl</editor>, ed. <date>1878–85</date>. <title
              level="m">Fragmenta Historicorum Graecorum.</title> 5 vols.
            <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>: <publisher>A. F. Didot</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="renear02"><author>Renear, Allen</author>, <author>David Dubin</author>, and
              <author>C. M. Sperberg-McQueen</author>. <date>2002</date>. <title level="a">Towards a
              Semantics for XML Markup</title>. <title level="m">DocEng ’02: Proceedings of the 2002
              ACM Symposium on Document Engineering</title>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >119–26</biblScope>. <pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>: <publisher>ACM Digital
              Library</publisher>. doi:<idno type="doi">10.1145/585058.585081</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="smith12"><author>Smith, D. Neel</author>, and <author>Christopher W.
              Blackwell</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">Four URLs, Limitless Apps:
              Separation of Concerns in the <title level="m">Homer Multitext</title>
              Architecture</title>. In <title level="m">Donum natalicium digitaliter confectum
              Gregorio Nagy septuagenario a discipulis collegis familiaribus oblatum: A Virtual
              Birthday Gift Presented to Gregory Nagy on Turning Seventy by His Students,
              Colleagues, and Friends</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>: <publisher>Center
              for Hellenic Studies, Harvard University</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://chs.harvard.edu/wa/pageR?tn=ArticleWrapper&amp;bdc=12&amp;mn=4846"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="wickett12"><author>Wickett, Karen M.</author>, <author>Andrea
              Thomer</author>, <author>Simone Sacchi</author>, <author>Karen S. Baker</author>, and
              <author>David Dubin</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="u">What Dataset
              Descriptions Actually Describe: Using the Systematic Assertion Model to Connect Theory
              and Practice</title>. Poster presented at the 2012 ASIS&amp;T Research Data Access and
            Preservation Summit, New Orleans, March 22–23. <ptr
              target="http://hdl.handle.net/2142/30470"/>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
