<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Editorial Introduction to Issue 8 of the Journal of the Text Encoding
          Initiative</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Arianna</forename>
            <surname>Ciula</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Arianna Ciula is <roleName>Research Facilitator</roleName> at
              <orgName>University of Roehampton</orgName> (London, UK), where she supports research
            and enterprise strategies and actively contributes to the research proﬁle and networks
            in particular of the Department of Humanities. She is the <roleName>secretary</roleName>
            of <orgName>EADH</orgName>, member of the ADHO Steering Committee and member of CLARIN
            Scientific Advisory Board. She served in the TEI Technical Council as well as TEI
            Board.</affiliation>
          <email>ariannaciula@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Fabio</forename>
            <surname>Ciotti</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Fabio Ciotti is <roleName>Assistant Professor</roleName> at the
              <orgName>University of Roma Tor Vergata</orgName>, where he teaches Digital Literary
            Studies and Theory of Literature. He is <roleName>President</roleName> of the
              <orgName>Associazione per l’Informatica Umanistica e la Cultura Digitale</orgName>
            (AIUCD, the Italian digital humanities association) and member of the EADH Executive
            Board. He has been scientific consultant for text encoding and technological
            infrastructures in several digital libraries and archives projects, and has served in
            the TEI Technical Council.</affiliation>
          <email>fabio.ciotti@uniroma2.it</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>07/12/2015</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Arianna Ciula</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Fabio Ciotti</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Martin Holmes</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="8">Selected Papers from the 2013 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Revues.org -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="editorialIntroduction">
        <p>We are pleased to introduce the eighth issue of the Journal of the Text Encoding
          Initiative featuring selected peer reviewed papers from the 2013 TEI Conference and
          Members Meeting, which was held at Università della Sapienza in Rome, 2–5 October.</p>
        <p>Like all TEI conferences, this was an international gathering and, compared to other
          conferences, enjoyed an exceptional and diverse range of participants. The collaboration
          between the <orgName>TEI Board of Directors</orgName> and the <orgName>Associazione
            Italiana di Informatica Umanistica e Cultura Digitale</orgName> (AIUCD) to ensure an
          Italian host for this event also aimed at marking the long standing involvement of the
          Italian Digital Humanities community in TEI. Indeed, Italian scholars have made
          considerable contributions to the development of TEI and Digital Humanities as a whole in
          terms of theory, technologies, and organisation. We must also mention the name of the late
          Antonio Zampolli, who contributed enormously to the conception and implementation of the
          TEI initiative and who hosted the first Members’ Meeting of the Consortium in Pisa in
          2001. Since the 1990s scholars at <orgName>Università della Sapienza</orgName> in Rome
          have played an equally important role in raising the awareness of the importance of TEI
          encoding for formal textual representation. In particular, thanks to the research group
          led by the late Giuseppe Gigliozzi, research and teaching activities related to TEI have
          spread throughout Italy.</p>
        <p>The theme of the conference—<q>The Linked TEI: Text Encoding in the Web</q>—focused on
          the role of text encoding and TEI in a networked cultural environment. This focus
          encouraged reflections on the semantics of the TEI conceptual model, on the relationships
          among TEI and other data models and encoding schemas, on the role of TEI within a
          framework of interconnected digital resources as well as on the diverse ways users can
          access and take advantage of TEI-encoded resources. The title hints obviously at a very
          topical theme in the digital realm: the emergence and diffusion of the Linked Data
          paradigm and of a Participatory Web. TEI has had a crucial—and widely recognised—role in
          encouraging and facilitating the creation of vast quantities of textual and linguistic
          resources. It has been one of the major enabling technologies in the Digital Humanities.
          However, the dominant paradigm in the creation of digital resources, especially in the
          academic domain, has been that of the individual archive, the single monolithic or
          boutique project, <foreign xml:lang="lat">perfectum</foreign> in itself. To continue in
          its role of stimulus for innovation in the Digital Humanities, TEI has to be able to
          embrace fully—albeit critically—the new paradigm. The sharing and the interconnection of
          data on the Web as well as the emergence of semantically-enriched data are interesting
          aspects of technological innovation which will bring about new developments. The vision
          around <q>Linked TEI</q> also encompasses issues of multilingualism and multiculturalism:
          to be connected means to recognise and collaborate with different traditions and
          languages.</p>
        <p>Contributions to the conference call for papers responded very well to the challenge with
          a rich range of topics and perspectives represented in the <ref
            target="http://digilab2.let.uniroma1.it/teiconf2013/program/">programme</ref>: from
          reflections on semantic models and textuality, to data modelling and analysis, from
          re-thinking research infrastructures and developing participatory approaches, to
          establishing bi-directional linking between dictionaries and corpora. Among the many
          papers, posters, and panels accepted and presented at the conference, a large number were
          submitted for consideration and peer review for this issue of the <title level="j">Journal
            of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>, resulting in the largest issue of the journal
          published to date.</p>
        <p>The set of articles published here follow three main threads of interests around the
          TEI:</p>
        <list rend="ordered">
          <item>TEI in relation to other semantic and modeling formalisms;</item>
          <item>TEI as an expression of domain-specific text and data models;</item>
          <item>TEI processing workflows and tools.</item>
        </list>
        <p>The first topic is opened by Ciotti, Lana, and Tomasi’s article. In line with the main
          theme of the conference, this paper describes the architecture of the <title level="m"
            >geolat</title> project, a digital library of Latin texts enriched with annotations
          related to places and persons. Based on different ontologies and Semantic Web languages,
          these annotations can be formally analysed and shared as Linked Open Data. Also within the
          context of linked environments, Berti et al. introduce the <title level="m">Leipzig Open
            Fragmentary Texts Series</title> project, the goals of which are the creation of linked
          and annotated digital editions of classical fragmentary texts and the development of the
            <title level="m">Perseids Platform</title>, a collaborative environment for crowdsourced
          annotations. Moving from practical use-cases to the theoretical consideration of diverse
          modeling frameworks, Eide’s and Piez’s papers reveal the constraints of the tools we use
          as well as the different views they cast on the material under study. In particular, Piez
          presents the non-hierarchical modelling language LMNL (the Layered Markup and Annotation
          Language) and how it can be combined with the TEI-XML formalism to enhance its
          representational capability. Eide describes different methods of establishing meaning in
          TEI documents via linking mechanisms between TEI and external ontologies and how these
          different methods determine the semantic openness and usability of TEI documents.</p>
        <p>The second cluster collects a set of articles related to the adaptation of the TEI
          encoding scheme to specific complex data and document types. Using the Shelley-Godwin
          Archive (S-GA) as a case study, Muñoz and Viglianti discuss the challenges of producing
          TEI-encoded data and an accompanying reading environment able to support both
          document-focused and text-focused approaches. Barbero and Trasselli describe the data
          model developed by the <orgName>Instituto Centrale per il catalogo Unico</orgName> (ICCU)
          to export manuscript descriptions from <title level="m">Manus OnLine</title> (MOL), the
          Italian national catalogue of manuscripts, to TEI documents to promote consistency in
          manuscript descriptions as well as data interchange. Haaf, Geyken, and Wiegand give an
          overview of the DTA <soCalled>Base Format</soCalled> (DTABf), a strict subset of the TEI
          P5 tag set developed by the <title level="m">Deutsches Textarchiv</title> (DTA) project to
          represent text types in historical corpora generated out of multiple printed sources.
          González-Blanco and Rodríguez discuss the use of the TEI Verse module to tag metrical and
          poetic structures in the <title level="m">Repertorio Digital de Métrica Medieval
            Castellana</title> (ReMetCa) project, where TEI-XML is integrated into a Relational
          Database Management System (RDBMS). Last but not least, Mörth et al. propose a
          customization of the TEI dictionary module to respond to the new requirements emerging
          from an environment of increasingly intertwined language resources, and in particular to
          the need to include statistical data obtained from language resources in lexicographic
          workflows.</p>
        <p>The contributions within the third set of papers describe various approaches and tools to
          create, manage, and disseminate TEI-encoded resources in a networked environment. De la
          Iglesia and Göbel’s work uses XML and related Web technologies to process semantic
          entities and produce data-driven visualizations of the forthcoming edition of Theodor
          Fontane’s notebooks as well as comparisons with other edition projects using TEI. Rosselli
          Del Turco et al. describe EVT (Edition Visualization Technology), a TEI based scholarly
          publishing tool under development since about 2010. Initially designed as a specific
          solution for the <title level="m">Digital Vercelli Book</title> project, EVT has evolved
          into a flexible tool to create Web-based digital editions incorporating transcription
          files encoded in TEI XML and digital facsimiles of the source texts. Portela and Rito
          Silva’s article presents the rationale and the technical approaches adopted for the
          digital edition of Fernando Pessoa’s <title level="m">Livro do Desassossego</title>
          (LdoD). Starting from the intrinsic complexity of this unfinished work, this project
          offers a digital model of all its authorial and editorial manifestations and aims to
          create a dynamic platform open to user interaction and collaboration. Dumont and Fechner’s
          paper illustrates the user-friendly and bottom-up design principles that have guided the
          development of the <title level="m">ediarum</title> TEI editing and publishing platform.
          Similarly, Boschetti and Del Grosso describe the design and development of <title
            level="m">TeiCoPhiLib</title>, a library of <ptr type="software" xml:id="Java"
            target="#Java"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#Java">Java</rs> software components devoted
          to editing, processing, and visualising TEI documents in the domain of philological
          studies. This tool is particularly suited to fostering collaborative philological work.
          This cluster is closed by Dalmau and Hawkins’s article, the focus of which is not on
          specific tools or platforms, but rather on the impact and adoption of TEI and text
          encoding practices in the library community.</p>
        <p>We conclude this introduction with a few words about how this issue fits within the
          current developments of TEI and of the Digital Humanities community more generally. Every
          now and then it is healthy to ask where the TEI is going and why we care about it. With
          the growing emergence of Digital Humanities curricula and research positions, the
          establishment of digital workflows and resources in the cultural heritage sector, and the
          ongoing transition from a print to digital scholarly communication cycle, it is easy to
          get caught in the vortex. With the flurry of new activity in Digital Humanities today, has
          the time and place for the TEI come and gone? A step back to think of where we are—and
          therefore where we are going—implies a reconsideration of the historical focus of the TEI:
          texts, and in particular the modeling of texts for representation and processing purposes.
          It is this historical focus together with a periodical shifting of its limits and
          limitations that ensures the continuing relevance of the TEI: the meanings of texts
          change; the term <soCalled>text</soCalled> itself is perceived and applied in a wide
          sense; what we want to do with texts changes. The heart of our research endeavours
          continues to be the slippery confines of our cultural productions, to be seen, analysed,
          reflected upon, deconstructed, formalized, processed, remediated, and re-interpreted.</p>
        <p>The key to ensuring that the TEI will continue its valuable contributions to scholarship
          and culture more generally lies therefore also in a slight but crucial tilt to its
          rhetorics: the TEI is not only about delivering a standard but rather, and perhaps more
          significantly, about the intellectual activity of creating and developing that standard in
          partnership with the diverse communities of researchers, archivists, librarians, and other
          professionals of the cultural heritage sector, software developers, infrastructures
          providers, artists, citizens. A linked TEI looks less and less like a jigsaw where all
          pieces are cut to fit together, and more like an intertwining of hands.</p>
        <p>Enjoy the reading.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
