<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Ontologies, Data Modeling, and TEI</title>
        <author>
          <name><forename>Øyvind</forename>
            <surname>Eide</surname></name>
          <affiliation>Øyvind Eide holds a PhD in Digital Humanities from King’s College London
            (2013) and is one of the two founding conveners of the TEI Ontologies SIG. His research
            interests are focused on the modeling of cultural heritage information, especially as a
            tool for critical engagement with the relationships between texts and maps as media of
            communication. He is a <roleName>lecturer</roleName> and <roleName>research
              associate</roleName> at the Chair of Digital Humanities, <orgName>University of
              Passau</orgName>, Germany.</affiliation>
          <email>oyvind.eide@uni-passau.de</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>09/04/2015</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Arianna Ciula</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Fabio Ciotti</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Martin Holmes</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="8">Selected Papers from the 2013 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Revues.org -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>ontologies</term>
          <term>conceptual modeling</term>
          <term>interchange</term>
          <term>CIDOC-CRM</term>
          <term>linked data</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract">
        <p>This paper discusses the relationships between TEI and ontologies from the perspective of
          computer-based modeling, understood here as a way to establish meaning. The distinctions
          between creation and use of models as well as between modeling for production and modeling
          for understanding are presented and compared with other categorizations or models of
          modeling. One method of establishing meaning in TEI documents is achieved via linking
          mechanisms between TEI and external ontologies. How such linking can be done and what it
          may imply for the semantic openness and usability of TEI documents is the practical focus
          of this article.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="intro">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>In philosophy, <term>ontology</term> has for at least 2,500 years denoted the study of
          being. Computer science <term>ontologies</term>, usually in the plural, are different from
          the philosophical concept of ontology. Computer science ontologies refer to shared
          conceptualizations expressed in formal languages (<ref type="bibl" target="#gruber09"
            >Gruber 2009</ref>) and have been a topic of study for some thirty years, initially
          connected to the artificial intelligence community. They have not been of much importance
          in digital humanities until the last ten to fifteen years, but are now gaining momentum as
          the semantic web develops.</p>
        <p>In this paper I will discuss ontologies in the context of the Text Encoding Initiative
          and based on the computer science tradition.<note>This paper springs out of work in the
            TEI Ontologies SIG since 2004. It is also based on long discussions with colleagues at
            the Unit for Digital Documentation at the University of Oslo and beyond. Two anonymous
            reviewers of this article and the editors of the journal contributed significantly to
            its final form. However, the interpretation and formulation, and responsibility for its
            errors and omissions, is mine alone.</note> However, although computer science
          ontologies are different from philosophical ontology, the two are not totally disconnected
            (<ref type="bibl" target="#zuniga01">Zúñiga 2001</ref>), and therefore some remarks will
          be made on relations with philosophy as well. The focus will be on how meaning can be
          established in computer-based modeling. Three broad areas will be described. One is the
          establishment of meaning through working with and interpreting documents seen as sources
          for scholarly work, be they primary or secondary. Another area is the establishment of
          meaning through the development of models, including ontologies. A third area of meaning
          production with particular reference to TEI happens through linking between TEI documents
          and external ontologies. How such linking can be done and what it may imply for the
          meaning and usability of TEI documents is an important focus of this article.</p>
        <p>TEI represents a shared conceptualization of what exists in the domains relevant to text
          encoding. It can be expressed in formal models, but it is questionable whether TEI can be
          seen as an ontology in the computer science sense. According to the classification by
          Guarino, Oberle, and Staab (<ref type="bibl" target="#guarino09">2009, 12–13</ref>), XML
          schemas are typically not expressive enough for the formality we need for ontologies.
          However, the level of language formality forms a continuum, and it is difficult to draw a
          strict line where the formal starts. So for instance, some parts of the TEI scheme, such
          as the systems used to encode dictionaries, bibliographies, and representations of
          persons, places, and events, may be closer to an ontology than other, less formalized
          parts of the standard (<ref type="bibl" target="#ore09">Ore and Eide 2009</ref>).</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="p4top5">
        <head>P4 to P5<note>This section is based on Eide and Ore (<ref type="bibl"
              target="#eideore07">2007</ref>) and Eide (<ref type="bibl" target="#eide07"
            >2007</ref>).</note></head>
        <p>In TEI P4, as in previous versions of TEI, names of places and people, as well as other
          strings referring to places, people, and organizations, could be encoded using elements
          such as <gi>rs</gi> and <gi>name</gi>. These elements were used to encode names and other
          referring strings as textual features. P4 included no construct<note>The guidelines
            pointed to <title level="a">Simple Analytic Mechanisms</title> and <title level="a"
              >Feature Structures</title> as <quote source="#quoteref1"
              ><supplied>a</supplied>ppropriate mechanisms for the encoding of such interpretative
              gestures</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref1" type="bibl" target="#tei01">TEI Consortium
              2001, ch. 20</ref>) but these mechanisms were never in common use, and P4 did not
            include any standard way to represent specific external entities such as places or
            persons, just mechanisms that could be used to model them.</note> to encode information
          about real world or fictitious entities that the strings in the text referred to: <cit>
            <quote source="#quoteref2">It should be noted however that no provision is made by the
              present tag set for the representation of the abstract structures, or virtual objects
              to which names or dates may be said to refer. In simple terms, where the core tag set
              allows one to represent a name, this additional tag set allows one to represent a
              personal name, but neither provides for the direct representation of a person.</quote>
            <ref xml:id="quoteref2" type="bibl" target="#tei01">TEI Consortium 2001, ch. 20</ref>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p>In P5 this was changed. Real or fictitious entities pointed to by referring strings in
          the text were now included in the standard so that in addition to the referring strings,
          which could still be encoded as in P4, the external entities could be represented as well: <cit>
            <quote source="#quoteref3">This module also provides elements for the representation of
              information about the person, place, or organization to which a given name is
              understood to refer and to represent the name itself, independently of its
              application. In simple terms, where the core module allows one simply to represent
              that a given piece of text is a name, this module allows one further to represent a
              personal name, to represent the person being named, and to represent the canonical
              name being used. A similar range is provided for names of places and organizations.
              The main intended applications for this module are in biographical, historical, or
              geographical data systems such as gazetteers and biographical databases, where these
              are to be integrated with encoded texts.</quote>
            <ref xml:id="quoteref3" type="bibl" target="#tei13">TEI Consortium 2013, ch. 13</ref>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p>This means that while P4 represented only textual occurrences, P5 goes beyond that
          limitation. In P5, names can be connected to a representation of the named object, which
          is typically placed in the header of the TEI document (<ref type="bibl"
            target="#wittern09">Wittern 2009</ref>). The inclusion of the new elements provided one
          standard way to create such representations, which was needed by many text encoders. We
          will see later how this header information represents one way among others with which to
          link the referring strings as they are encoded in the text to external ontologies. As
          other methods do exist, the inclusion of the new elements in P5 was not strictly necessary
          for interoperability, but did facilitate a standard way of creating the
          interconnections.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="modeling">
        <head>Two Ways of Modeling</head>
        <p>There are no ontologies without models — an ontology, after all, represents a model of a
          world or of a certain corner of it. The discussion in the paper will focus on active
          engagement with models, that is, on how meaning is generated and anchored when ontologies
          and other models are developed and used. For TEI specifically, the development of the
          standard was based on ontological assumptions regarding relevant textual sources (e.g.,
          their structure and components) in the philosophical sense. Further development, such as
          creating the new elements described in the <ref type="crossref" target="#p4top5">previous
            section</ref>, is based on similar considerations. Using TEI for encoding texts also
          involves the study of the source material and how it can be related to the standard as a
          whole, which has some similarities with the development of the standard itself. Here,
          however, I will focus on the differences between these two types of work.</p>
        <p>I will distinguish between two different, although overlapping, ways of modeling. First,
          one may use already existing models for data integration. An example of this is the task
          of integrating data from several different libraries and archives in order to create a
          common data warehouse in which the detailed classifications from each of the databases are
          preserved. In the process, one will want to use a common ontology for the cultural
          heritage sector, for instance, FRBRoo (<ref type="bibl" target="#bekiari13">Bekiari
            2013</ref>). One must develop a thorough understanding of the sources, be they TEI
          encoded texts or other forms, as well as of the target ontology—one will develop new
          knowledge.</p>
        <p>The task is intellectually demanding and those engaged in it will learn new things along
          the way. Still, the formal specification of the corner of the world they are working
          towards is already defined in the standard. Only in a limited number of cases will there
          be a need to develop extensions to the model. Once the job is done, inferences made using
          the ontology-based data warehouse can be used to understand the sources and what they
          document even better. Yet, despite all the new knowledge acquired, the process is still
          mostly restricted to the use of what is already there.</p>
        <p>The second way of working with models is to create an ontology or another formal model
          through studying a domain of interest. In this case, a group of people will analyze what
          exists in the domain and how one can establish classes which are related to each other.
          This may, for instance, be in order to understand works of fiction, as in the development
          of the <ref target="http://www.contextus.net/ontomedia/model">OntoMedia</ref>
                ontology,<note><bibl><author>K. Faith Lawrence</author>, <author>Michael
                Jewell</author>, and <author>Mischa Tuffield</author>, <title level="a">The
                OntoMedia Model</title>, accessed January 29, 2014, <ptr
                target="http://www.contextus.net/ontomedia/model"/>.</bibl></note> which is used to
          describe the semantic content of media expressions. It can also be based on long
          traditions of collection management in analog as well as digital form, as in the
          development of CIDOC-CRM (<ref type="bibl" target="#crofts11">Crofts et al. 2011</ref>) in
          the museum community. Although one will often study data from existing information systems
          as part of the process, the main goals of such studies are not mappings in themselves, but
          rather to understand and learn from previous modeling exercises in the area of
          interest.</p>
        <p>The historical and current development of TEI as a standard can be seen in this context.
          The domain of TEI has no clear borders, but the focus is on textual material in the
          humanities and cultural history. In order to develop a model of this specific corner of
          the world, one has to analyze what exists and how the classes of things are related to
          each other. This is a process in which domain specialists and people trained in the
          creation of data models must work together, as the history of TEI
            demonstrates.<note>Burnard (<ref type="bibl" target="#burnard13">2013</ref>). In
            addition to separate persons with separate skill sets working together we also find
            several individuals who are acting as both modeling experts and domain experts at the
            same time.</note></p>
        <p>When applying either of the two methods of modeling, knowledge is gained through the
          process as well as in the study and use of the end products; one can learn from modeling
          as well as from models, from the process of creating an ontology as well as from the use
          of already existing ones. Getting to know a description of a modeling standard rarely
          gives the same level of understanding as actively engaging with the model as a creator or
          a user. Reading the TEI Guidelines is a good way of getting an overview of the standard,
          but it is hard to understand it at a deeper level without using it in practical work, and
          among the best TEI experts are those who have taken part in creating the standard.</p>
        <p>There is no clear line between the two approaches to modeling, and they often use similar
          methods in practice. They both have products as the end goal, and new knowledge is created
          in the process. Some of this new knowledge is expressed in the end products. For example,
          working to understand better what is important for a concept such as
            <soCalled>person</soCalled> in the domain under study will result in new knowledge. This
          knowledge will be shared by the parties involved in the modeling exercise and may be
          expressed in the end product. However, there is a stronger pressure towards expressing
          such new knowledge clearly when a data standard is created than when a mapping is created.
          In the latter case the boxes are already made and one has to find the right fit between
          one’s data and those boxes, typically assuming that the ones who made them worked
          thoroughly on the matter. This is useful in many cases, but one is less inclined to
          question what is there and runs the risk of not seeing what is outside the standard (<ref
            type="bibl" target="#zafrin07">Zafrin 2007, 66</ref>). In the case of creating
          a standard, one has to build the boxes, establishing both the entities to be used, the
          relationships between them, and how to name and describe both entities, relationships, and
          the general principles behind the standard. Everything is open to question, and in the end
          a new world is built.</p>
        <p>These two methods are presented as distinct categories for the sake of analysis. They
          are, however, prototypical, and there is no strict line between them. Middle positions can
          be found when one takes an existing ontology and extends it, or uses terms taken from
          multiple ontologies in combination. Such border cases notwithstanding, the distinction
          between using and creating models is clear in most cases.</p>
        <p>In addition to the distinction between using models and creating models, we also have a
          distinction between modeling for production and modeling for understanding. Modeling for
          understanding is here seen as creating models with the sole or main purpose of learning
          new things through the modeling activity. The model in itself is not a main goal of the
          work. In modeling for production a version of the modeled entity is the main goal of the
          work. So even if the use of a model for production (for instance using TEI to encode a
          dictionary) is a research activity which gives new understanding, the main purpose is
          still the end product. The same was the case when the dictionary module of the TEI
          Guidelines itself was created. It gave new understanding, but the main purpose was to
          create the end product—the dictionary module. A well known example of modeling for
          production is the project <ref target="http://ibsen.uio.no/OmUtgaven.xhtml">Henrik Ibsen’s
            writings</ref>, where modeling and TEI encoding were used to create a series of printed
            volumes.<note>This was not the only output of the project, and other results were closer
            to modeling for understanding. See the webpage for details, accessed February 22, 2015,
              <ptr target="http://ibsen.uio.no/OmUtgaven.xhtml"/>.</note> An example of the use of
          modeling for understanding would be be to analyze a poem through iterative rounds of TEI
          encoding, finding and investigating new problems along the way. In this process, one could
          develop an ontology based on one’s growing understanding of the poem.<note>Such model
            development will happen through iterative cycles, and the connections to hermeneutics
            are interesting. They are, however, beyond the scope of this paper.</note> In <ptr
            type="crossref" target="#table1"/> these four types of modeling are presented as a table
          which expresses a model of modeling. I must repeat here that the distinctions in the table
          are not clear-cut, but rather an analytical tool to explore the complex and many-faceted
          activity of modeling.</p>
        <table xml:id="table1">
          <head>A model of modeling.</head>
          <row role="label">
            <cell>Why modeling?</cell>
            <cell>Using a model</cell>
            <cell>Creating a model</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="label">Modeling for production</cell>
            <cell>Using TEI to encode and publish a document</cell>
            <cell>Creating a module in the TEI Guidelines</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="label">Modeling for understanding</cell>
            <cell>Using TEI encoding as a research method</cell>
            <cell>Creating an ontology as part of a research effort</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <p>A well-established distinction in modeling theory in digital humanities and beyond is the
          one between <soCalled>models for</soCalled> and <soCalled>models of</soCalled>. McCarty,
          following Geertz, distinguishes between <quote source="#quoteref4">a denotative
              <soCalled>model <emph>of</emph></soCalled>, such as a grammar describing the features
            of a language, and an exemplary <soCalled>model <emph>for</emph></soCalled>, such as an
            architectural plan</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref4" type="bibl" target="#mccarty05"
            >McCarty 2005, 24</ref>).<note>This is in line with the distinction between a data model
            as an interpretation of a domain (a representational agenda) and as a plan of action (a
            cohortative agenda) (<ref type="bibl" target="#dubin13">Dubin, Senseney, and Jett
              2013</ref>).</note> This analytical distinction is not clear cut, and it <quote
            source="#quoteref5">also reaches its vanishing point in the convergent purposes of
            modeling; the model of exists to tell us what we do not know, the model for to give us
            what we do not yet have. Models realize</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref5" type="bibl"
            target="#dubin13">ibid.</ref>). Although not clear-cut, the distinction still has some
          consequences of relevance for <ptr type="crossref" target="#table1"/> above. Using a model
          for production and creating a model for understanding both have a tendency towards
          creating models of, whereas creating a model for production and using a model for
          understanding both have a tendency towards creating models for.</p>
        <p>To return to the examples used above: a dictionary is encoded in TEI as a model of a
          print dictionary. In creating it, one makes a <soCalled>simple</soCalled> (but usually
          labor-intensive) mapping. Through this process one might learn something new through
          making explicit certain components of the dictionary which were not apparent in the print
          version. In creating an ontology of a certain interpretive reading of a poem, one also
          creates a model of, but one of a different kind. The distance between the object being
          modeled and the model is much larger; one can learn more from the process.</p>
        <p>Creating a TEI module as tool for encoding dictionaries is modeling for in that it is not
          representing a specific document but provides a toolkit one can apply to multiple
            texts.<note>A model can always be seen both as a model of and a model for. In this
            specific example the TEI module can also be seen as a model of an abstract structure,
            that is the class of all dictionaries. Model of and model for represent different
            aspects of modeling and the <quote source="#quoteref6">choice of perspective on the
              model will of course determine what will be brought into the foreground</quote>. (<ref
              xml:id="quoteref6" type="bibl" target="#mahr09">Mahr 2009, 372</ref>).</note> In the
          case of using a model for understanding, one is aiming at discovering something new, so
          one is enabling a model for. Both of these are used as models for, but the former is more
          practically oriented, creating a tool for encoding, while the latter is more discovery
          oriented, using a model to elicit new knowledge.</p>
        <p>As the examples show, the tendencies towards a match with the modeling of/modeling for
          distinction are weak and will depend on context. This may indicate that the distinction
          between models for and models of does not match the distinctions in <ptr type="crossref"
            target="#table1"/> very well, and that they operate at another level. A closer study of
          their relationship is beyond the scope of this article, but what this unclear relationship
          does show is the limitations of any classification such as the one proposed in <ptr
            type="crossref" target="#table1"/> and for that matter of any model.</p>
        <p>Another distinction, established recently by Jannidis and Flanders, is the one between
          altruistic and egoistic modelers. This is a distinction which fits my classification quite
          well. They describe models created by altruistic modelers as the ones that <quote
            source="#quoteref7">serve as an interchange format for some types of users and user
            communities where data is typically being created and modeled with someone else’s needs
            in mind</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref7" type="bibl" target="#jannidis13">Jannidis and
            Flanders 2013, 238</ref>), which corresponds nicely to my row labeled <q>modeling for
            production</q>. They describe models created by egoistic modelers as having the function
            <quote source="#quoteref8">to express specific research ideas in cases where data is
            being created to support the creator’s own research needs</quote> (<ref
            xml:id="quoteref8" type="bibl" target="#jannidis13">ibid.</ref>), which is similar to my
          row labeled <q>modeling for understanding</q>.</p>
        <p>According to Jannidis and Flanders, these two ways of modeling lead to very different
          modeling practices. If this is true—and I believe it is—it may indicate that the
          distinction just discussed is more important than the distinction between creating and
          using models. This points towards the following hypothesis: while the distinction between
          making or using a model is significant as to how deeply one engages with the material and
          how well one learns the model, the distinction between modeling for production and
          modeling for understanding has more significant consequences for how one engages with the
          model: the broad scope with integration of different views on the one hand, and the narrow
          focus of specific theoretical assumptions and research interests on the other.</p>
        <p>I find it necessary here to be explicit about what was implicit in the previous
          paragraphs: the model I present in <ptr type="crossref" target="#table1"/> is tentative
          and should be developed further. This is an area for future research connected not only to
          the development and use of TEI, but also to better understanding of modeling as a digital
          humanities practice and how it relates to similar practices in cultural heritage (<ref
            type="bibl" target="#ciula14">Ciula and Eide 2014</ref>). This must go hand in hand with
          theoretical work on modeling in digital humanities, as called for by Jannidis and Flanders
            (<ref type="bibl" target="#jannidis13">2013, 237</ref>).</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="interconnections">
        <head>Interconnections</head>
        <p>When a TEI encoding of a text is established, it is the result of a process which
          includes modeling, even if the involved parties may not be explicitly aware of it. In this
          section I will discuss links between TEI and external ontologies used in the cultural
          heritage sector, using CIDOC-CRM as my main example. This will serve two purposes. First,
          it will give a better understanding of how the semantics of TEI documents are established
          and work. Are there differences between the ways one creates links between TEI and
          external ontologies which have consequences for the way the semantics of elements are
          established and used, comparable to the differences in types of modeling discussed in the
            <ref type="crossref" target="#modeling">previous section</ref>? Second, it is not only
          individual projects or specific editions created in TEI that have a need for integrating
          TEI documents with external ontologies. The need to integrate resources is shared by the
          cultural heritage and humanities community at large, where it has become a necessary
          addition to modeling. While integration with external standards is useful both in modeling
          for production and for understanding, such integration takes many different forms, as we
          will see.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure1">
          <graphic url="images/jtei-8-073-eide_image_01.png" width="1413px" height="833px"/>
          <head type="legend">Interconnected cultural heritage, showing three examples of digital
            cultural heritage information: 3D models of artifacts, ontologies, and TEI-encoded
            texts. The picture to the left is taken from the Arrigo showcase (<ref type="bibl"
              target="#havemann09">Havemann 2009</ref>).</head>
        </figure>
        <p>Whether the dream of a semantic web for cultural heritage, as expressed in a simplified
          way in <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure1"/>, is ever to be established will depend on
          better understanding of how the integration between TEI and other standards such as
          CIDOC-CRM works. In this larger picture, the current paper is located as the encircled
          arrow shown in <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure1"/>: in the link between texts and
          ontologies. Studying ways of linking them together can create practical basic
          understanding on which to build a theoretical framework. Such links are created when we
          use models, but the mechanisms for linking must be established when the models are created
          in the first place. This may be obvious in the creation of standards such as TEI or
          CIDOC-CRM, but it is also needed in ad hoc models created in research projects. In the
          latter case the need may not be equally obvious, but the necessity of providing links from
          a research argument to the sources on which it is based is crucial in the development of
          more open and reproducible research. Such linking is dependent on semantically
          well-defined points of entry in TEI for external systems to point to, and similarly on
          points of exit to be used to link TEI to other resources.<note>This is not at all a new
            understanding. Some earlier examples include Ciula, Spence, and Vieira (<ref type="bibl"
              target="#ciula08">2008</ref>), Haveman et al. (<ref type="bibl" target="#havemann09"
              >2009</ref>), as well as the harvesting of TEI data into a CIDOC-CRM–based common
            system in the CLAROS project, <ptr target="http://www.clarosnet.org/"/> (accessed
            January 29, 2014).</note></p>
        <p>How does this look from the other side? An ontology may be used to make statements of
          contradictory facts at different levels. This will often be related to different
          interpretations of source material. One example is various paper based sources for
          classifications of objects in a museum. What in 1880 was seen as pair of Old Norse skis
          could in 1980 be seen as a pair of Sami skis. The two classifications can be recorded in
          different protocols or index cards and may be based on different interpretations of the
          objects as well as of written sources about those objects. Although one of them will be
          chosen as the official classification presented by the museum, both should still be
          recorded in the museum information system in order to track the intellectual history of
          the field of study.</p>
        <p>While an ontology is a model of a domain, an individual mapping to an ontology will be
          based on specific sources. Links from ontologies to their sources are needed in order to
          ensure scholarly reproducibility. It is not enough that the references exist. It is also
          important to make the links easily accessible for human readers and computer algorithms
          alike. Thus, the links must be as precise as possible, point to the source at the highest
          possible level of detail, and must be formalized in a standardized way. This is to a large
          extent a matter of practical implementation, but an important one.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure2">
          <graphic url="images/jtei-8-073-eide_image_02.png" width="1499px" height="518px"/>
          <head type="legend">Integration seen from TEI. EDD RDBS is a local cultural heritage
            database system at the University of Oslo.</head>
        </figure>
        <p>In the situation visualized in <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure2"/>, TEI is the
          formalism in focus, and the rest of the world, meaning other formalisms and database
          systems, are seen as children that one needs to link to, based on a linking model which is
          coherent and usable from the TEI side. In short, it shows how the world of information
          integration may appear from the perspective of TEI. We will now examine how
          interconnections can be made in such an interlinked system. Where is the link to the
          external model to be found in the markup of the text? How is it formalized? It will be
          shown how, still from the perspective of TEI, we can provide mechanisms for well-defined
          links back to the encoded texts. We will also examine to what degree this will work
          differently for links from and to models for production as opposed to models for
          understanding.</p>
        <p>Based on practical experience and a close study of chapter 13 of TEI P5, I have
          established a number of interconnection strategies for elements such as referring strings
          and names. These are all similar in the sense that they are using references to external
          targets, in line with normal linked data methods. The links back to the TEI documents are
          provided through <att>xml:id</att> attributes which, together with stable identifiers for
          the individual documents, also work as linked data targets. Any RDF triplet can be encoded
          in TEI using the <gi>relation</gi> element. Thus, the RDF namespace is not strictly needed
          to make such statements. </p>
        <figure xml:id="figure3">
          <graphic url="images/jtei-8-073-eide_image_03.png" width="735px" height="727px"/>
          <head type="legend">Method A: Elements in the body of the TEI document point to an
            external ontology. Reverse: Links from the external ontology to elements in the body of
            the TEI document.</head>
        </figure>
        <figure xml:id="figure4">
          <graphic url="images/jtei-8-073-eide_image_04.png" width="919px" height="559px"/>
          <head type="legend">Method B: Elements in the body of the TEI document point to elements
            expressed in another namespace in the header; links from the header elements point to an
            external ontology. Reverse: Links from the external ontology to elements in another
            namespace in the header of the TEI document.</head>
        </figure>
        <figure xml:id="figure5">
          <graphic url="images/jtei-8-073-eide_image_05.png" width="941px" height="431px"/>
          <head type="legend">Method C: Elements in the body of the TEI document point to TEI
            elements in the header; links from the header elements point to an external ontology.
            Reverse: links from the external ontology to TEI elements in the header of the TEI
            document.</head>
        </figure>
        <table xml:id="table2">
          <head>The six ways to link between TEI and external ontologies.</head>
          <row role="label">
            <cell/>
            <cell>Links from TEI</cell>
            <cell>Links to TEI</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="label">TEI in body (method A)</cell>
            <cell>Elements in the body of the TEI document point to an external ontology.</cell>
            <cell>Links from external ontology to elements in the body of the TEI document.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="label">Non-TEI in header (method B)</cell>
            <cell>Elements in the body of the TEI document point to elements in another namespace in
              the header. Links from the header elements point to an external ontology.</cell>
            <cell>Links from external ontology point to elements in another namespace in the header
              of the TEI document.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="label">TEI in header (method C)</cell>
            <cell>Elements in the body of the TEI document point to TEI elements in the header.
              Links from the header elements point to an external ontology.</cell>
            <cell>Links from ontology point to TEI elements in the header of the TEI
              document.</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <p>As <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure3 #figure4 #figure5"/> indicate,<note>These three
            figures were first presented in a paper at the seminar The Message of the Old Book in
            the New Environment, L’Institut Finlandais en France, Paris, March 18–19, 2011, in the
            context of the Paris Book Fair. The colors of the dots indicate different classes in the
            ontology. </note> there are six different ways identified for links between TEI and
          external ontologies, shown together in <ptr type="crossref" target="#table2"/>; three
          types of links from TEI to external formalisms and three types of return links.<note>The
            TEI header and body in these examples do not have to be in the same document, but the
            situation with a header in a different document would not change the essence of the
            argument.</note> They are all based on a common methodology and on the same basic
          linked-data concepts. However, the differences we have identified have certain
          implications for how the links are used as part of modeling and how integration works in
          practice. The natural center of gravity in the linked system will reside in different
          places. These differences have significant theoretical consequences.</p>
        <p>Method C uses TEI elements. Thus, there is one and only one element available to
          represent a person, namely the <gi>person</gi> element. The same goes for other elements
          such as <gi>place</gi> and <gi>event</gi>. This means that the use of this method ensures
          that anyone aiming to harvest or link to such elements in TEI headers<note><p>These
              elements do not need to be in the TEI header, they can, for instance, be used in
              authority lists in the body of a separate TEI document. The argument about the
              semantics remains the same, however.</p></note> will have one set of elements with
          well-defined semantics to connect to.</p>
        <p>The same can to a certain degree be said of method A: as no information in the TEI header
          is used to represent the entities that the referring strings refer to, the linking from
          the external system must be done directly to the <gi>rs</gi> element and to the various
          elements used for names in the body of the TEI document. Thus, the elements are
          standardized and have well-defined semantics. The problem with this method, compared to
          method C, is the potentially high number of link targets in the TEI document because links
          must be made to every occurrence of a reference in the text, rather than to every external
          entity referred to by one or more referring strings. Links must be established to each
          particular reference rather than to each particular referred object.</p>
        <p>Method B is different from the other two in that it just states that the representation
          in the TEI header is expressed in an external namespace. This can be any namespace in
          which entities such as persons, places, or events are modeled. A number of potential
          namespaces and different elements exist, each with potentially different meanings.
          Examples include the CIDOC-CRM as it is expressed in the <ref
            target="http://erlangen-crm.org">Erlangen</ref> ecrm namespace,<note><title level="a"
              >The Erlangen CRM / OWL</title>, accessed February 22, 2015, <ptr
              target="http://erlangen-crm.org"/>.</note>
          <ref target="http://xmlns.com/foaf/spec/">FOAF</ref>,<note><title level="a">FOAF
              Vocabulary Specification 0.99. Namespace Document 14 January 2014 - Paddington
              Edition</title>, accessed February 22, 2015, <ptr target="http://xmlns.com/foaf/spec/"
            />.</note> and TEI. Semantic interoperability must therefore be ensured on a
          case-by-case basis. For instance, CIDOC-CRM includes only real-world persons in the
          definition of a person, whereas other models, such as TEI and FOAF, include fictitious and
          mythical persons. In FOAF all persons are agents, which is a restriction not found in TEI.
          Thus, all three have something they call <soCalled>person</soCalled> but the
              extensions<note><p>The extension of a word is what it refers to, that is a set of
              things in any real or non-real world that are labelled by that word.</p></note> are
          not identical.</p>
        <p>The semantic openness of the latter method puts different demands on models for
          production than on models for understanding. In a model for production, the openness
          should as far as possible be restricted through the establishment of well-defined
          comparisons between the meanings, at least stating the differences. In a model for
          understanding, on the other hand, this semantic openness may be used as an important part
          of the modeling research, making clearer to the researcher any differences detected in
          attempts to formalize the source material.</p>
        <p>This semantic openness is complex, however. When a group of TEI documents is encoded,
          method C will ensure the same semantic coverage of the elements for all documents. The
          openness is in the link to the external ontology. In method A, no semantic commitment is
          made in the TEI documents. Method B injects the semantic openness into the TEI header, so
          to speak. This may be desirable in certain kinds of modeling for understanding. It is a
          question of where to establish the semantic openness: in the TEI header (B), in the links
          between TEI and other formalisms (C), or in the other formalisms (A). In modeling for
          production the choice should be informed by the question of where in the system at large
          semantic mapping makes the most sense. In modeling for understanding it should be informed
          by the choice of the core area of the experimental modeling, if such a core exists. What
          is the most elegant solution will depend on the aims of the encoder—simply speaking, on
          whether TEI or another formalism is in focus. The world will indeed look different
          depending on which formalism is in focus.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure6">
          <graphic url="images/jtei-8-073-eide_image_06.png" width="1499px" height="518px"/>
          <head type="legend">Integration seen from CIDOC-CRM. DC is Dublin Core, EDD RDBS is a
            local cultural heritage database system at the University of Oslo.</head>
        </figure>
        <p>How would this look if we saw it from the perspective of CIDOC-CRM instead, as in <ptr
            type="crossref" target="#figure6"/>? A TEI document, or a fragment thereof, can be
          modeled as a CIDOC-CRM conceptual object. This can be used to explicitly document elements
          of the CIDOC-CRM model, as we see in <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure7"/>. In this
          example, an event is documented in CIDOC-CRM and the link is made directly to a TEI
            <gi>div</gi> element without using any of the TEI semantic elements.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure7">
          <graphic url="images/jtei-8-073-eide_image_07.png" width="1500px" height="866px"/>
          <head type="legend">A CIDOC-CRM model with a link to a specific element in a TEI document
            as an E84 Information Carrier entity.</head>
        </figure>
        <p> Another solution would be to use a referring string typed as representing an event:
            <tag>rs type="event"</tag>. But seen from an external formalism, this does not really
          matter. In many cases it is even good to be able to link to a document without changing
          its markup, so if references to events are not marked up in the text, linking to another
          element, even if it lacks the relevant semantic baggage, may be a good choice. Using
          mechanisms such as XPointer, one can even link to details within the text of an encoded
          element.</p>
        <p>Another significant point is that seen from the perspective of an external formalism,
          linking to a representation of the event itself in the TEI header (an <gi>event</gi>
          element) may not be a good solution, because the relevant textual documentation may be one
          specific string, not any string in the TEI document referring to the event. The link goes
          to a particular use of a referring string (an <tag>rs type="event"</tag> in the body of
          the TEI document) rather than to a representation of the entity referred to, and it does
          so on purpose. This may, for example, be necessary in order to identify an occurrence of a
          name in the dedication of a poem or in the list of witnesses at the end of a legal
          act.</p>
        <p>So in this interconnected world everyone can be at the center of their own universe, and
          where you stand with respect to which linking method is best depends on where you sit;
          that is, which linking method you prefer depends on the specificities of your task at hand
          and your relationship to other projects or standards. I see two important ways to cope
          with this potentially complex situation from the perspective of the TEI community. One is
          to establish canonical examples of linking out from and into TEI documents. The use of the
            <gi>equiv</gi> element as a tool for specifying semantic similarity is an important part
          of this, making it easier to establish common structures for linking between TEI and other
          formalisms, leading to further interoperability. The other is to make sure that TEI
          documents have sockets for linking to. While XPointers can be used for advanced references
          to any TEI document, an easier and more robust method would be to have <att>xml:id</att>
          attributes available on all elements of published TEI documents, along with stable
          identifiers for the documents themselves. This gives well-defined linking targets, in line
          with best practice in museum documentation.<note>See CIDOC’s <title level="u">Statement on
              Linked Data identifiers for museum objects</title>, accessed May 22, 2014, <ptr
              target="http://network.icom.museum/fileadmin/user_upload/minisites/cidoc/PDF/StatementOnLinkedDataIdentifiersForMuseumObjects.pdf"
            />.</note> These practices may be more crucial in modeling for production than in
          modeling for understanding. However, keeping the semantic room open, as is often a goal in
          modeling for understanding, should not lead to ill-defined linking mechanisms.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="straitjacket">
        <head>How Wide Do You Want Your Straitjacket?</head>
        <p>Standards for digital humanities and cultural heritage information will continue to be
          developed, and even if we develop common concepts for e.g., people and places, those
          concepts will still be developed in the contexts of those separate standards. A person
          referred to in a work of fiction is significantly different from a person referred to in a
          museum documentation system, and the only way of coping with such differences is to
          establish mappings. Mappings do not necessarily have to be done at a document-by-document
          level, but there are limits to how general this level can be. While each separate TEI
          document does not have to be mapped to CIDOC-CRM, one general mapping for all TEI
          documents will not work either. The solution lies somewhere in between.</p>
        <p>Such mapping can be used to close or at least reduce the semantic openness discussed
          above. While such openness is generally accepted as inherent in humanities and culture
          heritage data, we see a clear difference between modeling for production and modeling for
          understanding. In modeling for production, one would typically want to clarify the
          relationships as far as possible, trying to reduce openness in order to make more coherent
          models. In modeling for understanding, such openness may be an important element of the
          research: far from being seen as a problem to be solved, it may be central to the
          experimental modeling. Computer science tends to be solution-oriented in its approach,
          which is in line with what Mahr (<ref type="bibl" target="#mahr09">2009</ref>) calls the
          leading question of computer science.<note>Note that Mahr (<ref type="bibl"
              target="#mahr09">2009</ref>) is a translation of a German article using the term
              <term>Informatik</term>, which in Germany denotes what in English is usually called
            computer science. In the English version of the article, however, the term was
            translated to <term>information science</term>.</note> Thus, modeling for production is
          closer to traditional computer science, and modeling for understanding closer to
          traditional research in the humanities.</p>
        <p>TEI is a system commonly used for text encoding, where documents are directly created in
          TEI XML. This is, however, not its only possible use. TEI is also used as an export format
          for data produced in other systems, such as databases, which can be serialized as TEI XML
          documents. Dictionaries are a typical example. Encoding can be a step on the way towards
          typesetting the dictionary, but also works well as a solution to semantic problems
          connected to long-term preservation. Whether TEI was the production format or not, other
          systems will need access to TEI-encoded data, such as TEI header data for importing into
          library catalogues. The data may be semantic information from the header, like the types
          discussed in this article, or even full TEI documents. This is not limited to the present:
          if TEI is used as a long-term preservation format, then it will be necessary to import
          TEI-encoded data into other formalisms in the future, possibly including future non-XML
          versions of TEI. TEI P5 will not be the encoding system of choice in 2067.</p>
        <p>TEI is a formalism, and like any formalism, it limits what can be said. The scope of TEI
          is wide, but not limitless. One can claim, and I have even done so quite recently (<ref
            type="bibl" target="#eide14">Eide 2014</ref>), that TEI, being based on XML, can become
          too much of a straitjacket. Sometimes even oral language is felt as too restrictive for
          the communication one needs; for example, <q>I could not speak, I just had to give her a
            hug</q>. No formalism works in all situations. Dubin, Senseney, and Jett (<ref
            xml:id="quoteref9" type="bibl" target="#dubin13">2013</ref>) point out that this
          important truth is often hidden in the standards themselves: <quote source="#quoteref9">As
            a result of this trade-off one sees two complementary costs in standards adoption: that
            of relinquishing full control over stipulations to a broader community vs. the
            complexity necessary for generality of scope and flexibility of application. But the
            language of information standards doesn’t lay out this complementarity to their
            audience.</quote></p>
        <p>Different formalisms, however, work at their best in particular applications and for
          specific purposes. The difference between modeling for production and modeling for
          understanding is such a difference. We saw above that Jannidis and Flanders’s distinction
          between altruistic and egoistic modeling fits the distinction between modeling for
          production and modeling for understanding. Their claim that the differences between
          altruistic and egoistic modeling lead to different modeling practices could be followed by
          a claim that they will also lead to different linking practices. Such differences are
          indicated in this article, but a deeper study using real life examples is clearly an
          important area for further research.</p>
        <p>The products of any kind of intellectual and creative work, be they written or not,
          include the potential for future communication. If the work is scholarly, future
          integration with other resources should also be considered. Even when I sit privately in
          my study using modeling to better understand the text I am working on, I have an aim of
          communication, even if it may seem to be in a very distant future. Whether I model for
          production or for understanding, I need to be able to communicate not only my results, but
          also the source material behind them. In such a situation also the lack of formalism can
          be a hindrance to communication. So not only can overly-strict formalisms prevent
          communication, overly-loose formalisms can have a similar effect. We need our
          straitjackets to be just tight enough.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bekiari13"><editor>Bekiari, Chryssoula</editor>, <editor>Martin
              Doerr</editor>, <editor>Patrick Le Bœuf</editor>, and <editor>Pat Riva</editor>, eds.
              <date>2013</date>. <title level="m">FRBR: Object-oriented Definition and Mapping from
              FRBRER, FRAD and FRSAD (version 2.0)</title>. <pubPlace>[Heraklion]</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>International Working Group on FRBR and CIDOC CRM
            Harmonisation</publisher>. Accessed February 22, 2015. <ptr
              target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/docs/frbr_oo//frbr_docs/FRBRoo_V2.0_draft_2013May.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burnard13"><author>Burnard, Lou</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
              level="a">The Evolution of the Text Encoding Initiative: From Research Project to
              Research Infrastructure</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding
              Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>. <ptr target="http://jtei.revues.org/811"/>;
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.4000/jtei.811</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ciula08"><author>Ciula, Arianna</author>, <author>Paul Spence</author>, and
              <author>José Miguel Vieira</author>. <date>2008</date>. <title level="a">Expressing
              Complex Associations in Medieval Historical Documents: The Henry III Fine Rolls
              Project</title>. <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>, no. <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>:
              <biblScope unit="page">311–25</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ciula14"><author>Ciula, Arianna</author>, and <author>Øyvind Eide</author>.
              <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">Reflections on Cultural Heritage and Digital
              Humanities: Modelling in Practice and Theory</title>. In <title level="j">DATeCH ’14:
              Proceedings of the First International Conference on Digital Access to Textual
              Cultural Heritage</title> (May 19–20, Madrid, Spain), <biblScope unit="page"
              >35–41</biblScope>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>ACM</publisher>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.1145/2595188.2595207</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="crofts11"><editor>Crofts, Nick</editor>, <editor>Martin Doerr</editor>,
              <editor>Tony Gill</editor>, <editor>Stephen Stead</editor>, and <editor>Matthew
              Stiff</editor>, eds. <date>2011</date>. <title level="m">Definition of the CIDOC
              Conceptual Reference Model. Version 5.0.4.</title>
            <pubPlace>[Heraklion]</pubPlace>: <publisher>ICOM/CIDOC CRM Special Interest
              Group</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.cidoc-crm.org/docs/cidoc_crm_version_5.0.4.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="dubin13"><author>Dubin, David</author>, <author>Megan Senseney</author>, and
              <author>Jacob Jett</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a">What It Is vs. How We
              Shall: Complementary Agendas for Data Models and Architectures</title>. In <title
              level="m">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2013.</title>
            <series>Balisage Series on Markup Technologies</series>
            <biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.4242/BalisageVol10.Dubin01</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="eideore07"><author>Eide, Øyvind</author>, and <author>Christian-Emil
              Ore</author>. <date>2007</date>. <title level="u">Mapping from TEI to CIDOC-CRM: Will
              the New TEI Elements Make Any Difference?</title> Paper presented at TEI@20: 20 Years
            of Supporting the Digital Humanities. The 20th Anniversary Text Encoding Initiative
            Consortium Members’ Meeting, University of Maryland, College Park, November 1–3. <ptr
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/MembersMeetings/2007/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="eide07"><author>Eide, Øyvind</author>. <date>2007</date>. <title level="a"
              >The Perspective of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>. In <title level="m"
              >Ontology-Driven Interoperability for Cultural Heritage Objects: Working Notes.
              DELOS–MultiMatch Workshop, Tirrenia, Italy, 15 February 2007</title>, edited by
              <editor>Vittore Casarosa</editor> and <editor>Carol Peters</editor>, <biblScope
              unit="page">29–31</biblScope>. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>DELOS/MultiMatch</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.delos.info/files/pdf/DELOS%20Multimatch%202007/papersdelostirrenia.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="eide14"><author>Eide, Øyvind</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a"
              >Sequence, Tree and Graph at the Tip of Your Java Classes</title>. In <title level="u"
              >Digital Humanities 2014: Conference Abstracts</title>, <pubPlace>Lausanne</pubPlace>.
              <ptr target="http://dharchive.org/paper/DH2014/Paper-639.xml"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="gruber09"><author>Gruber, Thomas Robert</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title
              level="a">Ontology</title>. In <title level="m">Encyclopedia of Database
              Systems</title>, edited by <editor>Ling Liu</editor> and <editor>M. Tamer
              Özsu</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">1963–65</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Boston,
              MA</pubPlace>: <publisher>Springer US</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="guarino09"><author>Guarino, Nicola</author>, <author>Daniel Oberle</author>,
            and <author>Steffen Staab</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">What Is an
              Ontology?</title> In <title level="m">Handbook on Ontologies</title>, edited by
              <editor>Steffen Staab</editor> and <editor>Rudi Studer</editor>, <biblScope
              unit="page">1–17</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Springer</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="havemann09"><author>Havemann, Sven</author>, <author>Volker
              Settgast</author>, <author>René Berndt</author>, <author>Øyvind Eide</author>, and
              <author>Dieter W. Fellner</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">The Arrigo
              Showcase Reloaded—Towards a Sustainable Link between 3D and Semantics</title>. <title
              level="j">ACM Journal on Computing and Cultural Heritage</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>, no. <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.1145/1551676.1551680</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="jannidis13"><author>Jannidis, Fotis</author>, and <author>Julia
              Flanders</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a">A Concept of Data Modeling for
              the Humanities</title>. In <title level="m">Digital Humanities 2013: Conference
              Abstracts</title>, <biblScope unit="page">237–39</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>Center for Digital Research in the
              Humanities</publisher>. Available at <ptr
              target="http://dh2013.unl.edu/abstracts/ab-313.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mahr09"><author>Mahr, Bernd</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="a"
              >Information Science and the Logic of Models</title>. In <title level="j">Software
              &amp; Systems Modeling</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>, no. <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>:
              <biblScope unit="page">365–83</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1007/s10270-009-0119-2</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mccarty05"><author>McCarty, Willard</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title
              level="m">Humanities Computing</title>. <pubPlace>Basingstoke</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="ore09"><author>Ore, Christian-Emil</author>, and <author>Øyvind
              Eide</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">TEI and Cultural Heritage
              Ontologies: Exchange of Information?</title>
            <title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>, no. <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>:
              <biblScope unit="page">161–72</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1093/llc/fqp010</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tei01"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2001</date>. <title
              level="m">TEI P4: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange:
              XML-Compatible Edition</title>, edited by <editor>C. M. Sperberg-McQueen</editor> and
              <editor>Lou Burnard</editor>. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>: <publisher>TEI
              Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p4-doc/html/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tei13"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2013</date>. <title
              level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>.
              <edition>Version 2.5.0</edition>. Last updated July 26. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/2.5.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="wittern09"><author>Wittern, Christian</author>, <author>Arianna
              Ciula</author>, and <author>Conal Tuohy</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="a"
              >The Making of Tei P5</title>. <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic
              Computing</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>, no. <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>:
              <biblScope unit="page">281–96</biblScope>. doi: <idno type="doi"
              >10.1093/llc/fqp017</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="zafrin07"><author>Zafrin, Vika</author>. <date>2007</date>. <title level="u"
              >RolandHT, a Hypertext and Corpus Study</title>. PhD diss., Brown University. <ptr
              target="http://rolandht.org/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="zuniga01"><author>Zúñiga, Gloria L.</author>
            <date>2001</date>. <title level="a">Ontology: Its Transformation from Philosophy to
              Information Systems</title>. In <title level="m">FOIS ’01: Proceedings of the
              International Conference on Formal Ontology in Information Systems—Volume
            2001</title>, edited by <editor>Nicola Guarino</editor>, <editor>Barry Smith</editor>,
            and <editor>Christopher Welty</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">187–97</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Ogunquit, Maine</pubPlace>: <publisher>ACM</publisher>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1145/505168.505187</idno>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
