<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-cc-ra-fukushima-162-source.xml 822 2019-09-06 00:42:20Z ron $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Inside <title level="m">Digital Dinah Craik</title>: Feminist Pedagogy,
          Cognitive Apprenticeship, and the TEI</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Kailey</forename>
            <surname>Fukushima</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Kailey Fukushima is a <roleName>master’s student</roleName> in English at
              <orgName>the University of Victoria</orgName>. She earned her bachelor’s degree
            (honors) from <orgName>the University of Calgary</orgName> in 2016. Her research
            interests include Victorian popular literature and culture, food studies, cultural
            studies, and the digital humanities. Kailey was formerly the <roleName>project
              manager</roleName> of <title level="m">Digital Dinah Craik</title>—a digital edition
            of Dinah Craik’s correspondence—and has also worked in <orgName>Special Collections and
              Digitization and Repository Services</orgName> at <orgName>the University of Calgary
              Libraries and Cultural Resources</orgName>. She is currently a <roleName>Research and
              Teaching Assistant</roleName> in <orgName>the University of Victoria’s Department of
              English</orgName>.</affiliation>
          <email>ksfukush@uvic.ca</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Karen</forename>
            <surname>Bourrier</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Karen Bourrier is <roleName>Associate Professor</roleName> of English at
              <orgName>the University of Calgary</orgName>. Her research interests include Victorian
            literature and culture, disability studies, and the digital humanities. She is the
              <roleName>author</roleName> of <title level="m">Victorian Bestseller: The Life of
              Dinah Craik</title> (U Michigan P, 2019) and <title level="m">The Measure of
              Manliness: Disability and Masculinity in Mid-Victorian Fiction</title> (U Michigan P,
            2015). She is <roleName>project director</roleName> of a digital resource peer-reviewed
            by <orgName>NINES</orgName>, <title level="m">Nineteenth-Century Disability: Cultures
              and Contexts</title>, as well as <roleName>PI</roleName> for <title level="m">Digital
              Dinah Craik</title>.</affiliation>
          <email>karen.bourrier@ucalgary.ca</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>14/08/2019</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Janelle Jenstad</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Kathryn Tomasek</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Martin Holmes</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Anne Baillot</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="12">Selected Papers from the 2017 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>TEI 2017 Conference Abstracts.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>correspondence</term>
          <term>feminism</term>
          <term>pedagogy</term>
          <term>digital humanities</term>
          <term>student teaching</term>
          <term>cognitive apprenticeship</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2019-08-28">Ron Van den Branden updated publication date and revision
        description.</change>
      <change when="2019-08-16">Martin Holmes added author corrections.</change>
      <change when="2019-08-15">Martin Holmes added author corrections.</change>
      <change when="2019-08-14">Ron Van den Branden edited the encoding.</change>
      <change when="2019-08-09">Amy Tang encoded the file.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>In this essay, we describe our collaborative work as students and teachers on a TEI
          edition of Dinah Mulock Craik’s correspondence. Inside <title level="m"><ref
              target="http://www.digitaldinahcraikproject.org/">Digital Dinah Craik</ref></title>,
          our pedagogy is collaborative and inclusive, attentive to the material conditions of both
          the text and our labor, and is reproducible. We follow a cognitive apprenticeship model of
          education that emphasizes a community of practice where learners become increasingly
          proficient until, ideally, they are no longer apprentices but genuine collaborators. In
          this paper, we demonstrate how the five stages of apprenticeship learning—modeling,
          approximating, fading, self-directed learning, and generalizing (<ref
            target="#hansman2001" type="bibl">Hansman 2001, 47</ref>)—help us to foster what
          scholars such as Anne Balsamo, Elizabeth Losh, Jacqueline Wernimont, Laura Wexler, and
          Hong-An Wu call the <quote source="#quoteref1">foundational ethical principles</quote>
            (<ref xml:id="quoteref1" target="#balsamo2011" type="bibl">Balsamo 2011, 162–3</ref>)
          and <quote source="#quoteref15">feminist virtues</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref15"
            type="bibl" target="#losh2016">Losh et al. para. 26</ref>) of collaboration—confidence,
          humility, flexibility, integrity, and intellectual generosity.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="acknowledgements">
        <p>We would like to acknowledge and thank the past and present members of the <title
            level="m">Digital Dinah Craik</title> project: Hannah Anderson, Keila Aleman, Alyson
          Bennett, Will Best, Sidney Cunningham, Jaclyn Carter, Aaron Ellsworth, Kerry-Leigh Fox,
          Kylee-Anne Hingston, Christie Hurrell, Sonia Jarmula, Kelsey Jacobi, Sarah Kent, Elizabeth
          Ludlow, Janice Parker, Zainub Rahman, Ingrid Reiche, Pippa Ruddy, Lecia Givogue Stevenson,
          and Lindsey Stewart. At the University of Calgary, we would like to thank John Brosz and
          Paul Pival in Libraries and Cultural Resources for their assistance with data
          visualization and querying our data set. Finally, we would like to thank the audience at
          the 2017 TEI-C Conference and Members’ Meeting in Victoria, BC, and the anonymous referees
          of the jTEI for their helpful suggestions for this paper.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="introduction">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>Women writers hoping to succeed in Victorian England had a long apprenticeship to
          undertake. The informal elements of their apprenticeship often included writing
          extensively for periodicals, networking at those literary salons which welcomed women, and
          sometimes even moving to London to be closer to opportunities in the literary world (<ref
            target="#shattock2015" type="bibl">Shattock 2015, 29–31</ref>). The popular Victorian
          writer Dinah Craik pursued all these avenues in her literary apprenticeship. Her career
          path was similar to the way in which a contemporary graduate student might seek
          opportunities to publish first on professional blogs then in journals, to network and
          collaborate at conferences and on digital humanities projects, and to move to another city
          to pursue an advanced degree. In the apprenticeship model of education—which pays
          attention to the ways in which doing real, hands-on work can help transform students into
          professionals—we find an apt theoretical explanation for both the careers of successful
          Victorian writers like Craik, and for our own work on a TEI edition of her
          correspondence.</p>
        <p>In this essay, we describe our work as students and teachers on a TEI edition of Dinah
          Mulock Craik’s correspondence. We argue that an apprenticeship model of education helps us
          to build a collaborative and inclusive model of pedagogy, one which is attentive to the
          material conditions of both the text and our labor, and is reproducible. According to
          Catherine Hansman, who writes about teaching adult literacy, <quote source="#quoteref14"
            >paying attention to the interaction and intersection among people, tools, and context
            within a learning situation</quote> is essential to learning in context (<ref
            xml:id="quoteref14" type="bibl" target="#hansman2001">2001, 44</ref>). We find that this
          cognitive apprenticeship model helps us to involve students in a complex TEI research
          project while fostering what scholars such as Anne Balsamo, Elizabeth Losh, Jacqueline
          Wernimont, Laura Wexler, and Hong-An Wu call the <quote source="#quoteref101">foundational
            ethical principles</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref101" target="#balsamo2011" type="bibl"
            >Balsamo 2011, 162–3</ref>) and <quote source="#quoteref1501">feminist virtues</quote>
            (<ref xml:id="quoteref1501" type="bibl" target="#losh2016">Losh et al. para. 26</ref>)
          of collaboration—confidence, humility, flexibility, integrity, and intellectual
          generosity. In this paper, we demonstrate how the five stages of apprenticeship
          learning—modeling, approximating, fading, self-directed learning, and generalizing (<ref
            target="#hansman2001" type="bibl">Hansman 2001, 47</ref>)—help us to turn research
          assistants into collaborators.</p>
        <p>We approach the apprenticeship model of education through a feminist pedagogical lens.
          Following earlier work in feminist pedagogy, we hope to demonstrate how an apprenticeship
          model of education can join the ranks of feminist teaching practices that aim to de-center
          the patriarchal and hierarchical models of authority that prevail in traditional
              classrooms.<note><p>See <ref target="#cohee1998" type="bibl">Cohee et al.</ref>, <ref
                type="bibl" target="#maher2001">Maher and Tetrault</ref>, and <ref
                target="#crabtree2009" type="bibl">Crabtree, Sapp, and Licona</ref>.</p></note>
          Feminist pedagogy is a branch of critical pedagogy, and owes much to Brazilian educator
          Paolo Freire’s argument against hierarchical teaching practices. In <title level="m"
            >Pedagogy of the Oppressed</title>, Freire writes that many learning environments follow
          a <quote source="#quoteref11"><soCalled>banking</soCalled> concept of education</quote>
            (<ref xml:id="quoteref11" type="bibl" target="#freire2018">2018, 72</ref>). Within this
          model, <quote source="#quoteref111">individuals cannot be truly human</quote> because
          teachers treat learners as receptacles for knowledge rather than as active participants in
          intellectual processes (<ref xml:id="quoteref111" type="bibl" target="#freire2018">Freire
            2018, 72</ref>). Feminist pedagogy rejects this hierarchical model of education and
            <quote source="#quoteref10">situate<supplied>s</supplied> learning as a collaborative
            rather than top-down process</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref10" type="bibl"
            target="#deSantis2015">De Santis and Serafini 2015, 64</ref>). A feminist pedagogical
          model recognizes humanity and difference within the classroom, and attends to the fact
          that learners have diverse individual and social experiences that are historically
          situated, embodied, affective, and material (<ref target="#losh2016" type="bibl">Losh et
            al. 2016, para 4</ref>). Although the apprenticeship model of education begins from a
          traditional binary of teacher and learner and is not explicitly feminist, it aims to
          empower learners at each step of their education, and thus it gradually works toward
          building a non-hierarchical community of practice.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="DinahCraik">
        <head>Dinah Craik and Literary Apprenticeship</head>
        <p>The apprenticeship model of pedagogy mirrors Dinah Craik’s experience as a woman writer
          in nineteenth-century London. In the 1840s, she served what we might term <soCalled>a
            literary apprenticeship</soCalled> writing stories for literary magazines. As Sally
          Mitchell writes, Craik <quote source="#quoteref17">forged ahead <gap/>through the streets
            and into the editors’ offices, placing a poem here, a story there, an article elsewhere,
            making her contracts, learning her craft and grinding out the words</quote> (<ref
            type="bibl" target="#mitchell1983" xml:id="quoteref17">1983, 9</ref>). At the height of
          her apprenticeship, she wrote <quote source="#quoteref1701">five-thousand-word stories
            every two or three weeks</quote>, placing them in weekly magazines or monthly journals
            (<ref xml:id="quoteref1701" target="#mitchell1983" type="bibl">Mitchell 1983, 9</ref>).
          Craik began to learn her craft in the social and material context of periodical
          publishing, working with feedback from magazine editors and other writers to improve
          before taking on a three-volume novel. Her success culminated with the publication of her
          fifth novel, <title level="m">John Halifax, Gentleman</title>, a rags-to-riches tale that
          tells the story of an orphan who becomes a Captain of Industry with nothing but his head
          and his own two hands. <title level="m">John Halifax, Gentleman</title> was popular on
          both sides of the Atlantic, and was widely read until around World War II. Craik’s own
          story was very different; far from learning on her own, she continued to be deeply
          indebted to the social and material contexts of nineteenth-century publishing as she
          learned her own craft as a writer.</p>
        <p>Despite her tremendous popularity, today we know very little about Dinah Craik beyond her
          published work. Our project, <title level="m"><ref
              target="http://www.digitaldinahcraikproject.org/">Digital Dinah Craik</ref></title>,
          seeks to digitize her unpublished manuscript correspondence using methods developed by the
          TEI community. Over one thousand letters and fourteen years of Craik’s diaries exist in
          archives across the U.S. and the U.K.: most importantly the Mulock Family Papers at UCLA,
          the Craik collection in the Harry Ransom Center at the University of Texas at Austin, and
          the Parrish Collection of Victorian novelists at Princeton University. The letters include
          unpublished correspondence to Victorian luminaries including <ref
            target="http://tapasproject.org/digitaldinahcraik/files/letter-dinah-mulock-craik-elizabeth-barrett-browning-18-december-1856"
            >Elizabeth Barrett Browning</ref> and <ref
            target="http://tapasproject.org/digitaldinahcraik/files/letter-dinah-mulock-craik-oscar-wilde-17-july-1887"
            >Oscar Wilde</ref>, as well as personal correspondence to her brother in the Crimea and
          her father in the Staffordshire Insane Asylum. These letters are important not only
          because they shed light on the career of an important and well-connected author as well as
          on the Victorian era in general, but because of what they can tell us about the venues,
          types of publications, and networks of connection that could sustain a nineteenth-century
          woman writer’s career for upwards of forty years.</p>
        <p>Our work in creating a digital edition of Craik’s letters joins the efforts of feminist
          scholars to make difficult-to-access manuscript correspondence of nineteenth-century women
          writers widely available. While codex projects like the Pilgrim edition of <title
            level="m">The Letters of Charles Dickens</title>, which comprises twelve volumes and was
          edited over almost fifty years (from 1965 to 2002), or <ref target="#haight1954"
            type="bibl">Gordon S. Haight</ref>’s monumental nine-volume edition of <title level="m"
            >The George Eliot Letters</title> (edited from 1954 to 1978), have made the letters of
          canonical Victorian authors widely available, one of the challenges of working on popular
          nineteenth-century writers has been the lack of access to their correspondence. For the
          most part, the letters of popular women writers remain in manuscript only, and have often
          not even been quoted in scholarship, leaving us with a lack of contextual information
          about the lives and careers of these popular writers. Letters such as Dinah Craik’s have
          much to tell us about the working conditions of popular women writers, from how they
          negotiated their book contracts to how much they were paid for work in periodicals or
          volume form. Moreover, they can help us to shine light on the affective communities and
          networks of support that empowered women writers such as Dinah Craik to maneuver in the
          gendered landscape of the Victorian publishing industry.</p>
        <p>Many of the influential projects in Victorian studies in the digital humanities have
          focused on canonical male authors, including the <title level="m"><ref
              target="http://www.blakearchive.org/">William Blake Archive</ref></title> and Jerome
          McGann’s <title level="m"><ref target="http://www.rossettiarchive.org/">The Rossetti
              Archive</ref></title>. As <ref target="#stone2012" type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref22"
            >Marjorie Stone and Keith Lawson</ref> point out, many of the <quote
            source="#quoteref22">large scale single-author digital projects on nineteenth-century
            literature</quote> that scholars have identified as exemplary <quote
            source="#quoteref22">feature traditionally canonical white male writers</quote>; one of
          the problems that scholars working on non-canonical writers face is that they must often
          accomplish the <quote source="#quoteref2201">foundational tasks of reinterpreting and
            editing</quote>, which may leave little time <quote source="#quoteref2201">to seize the
            opportunities that digital technologies provide</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref2201"
            type="bibl" target="#stone2012">2012, 112–113</ref>). As Beshero-Bondar and Raisanen
          point out, in contrast to digital humanities projects focusing on male writers, <quote
            source="#quoteref3">a <soCalled>more is more</soCalled> approach has structured the
            major, lasting digital projects that address women writers. This collective
            comprehensiveness in the scale of such projects would seem pointedly to counteract a
            more mainstream <soCalled>digital turn</soCalled> in archival development, which has
            been accumulating a data-rich stock of the dominant western literary canon, individual
            writer by individual writer</quote> (<ref target="#beshero-Bondar2017" type="bibl"
            xml:id="quoteref3">2017, 740</ref>). Beshero-Bondar’s project, <title level="m"><ref
              target="https://digitalmitford.org/">Digital Mitford</ref></title>, demonstrates how
          the intensive study of a single non-canonical author can reveal <quote
            source="#quoteref301">social networks <supplied>that</supplied> highlight the people and
            contexts important to establishing a strong reputation in periodical publishing and
            theatrical production</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref301" type="bibl"
            target="#beshero-Bondar2017">Beshero-Bondar and Raisanen 2017, 746</ref>). Indeed, this
          situation is changing as scholars are editing and digitizing women writers simultaneously,
          demonstrating in the process the way that digital tools like the TEI can help us to carve
          out a space to reinterpret these authors and their works.</p>
        <p>Ten years after the completion of <title level="m">The Rossetti Archive</title> in 2008,
          an increasing number of digital humanities scholars are allocating their time and labor
          towards making the writing of women writers accessible.<note><p>The Complete Writings and
              Pictures of Dante Gabriel Rossetti: A Hypermedia Archive, accessed February 27, 2018,
                <ptr target="http://www.rossettiarchive.org/"/>.</p></note> Charlotte Mitchell,
          Ellen Jordan and Helen Schinske have worked to make the complete correspondence of Craik’s
          contemporary, the novelist Charlotte Yonge, available for the first time, with the hope
          that the digital edition will provide a <quote source="#quoteref18">substantial foundation
            of facts for the study of her fiction, her historical and educational writing and her
            journalism, and help to illuminate her biography and also her significance in the
            cultural and religious history of the Victorian age</quote> (<ref target="#mitchellC"
            type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref18">Mitchell, Jordan, and Schinske,
              n.d.</ref>).<note><p>Letters of Charlotte Mary Yonge, accessed February 27, 2018, <ptr
                target="https://c21ch.newcastle.edu.au/yonge/"/>.</p></note> Liz Stanley’s XML
          edition of <title level="m"><ref target="https://www.oliveschreiner.org/">The Olive
              Schreiner Letters Online</ref></title> aims to make over five thousand of the late
          Victorian novelist’s letters available.<note><p>The Olive Schreiner Letters Online,
              accessed February 27, 2018, <ptr target="https://www.oliveschreiner.org/"
            />.</p></note> Most influentially for our project, Elisa Beshero-Bondar’s aforementioned
            <title level="m">Digital Mitford Project</title> uses TEI standards to digitize the
          correspondence of Mary Russell Mitford, aiming to <quote source="#quoteref2">freely and
            fully publish</quote> over two thousand letters <quote source="#quoteref2">previously
            available only in manuscript form in obscure archives or in bowdlerized published
            forms</quote> (<ref target="#beshero-Bondar2018" xml:id="quoteref2" type="bibl"
            >Beshero-Bondar 2018</ref>).</p>
        <p>In addition to following the TEI Guidelines for encoding correspondence, we concentrate
          our efforts on tagging the people, places, organizations, and publications mentioned in
          Craik’s letters. Ultimately, we hope that this careful contextual encoding will help us
          uncover the epistolary networks that could bolster a woman writer’s career; however, the
          first step in our project is to undertake the labor-intensive process of transcribing and
          encoding the letters themselves. In the next section, we outline the origins of our
          project, paying particular attention to the material and economic conditions that underpin
          our work.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="projectBackground">
        <head>Project Background</head>
        <p>The first context for our project was the classroom. <title level="m">Digital Dinah
            Craik</title> began in Karen Bourrier’s Winter 2015 grad seminar on <q>Digitizing Women
            Writers</q>, where ten graduate students transcribed and encoded thirty letters, and
          worked together to develop our first encoding guidelines. Because of the amount of
          training involved, it became advisable to involve research assistants who would be able to
          work on the project for longer than a semester. We found ourselves faced with what Susan
          Brown et al. describe as the <quote source="#quoteref5">fairly basic choice</quote> in
          digital humanities projects between <quote source="#quoteref5">greater complexity and a
            fairly tight-knit group of collaborators, and lesser complexity and a more open
            collaborative model</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref5" type="bibl" target="#brown2006"
            >2006, 324</ref>) and considered that our project fell within the former camp. Because
          of the relative complexity of the project, we tend to draw research assistants from
          Bourrier’s upper-level undergraduate Victorian literature courses. Thus, to begin with,
          team members on the project are already in their third or fourth year of an English
          degree, and have some background in Victorian literature, which they can bring to a
          project that combines nineteenth-century history, paleography, and the TEI.<note><p>We are
              currently developing an ODD file, but worked without one for the first three years on
              this project as we developed our encoding standards. (We do check that
                <att>xml:id</att>s, the place that coders are most prone to error, are correct using
              a schematron file, modeled on the one for <title level="m">Digital Mitford</title>
              which Elisa Beshero-Bondar generously shared with us.) In part because we hire a small
              number of research assistants who have shown themselves to be meticulous in their term
              work, we find that our project members adhere for the most part to the tagset that we
              have defined in the Digital Dinah Craik codebook and do not need to be regulated by a
              prescriptive schema. We manually identify misused and unexpected tags when we check
              each other’s encoding, and we discuss alterations and additions to our tagset as a
              group.</p></note></p>
        <p>The choice to encode the letters at a level of relatively greater complexity and to work
          with students over a longer period of time rather than over a single semester has been
          enabled by the funding our project received. Two main streams of funding made our work
          possible: internal grants from the University of Calgary, and an external grant from SSHRC
          (the Social Science and Research Council of Canada). In terms of internal funding, two of
          our research assistants, Kailey Fukushima and Hannah Anderson, won University of Calgary
          research awards that allow undergraduates to work full-time with a professor over the
          summer. These PURE awards (Program for Undergraduate Research) pay students between C$3000
          and C$6000 depending on the number of weeks they work full-time on a project. The PURE
          awards have been helpful in supplementing the funding pool available for our project. But
          they also allow our undergraduate researchers to practice writing grant proposals, and
          enable them to bring their own funding and research interests to <title level="m">Digital
            Dinah Craik</title>. This, in turn, helps to decenter the economic power dynamics of our
          working group—providing an alternative to a traditional research project model, where all
          funding would flow through the principal investigator.</p>
        <p>We were also fortunate to procure a SSHRC Insight Development Grant, which enabled us to
          hire research assistants during the semester. Over the summer of 2017, we transitioned
          from a classroom model, where graduate students received credit for participating in the
          project, to a lab-based model, where undergraduate and graduate research assistants are
          paid to work on <title level="m">Digital Dinah Craik</title> in a collaborative
          environment for three hours a week. In our digital humanities lab, which took place in a
          room equipped with large screens and Wi-Fi in our campus library, the Taylor Family
          Digital Library, new research assistants interact with more experienced project members
          using the tools of the trade—computers equipped with an oXygen licence—in order to learn
          the basics of paleography, TEI, and prosopography.</p>
        <p>Although we may have been able to take on a smaller TEI project, as Bourrier did in her
          classroom, without this level of funding, securing internal and external funding for
            <title level="m">Digital Dinah Craik</title> has helped us to make great strides in our
          project. Funding has allowed us to hire students full-time on the project, and to buy
          oXygen licenses for all research assistants on the project.<note><p>At the beginning of
              each new work term, we check in with our project members to ask if they have access to
              laptops or if we should book weekly time in one of the University of Calgary’s
              computer labs. Thus far, we have been able to rely on our personal laptops, but we
              recognize that it is problematic to assume this will be the norm for our future
              collaborators. The University of Calgary Libraries and Cultural Resources has recently
              opened a collaborative digital workspace called LabNEXT, and in the future we plan to
              address this issue by booking desktop computers equipped with oXygen
            licenses.</p></note> We currently have over three hundred letters published on TAPAS,
          with another one hundred and eighteen that are close to completion. In the remainder of
          this paper, we will outline how the apprenticeship model of education has helped us to
          reach this stage in our collaborative work.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="apprenticeship">
        <head>Apprenticeship Learning and the TEI</head>
        <div xml:id="modeling">
          <head>Modeling</head>
          <p>The first stage in the cognitive apprenticeship model of education is modeling, which
            Hansman writes takes place in two ways: <list rend="inline ordered">
              <item><quote source="#quoteref1402">Behavioural modeling</quote>, where learners watch
                  <quote source="#quoteref1402">experienced members of a community</quote> perform
                an action, and</item>
              <item><quote source="#quoteref1402">Cognitive Modeling</quote>, where experienced
                practitioners explain how the activity is done (<ref xml:id="quoteref1402"
                  target="#hansman2001" type="bibl">2001, 47</ref>).</item>
            </list><note><p>Hansman’s widely cited article takes the cognitive apprenticeship model
                of learning and its stages from <ref target="#brandt1993" type="bibl">Barbara
                  LeGrand Brandt, James A. Farmer, Jr., and Annette Buckmaster</ref>’s 1993 article,
                  <title level="a">Cognitive Apprenticeship Approach to Helping Adults
                  Learn.</title></p></note> We find TEI templates and a lab-based model where
            immediate feedback and coaching is available to be essential for success in the modeling
            stage.</p>
          <p>We also argue that modeling has been essential to the success of the TEI community in
            general, as our project has benefited from the modeling of other projects. Before
            beginning work on <title level="m">Digital Dinah Craik</title>, Bourrier served in what
            we might term <soCalled>a cognitive apprenticeship</soCalled> on <title level="m">The
              Digital Mitford Project</title>. Elisa Beshero-Bondar,
            <!-- [RvdB] changed "the" to "that" in order to make the reference to The Digital Mitford Project more clear -->that
            project’s PI, has generously made their models—a codebook and TEI template—open-access.
            We took the template for Mitford’s letters as our starting point, and we now train
            students using a similar template that we have developed for <title level="m">Digital
              Dinah Craik</title>.</p>
          <p>We begin with cognitive modeling and textual encoding on a macro-level. In the first
            session, our goal is to get students to bring the knowledge they already have about what
            letters are and how they work into conversation with the idea of markup. Research
            assistants begin their training with a brief overview of what the TEI is, its
            vocabulary, and why we use it. Next, we ask students to brainstorm what the formal
            elements of a letter are: visually, how do you know that a document is a letter rather
            than a sonnet or a play? Research assistants quickly respond that letters typically have
            an address, a date, and a signature, among other formal features. We next show students
            how we would tag the formal features that they have identified. We open our TEI letter
            template and explain the macro-level structure of a TEI letter in order to familiarize
            research assistants with the functions of the <gi>teiHeader</gi>, <gi>respStmt</gi>, and
            the <gi>opener</gi>, body paragraphs, <gi>closer</gi>, and <gi>postscript</gi>. We would
            emphasize that this presentation is short, about ten minutes, and quickly moves to
            behavioral modeling as we demonstrate how we would encode an actual letter. As a group,
            we walk new project members through the template using text from a previously
            transcribed letter. We ask them, based on their knowledge of how letters work, where
            they think lines such as <q>My dear friend</q>, and <q>Lynover Cottage, Kilburn.
              London</q> would go in our template, and they are quick to suggest <gi>opener</gi> and
              <gi>dateline</gi> as the correct containers for these lines. We explain our process
            and reasoning to the group along the way, combining behavioral and cognitive
            modeling.</p>
          <p>As we model our TEI practice, we move inward from larger structures of correspondence
            to the smaller structures. After we have worked our way through macro-level encoding,
            our next step is to explain contextual encoding. We introduce our use of contextual tags
            such as <gi>persName</gi>, <gi>placeName</gi>, <gi>title</gi>, and <gi>orgName</gi>, and
            explain how we use <att>ref</att> attributes to link tags to specific <att>xml:id</att>s
            in our TEI prosopography. After this presentation, the group returns to the encoded
            letter and we ask new research assistants whether they see any people or places
            mentioned in the body of the letter. Once again, students are able to pick out names
            such as <q>Elizabeth Barrett Browning</q> and places like <q>Italy</q> quite quickly; we
            move from straightforward examples to potentially trickier ones. Picking out Elizabeth
            Barrett Browning’s <title level="m">Aurora Leigh</title> as the title of a book, for
            example, requires either some previous knowledge about Victorian literature or reading
            contextual clues in the letter, as when Craik refers to it as <quote source="#quoteref8"
              >the completest Poem, if not one of the grandest books, that any woman ever
              wrote</quote> (<ref target="#craik1856" type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref8">Craik
              1856</ref>). As a group, we work our way through a single letter, tagging all mentions
            of people, places, book titles, and organizations and point them towards their
            respective entries in the prosopography. All in all, the process of modeling our
            encoding process takes about thirty to forty-five minutes, and we try to ask as many
            questions as possible to involve students in the learning, and to have them apply the
            everyday knowledge that they already have about letters and letter-writing to the new
            arena of encoding.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="approximating">
          <head>Approximating</head>
          <p>Research assistants move from modeling to encoding their own letter within the first
            lab-session, and thereby enter the approximating stage of the apprenticeship model of
            education. In this stage, learners <quote source="#quoteref1403">try out the activity
              while articulating their thoughts about what they plan to do and why</quote> and then
            reflect on the process (<ref xml:id="quoteref1403" type="bibl" target="#hansman2001"
              >Hansman 2001, 47</ref>). After more experienced project members model encoding, all
            project members are assigned a subset of previously transcribed letters to work with on
            their own. At this point, we hand out hard copies of our <ref
              target="https://github.com/kbourrier/DigitalCraik"><title level="m">Digital Dinah
                Craik</title> codebook</ref>—a live catalog of our project standards and tagset—so
            that research assistants have a physical guide to follow along with.<note><p>Our Digital
                Dinah Craik Codebook is available for download on our project GitHub at <ptr
                  target="https://github.com/kbourrier/DigitalCraik"/>.</p></note> We find that
            giving new research assistants print copies of our otherwise digital codebook helps to
            eliminate toggling between oXygen and the codebook, and allows them to focus on the task
            of encoding.</p>
          <p>When working with undergraduate research assistants, we begin with short letters that
            Bourrier has already transcribed in her time in the archives to focus on the encoding
            alone. We start and end each lab session by talking about how our work is going and what
            types of encoding errors are coming up. This type of discussion and reflection is key to
            students’ learning. In fact, perhaps the largest unanticipated problem with our learning
            model is overcoming students’ shyness. The three new research assistants Bourrier hired
            for the Winter 2017 semester were all quiet students who preferred to work on their own,
            to the extent that they would try to figure out an encoding error on their own for
            twenty minutes rather than asking for help. We tried to address this issue by modeling
            discussion and by checking in periodically. In the future, we plan to break up the
            initial encoding checks and require new research assistants to share their work in three
            stages—structure, context, and then prosopography.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="fading">
          <head>Fading</head>
          <p>As research assistants gain competence in their apprenticeship, the next step is to
            take away some of the scaffolding as they begin to work independently. This is what
            Hansman identifies as the fading process, as <quote source="#quoteref1404">scaffolding
              and other support gradually decrease as learners’ abilities increase</quote> (<ref
              xml:id="quoteref1404" target="#hansman2001" type="bibl">47</ref>). After undergraduate
            research assistants encode approximately ten transcribed letters over the course of
            around half a dozen three-hour lab meetings, we challenge them to work on the
            transcription and encoding of a longer and more complex letter. This task takes place
            within the supportive environment of the lab, where research assistants can continue to
            ask questions about difficult words, research strategies for people mentioned in the
            letters that did not show up in the <title level="m">Oxford Dictionary of National
              Biography</title>, and TEI errors. Some research assistants go on to do this work
            independently in a full-time capacity.</p>
          <p>For many research assistants, fading is the most difficult phase of the apprenticeship.
            Research assistants typically have no experience in the TEI or in reading
            nineteenth-century handwriting, and yet they are tasked with producing near-perfect
            encoded transcriptions of handwritten letters in order to prepare them for scholarly
            publication. The initial results can be messy, but we have learned to embrace mess as a
            key learning and teaching opportunity, and to accept it as a key aspect of our praxis.
            For, as Elizabeth Losh, Jacqueline Wernimont, Laura Wexler, and Hong-An Wu remind us,
            embracing <quote source="#quoteref1504">messiness</quote> is a feminist act that helps
            us to counteract <quote source="#quoteref1504">popular notions of digital media as neat,
              clean, and hyper-rational</quote> instead of subjective, situated, and material (<ref
              xml:id="quoteref1504" type="bibl" target="#losh2016">2016, para 8</ref>). The fading
            phase also requires research assistants to develop a deep familiarity with our TEI
            prosopography—they learn how to navigate an expansive TEI file using some basic XPath as
            well as how to conduct and encode research according to our project standards.
            Initially, each RA uses oXygen on their own computer. Simultaneously, we use whiteboards
            to compile a list of prosopography entries that are being developed in real time.
            Because we tend to all work on one archival collection at a time, the same people often
            turn up in multiple research assistants’ letters, and we must collate information from
            each letter as we work to prevent duplication. This model encourages new research
            assistants to query each other’s transcriptions while also working together to
            contribute to the project.</p>
          <p>The fading phase, while difficult and often long, builds necessary research skills,
            encourages collaborative scholarship, and fosters confidence and independence. Part of
            the difficulty inherent in this phase of apprenticeship stems from the high demands of
            our TEI prosopography. We aim to encode all <gi>person</gi> entries with the same level
            of detail regardless of how well-known the person mentioned in the letter is. This means
            that our research assistants put significantly more time and labor into researching
            women, families, and the working classes—people whose lives are not necessarily detailed
            in traditional scholarly sources such as the <title level="m">Oxford Dictionary of
              National Biography</title>. And this, in our view, is good.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="selfDirectedlearning">
          <head>Self-Directed Learning</head>
          <p>It is often our project members’ complex work in the TEI prosopography that shifts them
            to the next phase of apprenticeship, self-directed learning. Students working on the
            project have been highly successful (and creative) in pursuing contextual research
            combining nineteenth-century newspaper and genealogical databases. We would add that the
            TEI itself also affords multiple opportunities for self-directed learning. In lab
            sessions, we always emphasize that our encoding practices are flexible, and we encourage
            research assistants to query our encoding practices as they gain independence in the
            project. Any proposals for amendments, additions, or deletions are presented, discussed,
            and agreed upon via consensus in our group lab sessions.</p>
          <p>Kailey Fukushima’s work on <title level="m">Digital Dinah Craik</title> exemplifies
            this phase of the apprenticeship model of education. Fukushima began working on the
            project as an advanced undergraduate, and she became deeply interested in the TEI,
            following current discussions on the TEI listserv and GitHub repository issue tickets,
            and thinking critically of alternative encoding practices. After a year and a half of
            working on the project, she prompted the team to make several changes to the original
            tags. At Fukushima’s behest, we changed the values of the <att>sex</att> attribute in
            our TEI prosopography from the numerical ISO standards to more descriptive value
            options—M, F, and U for unknown, with alternative options for confirmed intersex,
            non-binary, or transgender people. This amendment helped us to address the false
            hierarchy in the ISO standards where 1 is male and 2 is female; however, as <ref
              type="bibl" target="#hannesschläger2017">Vanessa Hannesschläger and Peter
              Andorfer</ref> point out in <title level="a"><ref
                target="https://hcmc.uvic.ca/tei2017/abstracts/t_100_hannesschlager_andorfer_gender.html"
                >Having Sex in the TEI: The TEI 2016 Gender Check</ref></title>, this change does
            not reflect the fact that we are actually encoding the gender of historical people and
            not their biological sex. Fukushima also suggested that we add a <gi>residence</gi> tag
            with the datable attributes <att>from</att> and <att>to</att> to our <gi>person</gi>
            entries. This allows us to track and document Craik’s many home addresses and will help
            future research assistants to provide more accurate date range estimates for undated
            letters. Following the July 2017 release of the TEI 3.2.0 (Telstar) Guidelines,
            Fukushima suggested that we add the new <att>type</att> attributes to
              <gi>occupation</gi> tags to distinguish the many nineteenth-century creative types who
            listed other <soCalled>official</soCalled> professions in census reports. In these
            cases, Fukushima identified a shortcoming in our available tags, turned to the TEI
            Guidelines and community for solutions, and then proposed changes at our weekly lab
            discussion. This kind of self-directed learning is encouraged of all research
            assistants—it helps them become more fluent in the affordances of TEI, fosters their
            integrity as collaborators, and works towards our group’s ultimate aim of
            non-hierarchical intellectual generosity.</p>
          <p>At this point in their apprenticeship, we encourage research assistants to consider
            applying for additional training opportunities. Bourrier budgets Digital Humanities
            Summer Institute (DHSI) funding for research assistants into grant applications so that
            our project members have the opportunity to expand their knowledge of TEI outside of the
            context of <title level="m">Digital Dinah Craik</title>. We ask project members who
            attend workshops, seminars, or conferences to teach the team any relevant skills they
            learned upon their return. This kind of self-directed learning opportunity is positioned
            to benefit early-career scholars by providing them with hands-on learning and teaching
            experiences. It also encourages us to practice generosity and humility in our
            scholarship, and to recognize ourselves as a community of learners as well as a
            community of practice.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="generalizing">
          <head>Generalizing</head>
          <p>The final step in the apprenticeship model of education is generalizing. In this phase,
            students take on more leadership roles and are asked to start teaching their skills to
            new project members. Some of the students who work on <title level="m">Digital Dinah
              Craik</title> will go on to develop their own projects in the digital humanities. And,
            if they stay on the project team, they are encouraged to query our dataset with their
            own research questions. But we hope that all the students who work on this project have
            gained greater competence and confidence with digital tools and the way that they relate
            to their English degrees. We have already seen two undergraduate research assistants use
            their experience on <title level="m">Digital Dinah Craik</title> to gain full-time
            employment as digitization assistants in Libraries and Cultural Resources at the
            University of Calgary. While this role does not require experience in TEI specifically,
            former research assistants who have taken on this role report that working on a digital
            humanities project gave them the confidence needed to know they could learn new digital
            tools and techniques. Supervisors in Libraries and Cultural Resources similarly report
            that the attention to detail and critical thinking that students learn working on a TEI
            project like <title level="m">Digital Dinah Craik</title> gives them the skills that
            they need to work as digitization assistants in the library.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="reflection">
        <head>Reflection and Conclusions</head>
        <p>As we reflect on our pedagogy and praxis, we are aware that this project has limitations.
          Getting research assistants to the final two stages of the apprenticeship model of
          education, those of self-directed learning and generalization, is difficult and does not
          happen in all cases. Geoffrey Rockwell and Stéfan Sinclair note that digital humanities
          projects working with an apprenticeship model raise the real issue of how to <quote
            source="#quoteref20">gracefully correct and encourage quality</quote> in student work.
          They write that apprenticeship <quote source="#quoteref20">is a very different
            relationship than marking an assignment that has no real purpose beyond
            assessment</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref20" target="#rockwell2014" type="bibl">2014,
            198 n32</ref>). To put this in practical terms, Bourrier can confirm that it is much
          easier to give a student a B+ on a paper that shows effort and promise than it is to send
          back multiple TEI letters that show effort and promise but must be perfect for
          publication.</p>
        <p>A related challenge has been getting students to be critical of other project members’
          encoding and transcription, and of Bourrier’s in particular. To address this issue, we
          have had discussions as a team about what it means to prepare a scholarly edition for
          digital publication. But research assistants are understandably apt to presume that the
          work of more experienced project members is correct. To foster a spirit of critical
          inquiry and collegiality, we plan to implement a rule that everyone must query at least
          three points of transcription or encoding in every letter, no matter whether the professor
          or the newest undergraduate on the project has done the work.</p>
        <p>Despite these challenges, the fact that this project is ultimately meant for publication,
          and that we do publish finished letters on the TEI Archiving Publishing and Access Service
          (TAPAS) as we go, can also be tremendously encouraging for students and research
          assistants. Students in Bourrier’s graduate class, as well as undergraduate research
          assistants, are able to add the letters they have transcribed and encoded as some of the
          first publication lines on their CVs, and many research assistants also gain valuable
          teaching experience as they mentor new students on a project.</p>
        <p>In sum, a feminist collaboration combined with the cognitive apprenticeship model has
          worked well for our project and has allowed us to decenter our power dynamics. Jacqueline
          Wernimont raises an important point when she notes that <quote source="#quoteref23">in
            most digital scholarly projects, collaboration is happening between a small set of
            trained graduate students, faculty, and IT and library staff</quote> (<ref
            xml:id="quoteref23" type="bibl" target="#wernimont2013">2013, para 19</ref>). She
          acknowledges that the material and economic conditions of labor in the academy have an
          impact on the size of the collaborative group, but questions whether we are <quote
            source="#quoteref2301">keeping non-professional users out of production to protect both
            academic privilege and the status of the traditional archive</quote> and whether we
          should <quote source="#quoteref2301">be looking to feminist digital literary projects to
            push the possibilities of decentering even further</quote> (<ref target="#wernimont2013"
            type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref2301">2013, para 19</ref>). Our pedagogy and praxis in
            <title level="m">Digital Dinah Craik</title> prepares undergraduate and graduate
          students to take on a real role in determining our encoding practices as well as the
          future of the project.</p>
        <p>Finally, we find that we have started to create a community of practice that is
          relatively easy for others, such as students, librarians, and community members, to join.
          Over the course of our project, two librarians, Christie Hurrell, Digital Initiatives and
          Scholarly Communication Librarian, and Ingrid Reiche, Metadata Librarian, have joined our
          regular meetings to keep up their TEI skills while contributing to a live project, and
          they have had much to contribute to our knowledge base as well. We have also had a member
          of the Calgary community, Alyson Bennett, join our meetings to contribute her knowledge of
          genealogy and to research the people mentioned in the letters. While the advent of the
          internet and laptop computers have made it possible for students and faculty members alike
          to do more of their work remotely, we find that moving the research process back into the
          university, and into the library in particular, and having a physical meeting at the same
          time and in the same place on a weekly or monthly basis, makes the work that we are doing
          more visible to the community and helps us accomplish our research goals.</p>
        <p>We think that the apprenticeship model is one that Dinah Craik would have approved of; in
          fact, it was a model that she seemed to follow in her own professional writing life. Craik
          benefited from the mentorship of more established women writers, such as Anna Maria Hall,
          early in her career, and she energetically mentored both men and women artists and writers
          once she was an established writer. Many of the letters we are digitizing give examples of
          concrete help she offered writers early on in their career in negotiating with editors and
          publishers. She wrote to the editor of a prestigious literary magazine, <title level="j"
            >The Cornhill</title>, offering a story by one of her young friends, and praising the
          publication for <quote source="#quoteref9">its introduction of new young names instead of
            worn out old ones—which is always a success</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref9" type="bibl"
            target="#craik1883">Craik 1883</ref>). One friend of Craik’s remembered her as <quote
            source="#quoteref19">the natural confidant, adviser, patron saint of girls, from the
            time when she was little older than her devotees</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref19"
            target="#oliphant1887" type="bibl">Oliphant 1887, 84</ref>). Thus far, most of the team
          members working on our project have identified as women, and most have been initially
          intimidated by the technological aspects of the project. By the end of the apprenticeship
          process, however, most project members report that it is actually the handwriting and the
          research on nineteenth-century people and places that are the most difficult part of the
          project, not the technical aspects of the TEI. It is our hope that working step-by-step
          through the five stages of apprenticeship will help us build and maintain an inclusive
          feminist collaborative through which students can gain competence and confidence as
          digital humanities researchers.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="balsamo2011"><author>Balsamo, Anne</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title
              level="a">Designing Learning: The University as a Site of Technocultural
              Innovation</title>. In <title level="m">Designing Culture: The Technological
              Imagination at Work</title>, <biblScope unit="page">133–183</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Durham</pubPlace>: <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>. <ptr
              target="https://doi.org/10.1215/9780822392149-005"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="beshero-Bondar2018"><author>Beshero-Bondar, Elisa</author>.
              <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">Methods and Practice</title>. <title level="m"
              >Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>. Last modified
              <date>February 27, 2018</date>. <ptr target="http://digitalmitford.org/about.html"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="beshero-Bondar2017"><author>Beshero-Bondar, Elisa</author>, and
              <author>Elizabeth Raisanen</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">Recovering
              from Collective Memory Loss: the Digital Mitford’s feminist project</title>. <title
              level="j">Women’s History Review</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">738–750</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="https://doi.org/10.1080/09612025.2016.1166882"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="brandt1993"><author>Brandt, Barbara LeGrand</author>, <author>James. A.
              Farmer, Jr.</author>, and <author>Annette Buckmaster</author>. <date>1993</date>.
              <title level="a">Cognitive Apprenticeship Approach to Helping Adults Learn</title>.
              <title level="j">New Directions for Adult and Continuing Education</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">59</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">69–78</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="brown2006"><author>Brown, Susan</author>, <author>Patricia
            Clements</author>, and <author>Isobel Grundy</author>. <date>2006</date>. <title
              level="a">Sorting things in: Feminist knowledge representation and changing modes of
              scholarly production</title>. <title level="j">Women’s Studies International
              Forum</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">317–325</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wsif.2006.04.010"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="cohee1998"><author>Cohee, Gail E.</author>, <author>Elisabeth
              Daumer</author>, <author>Theresa D. Kemp</author>, <author>Paula M. Krebs</author>,
              <author>Sue A. Lafky</author>, and <author>Sandra Runzo</author>. <date>1998</date>.
              <title level="m">The Feminist Teacher Anthology: Pedagogies and Classroom
              Strategies</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Teachers College
              Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="crabtree2009"><editor>Crabtree, Robbin D.</editor>, <editor>David Alan
              Sapp</editor>, and <editor>Adela C. Licona</editor>, eds. <date>2009</date>. <title
              level="m">Feminist Pedagogy: Looking Back to Move Forward</title>.
              <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>: <publisher>Johns Hopkins University
            Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="craik1856"><author>Craik, Dinah Mulock</author>. <date>1863</date>. <title
              level="a">Letter to Elizabeth Barrett Browning. December 18, 1856</title>. <title
              level="m">Digital Dinah Craik</title> on TAPAS. <ptr
              target="http://tapasproject.org/digitaldinahcraik/files/letter-dinah-mulock-craik-elizabeth-barrett-browning-18-december-1856"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="craik1883"><author>Craik, Dinah Mulock</author>. <date>1883</date>. <title
              level="a">Letter to James Payn, October 29, 1883</title>. <title level="m">Digital
              Dinah Craik</title> on TAPAS. <ptr
              target="http://tapasproject.org/digitaldinahcraik/files/letter-dinah-mulock-craik-james-payn-29-october-1883"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="deSantis2015"><author>De Santis, Carm</author> and <author>Toni
              Serafini</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title level="a">Classroom to Community:
              Reflections on Experiential Learning and Socially Just Citizenship</title>. In <title
              level="j">Feminist Pedagogy in Higher Education: Critical Theory and Practice</title>,
            edited by <editor>Tracy Penny Light</editor>, <editor>Jane Nicholas</editor>, and
              <editor>Renée Bondy</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">59–75</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Waterloo</pubPlace>: <publisher>Wilfrid Laurier University
            Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="freire2018"><author>Freire, Paulo</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title
              level="m">Pedagogy of the Oppressed</title>. <edition>50th Anniversary ed</edition>.
            Translated by Myra Bergman Ramos. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Bloomsbury</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="haight1954"><author>Haight, Gordon</author>. <date>1954–1978</date>. <title
              level="m">The George Eliot Letters</title>, <biblScope unit="volume">vol.
              1–9</biblScope>. <pubPlace>New Haven</pubPlace>: <publisher>Yale University
              Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hannesschläger2017"><author>Hannesschläger, Vanessa</author>, and
              <author>Peter Andorfer</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">Having Sex in the
              TEI: The TEI 2016 Gender Check</title>. Presentation at the TEI-C Conference,
            Victoria, BC, Nov. 11–15, 2017. <ptr
              target="https://hcmc.uvic.ca/tei2017/abstracts/t_100_hannesschlager_andorfer_gender.html"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hansman2001"><author>Hansman, Catherine</author>. <date>2001</date>. <title
              level="a">Context-Based Adult Learning</title>. <title level="j">New Directions for
              Adult and Continuing Education</title>, <biblScope unit="issue">89</biblScope>:
              <biblScope unit="page">43–52</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >doi:10.1002/ace.7</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="losh2016"><author>Losh, Elizabeth</author>, <author>Jacqueline
              Wernimont</author>, <author>Laura Wexler</author>, and <author>Hong-An Wu</author>.
              <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">Putting the Human Back into the Digital
              Humanities: Feminism, Generosity, and Mess</title>. In <title level="m">Debates in the
              Digital Humanities</title>, edited by <editor>Matthew K. Gold</editor> and
              <editor>Lauren F. Klein</editor>. <ptr
              target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/61"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="maher2001"><author>Maher, Frances A.</author>, and <author>Mary Kay Thomson
              Tetrault</author>. <date>2001</date>. <title level="m">The Feminist Classroom:
              Dynamics of Gender, Race, and Privilege</title>. <edition>Expanded ed</edition>.
              <pubPlace>Lanham</pubPlace>: <publisher>Rowman &amp; Littlefield</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mitchell1983"><author>Mitchell, Sally</author>. <date>1983</date>. <title
              level="m">Dinah Mulock Craik</title>. <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>: <publisher>Twayne
              Publishers</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mitchellC"><author>Mitchell, Charlotte</author>, <author>Ellen
              Jordan</author> and <author>Helen Schinske</author>. <date>n.d.</date>. <title
              level="m">Letters of Charlotte Yonge</title>. <ptr
              target="https://c21ch.newcastle.edu.au/yonge/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="oliphant1887"><author>Oliphant, Margaret</author>. <date>1887</date>. <title
              level="a">Mrs. Craik</title>. <title level="j">Macmillan’s Magazine</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">57</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">81–85</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="rockwell2014"><author>Rockwell, Geoffrey</author> and <author>Stéfan
              Sinclair</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">Acculturation and the Digital
              Humanities Community</title>. In <title level="m">Digital Humanities Pedagogy:
              Practices, Principles, and Politics</title>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >177–211</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Open Book
              Publishers</publisher>. <ptr target="http://books.openedition.org/obp/1635?lang=en"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="shattock2015"><author>Shattock, Joanne</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title
              level="a">Becoming a Professional Writer</title>. In <title level="m">The Cambridge
              Companion to Victorian Women’s Writing</title>, edited by <editor>Linda
              Peterson</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">29–42</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Cambridge University
            Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="stone2012"><author>Stone, Marjorie</author> and <author>Keith
              Lawson</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a"><q>One Hot Electric Breath</q>:
              EBB’s Technology Debate with Tennyson, Systemic Digital Lags in Nineteenth-Century
              Literary Scholarship, and the EBB Archive</title>. <title level="j">Victorian
              Review</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">101–125</biblScope>. doi: <idno type="DOI">doi:
              10.1353/vcr.2012.0001</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="wernimont2013"><author>Wernimont, Jacqueline</author>. <date>2013</date>.
              <title level="a">Whence Feminism? Assessing Feminist Interventions in Digital Literary
              Archives</title>. <title level="j">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>). <ptr
              target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000156/000156.html"/>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
