<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-cc-ra-flanders-176-source.xml 962 2020-05-19 22:32:54Z ron $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">TEI Pedagogy and TAPAS Classroom</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Julia</forename>
            <surname>Flanders</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Julia Flanders is a <roleName>professor</roleName> of the practice in English
            and the <roleName>director</roleName> of <orgName>the Digital Scholarship
              Group</orgName> in <orgName>the Northeastern University Library</orgName>. She also
            directs the <title level="m">Women Writers Project</title> and serves as
              <roleName>editor in chief</roleName> of <title level="j">Digital Humanities
              Quarterly</title>, an open-access, peer-reviewed online journal of digital humanities.
            She has served as <roleName>chair</roleName> of <orgName>the TEI Consortium</orgName>
            and as <roleName>President</roleName> of <orgName>the Association for Computers and the
              Humanities</orgName>. Her research interests focus on data modeling, textual
            scholarship, humanities data curation, and the politics of digital scholarly work. She
            is the <roleName>co-editor</roleName>, with Neil Fraistat, of <title level="m">The
              Cambridge Companion to Textual Scholarship</title>, and is also the
              <roleName>co-editor</roleName>, with Fotis Jannidis, of <title level="m">The Shape of
              Data in Digital Humanities: Modeling Texts and Text-based
            Resources</title></affiliation>
          <email/>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Syd</forename>
            <surname>Bauman</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Syd Bauman is the <roleName>Senior XML Programmer/Analyst</roleName> at
              <orgName>the Northeastern University Digital Scholarship Group</orgName>. Syd has been
            interested in descriptive markup since the mid-1980s, and in the TEI since he first
            thumbed through a copy of TEI P1.1 in 1990. He served as the <roleName>North American
              Editor</roleName> of the TEI from 2001 through 2007, and currently serves on
              <orgName>the TEI Council</orgName>.</affiliation>
          <email/>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Ashley</forename>
            <surname>Clark</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Ashley M. Clark is the <roleName>XML Applications Developer</roleName> for
              <orgName>the Northeastern University Library’s Digital Scholarship Group</orgName>.
            She builds and maintains digital ecosystems for TEI-based projects, including TAPAS and
            the <title level="m">Women Writers Project</title>.</affiliation>
          <email/>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Benjamin</forename>
            <surname>Love (Doyle)</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Benjamin J. Love (Doyle) is a <roleName>PhD candidate</roleName> in English
            at <orgName>Northeastern University</orgName>. His dissertation focuses on the
            intersections of human rights, extra-national subjectivity, and literature in the
            nineteenth-century Atlantic world.</affiliation>
          <email/>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Scott</forename>
            <surname>Hamlin</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Scott Hamlin is <roleName>co-founder</roleName> and
              <roleName>co-Director</roleName> of the TAPAS Project. He is also the
              <roleName>Director</roleName> of <orgName>Educational Technology and Support Services
              in Information Technology</orgName> at <orgName>Stonehill College</orgName>, where he
            oversees educational technology, media technology, and end user support. He has taught
            workshops on the use of TEI and TAPAS and regularly co-teaches digital humanities
            classes to undergraduates.</affiliation>
          <email/>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>William</forename>
            <surname>Quinn</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>William Quinn is a <roleName>PhD Candidate</roleName> in the English
            Department at <orgName>Northeastern University</orgName>. He worked as the
              <roleName>TAPAS Project Coordinator and Liaison</roleName> between 2017–2019. His
            research attends to the intersection of literary history, digital humanities, and
            periodical studies.</affiliation>
          <email/>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>14/08/2019</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Janelle Jenstad</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Kathryn Tomasek</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Martin Holmes</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Anne Baillot</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="12">Selected Papers from the 2017 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>TEI 2017 Conference Abstracts</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>pedagogy</term>
          <term>TAPAS</term>
          <term><ptr type="software" xml:id="R100" target="#xslt"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R100"
              >XSLT</rs></term>
          <term>validation</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2019-08-28">Ron Van den Branden updated publication date and revision
        description.</change>
      <change when="2019-08-26">Martin Holmes entered editorʼs proofing corrections.</change>
      <change when="2019-08-14">Ron Van den Branden edited the encoding.</change>
      <change when="2019-08-13">Martin Holmes edited the encoding.</change>
      <change when="2019-07-05">Amy Tang encoded the file.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>This paper focuses on recent work by the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R1"
          target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R1">TEI Archiving, Preservation, and Access Service
            (TAPAS)</rs> on pedagogy with TEI, and specifically on a recent initiative called
            <soCalled><ptr type="software" xml:id="R2" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R2">TAPAS</rs> Classroom</soCalled> focused on exploring pedagogical uses of TEI. We
          provide some background on <ptr type="software" xml:id="R3"
            target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R3">TAPAS</rs>, describe several case studies involving pedagogical
          partners who used <ptr type="software" xml:id="R4" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R4">TAPAS</rs> in teaching, and finally describe the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R5" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R5">TAPAS</rs> Classroom initiative
          and its outcomes.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="introduction">
        <head>Introduction and Background</head>
        <p><ref target="http://www.tapasproject.org"><ptr type="software" xml:id="R6"
          target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R6">TAPAS</rs></ref><note><p><rs type="soft.url" ref="#R6"><ptr
            target="http://www.tapasproject.org"/></rs>.</p></note> originated with the needs of
          humanities scholars and specifically with the rise (in the first decade of the
          twenty-first century) of scholarly interest in text encoding as a core humanities method.
          With expertise supported by the proliferation of text encoding workshops aimed at
          humanists, such scholars were typically not affiliated with large established projects but
          were often working independently on small, monograph- or article-scale projects, such as
          an edition of a single text, a small collection of manuscripts, or a small run of a local
          periodical. As already noted in a previous article (<ref target="#flanders2013"
            type="bibl">Flanders and Hamlin 2013</ref>), infrastructure for TEI publication was at
          that time (and still remains to some extent) challenging for individual scholars and small
          projects, because of the costs and logistics of maintaining servers, developing and
          supporting <ptr type="software" xml:id="R7" target="#xslt"/><rs type="soft.name"
            ref="#R7">XSLT</rs> stylesheets, and maintaining technical expertise for
          troubleshooting and longer term support. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R8"
            target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R8">TAPAS</rs> was developed to provide an alternative in
          the form of a web-based service for publishing TEI data. It offers a growing
          infrastructure of TEI publishing tools, a publishing venue that highlights the value of
          using TEI, and a long-term guarantee of visibility and access to the TEI data. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R9"
            target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R9">TAPAS</rs> was
          originally hosted at Brown University and is now hosted at Northeastern University, which
          also provides a guarantee of long-term repository support for <ptr type="software" xml:id="R10"
            target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R10">TAPAS</rs> data. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R11"
              target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R11">TAPAS</rs> has been
          generously funded by the TEI Consortium and by an initial planning grant from the
          Institute for Museum and Library Services, a digital humanities startup grant from the
          NEH, a research and development grant from the NEH, and most recently a digital humanities
          advancement grant which has supported <ptr type="software" xml:id="R12" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R12">TAPAS</rs> Classroom.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="tapasClassroom">
        <head><ptr type="software" xml:id="R13" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R13">TAPAS</rs> Classroom and TEI Pedagogy</head>
        <p>What do we envision when we think of TEI <soCalled>in the classroom</soCalled>? Three
          scenarios are particularly prominent. The first involves <emph>students contributing to
            TEI projects</emph>. Many faculty who lead TEI projects seek to involve students in
          those projects, either as part of a formal course or workshop, or through internships or
          paid positions. Here the term <soCalled>classroom</soCalled> may be quite literal, but it
          also may entail a broader range of pedagogical activities whereby students learn on the
          job. For the students, learning TEI may be an important and useful outcome (if they are
          interested in working on TEI projects or pursuing a TEI project of their own), but it may
          also be just one piece of a larger learning experience centering around the creation,
          management, and publication of digital materials. A second scenario involves
            <emph>students experimenting with TEI encoding</emph> in (digital) humanities courses or
          short workshops which aim to introduce them to the concepts of text markup. Here, TEI may
          be most valuable as an approachable form of data modeling that uses familiar concepts and
          terminology, and that usefully demonstrates the separation of data modeling from data
          presentation. In these situations, the goal is not to create high-quality TEI files or to
          give the students a thorough grounding in the TEI vocabulary but rather to stimulate
          thought and discussion using TEI as a stimulus. A third scenario involves <emph>students
            creating their own TEI projects</emph> in digital humanities courses or humanities
          courses, often as a substantial assignment in which the student selects, transcribes,
          encodes, and contextualizes one or more texts. Here, even though TEI skills may be only
          one part of a larger goal of acquainting students with digital humanities project planning
          and publishing tools, the sustained nature of the undertaking means that students will
          have an opportunity to gain familiarity with TEI, and that they may produce TEI data of
          enduring value. <ptr target="#table1" type="crossref"/> summarizes the potential learning
          outcomes in each of these scenarios. <table xml:id="table1">
            <head>Learning outcomes</head>
            <row role="label" rows="1" cols="1">
              <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
              <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">Learning general data concepts</cell>
              <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">Learning TEI vocabulary</cell>
              <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">Learning TEI practices and context</cell>
              <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">Create TEI data of value</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
              <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">Contribute to existing project</cell>
              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Yes</cell>
              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Yes</cell>
              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Maybe</cell>
              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Yes</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
              <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">Experiment with TEI in DH classroom</cell>
              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Yes</cell>
              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Maybe</cell>
              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">No</cell>
              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">No</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
              <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">Develop own project</cell>
              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Yes</cell>
              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Yes</cell>
              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Maybe</cell>
              <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Maybe</cell>
            </row>
          </table> During the development of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R14" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R14">TAPAS</rs> Classroom, several scholars were already
          experimenting with using <ptr type="software" xml:id="R15" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R15">TAPAS</rs> pedagogically. The following case studies describe how
          these different scenarios played out in practice.</p>
        <div xml:id="scenario1">
          <head>Scenario 1: A Course Designed Around Student Participation in a Faculty Research
            Project.</head>
          <p>Karen Bourrier, Digital Dinah Craik (<ptr target="http://www.tapasproject.org/node/443"
            />)</p>
          <p>Karen Bourrier is a faculty member at the University of Calgary and has been using
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R16" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R16">TAPAS</rs> for her project, <title level="m">Digital Dinah Craik</title>; a presentation at
            TEI 2017 by her research assistant and project editor Kailey Fukushima described the
            project’s work in detail. This project includes close to four hundred TEI files
            organized into six distinct collections. The project team includes a rotating group of
            undergraduate and graduate students who typically have no TEI experience when they start
            work, and who transcribe, encode, and add enhanced markup to each text as it proceeds
            through the project’s workflow. They are trained to encode in TEI/XML (using the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R87"
              target="#oxygen"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R87">Oxygen
                XML editor</rs>) and to use <ptr type="software" xml:id="R17" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R17">TAPAS</rs> once a completed text is ready to publish. Professor
            Bourrier’s pedagogical objectives for the course include professionalization of students
            through involvement in long-term digital projects, and engaging students in
            collaborative relationships with faculty and scholars in their field. (Kailey Fukushima
            reported that <ptr type="software" xml:id="R18" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R18">TAPAS</rs> publication constituted a useful addition to students’ CVs.)
            Practically speaking, because of the students’ lack of prior experience with TEI, it was
            important to have easy-to-use tools so that students could focus on concepts and gain
            fluency, thereby streamlining the process of training students to work on the
            project.</p>
          <p>Professor Bourrier’s pedagogical experimentation with <ptr type="software" xml:id="R19" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R19">TAPAS</rs> yielded several specific
            design considerations. First, a close linkage between process and outcome is valuable in
            motivating students and focusing their effort, so a workflow that permits immediate
            publication (and in which the concept of <soCalled>publication</soCalled> and the
            criteria for readiness are in the control of the instructor) has pedagogical value.
            Second, to support work in collaborative teams the publishing platform has a role to
            play in reinforcing the students’ sense of working as a team, through actions like
            sharing and reviewing draft work, being able to track progress towards a final
            publication goal, and being able to communicate with other team members through comments
            and discussion.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="scenario2">
          <head>Scenario 2: Student Experimentation with TEI as Part of a Larger Digital Humanities
            Course</head>
          <p>Mackenzie Brooks, Washington and Lee University (DH 190 Scholarly Text Encoding (winter
            2015) <ptr target="http://www.tapasproject.org/node/439"/> with schedule at <ptr
              target="http://tei.academic.wlu.edu/​dh-190-w15/​schedule/"/>; and DH 190 Scholarly
            Text Encoding (winter 2016) <ptr
              target="http://www.tapasproject.org/dh-190-scholarly-text-encoding-w16"/> with
            schedule at <ptr target="http://tei.academic.wlu.edu/dh-190-w15/schedule/"/>)</p>
          <p>Mackenzie Brooks is an assistant professor and digital humanities librarian at
            Washington and Lee University, who used <ptr type="software" xml:id="R20" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R20">TAPAS</rs> in two iterations of a one-credit
              <soCalled>lab</soCalled> course on scholarly text encoding with TEI, accompanying a
            course in French literature taught by Professor Stephen P. McCormick. The course covered
            the origins and theoretical orientations of text markup, document analysis, schema
            creation, encoding, and publication, and also provided students with a grounding in the
            technical skills necessary to create a digital edition as part of the work they were
            doing in the accompanying literature class. Working in groups, students created simple
            digital editions focused on a specific text drawn from the university’s rare book and
            manuscript collection.</p>
          <p>As Brooks reported in a paper that described this course in detail (<ref
              target="#brooks2017" type="bibl">Brooks 2017</ref>), digital humanities at Washington
            and Lee University has a strongly pedagogical focus, and this course was an experimental
            contribution to a discussion of what a DH course or indeed an entire DH curriculum might
            look like. Framing the digital component as a one-credit <soCalled>lab</soCalled>
            course, taught by library faculty, offered a way to integrate digital approaches more
            flexibly into the curriculum without creating a burden for disciplinary faculty. In this
            context, a platform like <ptr type="software" xml:id="R21" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R21">TAPAS</rs> enables the instructors to focus on the challenges of
            teaching text encoding and to reduce the technical overhead for both students and
            instructors so that questions relating to editorial theory and practice and literary
            interpretation can come to the fore.</p>
          <p>Constance Crompton and Michelle Levy, Simon Fraser University (<title level="m">Lyrical
              Ballads</title>, <ptr target="https://lyricalballadssfu.wordpress.com/"/>).</p>
          <p>Connie Crompton is a faculty member at the University of Ottawa (at the time of the
            course, she was at UBC Okanagan). She worked with a course that was taught by Michelle
            Levy at Simon Fraser University and focused on creating a digital edition of
            Wordsworth’s and Coleridge’s <title level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title>. In this case, all
            of the students collaborated on a single edition rather than working on their own. <ptr
              type="software" xml:id="R22" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R22"
              >TAPAS</rs> was one of a range of tools the class experimented with, along with
            visualization tools like <ptr type="software" xml:id="R88" target="#tableau"/><rs
              type="soft.name" ref="#R88">Tableau</rs>, publication tools like <ptr type="software"
              xml:id="R89" target="#islandora"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R89">Islandora</rs>, and
            text analysis with <ptr type="software" xml:id="R90" target="#r"/><rs type="soft.name"
              ref="#R90">R</rs>. Part of the design of the course was thus to experiment with the
            encoded TEI data through a plurality of tools and to produce a plurality of outcomes.
            This pedagogical orientation reinforces one of the core tenets (and challenges) of <ptr
              type="software" xml:id="R23" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R23"
              >TAPAS</rs>’s design, which is to avoid creating orthodoxies in TEI encoding arising
            from display outcomes that appear authoritative. The diversification of view packages in
              <ptr type="software" xml:id="R24" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R24"
              >TAPAS</rs>, and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R25" target="#tapas"/><rs
              type="soft.name" ref="#R25">TAPAS</rs>’s role as one of many possible venues for
            publishing and displaying TEI data, can help encourage students of TEI to focus on the
            informational strength of their encoding rather than solely on the appearance of the
            output.</p>
          <p>Mary Isbell, University of New Haven, Digital Editing Projects (Spring 2016; materials
            are private)</p>
          <p>Mary Isbell is a faculty member at the University of New Haven, where she has been
            experimenting with building a program of digital humanities pedagogy using TEI. In
            spring 2016 she taught a course on Digital Editing, in which her ten undergraduate
            students created individual digital TEI editions which were published in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R26" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R26">TAPAS</rs> as a
            private collection visible only to members of the project. The course was aimed at
            English majors with no encoding background, with a central learning goal of developing
            students’ skill in XML and TEI. It also attracted students from History and
            Communications. Here, as with Brooks’s course described above, having students create
            individual editions of their own design was an important focus and was closely aligned
            with the technical and conceptual skill of modeling textual data through text encoding.
            Treating the encoding process as a scholarly activity rather than a simple textual
            exercise aligns with core principles of digital humanities pedagogy articulated in
            articles such as <title level="a">A Tale of Two Internships: Developing Digital Skills
              Through Engaged Scholarship</title> (<ref target="#hswe2017" type="bibl">Hswe et al.
              2017</ref>), and also serves to empower students as both tool-users and creators of
            cultural meaning. Isbell noted that the ability to see their work realized as a readable
            edition was a crucial motivator for students in pushing through the process of learning
            and debugging their TEI/XML encoding. Because <ptr type="software" xml:id="R27" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R27">TAPAS</rs> was in beta when Isbell ran the
            course, she resourcefully integrated bug discovery and reporting explicitly into the
            course, so that students had some exposure to the processes of digital humanities tool
            development and had a sense of participation in that process—an unintended but very
            positive outcome.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="scenario3">
          <head>Scenario 3: TEI Pedagogy as Part of a Student-Led Project</head>
          <p>Doyle Calhoun and Anna Kijas, Boston College, Missionary Linguistics in Colonial
            Africa, <ptr
              target="http://www.tapasproject.org/missionary-linguistics/missionary-linguistics"/>,
              <ptr target="http://corpus-missionnaire.bc.edu"/>, <ptr
              target="https://library.bc.edu/newsletter/?p=28"/></p>
          <p>The <title level="m">Missionary Linguistics</title> project is part of an undergraduate
            thesis project undertaken by Doyle Calhoun with support from Anna Kijas, the Senior
            Digital Scholarship Librarian at Boston College. For this project, Calhoun encoded a
            proof-of-concept segment of a nineteenth-century dictionary, together with
            proof-of-concept authority lists for persons, organizations, and historical places.
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R28" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R28">TAPAS</rs> served as the data repository for the encoded files, which were also published
            through a project web site that included an interactive map using <ptr type="software" xml:id="R91"
              target="#carto"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R91">CartoDB</rs>.<note><p>For a
                more detailed account of the project, see <ref target="#kijas2016" type="bibl">Kijas
                  (2016)</ref>.</p></note> In addition to the outcomes for Calhoun’s own degree
            program and professional development, Kijas had some larger pedagogical objectives from
            the perspective of her digital humanities center: to involve non-faculty (library and DH
            center staff) in student teaching and student research, at both undergraduate and
            graduate level, and to introduce and support TEI as part of an institution-level
            initiative.</p>
          <p>Although supporting student-led research was not on the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R29" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R29">TAPAS</rs> project’s radar as a very
            likely usage scenario during the initial planning and design process for <ptr type="software" xml:id="R30" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R30">TAPAS</rs>
            Classroom, it is an important outcome that underscores the potential benefits of having
            access to <ptr type="software" xml:id="R31" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R31">TAPAS</rs> at the institutional level (i.e., as a benefit of TEI institutional
            membership). From the perspective of the library, one important feature of the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R32" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R32">TAPAS</rs>
            service is that it provides a low-cost but durable infrastructure easy for novices to
            master. From the perspective of the student researcher, the important features are the
            longevity and stability of the data (enabling continuity of the project through
            successive institutional moves) as well as ease of use.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="goals">
        <head>Goals and Desiderata</head>
        <p>Based on these experiments, the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R33" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R33">TAPAS</rs> development team set several important design goals
          for the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R34" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R34">TAPAS</rs> Classroom project, in supporting pedagogy with TEI: <list>
            <item><emph>Make the process easier</emph>: For faculty who teach with TEI (either for
              its own sake or as part of a larger course in digital humanities or humanities), some
              supporting infrastructure is needed. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R35" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R35">TAPAS</rs> can ideally streamline or eliminate the
              process of getting access to shared server space, setting up student accounts, and
              ensuring that data is stored safely and can be accessed after the course is over.
              These functions are valuable for instructors at all levels of technical expertise but
              are particularly enabling for instructors familiar with TEI but not with its
              supporting technologies (<ptr type="software" xml:id="R36" target="#xslt"/><rs
                type="soft.name" ref="#R36">XSLT</rs>, XML databases, web publishing
              frameworks).</item>
            <item><emph>Expose and demystify</emph>: The tool experimentation we saw in the <title
                level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title> course and in Mary Isbell’s Digital Editing course
              suggested the value of a publication system that makes it possible to see the
              publication apparatus as such, and to look under the surface: for instance by offering
              different stylesheets and viewing options and showing that the formatted display of
              TEI is independent of the underlying encoding. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R37" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R37">TAPAS</rs> can offer a multiplicity of
              viewing options and an interface that makes it easy to move between them, enabling
              students to make direct comparisons between different ways of handling the data and
              offering a clear causal view in which changes to the data have a visible effect on the
              output (thereby motivating students to experiment with the markup in greater
              detail).</item>
            <item><emph>Support the encoding</emph>: In these scenarios, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R38" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R38">TAPAS</rs> was used as an
              end-point and a publication venue, but it is clear that there is pedagogical value in
              user-friendly TEI tools earlier in the classroom narrative as well. Mary Isbell, for
              instance, noted the potential value of student-level error messages, and Karen
              Bourrier observed how students learned from their encounter with the workflow
              management aspects of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R39" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R39">TAPAS</rs>. Through user-friendly validation, interactive ways to
              inspect the TEI encoding, and other ways for students to explore their encoding in
              progress from many perspectives, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R40" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R40">TAPAS</rs> has potential value as a source of approachable
              information that can inform the encoding process.</item>
          </list> Under <ptr type="software" xml:id="R41" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R41">TAPAS</rs> Classroom, several major new pieces of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R42" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R42">TAPAS</rs> were developed that
          respond to these desiderata. First, we developed new stylesheets for viewing TEI files,
          aimed specifically at pedagogical uses; this grant also gave us an opportunity to develop
          a fully modular system for managing these <soCalled>view packages</soCalled> (about which
          more below). Second, we re-examined the ways in which validation functions in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R43" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R43">TAPAS</rs>, and
          began developing tools that present validation to students in a specifically pedagogical
          context rather than as part of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R44" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R44">TAPAS</rs>’s own data management systems. Third, we developed a
          set of sample and template files to serve as starting points for students, recognizing
          that in short courses where the goal is to get students quickly oriented in a new skill
          (as for instance in the Crompton example described above), it could be helpful to have
          some pre-established starting points that are well contextualized and self-explanatory.
          And finally, we developed a <soCalled>community workshops</soCalled> space within <ptr type="software" xml:id="R45" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R45">TAPAS</rs>
          that simplifies the process of setting up a teaching environment, aimed particularly at
          instructors teaching shorter workshops that may be repeated over time. In what follows, we
          focus on two components in particular: the view packages and our initial forays into
          thinking about validation.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="viewPackages">
        <head>View Packages</head>
        <p>The display of TEI files through the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R46" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R46">TAPAS</rs> interface is handled—as with almost all modern
          web display of TEI data—through <ptr type="software" xml:id="R47" target="#xslt"/><rs
            type="soft.name" ref="#R47">XSLT</rs> stylesheets, and indeed one of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R48" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R48">TAPAS</rs>’s most
          important functions is to enable users to transform and view their TEI data without having
          to write or run <ptr type="software" xml:id="R49" target="#xslt"/><rs type="soft.name"
            ref="#R49">XSLT</rs> on their own. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R50" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R50">TAPAS</rs>’s <ptr type="software" xml:id="R51"
            target="#xslt"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R51">XSLT</rs> stylesheets do not operate in
          isolation but as part of a more complex <soCalled>view package</soCalled> that includes
          several distinct components: <list>
            <item>One or more <ptr type="software" xml:id="R52" target="#xslt"/><rs
                type="soft.name" ref="#R52">XSLT</rs> stylesheets which transform the source TEI
              data into another format (typically XHTML but potentially JSON or other formats that
              are particularly suited to some viewing application)</item>
            <item>A CSS stylesheet that provides styling information</item>
            <item>Optional <ptr type="software" xml:id="R53" target="#javascript"/><rs
                type="soft.name" ref="#R53">JavaScript</rs> code to produce features of user
              interactivity (such as mouse-overs or selection of specific viewing options)</item>
            <item>Optional <ptr type="software" xml:id="R92"
              target="#xproc"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R92">XProc</rs> code which handles the sequential processing of the data by the
              individual components of the view package</item>
            <item>Optional RELAX NG or ISO Schematron files that formalize any specific data
              constraints required by the view package (for instance, a view package for displaying
              a bibliography might include a test to ascertain that the file contains a
                <gi>listBibl</gi>)</item>
            <item>Metadata about the view package that supports its use within the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R54" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R54">TAPAS</rs>
              system</item>
            <item>Supporting documentation of the view package, including a manifest that describes
              its components and the expectations concerning the kinds of data for which it is best
              suited</item>
          </list> Typically, each view package is oriented around a specific usage scenario, user
          community, or type of data, and offers some options for user choices and configuration
          that are appropriate for that scenario. For instance, a view package might focus on the
          display of heavily revised manuscripts and might offer readers the ability to view
          successive revision stages or choose which revisers’ work to make visible. (This interface
          is not currently available in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R55" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R55">TAPAS</rs> but would be a great future project.) In this way,
          view packages serve as reading environments rather than as individual stylesheets, and
          they enable <ptr type="software" xml:id="R56" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R56">TAPAS</rs> to group together multiple viewing options that complement one another
          within a specific usage scenario, such as the ability to alternate between a normalized
          and a diplomatic view of a manuscript source. All view packages are maintained on <ptr type="software" xml:id="R94"
            target="#github"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R94">GitHub</rs>,
          and a future goal for <ptr type="software" xml:id="R57" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R57">TAPAS</rs> is to use <ptr type="software" xml:id="R93"
            target="#github"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R93">GitHub</rs> as a collaborative tool—enabling community
          members to propose and develop new view packages for inclusion in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R58" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R58">TAPAS</rs>.</p>
        <p>From the user perspective, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R59" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R59">TAPAS</rs> contributors can specify a default view package for a
          given record or collection, so that when a reader visits that material their initial view
          of the TEI data reflects the contributor’s choice. For instance, the creator of a
          collection of historic letters (such as the <title level="m"><ref
              target="https://digitalmitford.org/">Digital Mitford</ref></title> project) might
          choose a view package that handles manuscript features well, while the creator of a
          teaching collection aimed at sparking discussion of XML visualization might instead choose
          the Hieractivity view package (described below) as the default. However, whatever the
          default setting is, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R60" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R60">TAPAS</rs> readers can select any view package option in the reading
          interface (even if it goes against the grain of the data), and this may offer readers
          additional insight into the TEI data that is shared via <ptr type="software" xml:id="R61" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R61">TAPAS</rs>.</p>
        <div xml:id="generic">
          <head><ptr type="software" xml:id="R62" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R62">TAPAS</rs> Generic View Package</head>
          <p>The basic goal of the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R63" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R63">TAPAS</rs> Generic view package is to handle almost any TEI markup in
            a moderately functional way. It is not intended as a high-function or specialized
            display; the term <soCalled>generic</soCalled> signals the fact that it displays TEI
            data in a general-purpose manner and can serve as the default stylesheet for almost any
            kind of data for which no more specialized viewing option has been provided. It offers a
            good basic reading interface, with a table of contents for navigation and the ability to
            shift between diplomatic and normalized views. For pedagogical purposes, it has the
            virtue that it is very forgiving: it does not require or assume adherence to any
            specific TEI schema or encoding protocol, and it produces a visible outcome from a wide
            variety of encoding features (so that any class involving TEI is likely to generate
            something that will get results). Its display options give emphasis to the areas of TEI
            encoding that see most frequent pedagogical use: personography and contextual
            information, transcription of primary source documents, and basic display of prose
            narratives such as fiction, life writing, and letters. It also supports renditional
            encoding (on <att>rend</att> or <att>style</att>) so that student encoders can exert
            some influence on the output. Instructors have also noted that it works well as a
            proofreading display to reveal both encoding errors and transcription errors.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="hieractivity">
          <head>Hieractivity View Package</head>
          <p>The Hieractivity view package was designed to offer a structural view rather than a
            textual view of a TEI document: that is, a view that emphasizes a reading of the markup
            rather than of the document itself. The view is zoomable so that a reader can view the
            document as if from a great distance to see its overall patterns, or up close to inspect
            particular features, and individual elements can be opened or collapsed. Similarly, the
            text can be <soCalled>zoomed</soCalled> from full visibility to invisibility. The
            package also works as a space for interactive inspection, offering the reader the
            ability to select specific elements for highlighting (from a list generated by the
            encoding in the document) and learn more about their frequency, distribution, and usage.
            Hieractivity is intended to stimulate students’ thinking about markup, focusing
            attention on how encoding reflects and enacts genre, and foregrounding the level of
            encoding detail and the presence of specific markup features. In a classroom setting,
            this view package can be used to compare the encoding of different texts and to
            highlight the differences and similarities between different students’ markup of the
            same text, between the structure of different texts, and between the encoding of
            different areas of the same text. The color highlighting and zoomability makes it easy
            to see patterns of comparison without having to interpret the TEI markup itself.
            Clicking on specific document structures produces a gloss on the markup being inspected,
            so that students can quickly see what markup was used in specific cases. This view can
            also serve as a report or rudimentary diagnostic of the markup in the text.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="other">
          <head>Other View Packages</head>
          <p><ptr type="software" xml:id="R64" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R64">TAPAS</rs> currently also offers two other view packages: an XML view package which shows
            the XML code and a view that uses the open-source <ptr type="software" xml:id="R98"
              target="#teiboilerplate"/><rs type="soft.name soft.url" ref="#R98"><ref
              target="http://dcl.ils.indiana.edu/teibp/index.html">TEI Boilerplate</ref></rs>
                stylesheets.<note><p>TEI Boilerplate: <ptr
                  target="http://dcl.ils.indiana.edu/teibp/index.html"/>. See <rs type="soft.bib.ref" ref="#R94"><ref
                  target="#walsh2013" type="bibl">Walsh and Simpson (2013)</ref></rs>.</p></note> The XML
            view is not remarkable in itself, but it is pedagogically useful within the overall
            ecology of the view packages because it allows students to see the direct connection
            between the markup and the different outcomes in the other view packages. It is also
            helpful for troubleshooting and for comparing results with other students. The <ptr type="software" xml:id="R95"
              target="#teiboilerplate"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R95">TEI
                Boilerplate</rs> view package was originally included because it offered an easy-to-install
            viewing option early in the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R65" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R65">TAPAS</rs> development process, but it has shown its value in
            other ways as well: it offers several proof-of-concept viewing options that help
            demonstrate the versatility of display through simple changes in CSS, and in the future
            it might offer a way for <ptr type="software" xml:id="R66" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R66">TAPAS</rs> to accommodate user-contributed CSS and control over
            document display by that means. It also connects <ptr type="software" xml:id="R67" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R67">TAPAS</rs> to other strands of research and
            development for TEI publication.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="validation">
        <head>Validation</head>
        <p>Validation was a key outcome for <ptr type="software" xml:id="R68" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R68">TAPAS</rs> Classroom and proved more challenging than we
          anticipated, for reasons that have to do with the way <ptr type="software" xml:id="R69" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R69">TAPAS</rs> data is ingested into the
          <ptr type="software" xml:id="R96"
            target="#fedora"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R96">Fedora</rs> repository component and how it is handled once ingested. There are three basic
          functions validation can potentially play in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R70" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R70">TAPAS</rs>: <list>
            <item>To test files upon ingestion to ensure they are XML documents, and specifically,
              TEI; this is a gatekeeping function with a simple yes or no answer. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R71" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R71">TAPAS</rs> currently
              uses validation in this way.</item>
            <item>To provide users with a more detailed profile of their data once it gets into
              <ptr type="software" xml:id="R72" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R72">TAPAS</rs>. This function would go beyond the simple gatekeeping function to give users
              information about where their TEI data matches or fails to match a given schema. The
              first step in this detailed profiling would be to provide a more detailed validation
              report based on validation against the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R73" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R73">TAPAS</rs> schema (currently
              <ident>tei_all</ident>), but a further (and extremely valuable) step would be to
              support this with more detailed validation reporting against user-supplied schemas.
              <ptr type="software" xml:id="R74" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R74">TAPAS</rs> is currently developing a validation reporting feature, described in more detail
              below.</item>
            <item>To test a given file or set of files against a specific functional scenario. For
              instance, in the context of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R75" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R75">TAPAS</rs> view packages, validation could be used to discover
              and report on whether a given TEI file will work appropriately within a given view
              package, and if not, what is missing from the encoding.</item>
          </list> For pedagogical purposes, validation serves a very specific set of needs. First,
          it can give students information about their own encoding (for example in the context of
          an assignment prompt) and can reinforce what students are learning about TEI by providing
          immediate feedback on the semantics and usage of specific elements. It can also support an
          instructor in evaluating and providing feedback on student work, by highlighting encoding
          errors (and potentially inconsistencies as well, depending on the validation approach).
          And it can be a useful stimulus to an in-class discussion of encoding, through comparison
          of different encoding approaches in relation to the stipulations of the standard. In all
          of these cases, the validation process raises a pedagogically valuable set of questions
          about the relationship—involving epistemological power, authority, and social
          consensus—between a schema and the documents students create. In some pedagogical
          settings, the schema may be accorded the status of a standard to be achieved, while in
          others it may function in more complex and dialogic ways as a hypothesis about texts to be
          tested and revised.</p>
        <p>To support these pedagogical functions, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R76" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R76">TAPAS</rs> plans to treat validation in a somewhat
          novel way, using the view package technology to situate validation as a
            <soCalled>view</soCalled> of the document itself through the lens of a schema.
          Technically, the process involves: <list>
            <item>running a validation process in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R97"
              target="#xproc"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R97">XProc</rs></item>
            <item>running an <ptr type="software" xml:id="R77" target="#xslt"/><rs type="soft.name"
                ref="#R77">XSLT</rs> stylesheet that integrates the validation output with the TEI
              document</item>
            <item>running an <ptr type="software" xml:id="R78" target="#xslt"/><rs type="soft.name"
                ref="#R78">XSLT</rs> stylesheet that transforms the whole thing into HTML for
              display (with <ptr type="software" xml:id="R79" target="#javascript"/><rs
                type="soft.name" ref="#R79">JavaScript</rs> as needed to support interaction
              such as navigation between the error report and the document itself).</item>
          </list> Along the way, the process substitutes error messages that are more intelligible
          to novices and also more reassuring and detailed, and collapses multiple occurrences of a
          given error message into a single instance. The result is to position the validation view
          less as an authoritative and fearsome report of failure and more as an informational
          report that describes the relationship between the document and the schema that has been
          invoked. An initial version of the validation view package was developed for <ptr type="software" xml:id="R80" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R80">TAPAS</rs>
          Classroom and is scheduled for release in 2020.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="conclusion">
        <head>Conclusion</head>
        <p>Pedagogical uses of TEI pose varied and distinctive requirements which depend on the role
          TEI plays in a particular classroom setting. In some cases, the goal may be to learn TEI
          and to excite students about its potential as a digital humanities tool. In other cases,
          the goal may be to use TEI as a way of framing a conversation about digital editing, data
          modeling, or data visualization. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R81" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R81">TAPAS</rs> (and the features developed through the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R82" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R82">TAPAS</rs>
          Classroom project) offers a platform for TEI display and publication that allows the
          complexities of TEI encoding to take a back seat—through encoding templates and a simple
          upload and publication workflow—in cases where expertise in TEI is not the main goal of
          the class. But at the same time, it offers the ability to look beneath the surface of
          those systems at any time, to gain greater insight into the encoding, and to explore what
          happens if the code or the display choices are changed. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R83" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R83">TAPAS</rs> also supports varied roles
          for students that give them different forms of scaffolded authority: as contributors to
          real-world publications, as creators of their own projects, as collaborators and
          experimenters in public spaces. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R84" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R84">TAPAS</rs> thus supports a vision of digital humanities
          pedagogy that is experiential, experimental, and collaborative.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="brooks2017"><author>Brooks, MacKenzie</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title
              level="a">Teaching TEI to Undergraduates: A Case Study in Digital Humanities
              Curriculum</title>. <title level="j">College and Undergraduate Libraries</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">467–481</biblScope>.
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10691316.2017.1326331"/>; <ptr
              target="https://repository.wlu.edu/handle/11021/33912"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="flanders2013"><ptr type="software" xml:id="R86"
            target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.bib.ref" ref="#R86"><author>Flanders, Julia</author>, and <author>Scott
              Hamlin</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a"><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R86">TAPAS</rs>: Building a TEI Publishing
              and Repository Service</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding
              Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/788"/>; DOI: <idno type="DOI"
              >10.4000/jtei.788</idno>.</rs></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hswe2017"><author>Hswe, Patricia, et al</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title
              level="a">A Tale of Two Internships: Developing Digital Skills Through Engaged
              Scholarship</title>. <title level="j">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>). <ptr
              target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/3/000319/000319.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kijas2016"><author>Kijas, Anna</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="a"
              >Digital Scholarship Project: Missionary Linguistics in colonial Africa / Corpus de
              travaux linguistiques des missionnaires</title>. <title level="j">Boston College
              Libraries Newsletter</title>. <ptr target="https://library.bc.edu/newsletter/?p=28"
            />.</bibl>
          
          <bibl xml:id="walsh2013"><ptr type="software" xml:id="R85"
            target="#teiboilerplate"/><rs type="soft.bib.ref" ref="#R85"><author>Walsh, John</author>, and <author>Grant Leyton
            Simpson</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a"><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R85">TEI Boilerplate</rs></title>. <title
              level="j">Journal of Digital Humanities</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>). <ptr
              target="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-3/tei-boilerplate/"/>.</rs></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
