<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-kokaze-177-source.xml 826 2019-09-06 00:55:53Z ron $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Toward a Model for Marking up Non-SI Units and Measurements</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Naoki</forename>
                  <surname>Kokaze</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Naoki Kokaze is a <roleName>PhD candidate</roleName> at <orgName>the
                     University of Tokyo</orgName>, specializing in British naval history in the
                  nineteenth and twentieth centuries. In September 2018, he joined the MA program in
                  Digital Humanities at <orgName>King’s College London</orgName>, focusing on text
                  encoding of historical sources. He has directed a cross-disciplinary workshop,
                  Tokyo Digital History, where historians, archivists, librarians, and programmers
                  discuss how to apply information technology to historical studies and explore
                  digital history.</affiliation>
               <email/>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Kiyonori</forename>
                  <surname>Nagasaki</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Kiyonori Nagasaki, PhD, is a <roleName>senior fellow</roleName> at the
                     <orgName>International Institute for Digital Humanities</orgName> in Tokyo. His
                  main research interest is in the development of digital frameworks for
                  collaboration in Buddhist studies. He also investigates the significance of
                  digital methodology in the humanities and in the promotion of DH activities in
                  Japan. He has participated in various DH projects at several institutions in Japan
                  and abroad. His activities also include postgraduate education in DH at the
                     <orgName>University of Tokyo</orgName>, as well as administrative tasks at
                  several scholarly societies including the <orgName>Japanese Association of Indian
                     and Buddhist Studies.</orgName></affiliation>
               <email/>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Makoto</forename>
                  <surname>Gotō</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Makoto Gotō, PhD, is an <roleName>associate professor</roleName> at the
                     <orgName>National Museum of Japanese History</orgName>. His research interests
                  are primarily Japanese ancient history and digital humanities research. He is
                  currently engaged in a research project called <soCalled>Integrated Studies of
                     Cultural and Research Resources</soCalled> and is conducting research on
                  various techniques for digitizing historical data. He served as the
                     <roleName>chair</roleName> of <orgName>the Special Interest Group of Computers
                     and Humanities</orgName> under the auspices of the <orgName>Information
                     Processing Society of Japan</orgName> from 2009 to
               2010.</affiliation><email/></author>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Yuta</forename>
                  <surname>Hashimoto</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Yuta Hashimoto, PhD, is an <roleName>assistant professor</roleName> at
                  the <orgName>National Museum of Japanese History, National Institutes for the
                     Humanities</orgName>. He is one of the <roleName>co-directors</roleName> of the
                  largest crowdsourcing DH projects in Japan, <title level="m"
                     >Minna-de-Honkoku</title>. He majored in the history of mathematics and
                  mathematics education before entering the doctoral course and focusing his
                  research on digital humanities. He has a bachelor’s degree from the
                     <orgName>Faculty of Literature</orgName> but has also worked as an <roleName>IT
                     engineer</roleName>, hence his interest in computer
               programming.</affiliation><email/>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>A. Charles</forename>
                  <surname>Muller</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>A. Charles Muller, PhD, is a <roleName>professor</roleName> at the
                     <orgName>University of Tokyo</orgName>, in the <orgName>Graduate School of
                     Humanities and Sociology</orgName> and its <orgName>Center for Evolving
                     Humanities</orgName>. He specializes in Korean Buddhism and East Asian
                  Yogâcāra, and has published numerous books and articles on these topics. He is one
                  of the earliest and most prolific developers of online research resources for the
                  field of Buddhist Studies, being the founder and managing editor of the online
                     <title level="m">Digital Dictionary of Buddhism</title>, the CJKV-English
                  Dictionary (<ptr target="http://www.acmuller.net"/>), the <title level="m"
                     >H-Buddhism Scholars Information Network</title>, along with having digitized
                  and published numerous reference works.</affiliation><email/>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Masahiro</forename>
                  <surname>Shimoda</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Masahiro Shimoda, PhD, is a <roleName>professor</roleName> in the
                     <orgName>Department of Indian Philosophy and Buddhist Studies</orgName>, within
                  the <orgName>Graduate School of Humanities and Sociology</orgName>, and also the
                     <roleName>director</roleName> of the <orgName>Digital Humanities
                     Initiative</orgName>, within the <orgName>Center for Evolving
                     Humanities</orgName>, at the <orgName>University of Tokyo</orgName>. He
                  specializes in the history of the formation of the Buddhist scriptures, which
                  elucidates the production and the process of passing down the scriptures of
                  traditional Indian Buddhism. As the head of the <orgName>Center for Evolving
                     Humanities</orgName>, established in 2013, he teaches the <soCalled>General
                     Introduction for Digital Humanities</soCalled> (<ptr
                     target="http://dh.iii.u-tokyo.ac.jp/"/>) as a core module of the
                  center.</affiliation><email/>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>29/06/2019</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor role="guest">Janelle Jenstad</editor>
            <editor role="guest">Kathryn Tomasek</editor>
            <editor role="guest">Martin Holmes</editor>
            <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Anne Baillot</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="12">Selected Papers from the 2017 TEI Conference</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>TEI 2017 Conference Abstracts.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>non-SI units and measurements</term>
               <term>TEI ODD</term>
               <term>TEI customization</term>
               <term><title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title></term>
               <term><att>factor</att> attribute</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-08-28">RvdB updated license.</change>
         <change when="2019-08-28">RvdB updated publication date and revision description.</change>
         <change when="2019-07-26">MH entered proofing corrections per AB.</change>
         <change when="2019-06-29">RvdB reformatted and checked the encoding.</change>
         <change when="2019-06-12">Amy Tang encoded the file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p>This paper presents a markup model for encoding non-SI units and measurements.
               Historical texts contain many examples of compound measurements, composed of sets of
               units and numerical components. Instead of using the <gi>measure</gi> element, which
               requires a single set of <att>unit</att> and <att>quantity</att>, we propose a newly
               defined set of tags for encoding idiosyncratic measurement semantics, namely
                  <gi>unitDecl</gi> (<ident>model.encodingDescPart</ident>), <gi>unitDef</gi>
                  (<ident>model.global</ident> and contained by <gi>unitDecl</gi>), <gi>unit</gi>
                  (<ident>model.measureLike</ident>), and a relevant attribute <att>factor</att>
               (which shows factors of numerical values given in a referenced <gi>unit</gi>
               element). All of these elements and attributes will be included in the TEI P5
               Guidelines, and they are especially useful when encoding units that are not based on
               the decimal system. Though this paper offers example encodings based on a Japanese
               historical source, the <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title>, this model is also
               applicable to the markup of units used for measurement within various cultural
               spheres other than Japan.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="acknowledgements">
            <p>We would like to thank all the researchers who engaged in the discussion to develop
               the markup model, both at the 2017 Annual Meeting of the TEI Consortium and on the
               TEI Consortium GitHub site, especially Elisa Beshero-Bondar, Dario Kampkaspar, Duncan
               Paterson, Laurent Romary, and James Cummings. Kathryn Tomasek deserves the greatest
               acknowledgment for her encouragement and for inviting us to join the research project
               MEDEA (Modeling semantically Enriched Digital Edition of Accounts).</p>
            <p>The project reported in this paper is funded by the National Institute of Japanese
               Literature and the National Museum of Japanese History, and supported by the Japan
               Society for the Promotion of Science Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research (S), <title
                  level="a">Construction of a New Knowledge Base for Buddhist Studies: Presentation
                  of an Advanced Model for the Next Generation of Humanities Research</title>,
               represented by Professor Masahiro Shimoda at the University of Tokyo.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="introduction">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <div xml:id="researchAim">
               <head>Research Aim</head>
               <p>This paper presents a markup model for encoding units and measurements which are
                  not based on the International System of Units (SI). The TEI P5 Guidelines
                  recommend the use of the <gi>measure</gi> element, which requires a single
                     <att>unit</att> and <att>quantity</att> (<ref target="#tei2018" type="bibl">TEI
                     Consortium 2018, <title level="a"><ref
                           target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-measure.html"
                              ><gi>measure</gi></ref></title></ref>)<note><p><ptr
                           target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-measure.html"
                        />.</p></note> for marking up the units used for measurement. But the main
                  issue we address in this paper is that some historical units and measurements
                  cannot be encoded in a single <gi>measure</gi> element because they are compounds
                  containing a set of variable units and numerical components. A typical example of
                  the compound unit would be a British imperial length measurement, such as 3 yds 2
                  ft 11 in (3 yards, 2 feet, and 11 inches). The same issue arises with the Japanese
                  historical measurements, as we can see from examples in the <title level="m"
                     >Engi-Shiki</title>, which was compiled as an administrative manual in ancient
                  Japan around the tenth century CE (<ref target="#bock1970" type="bibl">Bock
                     1970</ref>). <ptr target="#figure_1_4units" type="crossref"/> provides an
                  example of the compound units used to measure the weight of copper. In this text,
                  there are variable units, namely 斤 kin, 両 ryō, 分 bu, and 銖 shu. They were not
                  based on the decimal system, since 1 斤 kin was equal to 16 両 ryō, 1 両 ryō was 4 分
                  bu, and 1 分 was 6 銖 shu. In this example, <q>銅二千五百十六斤十両二分四銖 (Copper 2516 kin 10
                     ryō 2 bu 4 shu)</q> shows a specific weight expressed using these four
                  different units.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure_1_4units">
                  <graphic url="images/kokaze-177-fig-01.jpg" width="70px" height="553px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Sample description of a compound measurement for copper in the
                        <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title></head>
                  <head type="license">National Museum of Japanese History</head>
               </figure>
               <p>In order to encode such compound units, we propose three new elements and one new
                  attribute: <gi>unitDecl</gi> (<ident>model.encodingDescPart</ident>),
                     <gi>unitDef</gi> (<ident>model.global</ident> and contained by
                     <gi>unitDecl</gi>), <gi>unity</gi> (<ident>model.measureLike</ident>), and a
                  relevant attribute <att>factor</att> (which shows factors of numerical values
                  given in a referenced <gi>unit</gi> element), so that we can clarify the relations
                  among the units in the <gi>teiHeader</gi>. All of these will be included in the
                  TEI P5 Guidelines in due course, and the ODD File for them will be described in
                  detail later in this paper.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="implication">
               <head>Further Implications</head>
               <p>Although this paper provides a markup model based on a Japanese historical source,
                  this model also enables us to encode idiosyncratic systems of measurement within
                  various cultural spheres other than Japan. This set of tags is useful for encoding
                  units that are not based on the decimal system or whose unit conversion system
                  changed over time. For instance, conversion relations among the English coal
                  measures keel, chalder, and bushel had changed between the fifteenth century and
                  the implementation of the Imperial Weights and Measures Act of 1824 (<ptr
                     target="#figure_2_preImperial" type="crossref"/>). <figure
                     xml:id="figure_2_preImperial">
                     <graphic url="images/kokaze-177-fig-02.jpg" width="470px" height="478px"/>
                     <head type="legend">Pre-Imperial English coal measures (<ref
                           target="#zupko1977" type="bibl">Zupko 1977, 144, 151</ref>)</head>
                  </figure> The sample encoding of these units will be provided in <ptr
                     target="#oddFile" type="crossref"/>. below.</p>
               <p>Since texts related to measurement indicate such regional and chronological
                  differences, it is necessary to mark up the original historical figures as
                  precisely as possible. The new markup model enables us to express the complex and
                  changing semantics of the units and measurements.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="discussion">
            <head>Project-based Discussion</head>
            <div xml:id="project">
               <head>Our Project</head>
               <p>In this section, we describe the outline of our project—marking up the texts of
                  the <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title>—and compare it with other related projects
                  and previous studies.</p>
               <p>Delmer Brown, an American scholar of the <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title>,
                  describes it as <quote source="#quoteref14">a 50-volume work compiled between
                     <gap/> 907 and 927 <supplied>CE</supplied>. The first 10 volumes are Imperial
                     Shinto regulations (jingi 神祇) and the last 40 are codifications of criminal
                     (ritsu 律) and administrative (ryō 令) law</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref14"
                     target="#berkeley2010" type="bibl">UC Berkeley 2010</ref>). According to one of
                  the most influential researchers on ancient Japanese history, Toshiya Torao, the
                     <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title> contains a wide range of detailed
                  regulations on society and administration during the period from the Nara to the
                  Heian era (eighth to thirteenth centuries). For instance, the text lists rituals
                  and festivals held in various parts of Japan, the designation of offerings made at
                  rituals, tributes and taxes paid to the Ritsuryō government, and allocation of
                  Shōzei and Kugai (rice plants used as a kind of fund which were distributed to
                  each administrative county). To put it simply, by consulting the <title level="m"
                     >Engi-Shiki</title>, we can grasp various aspects of both state administration
                  and daily life in ancient Japan (<ref target="#torao1995" type="bibl">Torao
                     1995</ref>).</p>
               <p>But there is a historiographical problem. Because so many elements of interest are
                  described in such rich detail, previous research based on the <title level="m"
                     >Engi-Shiki</title> has tended to be subdivided into very specialized and
                  partial studies. For example, <ref target="#sakamoto1979" type="bibl">Sakamoto
                     (1979–1980)</ref> comprehensively lists the products of each administrative
                  county; <ref target="#fukushima1971" type="bibl">Fukushima (1971)</ref> and <ref
                     target="#ōsumi1996" type="bibl">Ōsumi (1996)</ref> focus on the aquatic
                  products; <ref target="#satō2012" type="bibl">Satō (2012)</ref> examines the dairy
                  products; papers and paper manufacturing are the focal point of <ref
                     target="#ōkawa1981" type="bibl">Ōkawa and Masuda (1981)</ref>; and <ref
                     target="#miyahara2014" type="bibl">Miyahara (2014)</ref> traces the records
                  related to abalone, which was the most circulated food at that time. This
                  subdivision and specialization makes it difficult to verify quantitative analyses,
                  because there is no text database in which researchers could search for numerical
                  values attached to specific products and items.</p>
               <p>Our research project has been working to provide a possible solution to this
                  problem. One of our aims is to formulate a text database enabling historians,
                  according to their individual interests, to extract numerical values by making use
                  of various machine-processable data on society and administration in ancient
                  Japan. One similar research project, the <ref target="https://jhti.berkeley.edu"
                     >Japanese Historical Text Initiative (JHTI)</ref>, based at the Center for
                  Japanese Studies at the University of California, Berkeley, offers digitized text
                  of the first ten volumes of the <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title> text in
                  Japanese and in English translation along with page images of the manuscript
                  volumes (<ref target="#berkeley2010" type="bibl">UC Berkeley 2010</ref>). Our
                  project will provide TEI-based text and numerical values attached to the various
                  kinds of products and items, comprehensively covering all fifty volumes of the
                     <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title>. For this purpose, we have proposed
                  expanding the functionality of the <gi>measure</gi> element (<ref
                     target="#kokaze2016" type="bibl">Kokaze and Nagasaki 2016</ref>).<note><p>We
                        have been greatly inspired by the projects of the <ref
                           target="https://medea.hypotheses.org">MEDEA Workshop</ref>, which deal
                        with the markup modeling of historical financial records (<ref
                           target="#tomasek2013" type="bibl">Tomasek and Bauman 2013</ref>). We hope
                        the future achievements of our project will be useful for their projects, as
                        well.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="basicStructure">
               <head>Basic Structure of the <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title></head>
               <p>We have based our project on the 土御門 Tsuchimikado version of the <title level="m"
                     >Engi-Shiki</title> (<ref target="#kokuritsu2000" type="bibl">Kokuritsu Rekishi
                     Minzoku Hakubutsukan Kanzō Shiryō Henshūkai 2000–</ref>).</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure_3_sample">
                  <graphic url="images/kokaze-177-fig-03.jpg" height="823px" width="694px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Sample passages from the <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title>,
                     from volume 1 四時祭式 Shijisai-Shiki</head>
                  <head type="license">National Museum of Japanese History</head>
               </figure>
               <p>The basic structure of the <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title> has a simple
                  hierarchy which goes down from 式 shiki to 条 jou. So, we mark up the sample passage
                  of the <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title>, shown in <ptr
                     target="#figure_3_sample" type="crossref"/>, using nested <gi>div</gi>
                  elements, as follows:</p>
               <figure xml:id="example_code_1">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <body>
                        <div ana="四時祭上" n="1" type="式" subtype="条">
                           <head type="式名">四時祭上</head>
                           <div type="条" n="1.1">
                              <head type="条名">祭祀大中小</head>
                              <p>凡践祚大嘗祭為大祀、祈年・月次・神嘗・新嘗・賀茂等祭為中祀、大忌・風神・鎮花・三枝・相嘗・鎮魂・鎮火・道饗・薗・韓神・松尾・平野・春日・大原野等祭為小祀、〈風神祭已上、並諸司斎之、鎮花祭已下、祭官斎之、但小祀祭官斎者、内裏不斎、其遣勅使之祭者斎之、〉</p>
                           </div>
                           <div type="条" n="1.2">
                              <head type="条名">祭日</head>
                              <p>凡祈年祭二月四日、大忌・風神祭並四月・七月四日、月次祭六月・十二月十一日、神嘗祭九月十一日、
                                 其子・午・卯・酉等日祭、各載本条、自余祭不定日者、臨時択日祭之、二月祭</p>
                           </div>
                           <!-- the rest of the contents -->
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Basic structure of the <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title>
                     encoding</head>
               </figure>
               <table xml:id="table1" rows="6" cols="3">
                  <head>Descriptions of the basic structural markup</head>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell role="label">Element</cell>
                     <cell role="label"><att>type</att></cell>
                     <cell role="label">Description</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>div</cell>
                     <cell>式</cell>
                     <cell>Nests a <gi>head</gi> element and several <gi>div</gi> elements;
                           <att>ana</att> and <att>n</att> provide the name and the index number of
                        the 式; <att>subtype</att>=<val>条</val> makes the hierarchical relation
                        between 式 &amp; 条 clear</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>head</cell>
                     <cell>式名</cell>
                     <cell>Includes the 式 Shiki’s Name</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>div</cell>
                     <cell>条</cell>
                     <cell>Nests a <gi>head</gi> element and a <gi>p</gi> element; <att>n</att>
                        gives the index number of the 条 within the 式, using <soCalled>.</soCalled>
                        as the delimiter (e.g., <code>n="1.2"</code>)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>head</cell>
                     <cell>条名</cell>
                     <cell>Includes the 条 Jou’s Name</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>p</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Contains the main text of each 条 Jou</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>Marking up the basic structure of the <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title> in this
                  way allows an overview of the tree structure of the source, using the Oxygen XML
                  Editor’s <soCalled>Grid</soCalled> mode, for example.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="markupExamples">
            <head>Markup Examples Based on TEI P5</head>
            <div xml:id="defining">
               <head>Defining Measurement in the <gi>teiHeader</gi></head>
               <p>Having outlined the basic document structure of the <title level="m"
                     >Engi-Shiki</title>, we can return to the encoding of the definitions of non-SI
                  units. Needless to say, TEI provides tags for taxonomies and classification (<ref
                     target="#tei2018" type="bibl">TEI Consortium 2018</ref>, <title level="a"><ref
                        target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-classDecl.html"
                           ><gi>classDecl</gi></ref></title>).<note><p><ptr
                           target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-classDecl.html"
                        />.</p></note> If you want to categorize and define non-SI units, you can
                  express them by the descendent elements of <gi>encodingDesc</gi>, as follows:</p>
               <figure xml:id="example_code_2">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                           <taxonomy>
                              <bibl>units of measuring weight</bibl>
                              <category xml:id="斤">
                                 <catDesc>斤is a unit measuring weight and equal to 16両.</catDesc>
                              </category>
                              <category xml:id="両">
                                 <catDesc>両is a unit measuring weight and equal to 4分.</catDesc>
                              </category>
                              <category xml:id="分">
                                 <catDesc>分is a unit measuring weight and equal to 6銖.</catDesc>
                              </category>
                              <category xml:id="銖">
                                 <catDesc>銖is a unit measuring weight.</catDesc>
                              </category>
                           </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                     </encodingDesc>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">A taxonomy of non-SI units</head>
               </figure>
               <p>In this way, relations among non-SI units of measurement might be described in a
                  human-readable way, within the <gi>catDesc</gi> element. However, it is difficult
                  to express the unit conversion system among the measurements in a machine-readable
                  way, especially when those units are not based on the decimal system.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="inline">
               <head>Inline Markup</head>
               <p>Instead of defining the unit conversion system in the <gi>teiHeader</gi>, we could
                  encode the compound measurements in the form of inline markup, as <ref
                     target="#cummings2013" type="bibl">Cummings and Wilcox (2013, sec. 7)</ref>
                  show in this example of encoding a value in old English money:<note><p><ptr
                           target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/926#tocto1n7"
                  />.</p></note></p>
               <figure xml:id="example_code_3">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <seg type="fee" rend="roman-numerals aligned-right">
                        <num type="totalPence" value="1240">
                           <!--orig: vli iijs iiijd -->
                           <num type="poundsAsPence" value="1200">v<hi rend="superscript"
                              >li</hi></num>
                           <num type="shillingsAsPence" value="36">iij<hi rend="superscript"
                              >s</hi></num>
                           <num type="pence" value="4">iiij<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></num>
                        </num>
                     </seg>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Old English money, as encoded by <ref type="bibl"
                        target="#cummings2013">Cummings and Wilcox (2013)</ref></head>
               </figure>
               <p>One of the important points of their markup is the use of nested <gi>num</gi>
                  elements with <att>type</att> attributes, indicating <soCalled>vli iijs
                     iiijd</soCalled> as a compound unit, not as separated units. Although this
                  example is inspiring for our project, we would prefer not to store converted
                  numerical values in <att>value</att> attributes; we would rather keep the original
                  data when it comes to inline markup. The reason for this is that the unit
                  conversion system has altered over time, as in the case of the British coal
                  measures shown in <ptr target="#figure_2_preImperial" type="crossref"/>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="markupModel">
            <head>Markup Model</head>
            <div xml:id="tagsets">
               <head>Elements and Attributes for Expressing the Metrological Semantics</head>
               <p>In order to structure, in the <gi>teiHeader</gi>, a wide variety of measurement
                  semantics within each of the historical documents, we propose a new set of
                  elements and attributes. To take an example from the <title level="m"
                     >Engi-Shiki</title>, the following is a definition of 斤, 両, 分, and 銖, all of
                  which are units for measuring weight. For the sake of readability, we omit the
                  compulsory <gi>fileDesc</gi> element. Customized elements and attributes are
                     <gi>unitDecl</gi>, <gi>unitDef</gi>, <gi>unit</gi>, and <att>factor</att>.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example_code_4">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <encodingDesc>
                        <unitDecl>
                           <unitDef xml:id="斤" type="weight">
                              <label xml:lang="ja">斤</label>
                              <label xml:lang="ja-Latn">kin</label>
                              <unit ref="#両" factor="16"/>
                              <desc xml:lang="en">斤is a unit measuring weight and equivalent to
                                 16両.</desc>
                           </unitDef>
                           <unitDef xml:id="両" type="weight">
                              <label xml:lang="ja">両</label>
                              <label xml:lang="ja-Latn">ryō</label>
                              <unit ref="#分" factor="4"/>
                              <desc xml:lang="en">両is a unit measuring weight and equivalent to
                                 4分.</desc>
                           </unitDef>
                           <unitDef xml:id="分" type="weight">
                              <label xml:lang="ja">分</label>
                              <label xml:lang="ja-Latn">bu</label>
                              <unit ref="#銖" factor="6"/>
                              <desc xml:lang="en">分is a unit measuring weight and equivalent to
                                 6銖.</desc>
                           </unitDef>
                           <unitDef xml:id="銖" type="weight">
                              <label xml:lang="ja">銖</label>
                              <label xml:lang="ja-Latn">shu</label>
                              <desc xml:lang="en">銖is a unit measuring weight.</desc>
                           </unitDef>
                        </unitDecl>
                     </encodingDesc>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Proposed usage of <gi>unitDecl</gi></head>
               </figure>
               <p>Here, the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> contains a <gi>unitDecl</gi> element that declares
                  information about the measurement semantics in that source, and nests
                     <gi>unitDef</gi> as the compulsory child. In this <gi>unitDef</gi> element, we
                  can define the identifier and the purpose of a unit by using <att>xml:id</att> and
                     <att>type</att> attributes respectively. The <gi>label</gi> and <gi>desc</gi>
                  elements contained by the <gi>unitDef</gi> can be used to describe how a unit of
                  measurement is used in the source and give some information about that unit.
                  Inside the <gi>unitDef</gi> we find the <gi>unit</gi> element, which was
                  originally suggested by Laurent Romary on the TEI Consortium GitHub
                           repository.<note><p><q>Add new element <gi>unit</gi></q>, opened by
                        @laurentromary May 20, 2016, <ptr
                           target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1461"/>.</p></note> Though we
                  have benefited from his contribution in developing our markup model, his approach
                  deals mainly with examples of in-line markup within the <gi>body</gi> element.
                  However, the proposed <gi>unit</gi> element can reasonably be used in the
                     <gi>teiHeader</gi> to indicate the relationship of the conversion between
                  units, along with <att>factor</att>, which shows the numerical formula. Together,
                  these elements enable us to mark up units that, in their original forms surviving
                  in the historical financial records, are not based on decimal notation.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="oddFile">
               <head>ODD File</head>
               <p>We propose the following TEI ODD specifications<note>The ODD file and encoding
                     examples are current at the time of writing, and are under consideration by the
                     TEI Council.</note> for marking up units:</p>
               <figure xml:id="example_code_5">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <elementSpec ident="unit" ns="http://www.example.org/ns/nonTEI" mode="add">
                        <desc>contains a symbol, a word or a phrase referring to a unit of
                           measurement in any kind of formal or informal system.</desc>
                        <classes>
                           <memberOf key="model.measureLike"/>
                           <memberOf key="att.canonical"/>
                           <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                           <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
                        </classes>
                        <content>
                           <macroRef key="macro.paraContent"/>
                        </content>
                        <attList>
                           <attDef ident="factor" mode="add">
                              <desc>shows factors of numerical values given in a referenced
                                    <gi>unit</gi> element</desc>
                              <datatype>
                                 <dataRef key="teidata.numeric"/>
                              </datatype>
                           </attDef>
                        </attList>
                     </elementSpec>
                     <elementSpec ident="unitDef" ns="http://www.example.org/ns/nonTEI" mode="add">
                        <desc>contains descriptive information related to certain unit.</desc>
                        <classes>
                           <memberOf key="model.global"/>
                           <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                           <memberOf key="att.datable"/>
                           <memberOf key="att.canonical"/>
                           <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
                        </classes>
                        <content>
                           <alternate maxOccurs="unbounded">
                              <elementRef key="unit" minOccurs="1"/>
                              <classRef key="model.labelLike"/>
                           </alternate>
                        </content>
                     </elementSpec>
                     <elementSpec ident="unitDecl" ns="http://www.example.org/ns/nonTEI" mode="add">
                        <desc> (unit declarations) provides information about non-SI (the
                           International System of Units) units and measurement.</desc>
                        <classes>
                           <memberOf key="model.encodingDescPart"/>
                           <memberOf key="att.global"/></classes>
                        <content>
                           <elementRef key="unitDef" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
                        </content>
                     </elementSpec>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Proposed ODD specification for marking up units</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Among these definitions in this ODD File, we need to explain why we choose
                     <ident>att.datable</ident> in the <gi>unitDef</gi> element. In order to
                  illustrate the reason for this choice, we provide a sample encoding of the
                  conversional transition within the English coal measures mentioned in <ptr
                     target="#implication" type="crossref"/> above:</p>
               <figure xml:id="example_code_6">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <encodingDesc>
                        <unitDecl>
                           <unitDef xml:id="keel_prev" type="coal_measure" from="1421" to="1676">
                              <label xml:lang="en">keel</label>
                              <unit ref="#chalder_prev" factor="20"/>
                              <desc>In England, keel was a unit for measuring coal and equal to 20
                                 chalders from 1421– 1676.</desc>
                           </unitDef>
                           <unitDef xml:id="chalder_prev" type="currency">
                              <label xml:lang="en">chalder</label>
                              <unit ref="#bushel_prev" factor="32" from="1421" to="1676"/>
                              <unit ref="#bushel_new" factor="36" from="1676" to="1824"/>
                              <desc>In England, chalder was a unit for measuring coal and equal to
                                 32 bushels from 1421–1676 and equivalent to 36 bushels from
                                 1676–1824.</desc>
                           </unitDef>
                           <unitDef xml:id="bushel_prev" type="currency">
                              <label xml:lang="en">bushel</label>
                              <desc>In England, bushel was a unit for measuring coal.</desc>
                           </unitDef>
                           <unitDef xml:id="keel_new" type="coal_measure" from="1676" to="1824">
                              <label xml:lang="en">keel</label>
                              <unit ref="#chalder_new" factor="12"/>
                              <desc>In England, keel was a unit for measuring coal and equivalent to
                                 12 chalders from 1676–1824.</desc>
                           </unitDef>
                           <unitDef xml:id="chalder_new" type="currency">
                              <label xml:lang="en">chalder</label>
                              <unit ref="#bushel_new" factor="36" from="1676" to="1824"/>
                              <desc>In England, chalder was a unit for measuring coal and equivalent
                                 to 36 bushels from 1676–1824.</desc>
                           </unitDef>
                           <unitDef xml:id="bushel_new" type="currency">
                              <label xml:lang="en">bushel</label>
                              <desc>In England, bushel was a unit for measuring coal, whose
                                 conversion formula was changed chronologically.</desc>
                           </unitDef>
                        </unitDecl>
                     </encodingDesc></egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Encoding of the conversions relating to English coal
                     measures</head>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="solutions">
               <head>Markup Solutions</head>
               <p>Finally, we present two markup examples of a passage in the <title level="m"
                     >Engi-Shiki</title>. First we encode the passage based on the current TEI P5
                  Guidelines, using the <gi>measure</gi> element and the <att>unit</att> attribute,
                  and then we demonstrate an example using <gi>unit</gi> elements within the
                     <gi>body</gi> texts. These two examples do not necessarily differ from each
                  other except in encoding, but both refer to the <att>xml:id</att> attribute
                  defined in the <gi>unitDef</gi>.</p>
               <p>The text shown below is a part of the section describing regulation of taxes
                  imposed upon the two administrative counties, 備中 Bicchū and 長門 Nagato. In this
                  case, the taxes were paid annually to the contemporary Ritsuryō government in
                  copper 銅 and lead 鉛 mineral resources.</p>
               <figure xml:id="example_code_7">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <div ana="主税上" n="26.95" type="条">
                        <head type="条名">鋳銭年料</head>
                        <p> 凡鋳銭年料銅鉛者、<placeName xml:id="備中国">備中国</placeName>
                           <measure commodity="銅" xml:id="備中_主税_銅" quantity="800" unit="#斤">
                              銅八百斤</measure>、 <placeName xml:id="長門国">長門国</placeName>
                           <measure commodity="銅" xml:id="長門_主税_銅" type="whole">銅 <measure
                                 quantity="2516" unit="#斤" type="each">二千五百十六斤</measure>
                              <measure quantity="10" unit="#両" type="each">十両</measure>
                              <measure quantity="2" unit="#分" type="each">二分</measure>
                              <measure quantity="4" unit="#銖" type="each">四銖</measure>
                           </measure>、 <measure commodity="鉛" xml:id="長門_主税_鉛" type="whole">鉛
                                 <measure quantity="1516" unit="#斤" type="each">千五百十六斤</measure>
                              <measure quantity="10" unit="#両" type="each">十両</measure>
                              <measure quantity="2" unit="#分" type="each">二分</measure>
                              <measure quantity="4" unit="#銖" type="each">四銖</measure>
                           </measure>、 </p>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Current scheme, <gi>measure</gi> with <att>unit</att>
                     attribute</head>
               </figure>
               <p>There are some points worth mentioning in this markup example. In the <gi>div</gi>
                  element, we provide metadata about the passage, using the relevant default TEI
                  attributes. These attributes explain that the text contained by the <gi>div</gi>
                  element is the 95th passage of the 26th volume of the <title level="m"
                     >Engi-Shiki</title>, 主税上 Shuzei-no-Jō. 鋳銭年料 Chūsen Nenryō, the passage title,
                  means the annual tax in the form of minted currency. Three <gi>measure</gi>
                  elements that have the <att>commodity</att> attribute contain one or more variable
                  units and numerical components. In the second and third examples, we describe the
                  relationship of the compound measurement, using <att>type</att>=<val>whole</val>
                  and <att>type</att>=<val>each</val>, inspired by <ref target="#cummings2013"
                     type="bibl">Cummings and Wilcox (2013)</ref>. Note that in this markup example
                  we avoid using <gi>measureGrp</gi> elements as parent elements of <tag
                     type="empty">measure type="each"</tag> elements, because the TEI P5 Guidelines
                  recommend using <gi>measureGrp</gi> when marking up a group of dimensional
                  specifications (<ref target="#tei2018" type="bibl">TEI Consortium 2018</ref>,
                     <title level="a"><ref
                        target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-measureGrp.html"
                           ><gi>measureGrp</gi></ref></title>).<note><p><ptr
                           target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-measureGrp.html"
                        />.</p></note></p>
               <p>Or, to mark up each of the units separately, <gi>unit</gi> elements can be used in
                  the inline markup, as follows: </p>
               <figure xml:id="example_code_8">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <div ana="主税上" n="26.95" type="条">
                        <head ana="鋳銭年料"/>
                        <p> 凡鋳銭年料銅鉛者、<placeName xml:id="備中国">備中国</placeName>
                           <measure commodity="銅" xml:id="備中_主税_銅">銅 <num value="800">八百</num><unit
                                 ref="#斤">斤</unit></measure>、 <placeName xml:id="長門国"
                              >長門国</placeName>
                           <measure commodity="銅" xml:id="長門_主税_銅" type="whole">銅 <measure
                                 type="each">
                                 <num value="2516">二千五百十六</num><unit ref="#斤">斤</unit></measure>
                              <measure type="each">
                                 <num value="10">十</num><unit ref="#両">両</unit></measure>
                              <measure type="each">
                                 <num value="2">二</num><unit ref="#分">分</unit></measure>
                              <measure type="each">
                                 <num value="4">四</num><unit ref="#銖">銖</unit></measure></measure>、
                              <measure commodity="鉛" xml:id="長門_主税_鉛" type="whole">鉛 <measure
                                 type="each">
                                 <num value="1516">千五百十六</num><unit ref="#斤">斤</unit></measure>
                              <measure type="each">
                                 <num value="10">十</num><unit ref="#両">両</unit></measure>
                              <measure type="each">
                                 <num value="2">二</num><unit ref="#分">分</unit></measure>
                              <measure type="each">
                                 <num value="4">四</num><unit ref="#銖">銖</unit></measure></measure>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Using <gi>unit</gi> element</head>
               </figure>
               <p>In this example, three <gi>measure</gi> elements that have the
                     <att>commodity</att> attribute contain one or more <gi>num</gi> and
                     <gi>unit</gi> elements as sibling elements. Each <gi>measure</gi> element shows
                  a specific weight of the mineral resource as a whole, using
                     <att>type</att>=<val>whole</val>. We store actual values in the
                     <att>value</att> attribute in the <gi>num</gi> elements in the form of Arabic
                  figures so that we can easily extract them using XSLT or other programming
                  languages.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="conclusion">
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>This paper proposes a markup model and gives examples for encoding non-SI units and
               measurements, based on our work with the <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title>.
               Historically, there have been many examples of compound measurement which require
               sets of various units and numerical components, so we have to consider how to encode
               them. Of course, the TEI P5 Guidelines offer us possible solutions, such as defining
               the taxonomies of measurement in the <gi>classDecl</gi> and providing nested
                  <gi>num</gi> or <gi>measure</gi> elements in the form of inline markup. But the
               major limitation of those solutions is that they are not amenable to machine
               processing based on the unit conversion system.</p>
            <p>Among the components of our proposal, <att>factor</att> and attributes from the
                  <ident>att.datable</ident> class (e.g., <att>from</att>, <att>to</att>) within the
                  <gi>unitDef</gi> element are the most effective for the purpose of describing the
               measurement semantics. As the example of the English coal measures keel, chalder, and
               bushel shows, the unit conversion formula is subject to change over time even within
               the same country. Therefore, it would be a reasonable practice when encoding non-SI
               units and measurements to describe the unit conversion formula with <att>factor</att>
               between variable units, capturing the dating context with <att>from</att> and
                  <att>to</att> in the <gi>unitDef</gi>.</p>
            <p>We note in closing that our interest in encoding units of measurement is shared by
               other members of the TEI consortium and we look forward to further discussion.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bock1970"><author>Bock, Felicia G.</author>
                  <date>1970</date>. <title level="m">Engi-Shiki: Procedures of the Engi
                  Era</title>. <pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>: <publisher>Sophia
                  University</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="cummings2013"><author>Cummings, James</author>, and <author>Pip
                     Willcox</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a">Stationers’ Register
                     Online: A Case Study of a Byte-Reduced TEI Schema for Digitization
                        (<ident>tei_corset</ident>)</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the Text
                     Encoding Initiative</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/926"/>; DOI: <idno type="DOI"
                     >10.4000/jtei.926</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="fukushima1971"><author>Fukushima, Yoshikazu</author>.
                  <date>1971</date>. <title level="a">Kodai Shokoku Kōnō Suisanbutsu no Bumpu ni
                     tsuite: Sono Rekishi Chirigakuteki Kōsatsu [The Geographical Distribution of
                     the Sea Products in the Ancient Empire of Japan]</title>. <title level="j"
                     >Jinbun Chiri [Human Geography]</title>, <biblScope unit="volume"
                     >23</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>): <biblScope unit="page"
                     >495–525</biblScope>. DOI: <idno type="DOI"
                  >10.4200/jjhg1948.23.495</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="kokaze2016"><author>Kokaze, Naoki</author>, and <author>Kiyonori
                     Nagasaki</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="u">Extensibility of
                        <soCalled>Transactionography</soCalled> for Multilingual Historical
                     Financial Records</title>. Presented at <pubPlace>the MEDEA Spring Meeting at
                     Wheaton College, Norton, MA</pubPlace>, <date>April 7–8, 2016</date>. Abstract
                  available at <ptr target="https://medea.hypotheses.org/478"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="kokuritsu2000"><author>Kokuritsu Rekishi Minzoku Hakubutsukan Kanzō
                     Shiryō Henshūkai</author>. <date>2000–</date>. <title level="m"
                     >Engi-Shiki</title>. <pubPlace>Kyoto</pubPlace>: <publisher>Rinsen
                     Shoten</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="miyahara2014"><author>Miyahara, Takeo</author>. <date>2014</date>.
                     <title level="m">Kodai Tōgoku no Chōyō to Nōmin [Tax and peasantry in the
                     ancient eastern counties of Japan]</title>. <pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Iwata Shoin</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ōkawa1981"><author>Ōkawa, Akinori</author>, and <author>Katsuhiko
                     Masuda</author>. <date>1981</date>. <title level="a">Seishi ni kannsuru Kodai
                     Gijutsu no Kenkyū [Technical study on paper making in the Nara Period (7–8th
                     century)]</title>. <title level="j">Hozon Kagaku [Science for
                     Conservation]</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">43–56</biblScope>.
                  Includes an abstract in English. <ptr
                     target="http://www.tobunken.go.jp/~ccr/pdf/20/pdf/02007.pdf"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ōsumi1996"><author>Ōsumi, Akiko</author>. <date>1996</date>. <title
                     level="a">Ritsuryōsei-ka ni okeru Kenkō Fukyū no Jittai: Kaisanbutsu no Kōnō
                     Tanni wo Chūshin toshite [On the Popularization of Weights under the Ritsuryo
                     Regime: Focusing on the Units of the Aquatic Products as Tributes]</title>.
                     <title level="j">Shiron [Historica]</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                  >22–44</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="sakamoto1979"><author>Sakamoto, Shintarō</author>.
                     <date>1979–1980</date>. <title level="a"><title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title>
                     kara mita Shokoku no Sambutsu Hyō [Lists of the Products of Each County in the
                        <title level="m">Engi-Shiki</title>]</title>. <title level="j">Waseda
                     Shogaku [Waseda Commercial Review]</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">281</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                     >79–130</biblScope>; <biblScope unit="volume">284</biblScope>: <biblScope
                     unit="page">1–32</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="satō2012"><author>Satō, Kentarō</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title
                     level="a">Kodai Nihon no Gyūnyū/Nyūseihin no Riyō to Kōshin Taisei ni tsuite
                     [Milk and its by-products as offerings under Japan’s ancient contribution
                     system]</title>. <title level="j">Kansai Daigaku Tōzai Gakujutsu Kenkyū Kiyō
                     [Bulletin of the Institute of Oriental and Occidental Studies, Kansai
                     University]</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                  >47–65</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tomasek2013"><author>Tomasek, Kathryn</author>, and <author>Syd
                     Bauman</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="a">Encoding Financial Records
                     for Historical Research</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding
                     Initiative</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/895"/>; DOI: <idno type="DOI"
                     >10.4000/jtei.895</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="torao1995"><author>Torao, Toshiya</author>. <date>1995</date>. <title
                     level="m">Engi-Shiki</title>. Vol. <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope> of
                     <title level="m">Nihon Rekishi Sōsho [Series on Japanese History]</title>,
                  edited by <editor>Nihon Rekishi Gakkai [The Japanese Historical
                     Association]</editor>. <pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>: <publisher>Yoshikawa
                     Kōbunkan</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tei2018"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2018</date>. <title
                     level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                     Interchange</title>. <edition>Version 3.4.0</edition>. Last updated July 23.
                     <pubPlace>N. p.</pubPlace>: <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.4.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="berkeley2010"><orgName>UC Berkeley (University of California,
                     Berkeley)</orgName>. <title level="m">Engi Shiki</title>. <publisher>Japanese
                     Historical Text Initiative</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://jhti.berkeley.edu/Engi%20shiki.html"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="zupko1977"><author>Zupko, Ronald Edward</author>. <date>1977</date>.
                     <title level="m">British Weights &amp; Measures: A History from Antiquity to
                     the Seventeenth Century</title>. <pubPlace>Madison</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>University of Wisconsin Press</publisher>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
