<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-cc-ra-alles-169-source.xml 960 2020-05-19 21:11:52Z martin $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Switchover: Teaching and Learning the Text Encoding Initiative in
               Spanish</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Susanna</forename>
                  <surname>Allés-Torrent</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Susanna Allés-Torrent is <roleName>Assistant Professor</roleName> in
                     <orgName>the Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</orgName> at
                     <orgName>the University of Miami</orgName>, where she teaches Digital
                  Humanities, Medieval and Early Modern Romance Literature, and Spanish
                  Culture.</affiliation>
               <email>susanna_alles@miami.edu</email>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Gimena</forename>
                  <surname>del Rio Riande</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Gimena del Rio Riande is <roleName>Adjunct Researcher</roleName> at
                     <orgName>the Instituto de Investigaciones Bibliográficas y Crítica Textual
                     (IIBICRIT-CONICET, Argentina)</orgName> and the <roleName>Director</roleName>
                  of <orgName>Humanidades CAICYT Lab</orgName> at <orgName>the Centro Argentino de
                     Información en Ciencia y Tecnología (CAICYT-CONICET)</orgName>. She is also
                     <roleName>External Professor</roleName> at <orgName>Universidad de Buenos Aires
                     (UBA)</orgName> and <roleName>co-director</roleName> of <orgName>the Digital
                     Humanities Master</orgName> at <orgName>LINHD-UNED
                  (Spain)</orgName>.</affiliation>
               <email>gdelrio@conicet.gov.ar</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>12/05/2020</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor role="guest">Janelle Jenstad</editor>
            <editor role="guest">Kathryn Tomasek</editor>
            <editor role="guest">Martin Holmes</editor>
            <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Anne Baillot</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="12">Selected Papers from the 2017 TEI Conference</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>TEI 2017 Conference Abstracts.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>teaching resources</term>
               <term>Spanish</term>
               <term>Latin America</term>
               <term>Spain</term>
               <term>humanidades digitales</term>
               <term>diversity</term>
               <term>distant learning</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2020-05-19">Martin Holmes and Kathryn Tomasek: minor proofing
            corrections.</change>
         <change when="2020-05-13">Martin Holmes: minor updates per authors.</change>
         <change when="2020-05-12">Martin Holmes and Janelle Jenstad made minor corrections and
            entered authorʼs corrections.</change>
         <change when="2020-05-08">Ron Van den Branden made minor corrections.</change>
         <change when="2020-05-07">Martin Holmes took over encoding.</change>
         <change when="2020-05-01">Amy Tang set up the file and started encoding.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p>This article analyses the current situation of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) in
               a Spanish-speaking digital humanities (DH) education and research context. It also
               examines the challenges faced when teaching TEI in Spanish and takes into
               consideration two main issues: the still not well-defined DH curriculum in many
               Spanish-speaking countries and the different pedagogical approaches to the TEI
               depending on the learning context: face-to-face instruction, distance education, and
               the Foreign Language Classroom. It aims as well to raise awareness about the lack of
               basic pedagogical materials—tutorials or guidelines—devoted to TEI in Spanish, an
               obstacle that has hindered the growth of a TEI community of practice from Spain and
               Latin America. It also offers some strategies and new resources that could benefit
               the outreach and adoption of the TEI inside and outside the Spanish-speaking DH
               community, while facilitating a new TEI curriculum in a higher education context.</p>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div xml:id="intro">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Digital humanities (DH) tools, methods, and resources are becoming increasingly
               common in the higher education context. The Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) standard
               for encoding and publishing digital texts is now part of the DH core undergraduate
               and graduate curriculum.<note>TEI will be used both to address to the consortium and
                  the markup language.</note> To be more precise, this statement is true for the
               anglophone world, which quickly took advantage of the TEI standards for creating
               searchable, enriched, interoperable, and well preserved texts and databases. However,
               the situation is significantly different in Spanish-speaking countries.</p>

            <p>The leading role of the anglophone DH community, as well as the hegemonic role of
               English for global scientific communication,<note>Such is the case of several
                  communities like Japan, India or South Africa, that use English as a
                     <term>koiné</term> language inside academia. This is not the case in Latin
                  America and other Spanish Speaking regions where English is not the language for
                  scientific communication.</note> have created a field where multilingual resources
               are still difficult to find. Yet, in the last five years, it may be observed that DH
               is in the midst of a significant global turn where many aspects related to diversity
               and equity have come into question, therefore highlighting the barriers to the
               participation of a globalized population and other equity-seeking groups within the
               field (<ref target="#odonnell2012" type="bibl">O’Donnell 2012</ref>; <ref
                  target="#galina2013" type="bibl">Galina 2013</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#fiormonte2014">Fiormonte 2014</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#odonnell_etal2016a">O’Donnell et al. 2016a</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#odonnell_etal2016b">O’Donnell et al. 2016b</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#fiormonte_delrioriande2017">Fiormonte and del Rio Riande 2017</ref>).</p>

            <p>DH has become not only a multidisciplinary field but also a more globally connected
               discipline, facing human challenges such as multilingualism, equity, and diversity.
               Consequently, the ability to communicate across cultural boundaries has gained
               increasing prominence in the field (<ref type="bibl" target="#delRioRiande2015a">del
                  Rio Riande 2015a</ref>, <ref type="bibl" target="#delRioRiande2015b">2015b</ref>,
                  <ref type="bibl" target="#delRioRiande2016a">2016a</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#delRioRiande2016b">2016b</ref>). This situation can be applied to the TEI
               and its global community of practice. In fact, one of the last TEI Conferences, held
               in Japan in 2018, was specifically titled <title level="a">TEI as a Global
                  Language,</title> highlighting the potential of TEI as a global (meta)language
               applied to Humanities and Social Science texts written in many different
                     languages.<note><ptr target="https://tei2018.dhii.asia/"/>.</note></p>

            <p>Throughout this work, the authors—who are both Spanish speakers, but working in two
               different academic contexts, one in North America and one in South America—will
               examine what it means to teach and learn the TEI in a Spanish-speaking class
               situation. This article will therefore focus on three main points: a general overview
               of the interest in adopting the TEI as a standard to represent a variety of
               humanities texts; the challenges of teaching TEI in Spanish within an ill-defined and
               emerging DH curricular context, as well as in different pedagogical environments such
               as face-to-face instruction and distance education in a native-speaking context, and
               the Foreign Language Classroom; and an outline of the obstacles and challenges we
               have faced after almost seven years of teaching TEI in Spanish, together with a set
               of strategies and resources for improving the overall situation.</p>

         </div>

         <div xml:id="dhCurriculumTei">
            <head>The Humanidades Digitales Curriculum and the TEI<note>Most of the themes and
                  topics in this section are studied more extensively by del Rio Riande in <title
                     level="a">Humanidades Digitales: Life on the other Side,</title> keynote
                  presentation at TEI conference and members meeting, Victoria, British Columbia,
                  Canada, November 11 - 15, 2017.</note></head>

            <p>Despite the early interest in the intersection between humanities and technology
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#marin1986">Marcos Marín 1986</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#irizarry1997">Irizarry 1997</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#delRioRiande2015a">del Rio Riande 2015a</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#delRioRiande2016a">2016a</ref>), DH only recently became a wider and
               recognizable field known as <soCalled>humanidades digitales</soCalled> in the
               Spanish-speaking world. Since 2012 several Latin American and Spanish DH
               associations, such as RedHD in Mexico,<note>Red de Humanidades Digitales (RedHD),
                     <ptr target="http://www.humanidadesdigitales.net/"/>.</note> AHDig: Associação
               das Humanidades Digitais in Brazil,<note>Associação das Humanidades Digitais (AHDig),
                     <ptr target="https://ahdig.hypotheses.org/"/>.</note> Sociedad Internacional de
               Humanidades Digitales Hispánicas (HDH) in Spain,<note>Humanidades Digitales
                  Hispánicas. Sociedad (HDH), <ptr
                     target="https://humanidadesdigitaleshispanicas.es/"/>.</note> the Associació
               d’Humanitats Digitals Catalanes in Catalonia,<note>Associació d’Humanitats Digitals
                  Catalanes (AHDCat), <ptr target="http://ahdcat.org/"/>.</note> and the Asociación
               Argentina de Humanidades Digitales (AAHD),<note>Asociación Argentina de Humanidades
                  Digitales (AAHD), <ptr target="http://aahd.net.ar/"/>.</note> founded in 2013
               during THATCamp Buenos Aires, started populating the global DH landscape.<note><ptr
                     target="http://buenosaires2013.thatcamp.org/."/></note> More recently, the Red
               Colombiana de Humanidades Digitales (RedCo)<note>Red Colombiana de Humanidades
                  Digitales, <ptr target="http://www.rehdi.co/"/>.</note> in Colombia came into
               play, as well as more informal initiatives in Perú and Uruguay,<note>Asociación
                  Uruguaya de Humanidades Digitales (HDU), <ptr
                     target="https://www.facebook.com/DHUruguay/"/>. This institutional growth of
                  associations is also a European trend, that in the last years has also seen the
                  creation of the Associazione di Informatica Umanistica (AIUCD), <ptr
                     target="http://www.aiucd.it/"/>, in Italy, the Digital Humanities im
                  deutschsprachigen raum (DHD), <ptr target="https://dig-hum.de/"/>, in Germany, and
                  Humanistica-Association francophone des humanités numériques/digitales, <ptr
                     target="http://www.humanisti.ca/"/>, smartly created as a Francophone
                  association in which it is the linguistic liaison that prevails, rather than the
                  geographic element. All of them count on listserv as their main channel of
                  communication to spread the news.</note> and others with a regional Latin American
               scope, such as Latamhd.<note>A mailing list that aims at bringing together dh’ers in
                  Latin America: latamhd@lists.humanidadesdigitales.net (<ptr
                     target="https://www.latamhd.net/"/>).</note></p>

            <p>Thus, during the last decade, the Spanish-speaking DH higher education curriculum
               experienced a sudden—although unstable—growth. In Spain, as early as 2006, the
               Escuela Superior de Ingeniería Informática at the Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha
               opened a short-lived MA in Digital Humanities, but only since 2016 have other Spanish
               universities, such as the Universidad de Salamanca, with its MA in Textual Heritage
               and Digital Humanities, the Universidad Pablo Olavide (Seville),<note>Máster
                  Universitario en Patrimonio Textual y Humanidades Digitales: <ptr
                     target="https://diarium.usal.es/masteriemyr/"/>.</note> with the MA in History
               and Digital Humanities, the Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona<note>MA in Humanities
                  and Digital Heritage: <ptr
                     target="https://www.uab.cat/web/estudiar/l-oferta-de-masters-oficials/informacio-general/humanitats-i-patrimoni-digitals-1096480139517.html?param1=1345803179474"
                  />.</note> and Universitat de Barcelona<note>MA in Digital Humanities:<ptr
                     target=" https://www.ub.edu/portal/web/informacio-mitjans-audiovisuals/masters-universitaris/-/ensenyament/detallEnsenyament/5900191/1"
                  />.</note> started incorporating DH in their postgraduate curriculum.<note>Máster
                  Universitario Historia y Humanidades Digitales: <ptr
                     target="https://www.upo.es/postgrado/Master-Oficial-Historia-y-Humanidades-Digitales"
                  />.</note> Also, postgraduate courses that focus on digital literature, such as
               the ones offered at the Universidad Complutense de Madrid by the Research Group
               LEETHI, joined the formal DH training landscape in Spain.<note><ptr
                     target="https://www.ucm.es/master-letrasdigitales/"/>.</note> In the realms of
               distance education, the Laboratorio de Innovación en Humanidades Digitales (LINHD),
               at the Universidad Nacional de Educación a Distancia (UNED), has been since 2014 the
               only institution with a continuous academic offering of DH courses in which
               professors from Spain and Latin America participate (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#gonzalez-blanco_etal2017a">González-Blanco et al. 2017a</ref>).<note><ptr
                     target="http://linhd.uned.es/."/>
               </note> In 2019, LINHD merged its different DH semester certificates—the Experto en
               Humanidades Digitales, Experto en Edición Digital Académica, Experto en Programación
               con R—into a single university-specific MA, the <soCalled>Máster Universitario en
                  Humanidades Digitales.</soCalled><note>For more information, see: <ptr
                     target="http://linhd.uned.es/p/dh-master-humanidades-digitales-2019/"/>.</note>
               Another online university, La Universidad en Internet­–Universidad Internacional de
               La Rioja (UNIR) has proposed a new MA in Digital Humanities that will include a
               module in digital editing.<note><ptr
                     target="https://www.unir.net/humanidades/master-humanidades-digitales/549203796794/"
                  />.</note> On the other side of the Atlantic Ocean, in Latin America, DH
               instruction has been mostly represented by the MA degree of the Universidad de Los
               Andes (Colombia)<note><ptr target="https://tinyurl.com/ycm9nsm3"/>.</note> and the
               one at the Universidad del Claustro de Sor Juana (México).<note><ptr
                     target="https://www.elclaustro.edu.mx/maestr%C3%ADas/maestria-en-comunicacion-y-humanidades-digitales/"
                  />.</note> However, there are many informal DH initiatives worth highlighting,
               such as the Seminario HD in México, that is part of the activities of the RedHD at
               UNAM (Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México, Facultad de Filosofía y
                     Letras)<note><ptr target="http://www.humanidadesdigitales.net/seminario-hd/"
                  />.</note> (<ref type="bibl" target="#priani2007">Priani Saisó 2007</ref>), and
               the many DH events organized between the Asociación Argentina de Humanidades
               Digitales (AAHD) and Humanidades Digitales CAICYT Lab (CONICET)<note><ptr
                     target="http://hdlab.space/"/>.</note> that have together been offering
               workshops, courses, and conferences.</p>

            <p>Despite this current positive context, the last ten years show a slow uptake in the
               use of the TEI as the standard for encoding and exchanging humanities data in most of
               the Spanish-speaking countries, being mostly limited to DH projects from Spain. In
               broad terms, the general feeling is a lack of awareness and mastery when compared,
               for instance, to anglophone Digital Scholarly Editions (DSE) projects, as well as a
               lack of communication with those research groups; TEI is not well known and its use
               is limited, especially if contrasted with other non-anglophone countries such as
               France or Germany, where it was adopted early in Humanities Computing projects.</p>

            <p>Nonetheless, we can trace an early interest in the TEI that goes back at least to the
               early 1990s and 2000s (<ref type="bibl" target="#faulhaber1994">Faulhaber 1994</ref>;
                  <ref type="bibl" target="#marin1994">Marcos Marín 1994</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#morras2003">Morrás 2003</ref>), though it is in the next decade when the
               TEI seems to gain more traction with one-day workshops such as <title level="a"
                  >Introducción a los lenguajes de marcado de texto: XML y TEI</title> (Alejandro
                  Bia),<note>See a full list of courses and workshops on his personal website: <ptr
                     target="http://alexbia.edu.umh.es/academia/docencia/"/>.</note> or as part of
               events (the workshop taught by Paul Spence at the First Conference of the HDH
               association in 2013 at the Universidade da Coruña, España), and also other very
               specific ones like <title level="a">XML-TEI for Ancient and Medieval Lexicographical
                  Works,</title> held at the Institució Milà i Fontanals-CSIC in Barcelona that same
                     year.<note><ptr target="http://gmlc.imf.csic.es/2013/Workshop/index.php"
                  />.</note> When it comes to TEI teaching, LINHD is currently, as mentioned, the
               only institution offering TEI training, devoting two three-month modules to text
               encoding and the TEI in its MA in DH. Moreover, since 2014, LINHD has been organizing
               DH summer schools in which TEI has always been part of the agenda.</p>

            <p>In contrast, in Latin America, we find TEI mostly confined to a few projects and
               informal education.<note>A very complete approach in <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#priani2019">Priani Saisó (2019)</ref>.</note> Since 2012 many TEI
               workshops have been held in México, at the RedHD conferences, and at the TEC
               (Monterrey) by North American experts. Further south, in Argentina, we find one-day
               TEI workshops on the TEI since 2013, initially at the THATCamp Buenos
                     Aires,<note><ptr target="http://buenosaires2013.thatcamp.org/"/>.</note> and
               then at the First National Conference of the AAHD (2014),<note><title level="a"
                     >Introducción a la Edición Digital Académica,</title> by Gimena del Rio Riande,
                  Clara Martínez Cantón, and Elena González Blanco. See: <ptr
                     target="https://www.aacademica.org/jornadasaahd/95"/>.</note> as well as at its
               Second International Conference (2016), and at Citep UBA (2018).<note>This workshop
                  was taught by the authors as part of the activities offered in Buenos Aires after
                  the Third International Conference of the AAHD, held in the city of Rosario,
                  Argentina, in 2018: <ptr
                     target="https://tthub.io/aprende/taller-hackathon-buenos-aires/"/>.</note>
               However, we can also trace postgraduate courses devoted to TEI at the Universidad de
               Buenos Aires<note>See the first DH four-month course taught by Gimena del Rio Riande
                  at Facultad de Filosofía y Letras in 2015: <ptr
                     target="https://tinyurl.com/ycsbjyzu"/> and others as part of the Medieval
                  Hispanic Literature classes (2017).</note> and the Universidad Nacional de Mar del
               Plata, as well as a one-month summer school on TEI at Universidad de La Plata
                  (2015).<note>An online two-month course taught by Gimena del Rio and Natalia
                  Corbellini (2016) in an Argentinian university. See: <ptr
                     target="https://tinyurl.com/y8rb2reu"/>.</note> Finally, two-day TEI workshops
               were also taught at Pontificia Universidad Católica in Chile in 2017,<note><ptr
                     target="https://tinyurl.com/y8eryh7d"/>.</note> and at different events in Cuba
               in 2017 and 2018.<note>In 2017, Gimena del Rio Riande and Elena González Blanco
                  taught a workshop on the use of TEI for DSE, as well as two other workshops
                  devoted to the Digital Editing inside and outside Academy, with special emphasis
                  on the use of TEI, in 2018 during the Feria del Libro de la Habana: <ptr
                     target="http://www.saavedra15-conicet.gov.ar/iibicrit-entrevista-a-la-dra-del-rio-riande-en-la-xxvii-feria-del-libro-de-la-habana/"
                  />.</note></p>

            <p>Scholarly literature about the TEI finds a certain continuity in Spain after the
               2000s (<ref type="bibl" target="#megias2008">Lucía Megías 2008</ref>). Other work
               published subsequently offers general overviews that concentrate only on the Spanish
               situation, with no reference to Latin American experiences (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#spence2014">Spence 2014</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#spence_blanco2014">Spence and González-Blanco 2014</ref>; <ref
                  type="bibl" target="#allestorrent2017">Allés-Torrent 2017</ref>). Nonetheless, in
               the last few years a growing number of publications dealing with TEI and its
               application in Spain and Latin American projects can be found (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#faulhaber1994">Faulhaber 1994</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#fradejasRueda2019-10">Fradejas 2009</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#revenga2014">Revenga 2014</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#allestorrent2015">Allés-Torrent 2015</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#gonzalez-blanco_etal2014">González-Blanco et al. 2014</ref>, <ref
                  type="bibl" target="#gonzalez-blanco_etal2016">2016</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#delRioRiande_Zubillaga2015">del Rio Riande and Zubillaga 2015</ref>; <ref
                  type="bibl" target="#castro2017">Rojas Castro 2017</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#priani2017">Priani Saisó 2017</ref>; and <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#mccarl2018">McCarl 2018</ref>, among many others).</p>

            <p>It is interesting to note that the landscape of DH projects and DSE related to
               Hispanic texts shows some very specific features. Gathering information from two
               existing catalogues<note>The Catalogue of Digital Editions, by Greta Franzini, <ptr
                     target="https://dig-ed-cat.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/"/>, and the <title level="m"
                     >Catalogue of Digital Scholarly Editions</title>, by Patrick Sahle, <ptr
                     target="http://www.digitale-edition.de/"/>.</note> we can assert that DSEs are
               a common practice among scholars interested in Medieval Hispanic texts (such as
               Cantar de Mío Cid)<note><ptr target="https://miocid.wlu.edu/?v=nor"/>.</note> and
               Early Modern Literature—the so-called Golden Age period—but TEI is not always used as
               a standard in them. In this group we find editions of classical plays such as Miguel
               de Cervantes’ <title level="m">La Entretenida</title> or Lope de Vega’s <title
                  level="m">La Dama Boba</title>, and others regarding Don Quixote through
               well-funded projects (<ref type="bibl" target="#allestorrent2017">Allés-Torrent
                  2017</ref>). Early Mexican manuscripts are minimally represented by <title
                  level="m">El sitio de Guaman Poma</title>, or the <title level="m">Codice
                  Mendoza</title>.<note><ptr
                     target="http://www.kb.dk/permalink/2006/poma/info/en/frontpage.htm"/> and <ptr
                     target="http://codicemendoza.inah.gob.mx/inicio.php"/>.</note> Other
               initiatives deal with the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, such as <title
                  level="m"><q>En el ojo del huracán</q> Cartas de Yltramar a España, 1823—Edición
                  Digital</title>, <title level="m">The Pérez Galdós Edition Project</title>, the
                  <title level="m">Manuscrito digital de Juan Goytisolo or Obras Completas de José
                  Luis Romero</title>,<note><ptr target="http://www.cartas-de-ultramar.net/"/>, <ptr
                     target="http://www.gep.group.shef.ac.uk/"/>, <ptr
                     target="http://goytisolo.unibe.ch/"/>, <ptr target="http://jlromero.com.ar/"
                  />.</note> among the ones using TEI. We emphasize that many of them were carried
               out in non-hispanic institutions (<title level="m">Cantar de Mio Cid</title>, <title
                  level="m">El sitio de Guaman Poma</title>, <title level="m">Manuscrito digital de
                  Juan Goytisolo</title>), and that others, like the Quijote Interactivo, a
               pioneering website hosted by the Biblioteca Nacional de España, were built with
               proprietary and quite obsolete technologies such as Adobe Flash Player, or not using
               any textual markup, as in the case of the <title level="m">Códice Mendoza</title>,
               funded by the INAH in Mexico, which seems focused on the spatial representation of
               the mesoamerican manuscript images. </p>


            <p>Even when using the TEI, these editions do not always declare their use thereof, and
               only a few of them, such as the <title level="m">Biblioteca Digital del Pensamiento
                  Novohispano</title>, present clear documentation on their encoding
                  practice.<note>Documentation can be found at the project’s site: <ptr
                     target="http://www.bdpn.unam.mx/documentation"/>. See also a list of projects
                  from Spain and Latin America that use the TEI for encoding and publishing in <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#priani2017">Priani Saisó 2017</ref>.</note></p>

            <p>TEI was used in the two most important Spanish projects in Digital Libraries in the
               early 2000s: the <title level="m">Biblioteca Virtual Miguel de Cervantes</title> and
                  <title level="m">Corpus Diacrónico del Español</title> (CORDE). Although these
               projects were pioneers in Spain and they undertook the creation of corpora using
               standards, such as the TEI, they left almost no documentation about their practice
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#bia_pedreno2001">Bia and Pedreño, 2001</ref>).</p>


         </div>

         <div xml:id="pedagogyInSpanish">
            <head>Pedagogy and TEI in Spanish</head>

            <div xml:id="whatToTeach">
               <head>What Do We Want to Teach or ... What Can We Teach?</head>

               <p>The growing global interest in DH has resulted in an increasing number of courses,
                  modules, certificates, and even degrees covering a broad range of topics at the
                  intersection of Humanities and Information and Communication Technology (ICT)
                  methods. However, despite the numerous efforts to train students and researchers
                  formally in the wide-ranging field of DH, <quote source="#quoteref1">scholarship
                     in this area has tended to focus on research methods, theories, and results
                     rather than critical pedagogy and the actual practice of teaching</quote> (<ref
                     type="bibl" target="#hirsch2012" xml:id="quoteref1">Hirsch 2012</ref>). The
                  publication of key resources, such as <title level="m">Digital Pedagogy in the
                     Humanities</title> by MLA Commons, filled this critical gap.<note><ptr
                        target="https://digitalpedagogy.mla.hcommons.org/"/>.</note> One of the most
                  important unanswered questions in our field remains whether we can—in theory and
                  practice—pursue not only new ways of thinking about the humanities but also new
                  ways of teaching and interacting with students mediated by digital tools. To that
                  end, open educational resources, tools, and training materials play a primary
                  role.</p>

               <p>Many academic publications have called for formal education in DH, including the
                  special edition of the DH Quarterly on Undergraduate Education<note><ptr
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/3/index.html"/>.</note>
                  and <ref type="bibl" target="#battershill2017">Battershill and Ross (2017)</ref>,
                  about DH in the classroom. Pedagogy has also been at the forefront of some key
                  events, such as the annual Digital Humanities Summer Institute in Victoria
                  beginning in 2007, and in the re-establishment of the Education SIG of the Text
                  Encoding Initiative at the TEI members’ meeting in November 2017.<note>For more
                     information, see: <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/SIG/Education/"
                     />.</note> Moreover, the mini-conferences on pedagogy now held regularly during
                  the ADHO conference have envisioned the establishment of an ADHO SIG on Digital
                  Pedagogy. Other initiatives support the curation of teaching materials, such as
                  the well-funded platform #dariahTeach under the mission of gathering
                     <q>open-source, high quality, multilingual [DH] teaching materials for the
                     digital arts and humanities.</q><note>The project is part of DARIAH (Digital
                     Research Infrastructure for the Arts and the Humanities) and available at <ptr
                        target="https://teach.dariah.eu/"/>. This initiative has recently created a
                     Registry of DH courses <ptr
                        target="https://registries.clarin-dariah.eu/courses/"/>, but, as expected,
                     it collects mostly European initiatives.</note> All in all, these initiatives
                  reflect more than ever how we—as instructors—want to communicate and interact with
                  our students. At the same time, they underscore the challenge of what we can
                  teach, depending on the different educational contexts.</p>

               <p>Inside the Spanish-speaking community, many debates on the anglo-US centrism, as
                  well as on the heterogeneity of approaches on topics such as how to understand DH,
                  what to teach, and, essentially, whether digital humanities equals humanidades
                  digitales, are taking place (<ref type="bibl" target="#delRioRiande2015a">del Rio
                     Riande 2015a</ref>, <ref type="bibl" target="#delRioRiande2016a">2016a</ref>,
                     <ref type="bibl" target="#delRioRiande2016b">2016b</ref>). What seems obvious
                  is that all global practices are born out of local circumstances that shape the
                  ways through which we navigate the different contexts, locally and globally. In
                  each country, and even at the lower levels of regions and institutions, we can
                  find a different academic tradition and a different methodological approach to
                  their cultural, literary, and artistic heritage. At this point, two key elements
                  come into play: on the one hand, the different academic dynamics that may hinder
                  the diversification of programs and approaches, and on the other hand, the fact
                  that the Spanish-speaking community has approached the TEI with a specific
                  interest in the creation of DSE and digital corpora. Although we do not intend to
                  deal with editorial theory in this paper, we think that, in addition to the
                  problem of language, one of the main challenges we should consider in order to
                  adopt and adapt the use of the TEI is the reconceptualization of the
                  Anglo-American and British textual critical traditions that generally inform the
                  TEI. The so-called <term>crítica textual hispánica</term> (hispanic textual
                  criticism) holds a central position in Spanish philological studies, but—with some
                  exceptions—it is completely unknown in Latin America, where scholars have
                  separated the concept of the literary text from philology or textual criticism
                     (<ref type="bibl" target="#rodriquez2008">Rodríguez Temperley 2008</ref>).
                  Thus, as an academic discipline, philology is almost nonexistent in Latin America,
                  where only Classical or Medieval Studies make reference to it. Approaches to texts
                  are, consequently, very different in Hispanic contexts than in anglophone
                  contexts. Teaching TEI in these settings requires different digital practices that
                  are adapted to these different cultural traditions in the classroom and in
                  research projects.</p>

               <p>This humanidades digitales context consequently demands, following <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#hirsch2012">Hirsch (2012)</ref>, not only the emergence of
                  research methods and theories, but also a critical pedagogical approach and a
                  reframing of teaching practice. In other words, we should meditate on how we
                  should approach the teaching of the TEI, under a set of particular cultural and
                  linguistic circumstances,<note>It is sometimes forgotten that most Latin American
                     countries do not integrate the higher positions in the English Proficiency
                     Index (EPI): <ptr target="https://www.ef.com.es/epi/"/>.</note> in order to
                  make it worth learning, to overcome the steep learning curve, and to convincingly
                  embrace it from a broader cultural and humanistic perspective. As instructors, we
                  should be able to readjust general and global goals to local or national praxis,
                  melding tradition with new digital practices. Consequently, among the many tasks
                  that we should undertake to facilitate the learning and thus the adoption of the
                  TEI in our different contexts, we should approach text encoding practice not only
                  in our own language but from our own cultural tradition; then, we should adapt
                  practices and guidelines to our own work and draft documentation in order to
                  facilitate learning; we should teach TEI and other text encoding methods, applying
                  truly digital processes and delivering digital outcomes; and finally, we should be
                  aware of job opportunities requesting DH expertise inside and outside academia,
                  and hence prepare students for those markets.</p>

               <p>From the student’s perspective, and in the case of TEI learning, we think that
                  instruction should be rooted in multiple competencies and goals, some of which
                  must target global trends towards best practices, while others must be adapted to
                  local ones. In broad terms and from a technical perspective, students should
                  master the fundamentals of XML standards and related languages; understand the
                  mechanisms of TEI; navigate and use the TEI Guidelines; be aware of the best
                  practices of the TEI community; model the markup of different textual types by
                  themselves; create and customize schemas; be able to draft technical documentation
                  about encoding and digital projects; be acquainted with the existing tools for
                  using, exploiting, and preserving TEI documents; and practice collaborative work.
                  But targeting these technical goals will not be enough if we do not also point
                  towards a bigger picture and to real-case examples and scenarios where TEI can be
                  useful, such as in cultural institutions, libraries, and publishing
                     houses.<note>Paige Morgan has collected a list of skills in libraries: <title
                        level="a">Requested skills and expertise, DH/DS front facing library
                        positions, 2010–2018,</title>
                     <ptr
                        target="https://public.tableau.com/profile/paige.morgan#!/vizhome/RequestedskillsexpertiseDHDSlibrarypositions2010-2018/RequestedskillsandexpertiseDHDSfrontfacinglibrarypositions2010-2018"
                     />.</note> Moreover, this change should be accompanied by a general discourse
                  on text technologies, by the many dimensions that a text can adopt, and by a
                  holistic understanding of how digital methods can improve the quality of students’
                  work and skills for the job market. </p>

            </div>

            <div xml:id="pedContexts">
               <head>Different Pedagogical Contexts</head>

               <p>The reflection on what we teach or what we can teach should take into
                  consideration where the teaching happens too. There are different pedagogical and
                  linguistic contexts in which TEI can be taught. From our teaching experience, we
                  can give account of at least three different scenarios where we have worked with
                  students on the use of TEI. Each of them required different pedagogical
                  approaches: first, the traditional face-to-face classroom teaching using a common
                  native language; second, distance education also using Spanish as a native
                  language; and third, the Foreign Language Classroom where learning TEI is
                  performed using a second language.</p>

               <div xml:id="f2fClass">
                  <head>Teaching TEI to Spanish Speakers in a Face-to-Face Classroom</head>

                  <p>Face-to-face teaching, also known as frontal teaching, chalk-and-talk, and
                     teacher-centered instruction (<ref type="bibl" target="#dee2014">Dee
                     2014</ref>), is the most traditional and unexceptional learning situation, as
                     well as the one that favors a more active-learning approach. However, we find
                     this approach adopted only for workshops, due to the fact that TEI is not yet
                     offered as part of a regular course at the undergraduate or graduate level at
                     universities. As expected, among the general benefits of this modality are the
                     possibility of doing hands-on practice in the classroom and correcting the
                     students’ work in class in a process that can involve professors, while also
                     exchanging materials among students and doing peer-revision. In addition, it
                     creates an environment that facilitates a situated learning experience, as
                     proposed by <ref type="bibl" target="#lave_wenger1991">Lave and Wenger
                        (1991)</ref>, who argue that the learning process should be in service of
                     the activity, context, and culture in which it occurs. Social interaction is
                     one of the most important components in this approach, as it empowers the
                     construction of, and feeling of belonging to, a community of practice. As TEI
                     is, precisely, a community of practice, this seems to be a perfect environment
                     for students to use a hands-on approach and feel more involved. These
                     advantages are obviously reinforced by the use of the students’ native language
                     and also the work on texts written in their native language. Of course, the
                     more familiar students are with them, the more likely they are to understand
                     what markup is appropriate or useful, though it involves the use of another
                     artificial language (that sometimes is not completely familiar). Nevertheless,
                     because this kind of training is represented mostly by two or four-hour
                     workshops, as part of conferences or specific events, instead of a full
                     semester class, there is not enough time to deal with the full stack of
                     technologies involved in the process of TEI publication.<note>For some
                        examples, see notes 30, 31, 32, 34 and 35. In 2019, Gimena del Rio started
                        directing the project <title level="a">Reis Trobadors: reconstrucción
                           filológico-musicológica de la lírica medieval románica con herramientas
                           digitales</title> (Filo:CyT) in which students learn to use the TEI and
                        publish medieval Castilian and Galician-Portuguese poetry with minimal
                        technologies. See: <ptr target="http://hdlab.space/Poesia-Medieval/"/> (site
                        under construction by the students with HD CAICYT Lab members’ supervision).
                        In 2020, del Rio and Raffaele Viglianti are starting the course <title
                           level="a">Digital Publishing with Minimal Computing: digital humanities
                           at a global scale,</title> which is part of the Global Classrooms Program
                        based at the University of Maryland (USA) and the Universidad del Salvador
                        (Argentina). The course, which will run for three years, uses minimal
                        publishing technologies based on TEI encoding.</note></p>
               </div>

               <div xml:id="distanceClass">
                  <head>Teaching TEI to Spanish Speakers in a Distance Classroom</head>

                  <p>Distance education is currently a leading force in the academic and
                     professional world: online universities, courses, and MOOCs have reconfigured
                     the way we teach and learn. As we stated previously, we have been involved with
                     LINHD’s distance <soCalled>MA in DH</soCalled> courses since 2015 and with its
                     summer schools since 2014. We have also taught a distance summer course devoted
                     to TEI and DSE at Universidad de La Plata (Argentina).<note>In 2019, we taught
                        the online course <title level="a">Explorar las Humanidades
                           Digitales</title> in Argentina: <ptr
                           target="http://citep.rec.uba.ar/explorar-las-humanidades-digitales-2/"/>.
                        Although the two-month course was not mainly focused on TEI, in the last
                        section devoted to semantic annotation with Recogito (Pelagios Network) we
                        presented a theoretical approach to TEI encoding.</note></p>


                  <p>Our TEI distance courses<note>See notes 19, 20 and 33.</note> have attracted
                     the attention of adult students with an academic background, a small amount of
                     time available (due to work or family reasons), and an engagement in continuous
                     educational training. The main advantage of this kind of course is the
                     permanent access to platforms and course materials, which confers a greater
                     flexibility for this audience in terms of <quote source="#quoteref2">the
                        learner’s own time</quote> and of their <quote source="#quoteref3"
                        >familiarities and motivation</quote> (<ref type="bibl" target="#dee2016"
                        xml:id="quoteref2">Dee, Foradi, Šarić 2016: 20</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                        target="#mahony_pierazzo2012" xml:id="quoteref3">Mahony and Pierazzo 2012:
                        224</ref>). However, in this kind of environment, both teachers and students
                     lose immediacy, since all communication has to be done through forums and
                     emails. While distance courses are able to attract a larger and more
                     heterogeneous student body, they hinder the instructor’s ability to interact
                     with individual students and their motivations and needs (<ref type="bibl"
                        target="#terras_etal2009">Terras, Van Den Branden &amp; Vanhoutte 2009:
                        299</ref>).</p>

                  <p>In this kind of environment, teaching TEI or other specific technologies faces
                     one major problem: learning a notably hands-on field only through a distance
                     method and by virtual learning. Thus, corrections and feedback on results are
                     sometimes difficult to explain, highlight, and follow, so it is hard to turn
                     these moments into an active learning experience. We believe that improvements
                     to distance Spanish TEI training should aim to address two needs: the need for
                     completeness and explicitness of the materials in an online educational space;
                     and the need to offer materials in Spanish, in a form neutral enough to respond
                     to different nations that share a common language (Spain, Latin America). In
                     the case of the distance courses in which we have been involved, the emphasis
                     was placed on creating our own learning materials in Spanish: some were
                     translations of parts of the TEI website content; some were newly-created
                     content adapted to projects and examples of Spanish text encoding; and others
                     required the creation of interactive quizzes through which students could test
                     their learning. We have also worked in building a specific and relevant Spanish
                     corpus for our students.</p>

               </div>

               <div xml:id="nonSpanish">
                  <head>Teaching TEI to Non-Spanish Speakers in Spanish</head>

                  <p>There is a third and perhaps more complex scenario where we teach TEI: the
                     foreign language classroom.<note>At an undergraduate level, some of our
                        experiences teaching TEI and guiding our students towards an editorial
                        project are: <title level="m">Mini Lazarillo: edición mínima del Lazarillo
                           de Tormes</title>, 2016, <ptr target="https://minilazarillo.github.io/"/>
                        (Columbia University), and <title level="m">Lorca descubriendo las
                           Américas</title>, 2017, <ptr
                           target="https://susannalles.github.io/teaching/SPA322/Web_Lorca/"/>, a
                        project that took advantage of a collection from the Richter Library at the
                        University of Miami, <ptr
                           target="http://merrick.library.miami.edu/cubanHeritage/chc5324/"
                        />.</note> In the case of the North American academy, for example, many
                     departments of Modern Languages and Literatures are hiring DH faculty, who are
                     bringing technologies, methods, and concepts to apply to it. This policy is not
                     only extending the importance of Spanish as a second language at university,
                     but giving visibility to the Hispanic community, the largest linguistic
                     minority in the United States, where some impressive digital initiatives and
                     projects are emerging, such as the Relaciones Geográficas<note><ptr
                           target="http://sites.utexas.edu/llilasbensonds/projects/relaciones-geograficas/"
                        />.</note> (providing data for 71 towns in New Spain) or the first US
                     Digital Humanities Center for Latina/o Studies at the University of
                           Houston.<note><ptr
                           target="https://uh.edu/news-events/stories/2019/august-2019/07312019-us-latino-digital-humanities-program.php"
                        />.</note></p>

                  <p>Needless to say, in these latter cases we work with advanced undergraduate
                     learners who have mastered a second language, although sometimes not
                     comprehensively. In an ideal situation, we would work with Spanish texts to be
                     encoded as well as teaching materials also in the target language. The reality,
                     however, is that we encounter great challenges, such as the lack of materials
                     adapted to different oral and written language levels. Students go through a
                     twofold process: they learn new DH concepts while they improve their language
                     skills. Thus, they need additional materials, such as bilingual glossaries,
                     which must be extremely detailed and self-explanatory. As a general conclusion,
                     we can say that learning an encoding practice and publishing with TEI can be a
                     way for students to engage with literature (<ref type="bibl"
                        target="#cummings2007">Cummings 2007</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                        target="#baldwin2013">Baldwin 2013</ref>); and it can also entail a certain
                     type of hermeneutics and appropriation of the texts (<ref type="bibl"
                        target="#burnard2001">Burnard 2001</ref>), while the student is using the
                     second language (in this case, Spanish) to communicate in class and learn.</p>

               </div>

            </div>

         </div>

         <div xml:id="dearthOfResources">
            <head>The Dearth of TEI Teaching Resources in Spanish</head>

            <p>Despite the enthusiasm for diving into DH topics and methods, including the TEI, we
               still face a dearth of resources for TEI written in Spanish. This problem affects
               instructors, students, and the TEI and DH global community in general, and it emerges
               in many different ways.<note>It must be highlighted that some capstone publications
                  on DH and Pedagogy, such as the <title level="m">Debates in Digital
                     Humanities</title> (<ref type="bibl" target="#gold2012">Gold 2012</ref>; <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#gold_klein2016">Gold and Klein 2016</ref>) or <title
                     level="m">Digital Humanities Pedagogy</title> (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#hirsch2012">Hirsh 2012</ref>) do not explore this problem, nor do
                  Spanish case studies appear in international publications on DSE (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#driscoll_pierazzo2016">Driscroll and Pierazzo 2016</ref>).</note>
               Without the aim of being exhaustive, we see the most prominent obstacles as
               follows.</p>

            <p>The TEI Guidelines, originally written in English, have never been completely
               translated into Spanish. The very first translation by Verónica Zumárraga and Marcela
               Tabanera, the <title level="m">Manual para la codificación e intercambio de textos
                  informatizados. Normas de la Text Encoding Initiative</title>, translated only
               version 1.01 of the Guidelines (<ref type="bibl" target="#marin1986">Marcos Marín,
                  1986: 89</ref>). This translation project was later taken up by Alejandro Bia and
               Carmen Arronis Llopis, and their unfinished work was published on the TEI
                  website.<note>For a list of translations, see <ptr
                     target="http://www.tei-c.org/Tools/I18N/"/>.</note> A complete and
               authoritative translation of TEI documentation (elements, attributes, and so forth)
               remains urgent. This challenge is now being addressed by the newly established TEI
               Working Group on Internationalization (I18n).<note>For information on the first TEI
                  internationalization efforts, see: <ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/tools/i18n/tei-internationalization-proposal/"/>. In
                  October 2019 a group of TEI members—Hugh Cayless, Martina Scholger, Luis Meneses,
                  Gimena del Rio Riande, Helena Bermúdez Sabel, and Kiyonori Nagasaki— met at the
                  Triangle Scholarly Communication Institute hosted by Duke University Libraries to
                  discuss the topic of <title level="a">Communicating the TEI to a Multilingual User
                     Community</title>. This second working group is part of the conversations at
                  that event. See:<ptr
                     target=" https://trianglesci.org/2019/07/17/communicating-the-tei-to-a-multilingual-user-community/"
                  />.</note>
            </p>

            <p>Although this is slowly changing, the TEI website itself does not offer even a
               landing page in other languages, and all descriptive prose is in English. This
               monolingual website thus becomes a barrier to novice users from other linguistic
               areas.</p>

            <p>There are still some debates as to how to accomplish internationalization, such as
               the translation of tags. In 2005, Sebastian Rahtz said <quote source="#quoteref4">we
                  need to make sure that the TEI and its Guidelines are internationalized and
                  localized so that they are accessible in all parts of the world</quote> (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#rahtz2005" xml:id="quoteref4">Rahtz 2005</ref>).
               Multilingualism is the new frontier in DH. Though we believe that glossaries and
               lists of equivalences can also help with the internationalization of the TEI, the
               vitality of multilingualism is a force both for the development of DH and the
               adoption of the TEI as standard, at least in countries where English is not
               understood as global or used as a language for scientific communication (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#honna2005">Honna 2005</ref>).</p>

            <p>The main channel of discussion in the TEI listserv is dominated by anglophones, while
               only a few other communities have their own channels, such as the French TEI
               listserv. This fact sometimes discourages Spanish speakers from raising their doubts,
               both because they are afraid of not expressing themselves correctly, and because the
               textual problems that they encounter are often difficult to contextualize not only
               from an anglophone perspective but also in a foreign language. Also, most of the news
               and updates on really useful materials, such as TEI Simple, are not disseminated in
               other languages and thus are not used in Spanish or Latin American projects.</p>

            <p>Unfortunately, the cost of membership and licenses, in the current context of the
               global economy, hinders many Global South researchers from becoming members of the
               TEI Consortium. Consequently, extremely useful resources such as TAPAS are not known
               and/or used by these communities. Also, one of the biggest drawbacks of teaching TEI
               in this context is the use of proprietary software in workshops. Although there are
               free XML editors, working with them is more challenging for novice Spanish students,
               requiring extra help for the markup activity and translation of tags. Proprietary
               licensing fees constrain the use of that software to short-term training
               opportunities.</p>

            <p>There is, as we have already mentioned, an absence of teaching materials in Spanish,
               such as websites, videos, presentations, and modules. While there are multiple web
               resources dealing with technical documentation in Spanish, such as tutorials on XML,
               XSLT, and XPath, they have not been created from a DH perspective, and thus they are
               inadequate for a humanities context. In addition, even though there are a lot of open
               access materials on the web on DH training and DSE in TEI in English,<note>This is
                  the case with, for instance, DiXit materials, <ptr
                     target="http://dixit.uni-koeln.de/programme/materials/"/>.</note> it is not
               enough for the Spanish-speaking community to translate them, since it is necessary to
               re-create the problems and adapt existing materials to their own needs and
               examples.</p>

            <p>There is a shortage of open source examples of real projects in Spanish.<note><ptr
                     target="https://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Samples_of_TEI_texts"/>.</note> As the
               TEI By Example team has noted, <quote source="#quoteref5">being able to view the
                  markup approaches of established scholars and projects in the field is an
                  essential tool for TEI teaching which is currently not utilized</quote> (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#terras_etal2009" xml:id="quoteref5">Terras, Van den Branden
                  and Vanhoutte 2009: 300</ref>). The few examples of encoded text in Spanish are
               the ones published by the Computergestützte literarische
                     Gattungsstilistik.<note><title level="m">Collection of 19th Century
                     Spanish-American Novels (1880–1916)</title>, edited by Ulrike Henny-Krahmer
                  (which contains 24 novels), or the <title level="m">Corpus of Spanish Novels from
                     1880–1940</title>, edited by José Calvo Tello (with 39 novels) (<ptr
                     target="https://github.com/cligs/textbox"/>).</note> This situation has been
               addressed in <ref type="bibl" target="#priani2017">Priani Saisó’s blog post
                  (2017)</ref>, where a list of TEI encoding examples in Spanish is provided.</p>

            <p>As a global trend, detailed documentation of editorial projects and other
               implementations of TEI is not a regular DH activity. This best practice should be
               highlighted by the TEI community and council as a benefit for the whole collective of
               TEI practitioners. Useful examples in Spanish include the contribution of the Red
                     CHARTA<note><ptr target="https://www.redcharta.es/"/>. The team released the
                  materials under the publication <ref type="bibl" target="#isasi_etal2020">Isasi
                     Martínez et al. (2020)</ref>.</note> on how to encode a particular text
               typology (documents from the twelfth to nineteenth centuries), and the above
               mentioned <title level="m">Biblioteca del Pensamiento Novohispano</title>.</p>

            <p>Finally, many editing platforms and tools for DSE are not well known, either because
               they depend on websites or software entirely developed in English, German, or Dutch,
               or because the sites are not open access or require advanced technical knowledge to
               install the software. There are many different frameworks and platforms for this kind
               of tasks, such as TAPAS, TEI Boilerplate, Juxta, the Versioning Machine 5.0
               (English), TextGrid and Ediarium (Germany), eLaborate (Holland), and Edictor
                  (Brazil).<note>Projects are available at: <ptr target="http://tapasproject.org/"
                  />, <ptr target="http://dcl.ils.indiana.edu/teibp/index.html"/>, <ptr
                     target="http://juxtacommons.org/"/>, <ptr target="http://v-machine.org/"/>,
                     <ptr target="https://textgrid.de"/>, <ptr
                     target="http://www.bbaw.de/telota/software/ediarum"/>, <ptr
                     target="https://www.elaborate.huygens.knaw.nl/login"/>, and <ptr
                     target="https://edictor.net/"/>.</note> However, for the Spanish-speaking
               community, the only current example we could highlight was the all-Spanish Virtual
               Research Environment (EVI-LINHD),<note><ptr target="http://evi.linhd.uned.es/"
                  />.</note> developed at LINHD (UNED) in Spain. The EVI-LINHD environment ran from
               2017 to 2020 creating very simple digital edition projects in an XML-TEI platform
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#gonzalez-blanco_etal2016">González-Blanco et al.
                  2016</ref>, <ref type="bibl" target="#gonzalez-blanco_etal2017b">2017b</ref>). It
               was developed as part of a research project that aimed at offering users an intuitive
               and user-friendly platform for encoding texts without seeing the TEI tags. Although
               EVI-LINHD was a good initiative, there is a clear need for more comprehensive and
               effective editing infrastructures for facilitating the use of the TEI in
               Spanish-speaking contexts. In a multilingual effort,<note><ptr
                     target="https://crowdin.com/project/tei-publisher/invite/public?show_welcome&amp;d=13c9b3c4d6ad86964f49920c6929ad491158629"
                  />.</note> the TEI Publisher (Exist DB Solutions) team has run a crowdsourcing
               project and started translations in different languages, including Spanish.</p>

         </div>

         <div xml:id="needForMaterials">
            <head>The Need for Online Teaching Materials and a Case Study: the <title level="m">Text
                  Technologies Hub</title> and the Online Tutorial <title level="m">Introducción a
                  la Text Encoding Initiative</title></head>

            <p>As we have tried to show in this article, in order to adopt the TEI, the academic
               community, individuals and institutions, need more resources available in their
               native language. In this last section, we would like to propose some strategies to
               address the challenges and issues mentioned above, particularly the translation of
               the TEI Guidelines and the creation of TEI educational materials in Spanish, and to
               outline an overall strategy for moving forward.</p>

            <p>Online tutorials devoted to text technologies and conceived for a broad array of
               learners—from beginners to advanced levels—are now commonplace (W3Schools, Lynda.com,
               CodeAcademy, among many others). Inspired by these kinds of resources, TEI By Example
               was developed several years ago, providing explanations, online tests, and exercises,
               although in English. This research team underscored in 2010 that: <cit>
                  <quote source="#quoteref6">If the digital humanities community wants to promote
                     the TEI markup framework as a serious candidate for dedicated courses in the
                     booming curricula on digital humanities <gap/> then there is an urgent need for
                     an on-line TEI course by example which is less generic than the two tutorials
                     published on the TEI website (A Gentle Introduction to XML and TEI Lite: An
                     introduction to Text Encoding for Interchange) and more general than the 29
                     guides to local practice on that site.</quote>
                  <ref type="bibl" target="#vandenbranden_etal2010" xml:id="quoteref6">Van den
                     Branden, Terras, and Vanhoutte, 2010</ref>
               </cit> They also stressed the need for <quote source="#quoteref7">an online TEI
                  course which is <gap/> more user friendly, comprehensive, and interactive than the
                  online workshop materials which are currently presented as stand alone teaching
                  materials</quote> (<ref type="bibl" target="#terras_etal2009" xml:id="quoteref7"
                  >Terras, Van Den Branden, and Vanhoutte 2009: 299</ref>). After all these years,
               while some of the issues that these authors emphasized remain the same, the
               importance of this kind of resource has been proved extensively and has significantly
               improved the overall situation for TEI users. </p>

            <p>Recently, other interesting initiatives offering pedagogical materials have emerged,
               such as the above mentioned #dariahTeach. This European project inside the consortium
               DARIAH has inaugurated a collection of courses in which we find three of them dealing
               with TEI: <title level="a">Text Encoding and the TEI</title> by Susan Schreibman and
               Roman Bleier in English; French and Spanish versions of the same course;<note><ptr
                     target="https://teach.dariah.eu/course/view.php?id=23"/>.</note> and <title
                  level="a">Digital Scholarly Editions: Manuscripts, Texts and TEI Encoding</title>
               by Elena Pierazzo and Marjorie Burghart. These three courses have explanatory videos,
               detailed contents, and exercises that can be considered as pioneers in the field of
               DH online teaching.</p>

            <p>In our case, for many years, we felt the need to gather in one single collaborative
               space the resources written in our language that would allow any Spanish-speaking
               researcher or student to work with the TEI and other text technologies. In 2018 we
               started a personal collaboration under the name of Text Technologies Hub or TTHub, a
               still-emerging project that aims to function as a collaborative open access platform
               of text technologies and materials in Spanish devoted to the Spanish community
               interested in the use of TEI as a standard for DSE and text technologies related to
                  them.<note>This project, available at <ptr target="http://tthub.io"/>, is
                  coordinated by the authors with the collaboration of the PhD student Gabriel
                  Calarco (University of Buenos Aires). So far, it is undertaken with no funding or
                  external support.</note> Our goal is to serve as a hub of open online materials,
               resources, news, software, and technologies that can potentially serve those
               interested in textual studies, digital editing, corpus construction, and digitization
               processes in Spanish. We think that many users of these resources, and especially
               textual scholars, need a site where they can find learning materials to uncover
               potential solutions in textual studies. As expected, our audience consists mostly of
               neophytes looking for introductory materials to the TEI, that is to say, those
               students and scholars with little or no prior experience in markup languages or
               textual data structures who would like to undertake a digital project or DSE.</p>

            <p>So far, our attention has been devoted to text encoding with TEI, but we hope to open
               up the site to other methods and technologies. The platform, created with Wordpress,
               follows best practices for publishing materials using an open science approach,
               following, among others, the FAIR Data and the Scholarly Commons principles.<note>The
                  FAIR Data Principles are a set of guiding principles in order to make data
                  findable, accessible, interoperable and reusable. FORCE11 houses the 15 FAIR Data
                  Principles: <ptr target="https://www.force11.org/group/fairgroup/fairprinciples"
                  />. The Scholarly Commons principles are a set of best practices, interfaces and
                  standards that aim at governing the multi-directional flow of scholarly objects
                  through all phases of the research process. More about these principles: <ptr
                     target="https://www.force11.org/scholarly-commons/about"/>.</note> We believe
               that when data is easily discoverable, accessible and reusable by others, knowledge
               can advance more quickly. In accordance with this set of principles, we offer all
               materials with an Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International Creative
               Commons License.<note><ptr
                     target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"/>.</note> Although
               this is a quite restrictive license, it must be considered that we publish very
               different kinds of materials from many different authors. We aim at protecting
               authorship while allowing scholars and students to build on each others’ work in a
               fair way that benefits the entire community. In that sense, TTHub offers two ways of
               participating, either as a user who just consults the online materials, or through a
               registry that allows posting and working with the team. Finally, the materials we
               build, like Susanna Allés’ lessons on TEI, are published as text and data with
               persistent identifiers: we generate a digital object identifier (DOI) archiving the
               materials in two open source repositories that work connected, GitHub and Zenodo. We
               consider that this is a best practice for making FAIR Open Educational Resources.</p>

            <p>TTHub is organized in four main sections: Learn (<title level="a">Aprende</title>),
               Participate (<title level="a">Colabora</title>), Resources (<title level="a"
                  >Recursos</title>), and News (<title level="a">Noticias</title>). In the <title
                  level="a">Learn</title> section of the TTHub, we offer presentations from our
               workshops and talks, and a list which brings together curated resources—a list of
               tools as well as a Spanish bibliography in Zotero<note><ptr
                     target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2285352/tei_en_espaol"/>.</note>— that we
               consider useful for learning TEI and other text technologies. All these sections are
               open to collaboration and community feedback and give users the opportunity to
               participate by contributing information or resources that might interest the
               Spanish-speaking TEI community. Most important, in this first section, we currently
               offer a tutorial <title level="a">Introducción a la Text Encoding Initiative</title>,
               divided into seven lessons in Spanish devoted to TEI.<note>They are available at <ptr
                     target="https://tthub.io/aprende/introduccion-a-tei/"/>. A flat version in PDF
                  of the single lessons can also be downloaded under a Creative Commons license and
                  accessed through our GitHub and Zenodo repositories: <ptr
                     target="https://github.com/tthub-repo/lecciones"/> and <ptr
                     target="https://zenodo.org/communities/tei_espanol/"/>.</note> These materials
               were developed by Allés-Torrent and are a version of the teaching materials inspired
               by the several seasons of the Experto Profesional en Humanidades Digitales created in
               January 2014 at the LINHD-UNED (currently the Master Universitario en Humanidades
               Digitales). It has circulated among more than 150 students thus far for more than
               five years with positive feedback.</p>

            <p>Within this TEI tutorial that covers the first steps in a DSE, we aim to give a
               general understanding of TEI mechanisms from the true beginner’s perspective, while
               we collaborate on distributing learning materials to the Spanish speaking community.
               We believe a resource such as this can facilitate the learning experience of scholars
               and students in a self-taught experience, as part of the materials of an academic
               syllabus, or even as the common ground for workshops and other training events. </p>

            <p>The tutorial is divided into seven lessons that, as a whole, explain how to build a
               complete DSE with TEI: 1. Introduction, 2. Fundamentals of XML Languages,<note><ptr
                     target="https://tthub.io/aprende/l2-xml/"/>.</note> 3. General structure of a
               TEI document and General TEI Elements,<note><ptr
                     target="https://tthub.io/aprende/l3-basicos-tei/"/>.</note> 4. The TEI
                     Guidelines,<note><ptr target="https://tthub.io/aprende/l4-guias/"/>.</note> 5.
               Textual typologies,<note><ptr target="https://tthub.io/aprende/l5-tipologias/"
                  />.</note> 6. Customization of schemas,<note><ptr
                     target="https://tthub.io/aprende/l6-esquemas/"/>.</note> and 7. Creation and
               use of the ODD.<note><ptr target="https://tthub.io/aprende/l7-odd/"/>.</note> These
               lessons are complemented by two other GitHub repositories, one containing
                     exercises<note><ptr target="https://github.com/tthub-repo/ejercicios"/>.</note>
               and another one showcasing examples<note><ptr
                     target="https://github.com/tthub-repo/ejemplos"/>.</note> of encodings in TEI
               created ad hoc by the team. Both repositories are open to collaboration, and we truly
               hope that these resources will be considered by the Spanish-speaking community to
               gather more samples. </p>

            <p>In the Resources section, we also offer a list, downloadable as a CSV file,<note><ptr
                     target="https://tthub.io/recursos/ejemplos-tei/"/>.</note> with online encoding
               examples. As the community grows, this examples section should be enriched with
               documentation and real case encoding samples with Spanish texts. The reason behind
               this list is the fact that, although there are already lists of projects using TEI,
               sometimes—and especially for our students—is difficult to locate the TEI encoded
               files. Consequently, we have a quicker access and we learn from real case
               scenarios.</p>

            <p>Finally, we would like to add that, in the <title level="a">Participate</title> tab,
               we have opened up a section to collaboratively participate in a crowdsourced Spanish
               translation of the TEI Guidelines. The idea is to involve the Spanish-speaking
               community in the use of the TEI, not only through a tutorial or through curated
               resources and tools, but also through a personal experience in which English turns
               into Spanish. This crowdsourced Spanish translation, in which professors and students
               from Argentina, Spain, and Chile are already actively participating online and in
               different TEI workshops, is open to any interested person in the TEI who wishes to
               collaborate. Through it we hope not only to spread the word about the advantages of
               the TEI, but also to create a linguistic community of practice. This initiative will
               be carried out together with the above mentioned TEI Internationalization Working
               Group.</p>

         </div>

         <div xml:id="conclusion">
            <head>Some Conclusions</head>

            <p>Teaching TEI using Spanish as a language for both written learning materials and
               written or oral communication in the different pedagogical contexts is a challenging
               experience. On the one hand, we face the specific physical characteristics of the
               different scenarios we have studied here—face-to-face and distance education, Foreign
               Language Classroom—each of which requires a different and specific strategic
               approach. On the other hand, we basically work within two linguistic levels since
               English has been very present in the primary materials we use or refer to, including
               the TEI tags,<note>The fact that an editor like Oxygen helps learners significantly
                  in this process must be highlighted, as it offers a translation of the tags while
                  using them in the encoding activity. However, it should be highlighted that in
                  recent years, different open source editors like JEdit or Atom, and also VS Code,
                  have made significant efforts to incorporate plugins to support TEI encoding (<ref
                     type="bibl" target="#nagasaki2020">Nagasaki 2020</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#schoch2020">Schöch 2020</ref>). Some of them are currently exploring
                  options for offering the tag content translated into other languages.</note> the
               TEI Consortium website, the TEI Guidelines text, and scientific articles and books,
               even as we slowly try to break this barrier by developing our own materials.</p>

            <p>Nevertheless, the slow process of creating and incorporating some translated but
               mostly new pedagogical materials adapted to the needs of our students in Spain and
               Latin America, and in the Foreign Language Classrooms in the United States, was, in
               fact, a turning point: it helped students see how adaptable a standard language, such
               as the TEI, could be, and how a markup language can enhance scholarship in the
               digital age. Moreover, having tutorials, examples, and documentation in our native
               language proved that the English in the metadata—in elements, attributes, or values—
               was not an insurmountable obstacle to surpass in order to work successfully in TEI,
               for instance, in the making of a DSE.</p>

            <p>A situated learning process based on Spanish literary texts and the creation of
               pedagogical materials in Spanish, such as our TTHub initiative, may facilitate the
               adoption of the TEI by the Spanish-speaking community around the world, and may help
               in other contexts, like the Foreign Language Classroom (where Spanish is the foreign
               language). Therefore, we believe that this type of multilingual resource may help not
               only to extend the use of a standard like the TEI, but also to consolidate DH as a
               global academic community around the world.</p>

         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="allestorrent2015"><author>Allés Torrent, Susanna</author>.
                     <date>2015</date>. <title level="a">Edición digital y algunas tecnologías
                     aliadas</title>. <title level="j">Ínsula</title>, <biblScope unit="issue"
                     >812</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">18–21</biblScope>. doi:<idno
                     type="DOI">10.7916/D89S1QFN</idno>. </bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="allestorrent2017"><author>Allés Torrent, Susanna</author>.
                     <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">Tiempos hay de acometer y tiempo de
                     retirar: literatura áurea y edición digital</title>. <title level="j">Studia
                     Aurea. Revista de Literatura Española y Teoría Literaria del Renacimiento y
                     Siglo de Oro</title>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">13–30</biblScope>.
                     doi:<idno type="DOI">10.5565/rev/studiaaurea.261</idno>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="baldwin2013"><author>Baldwin, Sandy</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
                     level="a">The Category of the Literary and the Essence of Digital Humanities,
                     or Some Notes on the Context of My Essay for <title level="m">Digital
                        Humanities Quarterly</title></title>. <title level="j">Digital Humanities
                     Quarterly</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>).
                     <ptr target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000155/000155.html"
                  />.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="battershill2017"><author>Battershill, Claire</author> and
                     <author>Shawna Ross</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="m">Using Digital
                     Humanities in the Classroom. A Practical Introduction for Teachers, Lecturers,
                     and Students</title>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Bloomsbury</publisher>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="bia_pedreno2001"><author>Bia, Alejandro</author>, and <author>Andrés
                     Pedreño</author>. <date>2001</date>. <title level="a">The Miguel de Cervantes
                     Digital Library: the Hispanic Voice on the Web</title>. <title level="j"
                     >Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">16 (2)</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >161–177</biblScope> doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/16.2.161</idno>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="burnard2001"><author>Burnard, Lou</author>. <date>2001</date>. <title
                     level="a">On the hermeneutic implications of text encoding</title>. In <title
                     level="m">New Media and the Humanities: Research and Applications</title>,
                  edited by <editor>Domenico Fiormonte</editor> and <editor>Jonathan Usher</editor>,
                     <biblScope unit="page">31–38</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Humanities Computing Unit</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="http://users.ox.ac.uk/~lou/wip/herman.htm"/>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="cummings2007"><author>Cummings, James</author>. <date>2017</date>.
                     <title level="a">The Text Encoding Initiative and the Study of
                     Literature</title>. In <title level="m">A Companion to Digital Literary
                     Studies</title>, edited by <editor>Ray Siemens</editor> and <editor>Susan
                     Schreibman</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">451–76</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Blackwell</publisher>. </bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="dee2014"><author>Dee, Stella</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title
                     level="a">Learning the TEI in a Digital Environment</title>. <title level="j"
                     >Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">7 (November)</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.4000/jtei.968</idno>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="dee2016"><author>Dee, Stella</author>, <author>Maryam Foradi</author>,
                  and <author>Filip Šarić</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">Learning by
                     Doing: Learning to Implement the TEI Guidelines Through Digital Classics
                     Publication</title>. In <title level="m">Digital Classics Outside the
                     Echo-Chamber: Teaching, Knowledge Exchange &amp; Public Engagement</title>,
                  edited by <editor>Gabriel Bodard</editor> and <editor>Matteo Romanello</editor>,
                     <biblScope unit="page">15–32</biblScope>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Ubiquity Press</publisher>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.5334/bat.b</idno>. </bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="delRioRiande2015a"><author>Del Rio Riande, Gimena</author>.
                     <date>2015a</date>. <title level="a">Humanidades Digitales. Mito, actualidad y
                     condiciones de posibilidad en España y América Latina</title>. <title level="j"
                     >ArtyHum</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">7–19 </biblScope>.
                  November. <ptr
                     target="https://www.artyhum.com/descargas/monograficos/MONOGR%C3%81FICO%20HD.pdf"
                  />.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="delRioRiande2015b"><author>Del Rio Riande, Gimena</author>.
                     <date>2015b</date>. <title level="a">¿De qué hablamos cuando hablamos de
                     Humanidades Digitales? </title>. In <title level="m">Actas I Jornadas de
                     Humanidades Digitales de la AAHD</title>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >50–62</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Buenos Aires</pubPlace>: <publisher>Editorial de
                     la Facultad de Filosofía y Letras</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://www.aacademica.org/jornadasaahd/3.pdf"/>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="delRioRiande2016a"><author>Del Rio Riande, Gimena</author>.
                     <date>2016a</date>. <title level="a">De todo lo visible y lo invisible o volver
                     a pensar la investigación en humanidades digitales</title>. <title level="j"
                     >Signa: Revista de la Asociación Española de Semiótica (UNED)</title>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">25</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">95–108</biblScope>.
                     <ptr target="http://revistas.uned.es/index.php/signa/article/view/16943"
                  />.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="delRioRiande2016b"><author>Del Rio Riande, Gimena</author>. <title
                     level="a">Ada en la encrucijada de las Humanidades Digitales</title>. <title
                     level="j">Luthor</title>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">29 (August)</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="http://www.revistaluthor.com.ar/spip.php?article149"/>.</bibl>

               <!-- No references to this in the text. -->
               <!--<bibl xml:id="delRioRiande2017"><author>Del Rio Riande, Gimena</author>.
                     <date>2017</date>.<title level="a">Construyendo las Humanidades Digitales entre
                     dos orillas. Desafíos desde el LINHD (II)</title>. <title level="m">Docentes en
                     línea</title>. Didáctica y TIC. Blog de la Comunidad virtual de práctica,
                     <date>July 16, 2017</date>. <ref
                     target="http://blogs.unlp.edu.ar/didacticaytic/2017/07/16/construyendo-las-humanidades-digitales-entre-dos-orillas-desafios-desde-el-linhd-ii/"
                  />.</bibl>-->

               <bibl xml:id="delRioRiande_Zubillaga2015"><author>Del Rio Riande, Gimena</author> and
                     <author>Carina Zubillaga</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title level="a">Un
                     proyecto de edición digital académica en Argentina. Diálogo Medieval</title>.
                  In <title level="m">Actas I Jornadas de Humanidades Digitales de la AAHD</title>,
                     <biblScope unit="page">100–114</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Buenos Aires</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Editorial de la Facultad de Filosofía y Letras</publisher>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="driscoll_pierazzo2016"><editor>Driscoll, Matthew James</editor> and
                     <editor>Elena Pierazzo</editor> (eds.). <date>2016</date>. <title level="m"
                     >Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and Practices</title>. <publisher>Open
                     Book Publishers</publisher>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                  >10.11647/OBP.0095</idno>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="faulhaber1994"><author>Faulhaber, Charles B.</author>
                  <date>1994</date>. <title level="a">La Text Encoding Initiative y su aplicación a
                     la codificación textual y explotación</title>. <title level="m">Actas del
                     Congreso de la Lengua Española: Sevilla, 7 al 10 octubre, 1992</title>,
                     <biblScope unit="page">331–340</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Madrid</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Instituto Cervantes</publisher>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="fiormonte2014"><author>Fiormonte, Domenico</author>. <date>2014</date>.
                     <title level="a">Digital Humanities from a global perspective</title>. <title
                     level="j">Laboratorio dell’ISPF</title>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="http://www.ispf-lab.cnr.it/2014_203.pdf"/>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.12862/ispf14L203</idno>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="fiormonte_delrioriande2017"><author>Fiormonte, Domenico</author> and
                     <author>Gimena del Rio Riande</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">Por
                     unas Humanidades Digitales globales</title>. <title level="j">Infolet. Cultura
                     e critica del media digitali</title>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="https://infolet.it/2017/10/09/humanidades-digitales-globales/"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="fradejasRueda2019-10"><author>Fradejas Rueda, José Manuel</author>.
                     <date>2009–2010</date>. <title level="a">La codificación XML/TEI de textos
                     medievales</title>. <title level="j">Memorabilia</title>, <biblScope
                     unit="issue">12</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">219–247</biblScope>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="galina2013"><author>Galina, Isabel</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
                     level="a">Is There Anybody Out There? Building a global Digital Humanities
                     community</title>. <title level="m">Blog colectivo de la Red de Humanidades
                     Digitales de México</title>, July 19, 2013, <ptr
                     target="http://humanidadesdigitales.net/blog/2013/07/19/is-there-anybody-out-there-building-a-global-digital-humanities-community/"
                  />.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="gold2012"><editor>Gold, Matthew K</editor>. (ed.). <date>2012</date>.
                     <title level="m">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>.
                     <pubPlace>Minneapolis, MN</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Minnesota
                     Press</publisher>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.5749/minnesota/9780816677948.001.000</idno>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="gold_klein2016"><editor>Gold, Matthew K.</editor>, and <editor>Lauren
                     F. Klein</editor> (eds.). <date>2016</date>. <title level="m">Debates in the
                     Digital Humanities</title>. <pubPlace>Minneapolis, MN</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>University of Minnesota Press</publisher>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="gonzalez-blanco_etal2014"><author>González-Blanco, Elena</author>,
                     <author>Clara Martínez Cantón</author>, <author>Gimena del Rio Riande</author>,
                  and <author>María Dolores Martos</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">La
                     codificación informática del sistema poético medieval castellano, problemas y
                     propuestas en la elaboración de un repertorio métrico digital: ReMetCa</title>.
                  In <title level="m">Visibilidad y divulgación de la investigación desde las
                     Humanidades Digitales. Experiencias y proyectos</title>, edited by
                     <editor>Alvaro Baraibar</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">172–185</biblScope>.
                     <publisher>Pamplona: Servicio de Publicaciones de la Universidad de
                     Navarra</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="http://www.unav.edu/publicacion/biblioteca-aurea-digital/BIADIG-22"
                  />.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="gonzalez-blanco_etal2016"><author>González Blanco García,
                     Elena</author>, <author>Antonio Robles-Gómez</author>, <author>Salvador
                     Ros</author>, <author>Gimena Del Rio Riande</author>, <author>Roberto
                     Hernández</author>, <author>Miguel Urizar</author>, <author>Clara Martínez
                     Cantón</author>, <author>Rafael Pastor</author>, and <author>Jesús
                     Cano</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">TEIScribe: A graphic tool
                     for composing and testing TEI documents in the context of the EVI-LINHD
                     environment</title>. In <title level="m">TEI Conference and Members’ Meeting
                     2016. Book of Abstracts</title>, edited by <editor>Claudia Resch</editor>,
                     <editor>Vanessa Hannesschläger</editor>, and <editor>Tania Wissik</editor>,
                     <biblScope unit="page">–</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Druck- und Handelsgesellschaft mbH</publisher>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="gonzalez-blanco_etal2017a"><author>González-Blanco, Elena</author>,
                     <author>Gimena del Rio</author>, and <author>Clara Martínez</author>.
                     <date>2017</date>a. <title level="a">Using e-learning systems for DH teaching:
                     the Spanish Humanidades Digitales case study at LINHD</title>. Abstract of
                  paper presented at Digital Humanities 2017. <pubPlace>Montréal</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>McGill University - Université de Montréal</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://dh2017.adho.org/abstracts/429/429.pdf"/>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="gonzalez-blanco_etal2017b"><author>González-Blanco, Elena</author>,
                     <author>Clara Martínez Cantón</author>, <author>Gimena del Rio Riande</author>,
                     <author>Salvador Ros</author>, <author>Rafael Pastor</author>, <author>Antonio
                     Robles-Gómez</author>, <author>Agustín Caminero</author>, <author>María Luisa
                     Díez Platas</author>, <author>Álvaro del Olmo</author>, and <author>Miguel
                     Urízar</author>. <date>2017</date>b. <title level="a">EVI-LINHD, a virtual
                     research environment for the Spanish-speaking community</title>. <title
                     level="j">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">32(2)</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                     >10.1093/llc/fqx025</idno>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="hirsch2012"><editor>Hirsch, Brett D.</editor>, ed. <date>2012</date>.
                     <title level="m">Digital Humanities Pedagogy. Practices, Principles and
                     Politics</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Open Book
                     Publishers</publisher>. doi:<idno type="DOI">10.11647/OBP.0024</idno>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="honna2005"><author>Honna, Nobuyuki</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title
                     level="a">English as a Multilingual Language in Asia and Intercultural
                     Literacy.</title>
                  <title level="j">Intercultural Communication Studies</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">XIV:2</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="https://web.uri.edu/iaics/files/06-Nobuyuki-Honna.pdf"/>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="irizarry1997"><author>Irizarry, Estelle</author>. <date>1997</date>.
                     <title level="m">Informática y literatura. Análisis de textos
                     hispánicos</title>. <pubPlace>Madrid</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Anthropos</publisher>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="isasi_etal2020"><author>Isasi Martínez, Carmen</author>, <author>Leyre
                     Martín Aizpuru</author>, <author>Santiago Pérez Isasi</author>, <author>Elena
                     Pierazzo</author>, and <author>Paul Spence</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title
                     level="m">Edición digital de documentos antiguos: marcación XML_TEI basada en
                     los criterios CHARTA</title>. <pubPlace>Sevila</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>EUS</publisher>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="lave_wenger1991"><author>Lave, Jean</author>, and <author>Etienne
                     Wenger</author>. <date>1991</date>. <title level="m">Situated Learning:
                     Legitimate Peripheral Participation</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="megias2008"><author>Lucía Megías, José Manuel</author>.
                     <date>2008</date>. <title level="a">Las relaciones entre la bibliografía
                     textual y la informática humanística: El incunable del hipertexto</title>.
                  Tipolologia. Rivista Internazionale di Studi Filologici e Linguistici sui testi a
                  stampa 1: 119–138.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="marin1986"><author>Marcos Marín, Francisco A.</author>
                  <date>1986</date>. <title level="a">Metodología informática para la edición de
                     textos</title>. <title level="j">Incipit</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                  >–</biblScope>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="marin1994"><author>Marcos Marín, Francisco A.</author>
                  <date>1994</date>. <title level="m">Informática y Humanidades</title>.
                     <pubPlace>Madrid</pubPlace>: <publisher>Gredos</publisher>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="mahony_pierazzo2012"><author>Mahony, Simon</author>, and <author>Elena
                     Pierazzo</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">Teaching Skills or
                     Teaching Methodology?</title> In <title level="m">Digital Humanities Pedagogy:
                     Practices, Principles and Politics</title>, edited by <editor>Brett D.
                     Hirsch</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">215–6</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Open Book Publishers</publisher>.
                     doi:<idno type="DOI">10.11647/OBP.0024</idno>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="mccarl2018"><author>McCarl, Clayton</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title
                     level="a">Multiple-Layered Encoding as an Editorial and Pedagogical Strategy in
                     Colonial Latin American Studies</title>. <title level="j">Bulletin for Spanish
                     and Portuguese Historical Studies</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">48 (1)</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                     >40–52</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="https://digitalcommons.asphs.net/bsphs/vol43/iss1/3/"/>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="morras2003"><author>Morrás, Maria</author>. <date>2003</date>. <title
                     level="a">Informática y crítica textual: realidades y deseos</title>. In <title
                     level="m">Literatura hipertextual y teoría literaria</title>, edited by
                     <editor>María José Vega</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">225–41</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>Madrid</pubPlace>: <publisher>Mare Nostrum
                  Communicación</publisher>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="nagasaki2020"><author>Nagasaki, Kiyonori</author>. <date>2020</date>.
                     <title level="a">Evasion of breathing tax: editing TEI with VSCode</title>. In
                     <title level="m">digitalnagasakiのブログ</title>. February 2nd, 2020. <ptr
                     target="https://digitalnagasaki.hatenablog.com/entry/2020/02/15/045531"
                  />.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="odonnell2012"><author>O’Donnell, Daniel P.</author>
                  <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">In a rich man’s world: Global DH?,</title>
                  <title level="j">dpod blog. The first draft of my research, teaching and
                     reading</title>, November 2, 2012, <ptr
                     target="http://dpod.kakelbont.ca/2012/11/02/in-a-rich-mans-world-global-dh/"
                  />.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="odonnell_etal2016a"><author>O’Donnell, Daniel P.</author>,
                     <author>Katherine L. Walter</author>, <author>Alex Gil</author>, and
                     <author>Neil Fraistat</author>. <date>2016</date>a. <title level="a">Only
                     Connect: The Globalization of the Digital Humanities</title>. In <title
                     level="m">A New Companion to Digital Humanities</title>, <edition>2nd
                     Edition</edition>, edited by <editor>Susan Schreibman</editor>, <editor>Ray
                     Siemens</editor>, and <editor>John Unsworth</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >493–510</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Chichester</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="odonnell_etal2016b"><author>O’Donnell, Daniel P.</author>,
                     <author>Barbara Bordalejo</author>, <author>Padmini Murray Ray</author>,
                     <author>Gimena del Rio</author>, and <author>Elena González-Blanco</author>.
                     <date>2016</date>b. <title level="a">Boundary Land: Diversity as a defining
                     feature of the Digital Humanities</title>. In <title level="m">Digital
                     Humanities 2016. Conference Abstracts</title>: <biblScope unit="page"
                     >76–82</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Kraków</pubPlace>: <publisher>Jagiellonian
                     University &amp; Pedagogical University</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="http://dh2016.adho.org/abstracts/406"/>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="priani2007"><author>Priani Saisó, Ernesto</author>. <date>2007</date>.
                     <title level="a">Revista Digital Universitaria: A Workshop of Digital Editing
                     at the Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México</title>. <title level="j"
                     >Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1 (2)</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/1/2/000014/000014.html"/>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="priani2017"><author>Priani Saisó, Ernesto</author>. <date>2017</date>.
                     <title level="a">Documentos con marcado TEI en español</title>.
                  ernestopriani.com, August 12. <ptr
                     target="https://ernestopriani.com/blog/documentos-con-marcado-tei-en-espanol/"
                  />.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="priani2019">
                  <author>Priani Saisó, Ernesto</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title level="a"
                     >Codificación y buenas prácticas. Crítica a la delimitación de las humanidades
                     digitales en América Latina</title>. <title level="m">Relaciones. Estudios de
                     historia y sociedad</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">XL(158)</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >129–144</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                  >10.24901/rehs.v40i158.343</idno>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="rahtz2005"><author>Rahtz, Sebastian</author>. <date>2005</date>. <title
                     level="a">TEI Internationalization</title> (Presentation). Available at: <ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/Talks/2005/Wuerzburg/i18n.pdf"/>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="revenga2014"><author>Revenga, Nàdia</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title
                     level="a">La edición crítica digital de textos teatrales. <title level="m">La
                        Estrella de Sevilla</title> como ejemplo</title>. <title level="j">Anuario
                     de Lope de Vega. Texto, literatura, cultura</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                  >99–121</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
                  >10.5565/rev/anuariolopedevega.85</idno>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="rodriquez2008"><author>Rodríguez Temperley, María M.</author>
                  <date>2008</date>. <title level="a">La Edad Media en las tierras del Plata: a
                     propósito del medievalismo en la Argentina</title>. <title level="j">Revista de
                     Poética Medieval</title>
                  <title level="j">21</title>: <biblScope unit="page">221–293</biblScope>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="castro2017"><author>Rojas Castro, Antonio</author>. <date>2017</date>.
                     <title level="a">La edición crítica digital y la codificación TEI. Preliminares
                     para una nueva edición de las Soledades de Luis de Góngora</title>. <title
                     level="j">Revista de Humanidades Digitales</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">4–19</biblScope>.
                     doi:<idno type="DOI">10.5944/rhd.vol.1.2017.16379</idno>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="schoch2020"><author>Schöch, Christof</author>. <date>2020</date>.
                     <title level="a">Can Atom replace oXygen?</title>
                  <title level="m">The Dragonflyʼs Gaze. Computational analysis of literary
                     texts</title>. March 28th, 2020. <ptr
                     target="https://dragonfly.hypotheses.org/1127"/>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="spence2014"><author>Spence, Paul</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title
                     level="a">Edición académica en la era digital: modelos, difusión y proceso de
                     investigación</title>. <title level="j">Anuario Lope de Vega: Texto,
                     literatura, cultura</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">47–83</biblScope>.
                     doi:<idno type="DOI">10.5565/rev/anuariolopedevega.74</idno>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="spence_blanco2014"><author>Spence, Paul</author>, and <author>Elena
                     González Blanco</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">A historical
                     perspective on the digital humanities in Spain</title>. <title level="m">The
                     Status Quo of Digital Humanities in Spain</title>, H-Soz-Kult, <ptr
                     target="http://www.hsozkult.de/debate/id/diskussionen-2449"/>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="terras_etal2009"><author>Terras, Melissa</author>, <author>Ron Van Den
                     Branden</author>, and <author>Edward Vanhoutte</author>. <date>2009</date>.
                     <title level="a">Teaching TEI: The Need for TEI by Example</title>. <title
                     level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">24 (3)</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                     >297–306</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI">10.1093/llc/fqp018</idno>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="vandenbranden_etal2010"><author>Van den Branden, Ron</author>,
                     <author>Melissa Terras</author>, and <author>Edward Vanhoutte</author>.
                     <date>2010</date>. <title level="m">TEI by Example</title>. Last updated July
                  9, 2010. <ptr target="http://www.teibyexample.org/"/>.</bibl>

            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
