<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:27+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Network Dynamics, Plot Analysis: Approaching the Progressive Structuration of Literary Texts Introduction and related works</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Frank</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">National Research University Higher School of Economics</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mathias</forename><surname>Göbel</surname></persName>
							<email>goebel@sub.uni-goettingen.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Göttingen State and University Library</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dario</forename><surname>Kampkaspar</surname></persName>
							<email>kampkaspar@hab.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Graz</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Austria Peer Trilcke</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Herzog</forename><forename type="middle">August</forename><surname>Library</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Potsdam</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Germany</forename><forename type="middle">Christopher</forename><surname>Kittel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Potsdam</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Network Dynamics, Plot Analysis: Approaching the Progressive Structuration of Literary Texts Introduction and related works</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction and related works</head><p>In recent years, the application of network analysis methods to literary texts has evolved into an independent research field of digital literary studies. Methods for the automated extraction of network data (named entity recognition, co-reference resolution) and their evaluation are of particular importance <ref type="bibr">(El- son et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Park et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Agrarwal et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Fischer et al. 2015</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Waumans et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Jannidis et al. 2016</ref>). Based on the data obtained, several types of analyses were developed: an empirical, quantitative and hierarchical description of literary characters ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Jannidis et al. 2016</ref>), corpus-based analyses exploring options for historical periodisation of literature ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Trilcke et al. 2015</ref>) and types of aesthetic modelling of social formations in and by literary texts <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Stiller et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Stiller &amp; Hudson 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Trilcke et al. 2016</ref>).</p><p>What has been neglected so far (although already suggested by Moretti 2011) is the application of network analysis as a tool for quantitative plot analysis. In fact, current approaches in the field of literary network analysis are not suited to gaining insights into the plot development of literary texts ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Prado et al. 2016</ref>). The sequential dimension of literary texts, as a consequence of their temporality, usually remains in the dark: what is extracted, visualised and analysed are static networks. Plot, however, is essentially a concept supposed to theoretically encompass the temporality of narrative (as well as dramatic) texts: "the repeated attempts to redefine parameters of plot reflect both the centrality and the complexity of the temporal dimension of narrative" <ref type="bibr">(Dannenberg 2005: pp. 435</ref>). Plot can be understood as a concept for the description of the "progressive structuration" <ref type="bibr">(Kukkonen 2013: §4)</ref> of literary texts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research objective: plot analysis</head><p>Attempts to further develop literary network analysis towards a quantitative plot analysis must consider the temporal dimension in the modelling of their research objects. The structure of a literary text is to be modelled as a changing sequence of network states. It is only through looking into these network dynamics that we can discuss network-analytic approaches for a quantitative plot analysis.</p><p>Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Prado et al. 2016</ref>, we are currently extending our research on literary networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Trilcke 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fischer et al. 2015ff</ref>.; <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Fischer et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Trilcke et al. 2016</ref>) to the analysis of progressive structuration. Our goal is to examine whether (and with what kind of limitations) we can flesh out an operationalisation for the plot analysis of literary texts. By doing so, we are, of course, not trying to replace the semantically rich and versatile concept of 'plot' with a quantitative and thus reductionist concept. Rather, we will show that certain aspects of what is commonly discussed within the framework of plot analysis can be retraced by means of a computer-based analysis of network dynamics.</p><p>The visualisation of dynamic graphs, as is common in other domains ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Pohl et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Frederico et al. 2011</ref>), has recently been transferred to literary networks ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Xanthos et al. 2016</ref>). While it may come in useful when close-reading a text and for didactic purposes, it is unsatisfactory when it comes to an actual corpus-based analysis. There are no canonical methods to help us compare network visualisations generated automatically by force-directed graph drawing algorithms. The reception of dynamic visualisations just does not offer practical analytical means. From a dedicated distant-reading kind of perspective, the calculation of dynamic network metrics and their statistical processing is much more promising as it offers options to describe general characteristics of networks from a larger corpus as well as to compare specific formal types of networks within the corpus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measuring dynamic literary networks</head><p>A number of basic global measures for the analysis of dynamic networks (i.e., size, density, homogeneity in the distribution of ties, rate of changes in nodes, rate of changes in ties) has been discussed by <ref type="bibr">Carley (2003: pp. 135-36)</ref>. In addition, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Prado et al. 2016</ref> recently suggested the application of actor-oriented measures, especially centrality indices, for the reconstruction of plot development. We are currently applying these measures to our own corpus, consisting of 465 German language plays. We also developed a set of other measures with recourse to traditional theoretical concepts for the description of specific phenomena of plot development, especially with regard to types of dramatic expositions <ref type="bibr">(Pfister 1977: pp. 124-36)</ref>, the "classical" act structure of tragedy and the composition principle of main and secondary plots <ref type="bibr">(Pfister 1977: pp. 286-89)</ref>. Calculation of these measures was implemented in our own network analysis tool dramavis (Kittel/Fischer 2017).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Event-based measures</head><p>In general, two types of measures can be distinguished for describing dramatic texts as dynamic networks: event-based and progression-based measures. Event-based measures are used to identify or characterise a particular point in time within a drama. In this context we developed an all-in index, a value that identifies the point in time at which all characters have occurred at least once in a drama (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>selected plays</head><p>The final-scene-size value characterises a specific point in time, in this case the last scene of a drama. It determines the percentage of all characters of a drama which appear on stage in the last scene. This value shows characteristic differences between dramatic subgenres, especially when comparing tragedies and comedies (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Progression-based measures</head><p>While event-based measures allow assumptions about a particular state/point in time of the dynamic network, progression-based measures allow a general characterisation of the transformation of a dramatic network. In this regard, we introduced a measure we call the drama-change rate. The basis of our calculation is a modified Levenshtein distance, which only takes into account insertions ("add character") and deletions ("delete character"). In each case, we compare characters present in two consecutive scenes, eventually resulting in what we call the segment-change rate <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Figure 3</ref>). The sum of all segment-change rates of a drama divided by the number of all segment-change rates is what we call the drama-change rate. The development of this rate can be represented in a chart, which due to its shape we tentatively called the beat chart ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure  4</ref>). Having calculated the drama-change-rate value for the entire corpus, we can start to compare a larger set of dramas with each other ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref>). It becomes evident that our corpus does not exhibit a clear trend along the timeline. Instead, we witness the emergence of characteristic types of dramas, which differ characteristically from the other texts in our corpus. On the one hand, we can identify dramas exhibiting a high drama-change rate, i.e., highly dynamic dramas with a constant alternation of characters on stage <ref type="figure">(Fig- ure 6</ref>). On the other hand, low-dynamic dramas can be identified, with only small changes taking place between scenes <ref type="figure">(Figure 7</ref>). A further option for the comparative analysis of our oscillatory beat charts is the analysis of the standard deviation of all segment-change rates of a drama. We can again distinguish two particularly striking types: On the one hand, there are dramas with a high standard deviation, indicating that extensive changes of characters alternate with small changes; we can call them high-dynamic dramas <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">(Figure 8</ref>). On the other hand, there are dramas showing a low standard deviation, so the change on stage takes place in the same rhythm, we call these texts low-dynamic dramas <ref type="figure">(Fig- ure 9</ref>). The preceding cases each describe characteristic deviations regarding the drama-change rate of groups of texts. In addition, a 'normal type' of drama can be identified, which corresponds to the mean value for the corpus both in terms of arithmetic mean and standard deviation <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 10</ref>). It also appears that strong upward shifts, accompanied by a complete exchange of characters on stage, often coincide with act boundaries (vertical orange lines), which is in accordance with historical conventions of dramatic composition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary and further research</head><p>Our research on dynamic networks provides basic components for a quantitative analysis of the progressive structuration of dramatic texts. Future research will have to develop and evaluate additional measures and it will be decisive to hold interpretations of these measures against the backdrop of historical drama poetics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bibliography</head><p>Agarwal, A., Corvalan, A., Jensen, J., <ref type="bibr">Rambow</ref>  . Federico, P., Aigner, W., Miksch, S., Windhager, F., Zenk, L.</p><p>(2011). A Visual Analytics Approach to Dynamic Social Networks. Proceedings of the 11th International Conference on Knowledge Management and Knowledge Technologies (i-KNOW). Graz, http://publik.tuwien.ac.at/files/PubDat_198995.pdf <ref type="bibr">[accessed 27 Mar 2017]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fischer, F., Göbel, M., Kampkaspar, D., Trilcke, P. (2015).</head><p>Digital Network Analysis of Dramatic Texts. Digital Humanities 2015. Conference Abstracts. University of Western Sydney, http://dh2015.org/abstracts/xml/FISCHER_Frank_Digital_Network_Analy-sis_of_Dramati/FISCHER_Frank_Digital_Network_Analy-sis_of_Dramatic_Text.html <ref type="bibr">[accessed 27 Mar 2017]</ref>. <ref type="figure">Fischer, F., Göbel, M., Kampkaspar, D.</ref>, Kittel, C., Trilcke, P. (2015ff.).</p><p>[Blog] dlina - Digitally-Driven Literary Network Analysis (of Dramatic Texts).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: All-in index for 6 selected plays</figDesc><graphic url="image-1.png" coords="2,68.46,540.06,228.96,152.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Final-scene-size index (mean values of entire corpus and subgenres)</figDesc><graphic url="image-2.png" coords="2,331.02,158.46,226.32,150.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Calculation of the segment-change rate (example)</figDesc><graphic url="image-3.png" coords="2,331.02,508.14,235.20,76.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Beat chart for Goethe's play "Iphigenie auf Tauris" (1787)</figDesc><graphic url="image-4.png" coords="3,68.46,72.30,228.96,138.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Historical distribution of drama-change rates in the DLINA corpus</figDesc><graphic url="image-5.png" coords="3,54.30,329.58,228.96,143.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 :Figure 7 :</head><label>67</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Two examples of highly dynamic dramas -left: Goethe's "Egmont" (1788); right: Lenz's "Der Hofmeister" (1774)</figDesc><graphic url="image-6.png" coords="3,54.30,580.14,218.40,65.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8: Two Examples for high-dynamic dramas -left: Benkowitz's "Die Jubelfeier der Hölle" (1801), right: Goethe's "Faust I" (1808)</figDesc><graphic url="image-9.png" coords="3,316.86,446.22,227.52,68.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10: Beat chart for Ganghofer's "Der Herrgottschnitzer von Ammergau" (1880)</figDesc><graphic url="image-10.png" coords="4,54.30,72.30,216.72,132.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of Methods for the Identification of Main Characters in German Novels</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jannidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Reger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krug</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Weimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Macharowsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Puppe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://dh2016.adho.org/abstracts/297[accessed27" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Digital Humanities 2016. Conference Abstracts</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="578" to="82" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Jagiellonian University &amp; Pedagogical University, KrakówKraków</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kittel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://github.com/lehkost/dramavis" />
		<title level="m">GitHub repo</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-03" />
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>dramavis (v0.3</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plot. Hü hn</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kukkonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Living Handbook of Narratology</title>
		<editor>P. et al.</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Hamburg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Network Theory, Plot Analysis. Stanford Literary Lab Pamphlets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Moretti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://litlab.stanford.edu/LiteraryLabPamphlet2.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-03" />
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural Analysis on Social Network Constructed from Characters in Literature Texts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G.-M</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S.-H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-G</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ojs.academypublisher.com/index.php/jcp/arti-cle/view/jcp080924422447/7672" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Das Drama. Theorie und Analyse</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pfister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1977" />
			<publisher>Fink</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">As Time Goes by. Integrated Visualization and Analysis of Dynamic Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Reitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Birke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">10.1145/1385569.1385636</idno>
		<idno>ac- cessed 27</idno>
		<ptr target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1385569.1385636" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">AVI 2008 - Proceedings of the Working Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces. Neapel</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-03" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="372" to="75" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temporal Network Analysis of Literary Texts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Prado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dahmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L C</forename><surname>Bazzan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mac Carron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kenna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1602.07275" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advances in Complex Systems (ACS)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Character Networks and Centrality. Thè se de Doctorat</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yannick</forename><surname>Rochat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://infos-cience.epfl.ch/record/203889/files/yrochat_thesis_in-foscience.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-03" />
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Lausanne</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Small World of Shakespeare&apos;s Plays. Human Nature 14</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stiller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nettle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I M</forename><surname>Dunbar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.staff.ncl.ac.uk/daniel.net-tle/shakespeare.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-03" />
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Weak Links and Scene Cliques Within the Small World of Shakespeare</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stiller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cultural and Evolutionary Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">200 Years of Literary Network Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Trilcke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Göbel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kampkaspar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://dlina.github.io/200-Years-of-Literary-Network-Data/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-03" />
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theatre Plays as &apos;Small Worlds&apos;? Network Data on the History and Typology of German Drama, 1730-1930</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Trilcke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Göbel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kampkaspar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kittel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://dh2016.adho.org/abstracts/407" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Digital Humanities 2016. Conference Abstracts</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-03" />
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Jagiellonian University &amp; Pedagogical University, Krakówków</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Social Network Analysis (SNA) als Methode einer textempirischen Literaturwissenschaft</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Trilcke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ajouri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Empirie in der Literaturwissenschaft. Mü nster: mentis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="247" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Topology Analysis of Social Networks Extracted from Literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Waumans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nicodème</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bersini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0126470</idno>
		<idno>ac- cessed 27</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0126470" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plos One</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Xanthos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Pante</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rochat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grandjean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://dh2016.adho.org/abstracts/407[accessed27" />
		<title level="m">Visualising the Dynamics of Character Networks. Digital Humanities 2016. Conference Abstracts. Jagiellonian University &amp; Pedagogical University, KrakówKraków</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="436" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
