<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:31+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Character Distributions of Classical Chinese Literary Texts: Zipf&apos;s Law, Genres, and Epochs Introduction and Main Findings</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chao-Lin</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">National Chengchi University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Shuhua</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<email>shuhuazhang1@sina.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>United States of America</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yuanli</forename><surname>Geng</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>United States of America</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Huei-Ling</forename><surname>Lai</surname></persName>
							<email>hllai@nccu.edu.tw</email>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">National Chengchi University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hongsu</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<email>hongsuwang@fas.harvard.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>United States of America</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Character Distributions of Classical Chinese Literary Texts: Zipf&apos;s Law, Genres, and Epochs Introduction and Main Findings</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Corpora and Comparisons</head><p>For ease of references, we assigned an acronym for each of the 14 corpora, and show their names in Chinese (Collection) and periods of publication (Time) in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>. The corpora consist of representative literature that has been published since 1046BC. In particular, we have at least one collection for each of the major dynasties that existed before 1644AD. The majority of our collections are of poetic works (we consider SJ, CV, HF, PT, CTP, CSP, CSL, YSX, and LCSJ collections of poetic works) which fact lends itself to the study of the effects of genres on the character distributions. A collection of poetic works for the Qing Dynasty (which lasted from 1644 to 1912AD) is unavailable because an editorial committee is still working on its production <ref type="bibr">(Zhu, 1994)</ref>.</p><p>The corpora contain more than 42 million characters, excluding the punctuation marks that were added into the corpora by the data providers. When counting the characters, we also exclude characters that cannot be shown on ordinary computers. The frequencies of such rare and obsolete characters are not large, so ignoring them will not affect the statistical properties reported in this study.</p><p>Only the ASBC was segmented and the segmentation was verified by human experts. Hence, we can inspect its character and word distributions. The other corpora were written in classical Chinese and we do not have a reliable way for segmentation, so we will only analyze the character distributions.</p><p>We created charts that are based on the typical form of Zipf's law:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">( ) ) ( log ) ( log w r k N w f α − = ⎟ ⎠ ⎞ ⎜ ⎝ ⎛</formula><p>where w, f(w), and r(w) denote a word, its frequency, and rank in a corpus, respectively. The rank of the most frequent word in a corpus is 1. N is the size of the corpus, and k and 񮽙 are constants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Observations and Discussions: Influences of Genres and Epochs</head><p>The generalizability of the Zipf's law is the main reason that it has attracted the attention of many researchers. It can be applied to various natural distributions including those of part-of-speech of words ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Wang et al, 2012</ref>), city sizes ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Anderson and Ge, 2005)</ref>, and corporal revenues <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Chen et al, 2008</ref>). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> shows the Zipfian curves when we consider the character distributions of all of the 14 corpora. We intentionally plot the curves in one chart, although this makes the individual curves undistinguishable. Although the curves are not linear, which is common as reported in the literature, the curves show a consistent trend, suggesting a common regularity that is shared by Chinese texts that were produced over the period of 3000 years. Instead of treating the 14 corpora as a single corpus to fit the resulting distribution for Zipf's law, we examined the curves to investigate possible factors that influenced the positions of the curves. In <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>, we show the curves of lyrics ("詞" /ci2/) and poems ("詩" /shi1/. The left halves of the curves overlap almost perfectly, which strongly indicates that the poetic works share very close statistical characteristics. <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref> lists ten most frequent characters found in each of the corpora and for which the curves are plotted in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. The lists are very similar, and, out of the 60 characters in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>, there are only 16 distinct characters (some of which are homonyms, for which only one pronunciation is provided). In fact, we can compare the most frequent characters of any two corpora, e.g., the CTP and the CSP, to further investigate their similarity <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Chen et al, 2012</ref>), and we found that the most frequent 1700 characters in the CTP and the CSP are the same characters.</p><p>Not all of the corpora of poetic works have similar curves. We added the curves for the SJ, CV, and HF in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref>, and it is evident that these new curves do not overlap with those in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> very well. The poetic works in the SJ, CV, and HF were produced very much earlier than those listed in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. While the time of the production of the corpora affects the Zipfian curves, the curves for corpora that were produced in the same dynasty may not be the same. The CTW, MZM, and CTP are three different types of works that were all produced in the Tang Dynasty. We compared the most frequent characters shared by the CTP and CTW, and found that the sets of their most frequent 2000 characters differ only in three characters. Despite such an extreme overlap, their curves in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref> suggest that genre affects the character distributions. Given the above observations, one may have expected that the curves for the novels that were published in the 16 th and 18 th centuries, i.e., the JTTW and DRC, will deviate from the curves for the earlier poems, as the curves in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5</ref> show. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Character vs. Word distributions</head><p>We considered the character distribution when we analyzed the contents of the ASBC in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, where we found that the character distributions of the vernacular and classical Chinese texts show a reasonable common trend. The ASBC contains documents that were written in vernacular Chinese, so we must also analyze its word distribution, and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure  6</ref> shows the curves for both the character and word distributions.</p><p>A chart like that of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 6</ref> can mislead one to infer that Chinese texts do not conform to Zipf's law. It is well accepted that the number of Chinese characters is limited, although there is no consensus about the exact number of characters. In contrast, there is virtually no limit on the number of legal Chinese n-grams. As a result, the sharp downturn of the character distribution and the intersection of the two curves in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 6</ref> are expected, and this can be observed in languages other than Chinese in some special settings <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Montemurro, 2001</ref>). We should examine the Zipfian curves on the same basis, e.g., character or word, while considering cultural factors that may influence actual language usage. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Concluding Remarks</head><p>We have judged the similarity between the Ziphian curves based on the visual closeness, though we can quantify the degree of similarity when desired (Hu and <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Kuo, 2005</ref>). Researchers have noticed the deviations of Zipfian curves at the high- and low-frequency ends ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hu and</ref><ref type="bibr">Kuo, 2005, Rousseau and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Zhang, 1992</ref>) and tried to find density functions that fit the data. The statistics at the high-frequency ends of the curves are evidently more reliable. We focused on the deviations at the high-frequency ends of the curves, and discussed how the deviations in these regions may relate to the genres and epochs of the corpora, employing the lists of most frequent characters of the corpora as extra supports.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Zipfian curves of 14 corpora suggest a common trend. (Character distributions)</figDesc><graphic url="image-2.png" coords="2,316.86,213.66,238.08,155.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Curves for ancient poetic works (SJ, CV, and HF) do not coincide with those of later poems.</figDesc><graphic url="image-5.png" coords="3,54.30,390.06,238.08,153.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Curves of corpora that belong to the same dynasty but of different genres deviate from each other.</figDesc><graphic url="image-6.png" coords="3,316.86,72.30,241.44,156.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Curves of corpora that contain novels of 16th and 18th century (JTTW &amp; DRC, respectively) deviate from the curves in Figure 2.</figDesc><graphic url="image-7.png" coords="3,316.86,329.34,241.44,157.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. Word and character distributions for the ASBC differ significantly.</figDesc><graphic url="image-8.png" coords="4,54.30,201.42,241.20,157.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>The corpora used in this study include texts 
published during 1046BC-2007AD. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>The most frequent ten characters in poems and lyrics remaining stable over time</figDesc><table></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>This research was supported in part by the grant 104-2221-E-004-005-MY3 from the Ministry of Science and Technology of Taiwan, the grant USA-HAR-105-V02 from the Top University Strategic Alliance of Taiwan, and the Senior Fulbright Research Grant 2016-2017.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bibliography</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Altmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-H</forename><surname>Best</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hřebíček</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Köhler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kromer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Rottmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schulz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wimmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ziegler</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Glottometrics</title>
		<editor>A.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<publisher>RAM-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The size distribution of Chinese cities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Regional Science and Urban Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="756" to="776" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A statistical study on Chinese word and character usage in literatures from the Tang dynasty to the present</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Quantitative Linguistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Zipf&apos;s law in the revenue of top 500 Chinese companies</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Wang</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the Fourth Int&apos;l Conf. on Wireless Communications, Networking and Mobile Computing</title>
		<meeting>of the Fourth Int&apos;l Conf. on Wireless Communications, Networking and Mobile Computing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rank-frequency relation for Chinese characters</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Deng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Allahverdyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Wang</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The European Physical Journal B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">47</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Extension of Zipf&apos;s law to word and character n-grams for English and Chinese, Int&apos;l J. of Computational Linguistics and Chinese Language Processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Ha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Sicilia-Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="102" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Universality and scaling in the statistical data of literary works, POLA Forever: Festschrift in Honor of Professor William S</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C.-K</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W.-C</forename><surname>Kuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Wang on His 70 th Birthday</title>
		<editor>Ovid J. L. Tzeng</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="139" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond the Zipf-Mandelbrot law in quantitative linguistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Montemurro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physica A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">300</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="567" to="578" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Zipf&apos;s word frequency law in natural language: A critical review and future directions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Piantadosi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychonomic Bulletin &amp; Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1112" to="1130" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Applications and Explanations of Zipf&apos;s Law</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M W</forename><surname>Powers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Workshop on New Methods in Language Processing and Computational Natural Language Learning</title>
		<meeting>the Workshop on New Methods in Language Processing and Computational Natural Language Learning</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="160" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Zipf&apos;s data on the frequency of Chinese words Revised</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rousseau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="220" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lotka phenomenon in the words&apos; syntactic distribution complexity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="483" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Chinese Lexicography</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Selected Studies of the Principle of Relative Frequency in Language</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Zipf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1932" />
			<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zipf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
