<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:29+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">947 Partition on the Margins: The Untold Testimonies of Sikh, Bahawalpur and Marwari Communities</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Shaifali</forename><surname>Arora</surname></persName>
							<email>arora.shaifali16@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">School of Humanities and Social Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Humanities and Social Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Indian Institute of Technology Indore</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>India Nirmala Menon</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Indian Institute of Technology Indore</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">947 Partition on the Margins: The Untold Testimonies of Sikh, Bahawalpur and Marwari Communities</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>There are several ongoing digital projects that contextualise historical events into narratives such as 1947 Partition Archive, 1984 Living History, Kashmir Oral History, Indian Memory Project and</head><p>Holocaust Memorial Museum. The memory projects on the 1947 partition such as 1947 Partition Archive mostly record stories that are often (rightly so) narratives of violence and bloodshed. However, there is gap in existing literature and database that do not document less violent partition experiences of a large population that mostly live at the western Indian border. The aim of the current project is to document those unheard communities which escaped immediate violence but continue to suffer the residual pains of geo-cultural and economical traumas in post-partition India. The poster also offers a framework of methodology to be followed for developing the project. The methodology involves collection of data by visiting the villages, audio-video interviews with families, collecting photographs and letters, transcription and description of interviews and contextualising photographs and letters in narratives. The development of final testimonies achieved through these working stages will be developed into an open access website, hosted through KSHIP (Knowledge Sharing In Publication) which is a multilingual academic publishing project at IIT (Indian Institute of Technology) Indore, India.</p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
