<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/yoann/Work/Grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.4-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-05T06:42+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Contextual interpretation of digital music notation</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><surname>Page</surname></persName>
							<email>kevin.page@oerc.ox.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
							<email>david.lewis@oerc.ox.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Weigl</surname></persName>
							<email>david.weigl@oerc.ox.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Contextual interpretation of digital music notation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Linked notation in support of musicology</head><p>Notation examples are a vital part of analytical essays in musicology, helping to illustrate analytical observations and justify hypotheses, arguments and conclusions. They can be excerpts from a score, or custommade notations which add annotations or comments to the original notation.</p><p>Furthermore, the presentation of multiple analogous musical extracts for comparison is often required to support a musicological narrative. Paradigmatic analysis, for example, involves passages of music placed one above another such that analogous elements are directly juxtaposed, with gaps left as necessary to ensure that vertical alignment is preserved. Stacked presentation of different scores or different parts of the same score have been used for well over a century, but they quickly become unwieldy and hard to interpret, especially as the number of extracts increases. What is not available in such paper-based approaches is the interactivity that can make complex comparisons between many extracts practical by turning a static presentation into an iterative exploration of digital materials.</p><p>In this paper we consider the example of a digital companion presenting the contents of a Research Object studying the interpretation of leitmotif examples from Wagner's compositions, specifically the Ring cycle, as they are presented in numerous historical introductions, opera guides, leitmotivic threads and leitmotif lists included in libretto editions and piano scores. The study of the incidences of these particular leitmotif identifications consists of both the gathering of source material and its digitisation and cataloguing, and a musicological study of the potential relationships, influence and evolution between leitmotif interpretations. To enable the extension and repurposing of the identified leitmotif relationships they are structured using an ontology.</p><p>Notation examples in leitmotif guides are usually abstractions drawn from a piano score. When reporting findings from this research it is desirable to present and relate the scholarly arguments back to the musicological context within which they are made: from the score excerpts in the source material; and to MEI encodings that illustrate and encode both the examples from which they are drawn and to complete (piano) scores of the overall operas.</p><p>This enables matching and linking of the examples as they are described in the scholarly text, via semantic hyperlinks, to and from the score, including exact matches and variants, illustrating interpretations, and situating the examples back in context. Encoding interpretations in the form of notation examples as variant readings of a certain passage could thereby chart the 'understanding' of the work as a history of its variants.</p><p>(</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>For example comparing: Richard Wagner, Die Walküre, piano score by Felix Mottl, Leipzig, Peters, 1914, p.165; Hans von Wolzogen, Thematischer Leitfaden durch die Musik zu Richard Wagners Festspiel Der Ring des Nibelungen, 2 nd ed., Leipzig, Schloemp, 1876, p.58, 'Schicksalsmotiv'; Gustav Kobbé, Wagner's Music Dramas Analyzed With the Leading Motives, New York: Schirmer, 1923, p. 57, 'Motive of Fate'; George Dunning Gribble, The Master Works of Richard Wagner, London, Everett, 1913, p. 289, 'Fate Motif'.)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introducing MELD: Music Encoding and Linked Data</head><p>To realise the digital notation companion we have developed the MELD framework (Music Encoding and Linked Data). MELD enables the interactive presentation of multimedia contents of the Research Object, such as the images, text, audio, and MEI encoded music notation described in the previous section. These can be explored contextually alongside each other through the use of semantic links, encoded using RDF, which describe the musicological relationships between the resources (and elements within them). In contrast to earlier technologies which have typically aligned resources against a timeline (e.g. in milliseconds, or using MIDI), MELD expresses relationships anchored to musically meaningful items scoped using MEI. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure  1</ref> shows a screenshot of MELD displaying text and notation, highlighting leitmotifs as identified in different historical guides. To render our music notation (encoded using MEI) we use Verovio ( <ref type="bibr">Pugin et al. 2013</ref>), an open-source MEI renderer that produces beautiful SVG renditions of the score. In addition, Verovio provides an architecture in which identifiers (in other words, anchors for our relational Linked Data expressions in the MEI XML) are persisted through to the rendering (in SVG) which can be connected to identifiers in our contextual information (in RDF). When rendered (and re-rendered) for the user in our web based application interface, the browser uses these identifiers to generate interface elements and undertake actions that combine information from the MEI and the Linked Data. Within the Research Object, we treat the XML IDs of elements within the MEI resource as fragment identifiers, so URIs can be straightforwardly generated for each notation element of interest. We employ the Web Annotation Data Model ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Sanderson et al. 2017</ref>), using these URIs as targets of annotations representing each musicological marking. Corresponding annotation bodies are associated with semantic tags defined to encode the different musicological interpretations, which are in turn the annotation bodies of a top-level annotation targeting the URI of the files currently being viewed, including the music encoding (MEI) and scholarly interpretation (HTML). A simplified example of such relationships is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>. The MELD client then uses HTML/CSS and JavaScript, served by a simple web service implemented with Python Flask, and illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>. The procedure driving the rendering and user interaction is illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. The client processes a framed (see the explanation of framing) JSON-LD representation of the RDF graph instantiating the data model. It then performs an HTTP GET call to acquire the MEI resource targeted by the top-level annotation, and renders the corresponding musical score to SVG using Verovio. User interactions are captured using HTML divs drawn as bounding boxes over portions of the SVG corresponding to MEI elements of interest; this is simplified by Verovio's retention of MEI identifiers in the produced SVG output.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. MELD displaying contextualised text and music notation.</figDesc><graphic url="image-1.png" coords="2,316.86,72.30,241.44,139.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Musicological relationships, encoded using Open Annotations, within the Research Object (simplified).</figDesc><graphic url="image-2.png" coords="2,317.68,410.94,238.62,136.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. The MELD framework (shading corresponds to that in Figure 2).</figDesc><graphic url="image-3.png" coords="3,54.30,127.50,241.44,93.36" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>This work has been supported by the UK Arts and Humanities Research Council grant AH/L006820/1 'Transforming Musicology', and EPSRC grant EP/L019981/1 'Fusing Audio and Semantic Technologies for Intelligent Music Production and Consumption'. We thank all our colleagues on these projects who have supported and encouraged this work, particularly Carolin Rindfleisch for her complementary work on musicological ontologies, and Laurence Dreyfus for wider inspiration and motivation in developing these technologies.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Why linked data is not enough for scientists</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bechhofer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Buchan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>De Roure</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Missier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ainsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bhagat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Couch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cruickshank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Delderfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Dunlop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gamble</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Future Generation Computer Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="599" to="611" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Review: Music Encoding Initiative</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Crawford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Musicological Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="285" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plans and Performances: Parallels in the Production of Science and Music. Proceedings of the</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>De Roure</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Klyne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Page</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pybus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weigl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wilcoxson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Willcox</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="192" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using Digital Libraries in the Research of the Reception and Interpretation of Richard Wagner&apos;s Leitmotifs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dreyfus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rindfleisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1st International Workshop on Digital Libraries for Musicology</title>
		<meeting>the 1st International Workshop on Digital Libraries for Musicology</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="3" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digital Annotation Tooling for Opera Performance Studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Page</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nurmikko-Fuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rindfleisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Weigl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Digital Humanities 2016: Conference Abstracts</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Kraków</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="306" to="309" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Jagiellonian University &amp; Pedagogical University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Verovio: A Library for Engraving MEI Music Notation into SVG. Proceedings of the 15th International Society for Music Information Retrieval Conference</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pugin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zitellini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Roland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="112" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Web Annotation Data Model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sanderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ciccarese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>W3C recommendation</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
