<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Locative Media for Queer Histories: Scaling up "Go Queer"</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Engel</surname>
                        <forename>Maureen</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>mengel@ualberta.ca</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014-12-19T13:50:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Name, Institution</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Street</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>City</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Country</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Name</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Paper (was submitted as Long Paper)</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>queer studies</term>
                    <term>locative media</term>
                    <term>mobile media</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>gender studies</term>
                    <term>geohumanities; spatial &amp; spatio-temporal analysis</term>
                    <term>modeling</term>
                    <term>visualization</term>
                    <term>technologies</term>
                    <term>cultural studies</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                    <term>feminist studies</term>
                    <term>public humanities and community engaged scholarship</term>
                    <term>queer studies</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>This paper reports on the completion and launch of the locative media app “Go Queer.” Taking the theorization, iteration, and development of “Go Queer” as a model and case study, the paper argues that locative media is uniquely suited to re/mediating queerness. It then proposes that these findings can be used as a framework and set of best practices for developing a variety of queer history applications.</p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Go Queer </hi>is a ludic, locative media experience that occurs on location, in the city, on the playful border between game and story, the present and the past, the queer and the straight, the normative and the 
                <hi rend="italic">slant</hi>. The app takes the city of Edmonton’s queer history as its text, and produces a locative, spatialized narrative of that history by displaying text, images, video and audio in place at the actual locations where they occurred, thus creating what Richardson and Hjorth (2014, 256) call “the hybrid experience of place and presence.” The app invites its users to drift queerly through the city, discovering the hidden histories that always surround us, yet somehow remain just beyond our apprehension. It compiles these traces into a media layer that augments quotidian city space, juxtaposing the past onto the present, creating a deep, queer narrative of place. By bringing together the physical navigation of the contemporary city with the imaginative navigation of its queer past, the app enacts a praxis that I characterize as a 
                <hi rend="italic">queer ludic traversal</hi>, one that renders the navigation itself as queer as the content that it presents. In so doing, the app produces the experience of 
                <hi rend="italic">place</hi>, in Lucy Lippard’s (1997) formulation that
            </p>
            <p>Place is latitudinal and longitudinal within the map of a person’s life. It is temporal and spatial, personal and political. A layered location replete with human histories and memories, place has width as well as depth. It is about connections, what surrounds it, what formed it, what happened there, what will happen there. (7)</p>
            <p>The app proposes that a productive and underrepresented setting for queer play is the space of the city itself, and that the hybrid reality of locative media provides specific affordances to enable particularly queer navigations, occupations, and constructions of urban space. </p>
            <p>The app arises from, and takes shape in relation to, a range of theoretical inspirations. First are the contributions queer theories of space, the urban, and community, such as David Bell’s (2001) observation of “the special relationship between the city and the deviant” (84) and Theories recognizing the very public-ness of the formation, circulation, and inhabiting of queer identities (D’Emilio, 1983; Berlant and Warner, 1998); central here is Sara Ahmed’s theorization of “orientation” and her contention that “orientations are about the directions we take that put some things and not others in our reach” (552). New theorizations of space and place that have come to be called 
                <hi rend="italic">the spatial turn</hi> have similarly mobilized our thinking, challenging us to imagine space as a complex social production (Lefebvre, 1992) and asking us to think through how we move in space as either 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">tactical </hi>or 
                <hi rend="italic">strategic</hi> (deCerteau, 2011). Praxis-based interactivity, which I draw principally from the field of Game Studies, has introduced concepts like the fidelity context (Galloway 2004) and ambient experience (Flanagan 2009). Deep mapping offers new possibilities for modeling space, particularly historical space, by bringing together the explanatory and critical capacities of both narrative and mapmaking (Bodenhamer 2007). These theoretical methods intersect in locative media itself, the vehicle for “Go Queer” and a platform, I argue, that holds significant promise for queer scholarship and expression.
            </p>
            <p>By exploring how each of these theoretical arenas is literalized in the app itself, this paper aims to provide a framework and method for other practitioners interested in deploying locative media technologies to engage queer subjects, histories, and cultural productions.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>Anthropy, Anna. Rise of the Videogame Zinesters: How Freaks, Normals, Amateurs, Artists, Dreamers, Drop-Outs, Queers, Housewives, and People Like You Are Taking Back an Art Form. New York: Seven Stories Press, 2012. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Bell, David, and Jon Binnie. “Authenticating Queer Space: Citizenship, Urbanism and Governance.” Urban Studies 41.9 (2004): 1807–1820. usj.sagepub.com. Web. 12 Feb. 2015.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bell, David, and Gill Valentine. Mapping Desire: Geographies of Sexualities. 1 edition. London ; New York: Routledge, 1995. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Berlant, Lauren, and Michael Warner. “Sex in Public.” Critical Inquiry 24.2 (1998): 547–566. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Binnie, Jon et al. Pleasure Zones: Bodies, Cities, Spaces. Syracuse: Syracuse Univ Pr, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Bodenhamer, David J. “Creating a Landscape of Memory: The Potential of Humanities GIS.” Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts Computing: A Journal of Digital Humanities 1.2 (2007): 97–110. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Cabiria, Jonathan. “Virtual World and Real World Permeability: Transference of Positive Benefits for Marginalized Gay and Lesbian Populations.” Journal of Virtual Worlds Research 1.1 (2008): n. pag. Web.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Certeau, Michel de. The Practice of Everyday Life. Trans. Steven F. Rendall. 3rd Revised edition edition. University of California Press, 2011. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Chisholm, Dianne. Queer Constellations: Subcultural Space In The Wake Of The City. 1 edition. Minneapolis: Univ Of Minnesota Press, 2004. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Chrisman, Nicholas R. “Design of Geographic Information Systems Based on Social and Cultural Goals.” Photogrammetric Engineering &amp; Remote Sensing 53.10 (1987): 1367. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Craig, William J., and Sarah A. Elwood. “How and Why, Community Groups Use Maps and Geographic Information.” Cartography &amp; Geographic Information Systems 25.2 (1998): 95. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Crampton, J.W. “Maps as Social Constructions: Power, Communication and Visualization.” Progress in Human Geography 25.2 (2001): 235–252. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Crang, Mike. “Public Space, Urban Space and Electronic Space: Would the Real City Please Stand Up?” Urban Studies (Routledge) 37.2 (2000): 301–317.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Danielson, Laura. “An Exploration of Deep Maps.” N.p., thepoliscenter.iupui.edu.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Désert, Jean-Ulrick. “Queer Space.” Queers in Space: Claiming the Urban Landscape. Ed. Gorden Brent Ingram, Gordon B. Ingram, and Yolanda Retter. Seattle, Wash: Bay Pr, 1997. 17–26. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Dodge, Martin, Rob Kitchin, and Chris Perkins, eds. The Map Reader: Theories of Mapping Practice and Cartographic Representation. Chichester, West Sussex, UK; Hoboken, NJ: Wiley, 2011. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Flanagan, Mary. Critical Play: Radical Game Design. The MIT Press, 2013. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Gieseking, Jen Jack et al., eds. The People, Place, and Space Reader. People, Place, and Space: A Reader: Routledge, 2014. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Goodchild, Michael F., and Donald G. Janelle. “Toward Critical Spatial Thinking in the Social Sciences and Humanities.” GeoJournal 2010: 3. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Gregory, Derek. Geographical Imaginations. Cambridge, MA : Blackwell, 1994. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Gregory, Ian, and Paul S. Ell. Historical GIS [electronic Resource] : Technologies, Methodologies and Scholarship / Ian N. Gregory, Paul S. Ell. Cambridge, UK ; New York : Cambridge University Press, 2007. Cambridge Studies in Historical Geography: 39.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Halberstam, Judith. “What’s That Smell? Queer Temporalities and Subcultural Lives.” International Journal of Cultural Studies 6.3 (2003): 313–333. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Hall, Stuart. “Encoding/Decoding.” Media and Cultural Studies: KeyWorks. Ed. Meenakshi Gigi Durham and Douglas M. Kellner. Revised Edition. Malden MA: Blackwell, 2006. 163–173. KeyWorks in Cultural Studies.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Harris, Trevor M., John Corrigan, and David J. Bodenhamer. The Spatial Humanities : GIS and the Future of Humanities Scholarship. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Harris, Trevor, and Daniel Weiner. “Empowerment, Marginalization, and ‘Community-Integrated’ GIS.” Cartography and Geographic Information Systems 25.2 (1998): 67–76. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Hjorth, Larissa, and Sun Sun Lim. “Mobile Intimacy in an Age of Affective Mobile Media.” Feminist Media Studies 12.4 (2012): 477–484. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Johnston, Lynda, and Robyn Longhurst. Space, Place, and Sex: Geographies of Sexualities. Lanham: Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers, 2009. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Juliano, Linzi. “Digital: A Love Story; Bully; Grand Theft Auto IV; Portal; Dys4ia (review).” Theatre Journal 64.4 (2012): 595–598. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Kirkpatrick, Graeme. Computer Games and the Social Imaginary. Polity, 2013. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Knowles, Anne Kelly. Past Time, Past Place : GIS for History / Edited by Anne Kelly Knowles. Redlands, Calif. : ESRI Press, 2002. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lefebvre, Henri. The Production of Space. 1 edition. Wiley-Blackwell, 1992. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lippard, Lucy. Lure of the Local: Senses of Place in a Multicentered Society. 1 edition. New York: The New Press, 1998. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lynch, Kevin. The Image of the City. Cambridge, Mass.: The MIT Press, 1960. Mattern, Shannon. Deep Mapping the Media City. Univ Of Minnesota Press, 2015. </bibl>
                    <bibl>McLafferty, Sara. “Mapping Women’s Worlds: Knowledge, Power and the Bounds of GIS.” Gender, Place and Culture 9.3 (2002): 263–269. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Murphy, Kevin. “Walking the Queer City.” Radical History Review 62 (1995): 195–201. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Paglen, Trevor, and John Emerson. An Atlas of Radical Cartography. Ed. Lize Mogel and Alexis Bhagat. Slp edition. Los Angeles: Journal of Aesthetics and Protest Press, 2008. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Pavlovskaya, Marianna. “Theorizing with GIS: A Tool for Critical Geographies?” Environment and Planning A 38.11 (2006): 2003–2020. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Presner, Todd, David Shepard, and Yoh Kawano. HyperCities: Thick Mapping in the Digital Humanities. Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University Press, 2014. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Retter, Yolanda, Anne-Marie Bouthillette, and Gordon Brent Ingram, eds. Queers in Space: Communities, Public Places, Sites of Resistance. Seattle, Wash: Bay Press, 1997. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Ridge, Mia, Don Lafreniere, and Scott Nesbit. “Creating Deep Maps and Spatial Narratives through Design.” Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts Computing: A Journal of Digital Humanities 7.1/2 (2013): 176–189. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Rundstrom, Robert A. “GIS, Indigenous Peoples, and Epistemological Diversity.” Cartography and Geographic Information Systems 22.1 (1995): 45. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Shaw, Adrienne. “Putting the Gay in Games: Cultural Production and GLBT Content in Video Games.” Conference Papers -- International Communication Association (2008): 1–29. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Skeggs, Beverley et al. “Queer as Folk: Producing the Real of Urban Space.” Urban Studies 41.9 (2004): 1839–1856.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Soja, Edward W. Postmodern Geographies: The Reassertion of Space in Critical Social Theory. 2nd edition. London; New York: Verso, 2011. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Warf, Barney, and Santa Arias. The Spatial Turn : Interdisciplinary Perspectives / Edited by Barney Warf and Santa Arias. London : Routledge, 2009</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wood, Denis, John Fels, and John Krygier. Rethinking the Power of Maps. New York: The Guilford Press, 2010. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
