<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Remediating Machistán: Bridging Espacios Queer in Culturas Digitales, or Puentes over Troubled Waters</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Guzman</surname>
                        <forename>Carina Emilia</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Toronto, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>cartogeosapiens@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Cowan</surname>
                        <forename>T.L.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Toronto, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>tl.cowan@utoronto.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Rault</surname>
                        <forename>Jasmine</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Toronto, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>jas.rault@utoronto.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Gutierrez</surname>
                        <forename>Itzayana</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>McGill University, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>itzayana.gutierrez@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-05-02T17:45:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Name, Institution</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Street</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>City</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Country</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Name</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Panel / Multiple Paper Session</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>queer infrastructure</term>
                    <term>remediation</term>
                    <term>feminist epistemologies</term>
                    <term>decolonial epistemologies</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>gender studies</term>
                    <term>creative and performing arts</term>
                    <term>including writing</term>
                    <term>cultural studies</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                    <term>feminist studies</term>
                    <term>digital ecologies and critical infrastructure studies</term>
                    <term>queer studies</term>
                    <term>digital humanities history</term>
                    <term>theory</term>
                    <term>epistemology</term>
                    <term>criticism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Introduction</p>
            <p>This panel consists of two papers in Spanish and two in English. They span a varied collection of subjects which foreground the remediation that bridging entails; bridging spaces and architectures, bridging epistemologies and cultures, bridging the digital-analog divide, bridging into the imaginary and beyond. Remediation, these papers will address directly and indirectly, is a trouble: it implies the interpretation and translation of knowledge and creation. Who remediates and under what terms? How can we think of remediation as a bridge that invites us establish series of ethical considerations when approaching the sources and objects we will inevitably remediate? </p>
            <p>In the first Spanish-language paper, author Carina Guzmán gestures towards a framework capable of bridging methods for the GIS-based study of a map/codex purported to have been generated within the highest realms of Aztec imperial administration: the Aztec Tribute Scroll, and its interpretations in 20th century historiography, on the one hand, and on the other, auto-ethnographic research in queer world-making in the 21st century Mexico City nightscape. Some of the bridging concepts this paper discusses are derived from Cultural and Radical Geography, such as space as a cultural product and the (economic) politics of territorialisation. Further bridging concepts explored come from the realm of Information and Archival theory, these include questions how space and memory function as archives, and how/what digital tools can contribute to developing an epistemology for their study.</p>
            <p>In the second paper, in English, Jasmine Rault traces the conceptual and ideological bridge between twentieth century modern architectures and digital social design. It considers what queer architectures -- from Eileen Gray’s domestic designs to Mexico City’s 
                <hi rend="italic">vecindades</hi> -- can teach us about reimagining and redesigning the modern colonial logics of digital spaces, cultures and socialities. How might we remediate the decolonial, alter-modern potentialities of queer architecture for ethical digital social design? What futurities of decolonial digital cultures, ethics and spaces might be made possible by designing after these queer architectural histories?
            </p>
            <p>T.L. Cowan proposes, in third paper, also in English, that studying genealogies of discourses of hygiene (cleanliness, health, safety) offers us an important lesson when we find ourselves in the situation in which “hygiene” is remediated to the digital realm. Bridging long-standing critiques of “hygiene” with contemporary digital culture, this paper presents a queer, decolonial reading of hygiene and contamination, re-thinking the ways that we recycle/repurpose/remediate/resuscitate these discourse and values in our digitally-mediated lives and offering practices of shared risk and mutual care as alternatives to the hygenic model. </p>
            <p>The final paper, in Spanish, by Itzayana Gutiérrez, works with the remediation of a printed comic magazine into four online and for free download videogames. The comparison will be articulated considering the bridges between two media, the analog comic magazine and the videogame; and the bridges between two genres, the orientalist comic adventure and the war video game. It is important to mention that there are narrative as well as visual vocabulary continuities in this dual system, and both the comic and the videogame play with hyper-hygienic homoerotic scenarios to sanitize, purify and militarize interracial affects and national imaginaries.</p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold">El espacio y el archivo como puente: una propuesta epistemológica</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Carina Guzmán</p>
            <p>En esta ponencia abordaré de dos temas aparentemente dispares: un estudio sobre la Matrícula de tributos que realicé a través de un sistema de información geográfico (el software libre QGIS), y un proyecto de investigación basado en mi experiencia personal como organizadora de fiestas lésbicas en la Ciudad de México desde un espacio mágico: Machistán. Presento estos dos estudios académicos en planos paralelos y trazaré entre ellos un puente con dos bases. La primera conformada por en una serie de conceptos subyacentes compartidos: que el espacio es una creación cultural, que los lugares son producto de procesos políticos, y que –por ende- aquellos metros cuadrados de superficie terrestre que canónicamente solemos llamar “palimpsesto”, están sujetos a procesos políticos y económicos de territorialización con sus respectivas disputas e identificaciones. La segunda base consiste en establecer la necesidad metodológica de valorar y procurar una epistemología planteada por el objeto de estudio no tradicional en sí; para tratar estos casos me acercaré a la epistemología de la Información (misma que subyace al concepto de Humanidades digitales y compartida con las demás ponencias de este panel) que considera que algunos objetos, como lo podrían ser un códice mesoamericano o una fiesta lésbica, han sido infravalorados por el quehacer académico al no existir un esfuerzo por conceptualizarlos y por lo tanto de archivarlos e investigarlos en sus propios términos.</p>
            <p>La Matrícula de tributos es un texto de tradición mesoamericana que (se asume) reúne información sobre el tributo que se pagaba a la Triple Alianza al momento de la Conquista. Hacia 1949 Barlow localizó los poblados tributarios enlistados en el códice, realizando así la primera proyección cartográfica de lo que él llamó el imperio colhua-mexica. En 1996, Berdan et al. elaboraron una contrapropuesta cartográfica que pretendió dar cuenta de una diferenciación política entre territorios tributarios y estratégicos del imperio ahora llamado azteca. Aunque distintos, ambos mapas comparten la misma exigencia: ilustrar el aspecto de un imperio. En esta ponencia explico mis intentos por tender un puente hacia el conocimiento contenido en la Matrícula de tributos al elaborar un mapa (con la herramienta digital QGIS) cuya pretensión es el análisis de la información geográfica contenida en el códice sin que necesariamente rinda cuentas sobre una dinámica fiscal, ni que represente el aspecto cartográfico de un territorio imperial.</p>
            <p>En otro plano, Machistán es el universo imaginado de las “machas”: así nos llamábamos entre nosotras dentro de una pequeña colectiva de lesbianas y mujeres queer a la que pertenecí hacia el año 2005. Nuestro proyecto político era la organización de fiestas que fueran una alternativa a los bares y antros gays y su hostilidad hacia las mujeres: la misión era crear el deleite lúdico colectivo que sólo la noche ofrece 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">al margen de la vida nocturna comercial </hi>de la Ciudad de México. En esta ponencia explicaré que Machistán es una fuente en sí: un archivo o sistema de información. A través de este espacio mágico se puede entender la creación de conocimiento; la producción cultural; el trabajo (digital y análogo) y los afectos que se llevan a cabo sobre azoteas y bajo lonas para que decenas de queers se reúnan con el fin compartir un espacio/instante.
            </p>
            <p>Así pues, propondré comprender la dimensión epistemológica de la información de estos objetos de estudio, y así entenderlos como archivos; de diseñar una metodología y quizás un sistema de información capaz de manejar el conocimiento y la creación presentes en estas fuentes, y que permita entenderlos e investigarlos críticamente </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Decolonizing Architectures of Digital Modernity: Queer Futurity from Sapphic Modernist Design to Digital </hi>
                <hi rend="italic bold">Vecindades</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jasmine Rault</p>
            <p>What can early twentieth century modernist architecture and design teach us about contemporary decolonizing, feminist, queer and anti-racist practices and protocols for networked digital architecture? European modernist architecture was driven by ideals of internationally standardized open communication – the open floor plan, strip windows and glass walls, unimpeded visual access to interior and exterior space, eliminating walls and structural as well as decorative or symbolic obstructions to complete open access. There are some striking ideological continuities between these modernist architectural ideals (and aesthetics) and contemporary Euro-Atlantic values of unbridled digitization, designing global information networks for unobstructed open access – and these continuities need to be understood within a context of modern-colonial regimes of gender, sexuality and race. In my collaboration with T.L. Cowan to build the Cabaret Commons, have found ourselves taken, like so many researchers recently, by the fever to (digitally) archive precarious, precious, minoritized, invisibilized, intimate, forgotten trans- feminist and queer knowledges, scenes, resistance cultures and alternative futures. Bound by their beauty we are also, however, bound by the institutional and platform logics that we hope these archives can transform, and how we can be accountable to the “the people whose belongings have become [our] ‘collections’” (Nowviski 2016). Although generally well- intentioned, conventionalised Western epistemological research practices reflect longstanding and ongoing acquisitional, abductive, possessive, extractive practices that prioritize the needs and values of the research community over the needs and values of the 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">researched </hi>community.
            </p>
            <p>If, as I argue, contemporary digital spaces, cultures and research practices have been designed by modern colonial discourses, politics and aesthetics of early twentieth century European architecture we might find generative decolonizing digital models, ethics and aesthetics in the queer architectures that have been designed against, or sometimes simply askew to, the modern. My presentation will take up two main types of queer architecture: the early twentieth century Sapphic modernist designs of women working with and deliberately against European modernist architectural ideals (Rault 2011); and the Mexican architectural innovation of the 
                <hi rend="italic">vecindad</hi>. In Spanish, the word 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">vecindad </hi>can mean neighbourhood, but in Mexico City it typically describes a style of architecture: “The 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">vecindad </hi>is usually known as a row of one room dwellings surrounding an open space or patio” (Alejandro M. Rebolledo 1998, 1). 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Vecindades </hi>were the main form of working-class architecture in Mexico City from around the sixteenth century until the mid-twentieth century, incorporate pre-colonial and Spanish colonial design and were more often built 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">by </hi>than for their inhabitants. By the 1940s, they were cast as examples of unhygienic, degenerate, backward dwelling design that (largely European) modernist architecture should replace, and provide a compelling alternative to the gender, sexual, racial and class ideology of openness and transparency structuring architectural and digital modernity. What futurities of decolonial digital cultures, ethics and spaces might be made possible by designing after these queer architectural histories?
            </p>
            <p>Dirty Queers, a love letter: Vulnerability, Care, Contamination, Migration, and Discourses of Digital Hygiene</p>
            <p>T.L. Cowan</p>
            <p>In this paper I propose that our current moment of technocultural embodiment offers us the opportunity to observe the long history of a particular configuration of power: namely, discourses of digital hygiene that fail to account for queer, feminist, decolonial and anti- racist critiques of ‘hygiene’ as a mode of social control. I argue that “digital hygiene” is promoted as a monitoring practice that is at once meant to keep you 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">and </hi>your computer clean 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">and </hi>safe—self-protection against both malware viruses and human trolls. Importantly, digital hygiene is also framed as responsible digital practices that keep others safe from infection 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">by </hi>you; if you have a dirty digital existence, you put yourself 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">and others </hi>at risk. Rather than worrying about whether we are clean or dirty, I propose we worry about how our understandings of the conditions of cleanliness/purity and dirtiness/contamination have been shaped and how they continue to determine our digital existences.
            </p>
            <p>Here, I trace the ways that hygiene protocols have been enacted as oppressive regimes through colonial, racist, classist, misogynist and homophobic surveillance and regulation against immigrant populations; women and other feminized populations; and Indigenous and Black youth and other negatively racialized populations. In our social imaginaries informed by the logics of digital hygiene, if we fail to practice all of the enforced/‘recommended’ forms of self-protection/inoculation/prophylaxis and we get ‘infected’ by viruses or attacked/infiltrated by identity-thieving or rape-and-death- threatening trolls, we are held at least partially at fault, due to our risky behaviour. As an alternative to discourses of digital hygiene, I focus here on queer theories and practices of mutual care, shared risk and activist methods like those practices by the Center for Solutions to Online Violence (
                <ref target="http://femtechnet.org/csov/">
                    <hi rend="underline color(1155CC)">http://femtechnet.org/csov/</hi>
                </ref> ), which offers users ways to practice “safer” digital practices, while also--following Wendy Hui Kyong Chun and others-- taking an activist approach in which we “fight for a space in which one can be vulnerable and not attacked” (2016, 158). At once a history of hygiene, and a love letter to the “dirty” queer, migrant and other marginalized practices of shared risk and mutual care, this paper considers how a shift away from hygiene and towards other imaginaries may transform our digital lives.
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold">Kalimán: el puente del lenguaje gráfico entre los comics y los videojuegos</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Itzayana Gutiérrez</p>
            <p>Durante el último tercio de 2016, distintos medios noticiosos dieron cobertura al emocionante lanzamiento de una serie de 4 videojuego basado en el comic mexicano más exitoso de todos los tiempos: 
                <hi rend="italic">Kalimán el hombre increíble</hi>.
            </p>
            <p>Esta no es la primera vez que Kalimán cruza el puente entre un medio y otro. Sus aventuras comenzaron como radionovelas en la década de los 60 pero explotaron el mercado cultural como historias gráficas impresas en el mundo de las revistas de comic baratas. Su circulación impresa fue amplia y sostenida desde mediados de 1960 hasta principios de 1990 en México pero alcanzó importantes números de distribución en Sudamérica. Este éxito intentó ser recapitalizado en películas, novelas, readaptaciones gráficas digitales y ahora en esta serie de videojuegos.</p>
            <p>Mi presentación en este panel de humanidades digitales hará un seguimiento de las actualizaciones y agregados del lenguaje gráfico de Kalimán a través de su traducción y rediseño para videojuegos. Desde mi punto de vista, Kalimán es una aventura veladamente homoerótica, codificadamente racista y abiertamente orientalista. Y este tono establecido en el mundo gráfico sólo se intensifica con un giro más belicista aún.</p>
            <p>Kalimán eviste turbante blanco y mallas blancas que evocan modas del subcontinente Indio aunque sus frecuentes apariciones estelares con el torso desnudo hacen que su traje sea lo de menos (1). Su cuerpo musculoso y bello se completa con ojos azules y detalles faciales que acentúan ciertas convenciones de belleza masculina asociadas con conductas militares y de ocupación colonial.   Kalimán tiene además de estas características utilizadas ampliamente en la gramática de otros superhéroes, poderes mentales y espirituales incomparables que le otorgan autoridad moral para el ejercicio libre de su violencia. Como en los lenguajes gráficos de vanguardia utilizados ampliamente por los fascismos y la propaganda de guerra, su cuerpo se beneficia de una autoridad seductora y vibraciones homoeróticas.</p>
            <p>En este universo gráfico de convenciones raciales, orientalistas, estrategias misóginas y homoeróticas, mi presentación intentará aclarar las innovaciones y actualizaciones del lanzamiento de los videojuegos. Según el anuncio de su desarrollador Eduardo Guerrero, el producto tiene 4 ofertas.</p>
            <p>Las 3 primeras están desarrolladas para dispositivos móviles y en un esquema de descarga gratuita. La primera, según dice Guerrero “se dedica a trabajar toda la parte mental” y recuerda esquemas lógicos de Candy Crush y otros sistemas de acumulación de puntos a través de niveles progresivos de dificultad. El segundo se basa en las historietas de Kalimán, en lo que parece ser un esquema de 8 bits similar a Zelda. El tercero usa el legendario modelo de enfrentamientos de Street Fighter. El cuarto videojuego, más ambicioso y complejo, por el que hay que pagar, está desarrollado para consolas y modelos inversivos de navegación en donde se presenta a “Kalimán evolucionado”, quien se engancha en tareas de batalla en ambientes del Medio Este utilizando una variedad de tecnologías de observación, desplazamiento y ataque militares (“Kalimán ahora en videojuego” Entrevista con el realizador Eduardo Guerrero para NOTIMEX, 
                <ref target="https://youtu.be/ZaF31NUqmUg">https://youtu.be/ZaF31NUqmUg</ref>).
            </p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Banta, M.</hi> (2003). Barbaric Intercourse: Caricature and the Culture of Conduct 1841-1936. Chicago and London: University of Chicago Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Barlow, R.</hi> (1949). The Extent of the Empire of the Culhua-Mexica. Berkeley: University of California Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Bartra, A.</hi> Piel de papel. Los pepines en la educación sentimental del mexicano. En Revista Latinoamericana de Estudios sobre la Historieta, vol. 1.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Berdan, F.</hi> et al (1996). Aztec Imperial Strategies. Washington DC: Dumbarton Oaks Publishing Service.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Herner, I.</hi> (1979). Mitos y monitos, historietas y fotonovelas en México. México: Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México / Nueva Imagen. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Chun, W. H. K.</hi> (2016.) Updating to Remain the Same: Habitual New Media. Cambridge: The MIT Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Groensteen, T.</hi> (2009). The System of Comics. Translated by Bart Beaty and Nick Nguyen. Jackson: University Press of Mississippi.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold">Leslie, E.</hi> (2004). Hollywood flatlands. Animation, critical theory and the avant-garde. London / New York: Verso.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
