<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Cretan Institutional Inscriptions: A New EpiDoc Database</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Irene</forename>
                  <surname>Vagionakis</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Irene Vagionakis is currently a <roleName>research fellow</roleName> in
                  digital humanities at the Department of History and Cultures of the <orgName>Alma
                     Mater Studiorum University of Bologna</orgName>.</affiliation>
               <email>irene.vagionakis2@unibo.it</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date/>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue">Rolling Issue</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for
               journals in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking
               to publish full-text articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <!--          Crete, EFES, EpiDoc, digital epigraphy, Greek history, Kiln, institutions-->
               <term>Crete</term>
               <term>EFES</term>
               <term>EpiDoc</term>
               <term>digital epigraphy</term>
               <term>Greek History</term>
               <term>Kiln</term>
               <term>institutions</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p>The paper presents the database Cretan Institutional Inscriptions, which was created
               as part of a PhD research project carried out at the University of Venice Ca’
               Foscari. The database, built using the EpiDoc Front-End Services (<ptr
                  type="software" xml:id="R1" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R1"
                  >EFES</rs>) platform, collects the EpiDoc editions of six hundred inscriptions
               that shed light on the institutions of the political entities of Crete from the
               seventh to the first century BCE. The aim of the paper is to outline the main issues
               addressed during the creation of the database and the encoding of the inscriptions
               and to illustrate the core features of the database, with an emphasis on the
               advantages deriving from the combined use of the TEI-EpiDoc standard and of the <ptr
                  type="software" xml:id="R2" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R2"
                  >EFES</rs> platform.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="acknowledgements" xml:id="ak">
            <p>I would like to express my gratitude to my PhD supervisors, Claudia Antonetti and
               Gabriel Bodard, and to all those who have enriched me with their invaluable advice
               and support, especially Alice Bencivenni, Lucia Criscuolo, Giovanni Geraci, Francesco
               Guizzi, Pietro Maria Liuzzo, Federicomaria Muccioli, Jamie Norrish, Simona Stoyanova,
               Polina Yordanova, and the two anonymous reviewers of the paper. My research would not
               have been possible without the support of the University of Venice Ca’ Foscari and
               the Italian School of Archaeology at Athens. I am also very grateful to the Venice
               Centre for Digital and Public Humanities (VeDPH), the Institute for Computational
               Linguistics A. Zampolli of the National Research Council of Italy (ILC-CNR) and the
               Italian node of Common Language Resources and Technology Infrastructure (CLARIN-IT)
               for publishing the database.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="introduction">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>The database <title level="m">Cretan Institutional Inscriptions</title>, which is
               available under an Open Access license at <ptr
                  target="http://cretaninscriptions.vedph.it"/>,<note><ref type="bibl"
                     target="#vagionakis2021">Vagionakis 2021</ref>. The related dataset is
                  accessible at <ptr target="http://hdl.handle.net/20.500.11752/OPEN-548"/>,
                  accessed July 21, 2021. All the contents are distributed under a Creative Commons
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</note> was created
               in the context of my PhD research project at the University of Venice Ca’ Foscari
                  <title level="u"><foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">Kretikai Politeiai</foreign>: Cretan
                  Institutions from VII to I Century BC</title>, under the supervision of Claudia
               Antonetti and Gabriel Bodard.</p>
            <p>The aim of the project, which started in September 2016 and ended in February 2020,
               was to examine the records pertaining to Cretan institutions, in particular the
               epigraphic records, in order to propose an up-to-date reconstruction of the
               institutional framework of the island’s political entities from the rise of the
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">poleis</foreign> and the appearance of the first
               inscriptions in Greek alphabet(s) to the Roman conquest of Crete (seventh to first
               century BCE).</p>
            <p>The epigraphic records I examined consisted of six hundred Greek inscriptions, for
               each of which I have provided a digital XML edition compliant with the TEI-EpiDoc
               standard, including a commentary focused on the institutional data offered by the
               document. The editions of these inscriptions, along with a collection of the most
               relevant literary sources, have been collected in the database Cretan Institutional
               Inscriptions, which I created using the EpiDoc Front-End Services (<ptr
                  type="software" xml:id="R3" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R3"
                  >EFES</rs>) platform. To facilitate consulting the epigraphic records, the
               database also includes, in addition to the ancient sources, two catalogs providing
               information about the Cretan political entities and the institutional elements
               considered.</p>
            <p>The aim of this paper is to illustrate the main issues tackled during the creation of
               the database and to examine the choices made, focusing on the advantages offered by
               the use of EpiDoc and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R4" target="#EFES"/><rs
                  type="soft.name" ref="#R4">EFES</rs>.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="Cretan_epigraphy">
            <head>Cretan Epigraphy and Cretan Institutions</head>
            <p>I decided to investigate the Cretan institutions because of the widespread
               tendency—resulting from the postulation of the existence of <emph>one</emph> cohesive
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">Kretike politeia</foreign> (on which see Arist.
                  <title level="m">Pol.</title> II 1263b-1273b, Ephor. <title level="m"
                  >FGrHist</title> 70 F 149)—to extend <foreign>a priori</foreign> to the rest of
               the island what was known only for few delimited better explored areas, especially
               Gortyn, in the attempt to trace back to a single model the rich variety of <quote
                  source="#HomIl">one hundred-citied Crete</quote> (<bibl xml:id="HomIl">Hom. <title
                     level="m">Il.</title> 2.649</bibl>). I considered it essential, instead, to
               take a geographical approach in order to examine the specificity of each political
               entity of Crete (<foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">poleis</foreign>, <foreign
                  xml:lang="grc-Latn">koina</foreign>, dependent communities, extra-urban
               sanctuaries and hegemonic alliances).</p>
            <p>A very successful study of Cretan inscriptions and institutions that took account of
               the local peculiarities had already been made by Federico Halbherr and Margherita
               Guarducci, culminating in the publication by the latter of the four volumes of the
               corpus of the <title level="m">Inscriptiones Creticae</title> (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#icret">Guarducci 1935–50</ref>). The epigraphic findings of the last
               seventy years, however, have nearly doubled the number of available inscriptions,
               from about 2,000 to about 3,900,<note><p>This estimate is based on a cross-check of
                     the <title level="j">Supplementum Epigraphicum Graecum</title>, of the <title
                        level="a">Bulletin Épigraphique</title> included in the <title level="j"
                        >Revue des Études Grecques</title> and of the database <title level="m"
                        >Searchable Greek Inscriptions</title> of the Packard Humanities Institute
                     (last updated July 13, 2020, <ptr target="https://inscriptions.packhum.org/"
                     />).</p></note> making it necessary to review the material in light of the
               discoveries made after the publication of the <ref type="bibl" target="#icret"><title
                     level="m">Inscriptiones Creticae</title></ref>.<note><p>A similar review was
                     accomplished, from a linguistic perspective, by Genevrois (<ref type="bibl"
                        target="#genevrois2017">2017</ref>).</p></note></p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="institutional_inscriptions">
            <head><soCalled>Institutional</soCalled> Inscriptions</head>
            <p>The preparation of an epigraphic collection of Cretan
                  <soCalled>institutional</soCalled> inscriptions posed many problems, starting from
               the selection of the material: What epigraphic documents could be properly considered
               as <soCalled>institutional</soCalled>? How could the study of a discouragingly
               fragmentary documentation be approached? In what way could a collection of such texts
               prove to be useful?</p>
            <p>The very first issue to tackle at the beginning of my research was, naturally, what
               should be considered an <soCalled>institution</soCalled>. The institutional elements
               that I have included in my analysis are the outcome of an arduous selection intended
               to come as close as possible to the ancient concept of
                  <soCalled>institution</soCalled>. This term tends to cover almost everything
               pertaining to the public life of the communities being considered, ending up
               coinciding with what in the Cretan inscriptions is summarized in the formulaic
               expression <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">ta thina kai ta anthropina panta</foreign>
                  (<q>all the divine and the human things</q>). The breadth of the ancient concept,
               therefore, has been an incentive to make as inclusive as possible a selection of
               aspects pertaining to the public sphere, excluding the cults: assemblies, officials,
               boards, associations, civic subdivisions (including tribes, social statuses, and age
               classes), months, celebrations (including festivities, sacrifices and religious
               rites, competitions, performances, and practices linked with commensality),
               institutional practices and instruments (such as polls or public seals), public
               spaces (such as courthouses or archives), and institutional frameworks in the broad
               sense.</p>
            <p>Given the nature of the records, eminently epigraphic and only to a small extent of
               literary, numismatic, or archaeological origin, another central issue that I had to
               address during the initial phases of my research was to reflect on which inscriptions
               could be properly considered <soCalled>institutional</soCalled>, or more precisely,
                  <soCalled>institutionally relevant</soCalled>.</p>
            <p>There are, in fact, some obvious cases like the majority of the well-preserved public
               documents, such as the decree from Knossos <ref type="bibl" target="#icret"><title
                     level="m">I.Cret.</title></ref> I 8 12 of the late second century BCE, where an
               undamaged enactment formula mentions the board of the officials called <foreign
                  xml:lang="grc-Latn">kosmoi</foreign> and the <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn"
                  >polis</foreign> as those responsible for the decreeing (l. 1, ἔδοξεν Κνωσίων τοῖς
               κόσμοις καὶ τᾶι πόλι).</p>
            <p>Institutionally relevant information, however, can also be provided by nonofficial
               inscriptions, such as the private epitaph for Adrastos, who died prematurely, from
               Polyrrhenia <ref type="bibl" target="#icret"><title level="m">I.Cret.</title></ref>
               II 23 20 of the second century BCE, mentioning the <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn"
                  >agela</foreign>, the group of young men—somewhat similar to the Athenian <foreign
                  xml:lang="grc-Latn">ephebia</foreign>—to which he belonged (l. 1, ἐξ̣
               ἀγέλας̣).</p>
            <p>In many other documents, again, the meaningful terms are well preserved, but their
               context is irreparably lost, as in the case of the inscription from Milatos <ref
                  type="bibl" target="#icret"><title level="m">I.Cret.</title></ref> I 21 2 of the
               third or second century BCE, where the term <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn"
                  >kosmos</foreign>, perfectly legible, is completely surrounded by lacunae (l. 2,
               [- - -] κόσμον [- - -]).</p>
            <p>More challenging are the cases where the meaningful terms themselves are lost. For
               example, in the building inscription from Gortyn <ref type="bibl" target="#icret"
                     ><title level="m">I.Cret.</title></ref> IV 258 of the second century BCE the
               verb <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">epimeleomai</foreign> (<mentioned>to take care
                  of</mentioned>) clearly indicates that the name of the promoter of the initiative
               was originally written on the stone (l. 2, [- - - ἐπε]μ̣ελῆθε̣[ν - - -]).
               Analogously, in the treaty between Hierapytna and another city whose name is lost
                  <ref type="bibl" target="#icret"><title level="m">I.Cret.</title></ref> III 3 6,
               of the late third or early second century BCE, the terms <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn"
                  >menos</foreign> (<mentioned>month</mentioned>) and <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn"
                  >edoxen</foreign> (<mentioned>it was decreed</mentioned>) are preserved, but the
               names both of the month and of the promoter of the decreeing are lost (ll. 1–2, μηνὸς
               [- - -] τάδε ἔδ̣[οξ]εν̣ τ[- - -]). In these cases, therefore, I have deemed it
               appropriate to consider these absences too, taking account also of the additional
               terminology connected to <soCalled>institutional</soCalled> actions, such as nouns
               like <mentioned>month</mentioned>, or verbs like <mentioned>to take care
                  of</mentioned>, <mentioned>to decree</mentioned> or <mentioned>to vote</mentioned>
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">psephizo</foreign>), or even prepositions and
               articles like <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">epi ton</foreign>, which in dating
               formulas reveal, for example, the originary mention of the tribe in office. Dealing
               with extremely fragmentary records, therefore, I took the approach of paying due
               attention to the excerpts from the originary contexts and to the voids, which could
               lead to a better understanding of formulaic expressions and of their variations.</p>
            <p>Following these criteria, I selected a collection of six hundred
                  <soCalled>institutional</soCalled> inscriptions, comprising texts coming from
               Crete or concerning Crete, as the documentary base of my study.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="digital_epigraphic_collection">
            <head>Towards the Creation of a Born-Digital Epigraphic Collection with <ptr
               type="software" xml:id="R5" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R5"
                  >EFES</rs></head>
            <p>Once the relevant material had been defined, another major issue that I had to face
               was to decide how to deal efficiently with it. While I was in the process of starting
               a more traditional and <soCalled>monographic</soCalled> study of Cretan institutions,
               a fortuitous coincidence of circumstances led me toward a more stimulating approach:
               the preparation of an annotated born-digital collection of the inscriptions I had
               previously selected.</p>
            <p>In the first place, my shift toward an eminently epigraphic approach derived from the
               difficulty of dealing with the epigraphic attestations of the institutions in any
               other way. These attestations, in fact, were so strictly interconnected with their
               context as to be hardly extractable from the inscriptions where they occurred; to
               analyze them required having the complete texts of those inscriptions constantly at
               hand. This practical need then led to my decision to prepare new editions of the
               inscriptions, mainly because many of them were outdated, and also because of the
               discovery of Gérard Genevrois’s admirable monograph on Cretan institutional
               terminology (<ref type="bibl" target="#genevrois2017">Genevrois 2017</ref>), which
               definitively dissuaded me from configuring my study in a way that could have ended up
               overlapping too much with his work.</p>
            <p>Immediately after this discovery I was able to shift from creating a traditional
               collection of editions of the previously selected six hundred inscriptions to
               creating it as a born-digital epigraphic collection because of another event that
               also happened in 2017: the appearance of a powerful new tool for digital epigraphy,
               EpiDoc Front-End Services (<ptr type="software" xml:id="R6" target="#EFES"/><rs
                  type="soft.name" ref="#R6">EFES</rs>).<note><p>GitHub repository, accessed July
                     21, 2021, <rs
                        type="url" ref="#R6"><ptr target="https://github.com/EpiDoc/EFES"/></rs>.</p></note> Although I
               was already aware of the many benefits deriving from a semantic markup of the
                     inscriptions,<note><p>On which see <ptr type="crossref" target="#EpiDoc_EFES"/>
                     and <ptr type="crossref" target="#encodingInstitutions"/>.</p></note> what
               really persuaded me to adopt a TEI-based approach for the creation of my epigraphic
               editions was actually the great facilitation that <ptr type="software" xml:id="R7"
                  target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R7">EFES</rs> offered in using
               TEI-EpiDoc, which I will discuss in the following section.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="EpiDoc_EFES">
            <head>The Benefits of Using EpiDoc and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R8" target="#EFES"
            /><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R8">EFES</rs></head>
            <p>I was already familiar with the epigraphic subset of the TEI standard,
                        EpiDoc,<note><p><title level="u">EpiDoc: Epigraphic Documents in TEI
                        XML</title>, accessed July 21, 2021, <ptr target="http://epidoc.stoa.org/"
                     />, <ref type="bibl" target="#epidoc">Elliott et al. 2020</ref>.</p></note>
               which I had been using since 2014 on other projects, the <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#igcyr"><title level="m">Inscriptions of Greek
                     Cyrenaica</title></ref><note><p>In the HELLAS Unibo Laboratory Department of
                     History and Cultures (DiSCi), Alma Mater Studiorum University of Bologna,
                     accessed July 21, 2021, <ptr
                        target="https://disci.unibo.it/it/ricerca/laboratori-di-ricerca/hellas-unibo"
                     />.</p></note> and <ref type="bibl" target="#aio"><title level="m">Attic
                     Inscriptions Online</title></ref>. This previous experience with EpiDoc
               encoding made me extremely aware both of its advantages and of its limits.</p>
            <p>Starting with the advantages, EpiDoc’s semantic nature allows users to mark up
               efficiently not only the traditional components of a critical edition of an
               inscription (such as its metadata, text, apparatus, translation, commentary, and
               bibliography), but also specific interpretive features occurring in the epigraphic
               texts themselves, which could be linguistic, historical, topographic,
               prosopographical, and so on.<note><p>See <ref type="bibl" target="#epidoc">Elliott et
                        al. 2020</ref>.</p></note> The flexibility of the EpiDoc encoding, moreover,
               allows the digital epigraphists to choose what features to mark up, according to
               their particular research topics.</p>
            <p>The possibility of semantically encoding internal features of the texts definitely
               opens wide the doors to enriched ways of interacting with epigraphic
                     editions.<note><p>On the usefulness of adopting EpiDoc in the epigraphic field
                     see Babeu (<ref type="bibl" target="#babeu2011">2011</ref>) and Bodard and
                     Stoyanova (<ref type="bibl" target="#bodard_stoyanova2016"
                  >2016</ref>).</p></note> A collection of semantically encoded inscriptions, in
               fact, could be queried in a very accurate way, allowing digital epigraphists to
               identify recurring patterns and features more easily. Furthermore, EpiDoc markup
               could lead to faster indexing of specific elements, such as places or personal names,
               that are mentioned in the texts.</p>
            <p>My previous experience, however, also showed me that it is not always possible to
               transform these potentialities into reality quickly, especially in the context of
               small projects lacking the support of IT experts. And wider epigraphic projects often
               benefit from IT support only in the initial and final phases of the work. In some
               cases, the epigraphists are able to see the fruits of their intense and years-long
               encoding effort only at the publication stage, at the end of their work, which may be
               quite discouraging!</p>
            <p>This is particularly true for the creation of publishable output of the encoded
               inscriptions. The <ptr type="software" xml:id="R9" target="#epidocxslt"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R9">EpiDoc Reference
               XSLT Stylesheets</rs>, created <q>for transformation of
                  EpiDoc XML files into HTML</q>,<note><p>Accessed July 21, 2021, <rs type="url" ref="#R9"><ptr
                        target="https://github.com/EpiDoc/Stylesheets"/></rs>.</p></note> require
               relatively advanced knowledge of XSLT to use them to produce a satisfying HTML
               edition for online publication or to generate a printable PDF. Not to mention the
               creation of a complete searchable database to be published online, equipped with
               indexes and appropriate search filters: this is far beyond the IT skills of the
               average epigraphist.</p>
            <p>The situation is a little better for those who use EpiDoc as a tool for simplifying
               their research work on a collection of ancient documents, without aiming at the
               publication of the encoded inscriptions. The querying of a set of EpiDoc inscriptions
               is possible to some extent even without technical support: in some advanced XML
               editors, particularly <ptr type="software" xml:id="R10" target="#oxygen"/>
               <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R10">Oxygen</rs>, it is possible to perform XPath queries that allow the
               identification of all the occurrences of specific features in the epigraphic
               collection according to their markup. The XPath queries in an advanced XML editor
               also allow the creation of lists of specific elements mentioned in the inscriptions,
               but to my knowledge the creation of proper indexes—before <ptr type="software"
                  xml:id="R11" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R11">EFES</rs>—was
               almost impossible to achieve without the help of an IT expert.</p>
            <p>Thus, despite the many benefits that EpiDoc encoding <emph>potentially</emph> offers,
               epigraphists might often be discouraged from adopting it by the amount of time that
               such an approach requires, combined with the fact that in many cases these benefits
               become tangible only at the end of the work, and only if one has IT support.</p>
            <p>In light of these limitations, it is easy to understand how deeply the release of
               <ptr type="software" xml:id="R12" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name"
                  ref="#R11">EFES</rs> has transformed the field of digital epigraphy. <ptr
                     type="software" xml:id="R13" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R13">
                        EFES</rs>, developed at the Institute of Classical Studies of the School of
               Advanced Study of the University of London as the epigraphic specialization of the
               <ptr type="software" xml:id="R14" target="#kiln"/>
               <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R14">Kiln platform</rs>
               ,<note><p><title level="a">New Digital Publishing Tool: EpiDoc Front-End
                        Services</title>, September 1, 2017, <ptr
                        target="https://ics.sas.ac.uk/about-us/news/new-digital-publishing-tool-epidoc-front-end-services"/>;
                  see also the Kiln GitHub repository, accessed July 21, 2021,<rs type="url" ref="#R14">
                     <ptr target="https://kcl-ddh.github.io/kiln/"/></rs>.</p></note> is a platform that
               simplifies the creation and management of databases of inscriptions encoded following
               the EpiDoc Guidelines. More specifically, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R15" target="#EFES"/>
               <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R15">EFES</rs> was developed to make
               it easy for EpiDoc users to view a publishable form of their inscriptions, and to
               publish them online in a full-featured searchable database, by easily ingesting
               EpiDoc texts and providing formatting for their display and indexing through the
               <ptr type="software" xml:id="R9" target="#epidocxslt"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R16">
                  EpiDoc reference XSLT stylesheets</rs>. The ease of configuration of the XSLT
               transformations, and the possibility of already having, during construction, an
               immediate front-end visualization of the desired final outcome of the TEI-EpiDoc
               marked-up documents, allow smooth creation of an epigraphic database even without a
               large team or in-depth IT skills. Beyond this, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R17"
                  target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R17">EFES</rs> is also remarkable for
               the ease of creation and display of the indexes of the various categories of
               marked-up terms, which significantly simplifies comparative analysis of the data
               under consideration. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R18" target="#EFES"/><rs
                  type="soft.name" ref="#R18">EFES</rs> is thus proving to be an extremely useful
               tool not only for publishing inscriptions online, but also for studying them before
               their publication or even without the intention of publishing them, especially when
               dealing with large collections of documents and data sets.<note><p>See Bodard and
                     Yordanova (<ref type="bibl" target="#bodard_yordanova_2020"
                  >2020</ref>).</p></note></ptr>
               <p>Some of these useful features of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R19" target="#EFES"
               /><rs type="soft.name" ref="R19">EFES</rs> are common to other existing tools,
                  such as <ptr type="software" xml:id="R20" target="#teipublisher"/><rs type="soft.name"
                     ref="#R20">TEI Publisher</rs>,<note><p>Accessed July 21, 2021, <ptr
                        target="https://teipublisher.com/index.html"/>.</p></note>
                  <ptr type="software" xml:id="R21" target="#tapas"/><rs type="soft.name"
                     ref="#R21">TAPAS</rs>,<note><p>Accessed July 21, 2021, <ptr
                        target="http://www.tapasproject.org/"/>.</p></note> or Kiln itself, which is
                  <ptr type="software" xml:id="R22" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name"
                     ref="#R22">EFES</rs>’s direct ancestor. What makes <ptr type="software"
                        xml:id="R23" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R23">EFES</rs> unique,
               however, is the fact that it is the only one of those tools to have be designed
               specifically for epigraphic purposes and to be deeply integrated with the EpiDoc
               Schema/Guidelines and with its reference stylesheets. Not only does it use, by
               default, the EpiDoc reference stylesheets for transforming the inscriptions and for
               indexing, it also comes with a set of default search facets and indexes that are
               specifically meant for epigraphic documents. The default facets include the findspot
               of the inscription, its place of origin, its current location, its support material,
               its object type, its document type, and the type of evidence of its date. The
               search/browse page, moreover, also includes a slider for filtering the inscriptions
               by date and a box for textual searches, which can be limited to the indexed forms of
               the terms. The default indexes include places, personal names (onomastics),
               identifiable persons (prosopography), divinities, institutions, words, lemmata,
               symbols, numerals, abbreviations, and uninterpreted text fragments. New facets and
               indexes can easily be added even without mastering XSLT, along the lines of the
               existing ones and by following the detailed instructions provided in the <ptr
                  type="software" xml:id="R24" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R24"
                  >EFES</rs> Wiki documentation.<note><p>Accessed July 21, 2021, <ptr
                        target="https://github.com/EpiDoc/EFES/wiki"/>. Creation of new facets, last
                     updated April 11, 2018: <ptr
                        target="https://github.com/EpiDoc/EFES/wiki/Search-interface"/>. Creation of
                     new indexes, last updated May 27, 2020: <ptr
                        target="https://github.com/EpiDoc/EFES/wiki/Indices"/>.</p></note>
                  Furthermore, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R25" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name"
                     ref="#R25">EFES</rs> makes it possible to create an epigraphic concordance of the
               various editions of each inscription and to add information pages as TEI XML files
               (suitable for displaying both information on the database itself and potential
               additional accompanying information).</p>
            <p>Against this background, the combined use of the EpiDoc encoding and of the <ptr
               type="software" xml:id="R26" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R26"
                  >EFES</rs> tool seemed to be a promising approach for the purposes of my research
               project, and so it was.</p>
            <p>I initially aimed to create updated digital editions of the inscriptions mentioning
               Cretan institutional elements that could be used to facilitate a comparative analysis
               of the latter. The ability to generate and view the indexes of the mentioned
               institutional elements gradually, while I was in the process of encoding the
               inscriptions in EpiDoc, totally met my needs, and helped me very much in the
               identification of recurring patterns. As I was expected to submit my doctoral thesis
               in PDF format, I also needed to convert the epigraphic editions into PDF, and by
               running <ptr type="software" xml:id="R27" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name"
                  ref="#R27">EFES</rs> locally I have been able to view their transformed HTML
               versions on a browser and to naively copy and paste them into a Microsoft Word
                     file.<note><p>I am very grateful to Pietro Maria Liuzzo for teaching me how to
                     avoid this conversion step by using XSL-FO, which can be used to generate a PDF
                     directly from the raw XML files. The use of XSL-FO, however, requires some
                     additional skills that are not needed in the copy-and-paste-from-the-browser
                     process.</p></note> Although I had not planned it from the beginning, <ptr
                        type="software" xml:id="R28" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R28"
                  >EFES</rs> also proved to be useful in the (online) publication of the results of
               my research. The ease with which <ptr type="software" xml:id="R29" target="#EFES"
               /><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R29">EFES</rs> allows the creation of a searchable
               epigraphic database, in fact, spontaneously led me to decide to publish it online
               once completed, making available not only the HTML editions—which can also be
               downloaded as printable PDFs—but also the raw XML files for reuse. The aim of the
               online publication, in fact, is to allow other researchers to query the epigraphic
               collection for their needs and to encourage the reuse of the dataset for
               unpredictable future digital humanities purposes.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="overview">
            <head><title level="m">Cretan Institutional Inscriptions</title>: An Overview of the
               Database</head>
            <p>The core of the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R30" target="#EFES"/><rs
               type="soft.name" ref="#R30">EFES</rs>-based database <title level="m">Cretan
                  Institutional Inscriptions</title> consists of the EpiDoc editions of the
               previously selected six hundred inscriptions, which can be exported both in PDF and
               in their original XML format. Each edition is composed of an essential descriptive
               lemma; a bibliographic lemma, also including links to external online resources; a
               critical edition of the Greek text; a selective apparatus—where necessary—recording
               mainly the most significant readings or restorations affecting the institutional
               terms; and a commentary to contextualize the institutional elements mentioned in the
               document.</p>
            <p>Thanks to the EpiDoc markup of the texts and of their metadata,<note><p>On which see
                        <ptr target="#encodingInstitutions" type="crossref"/>.</p></note> the
               inscriptions can be browsed by applying one or more customized search facets, which
               allow the selection of the documents according to the bibliographic reference of
               their main editions, period, specific date, place, and wider area of origin, current
               location, documentary type, support type, and also to the mentioned divinities,
               toponyms, or ethnic adjectives and, most importantly, institutional elements. As for
               the latter, specific facets further allow one to browse the inscriptions on the basis
               of the occurrence in their texts of precise institutional terms (such as <foreign
                  xml:lang="grc-Latn">boule</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn"
                  >agoranomos</foreign>), or of their institutional categories (such as
                  <mentioned>assembly</mentioned> or <mentioned>official</mentioned>), or of their
               spheres of competence or roles (such as <mentioned>decreer</mentioned> or
                  <mentioned>eponym</mentioned>).</p>
            <p>The EpiDoc markup also provides the foundation for the rich query possibilities of
               the database. It allows the insertion of elements with attributes having as values
               the base forms of the terms both in Greek—with the preservation of the local
               dialectal variants—and in a standardized transliteration. This enables textual
               searches to be performed that would otherwise be inconceivable on an epigraphic
               record such as the Cretan one, which is scattered with graphic variants and lacunae,
               by using the indexed terms to overcome the limits of the record.</p>
            <p>In addition to the inscriptions, the database includes two catalogs, whose aim is to
               offer some insights into the complex mosaic of the many political entities of Crete
               and of their institutions. Also, the database includes a collection of the most
               significant literary sources pertaining to the Cretan institutions and a list of all
               the mentioned bibliographic references. These four sections, <title level="a"
                  >Political entities</title>, <title level="a">Institutions</title>, <title
                  level="a">Literary sources</title>, and <title level="a">Bibliographic
                  references</title>, have been added to the database as pages generated from TEI
               XML files, which could be natively included in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R31"
                  target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R31">EFES</rs>.</p>
            <p>As mentioned above, the database also includes several thematic indexes listing the
               marked-up terms along with the references to the inscriptions in which they occur,
               divided into institutions, toponyms and ethnic adjectives, lemmata (both of
               institutions and of other significant terms), prosopographical elements,
               anthroponyms, and names of divinities, nymphs, and heroes.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="encodingInstitutions">
            <head>Encoding Institutions (and More) with EpiDoc</head>
            <p>For my epigraphic collection, the TEI-EpiDoc markup was beneficial as applied to the
               entire editions of the inscriptions,<note><p>Following the structure of the EpiDoc
                     template that can be found in the EpiDoc Guidelines v. 9.2, October 13, 2020:
                        <ptr
                        target="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/ex-epidoctemplate.xml?format=raw"
                     />. See also EpiDoc Guidelines v. 9.2, October 13, 2020, <ptr
                        target="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/supp-structure.html"/> and <title
                        level="a">EpiDoc Edition Structure Quick Reference</title>, March 17, 2017,
                        <ptr
                        target="https://svn.code.sf.net/p/epidoc/code/trunk/guidelines/msword/structure-cheatsheet.pdf"
                     />.</p></note> but it proved to be particularly useful in the encoding of the
               Greek texts (in the <tag type="start">div type=&quot;edition&quot;</tag>), where it
               was strictly connected to my research questions. The EpiDoc elements, attributes and
               attribute values I chose to use inside the <tag type="start">div
                  type=&quot;edition&quot;</tag> facilitated my analysis of the institutional
               elements mentioned in the documents, aiming at the identification, contextualization,
               and indexing of the institutional terms and of the attested individuals holding an
               office. A TEI-based approach proved to be especially effective for dealing with the
               challenging Cretan institutional records,<note><p>See <ptr type="crossref"
                        target="#institutional_inscriptions"/> above.</p></note> because, in
               particular, the possibility of using multiple attributes in the same element allowed
               me to extract the institutional occurrences as contextually as possible. In other
               words, it allowed me to identify and index not only the simple occurrence of the
               institutional terms, but also a set of connected details that were extremely valuable
               for examining and then classifying them according to several variables.</p>
            <p>Let us now look in detail at the markup of the institutional terms. The EpiDoc
               Guidelines, in this respect, do not offer many details. The closest case is the one
               presented in the <title level="a">Titles, Offices, Political Posts, Honorifics,
                  Occupations</title> section.<note><p>EpiDoc Guidelines v. 9.2, October 13, 2020,
                        <ptr target="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/idx-titlesoffices.html"
                     />.</p></note> Here, besides suggesting that one encode <q>different types of
                  offices, posts, and other titles</q> with the <gi>w</gi> element and the
                  <att>lemma</att> attribute for indexing purposes, it also suggests using the
                  <gi>rs</gi> (referencing string) element with a <att>type</att> attribute, and
               possibly also a <att>ref</att> or <att>key</att> attribute to point to an authority
               list of the marked-up terms. The most relevant of the two examples included in the
               page accordingly proposes marking up <mentioned><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                     >ἀρχόντων</foreign></mentioned> with <tag type="start">rs type="official"
                  key="archon"</tag>.</p>
            <p>Starting from this approach and expanding it, I decided to adopt the following markup
               for the institutional elements mentioned in the inscriptions. Each institutional term
               was encoded using the <gi>rs</gi> element with a <att>type</att> attribute having the
               value <val>institution</val> (conceptually wider than <val>official</val>). Each
                  <gi>rs</gi> has been provided with a <att>key</att> attribute, used to define a
               standardized transliterated base form of each institutional element; all the possible
               values of the <att>key</att> attribute have been listed in the connected authority
               list.</p>
            <p>Another crucial role has been played by two further attributes of <gi>rs</gi> that I
               decided to add: <att>subtype</att> and <att>role</att>, whose values have also been
               listed in the related authority lists. These attributes have been particularly useful
               to my research because they have allowed the specification—on a case-by-case basis—of
               the nature and the role or sphere of competence of each occurrence of an
               institutional element. This avoided the risky operation of trying to define them in
               an abstract way, on the basis of etymological speculation, or preconceptions derived
               from the literary sources, or not always pertinent parallels.<note><p>One example of
                     these tendencies is the assumption, on the basis of Arist. <title level="m"
                        >Pol</title>. II 1272a, that one of the main tasks of the <foreign
                        xml:lang="grc-Latn">kosmoi</foreign> was to be military leaders. However, in
                     none of the 760 epigraphic occurrences of the Cretan <foreign
                        xml:lang="grc-Latn">kosmoi</foreign> are they mentioned as such!</p></note>
               In particular, I have used the attribute <att>subtype</att> to specify for each
               occurrence the institutional category it belongs to, such as <val>official</val> or
                  <val>assembly</val>, and the attribute <att>role</att> to specify its precise
               function in that particular context, for example <val>dedicant</val> or
                  <val>decreer</val>, or, if its function is unknown, its field of action, such as
                  <val>cult</val> or <val>war</val>. The combination of these attributes proved to
               be particularly efficient for addressing my main research questions, which were aimed
               at understanding the variations of the forms in which the institutional elements
               appear and of their role/function/sphere of competence: the same institutional
               element, for example an official like the <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn"
                  >kosmos</foreign>, could sometimes appear alone as a single official (<tag
                  type="start">rs type="institution" subtype="official" role="..."
                  key="kosmos"</tag>), sometimes as a member of the board of the <foreign
                  xml:lang="grc-Latn">kosmoi</foreign> (<tag type="start">rs type="institution"
                  subtype="board" role="..." key="kosmos"</tag>). Some actions, also, turned out to
               be performed only by the full board of the <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn"
                  >kosmoi</foreign> (for example the act of decreeing, <tag type="start">rs
                  type="institution" subtype="board" role="decreer" key="kosmos"</tag>, or the
               promotion of building activities, <tag type="start">rs type="institution"
                  subtype="board" role="builder" key="kosmos"</tag>), whereas other actions were
               sometimes attested in connection with single <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn"
                  >kosmoi</foreign> and sometimes with their full board (for example being a
               dedicant: <tag type="start">rs type="institution" subtype="official" role="dedicant"
                  key="kosmos"</tag>, but also <tag type="start">rs type="institution"
                  subtype="board" role="dedicant" key="kosmos"</tag>).</p>
            <p>The use of another attribute of <gi>rs</gi>, <att>ref</att>, also allowed a direct
               link between the specific occurrences of institutional elements and the political
               entity they belong to, pointing to the authority list of the places. The possibility
               of linking each occurrence to its political entity, in fact, was absolutely essential
               given the geographical approach of my research, aimed at identifying and valorizing
               the institutional specificity of each political entity of Crete.<note><p>See <ptr
                        type="crossref" target="#Cretan_epigraphy"/> above.</p></note> The attribute
                  <att>ref</att> proved to be very useful because the political entity of the
               institutional element very often differs from the findspot or the origin place of the
                     inscription,<note><p>This is particularly true for treaties, which always
                     involve at least two different political entities, and for the inscriptions
                     which were placed in extra-urban sanctuaries.</p></note> and therefore this
               information could not be extracted from any of the metadata of the inscription
               itself.</p>
            <p>In addition to <gi>rs</gi>, I have marked up the institutional terms—as well as some
               other significant terms, even if not strictly institutional—with the <gi>w</gi>
               element and its attribute <att>lemma</att>, as suggested also by the EpiDoc
                     Guidelines.<note><p>EpiDoc Guidelines v. 9.2, October 13, 2020, <ptr
                        target="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/idx-titlesoffices.html"/>. See
                     also EpiDoc Guidelines v. 9.2, October 13, 2020, <ptr
                        target="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/idx-wordslemmata.html"
                  />.</p></note> In the cases in which the term is preceded or followed by the name
               of the individual holding that office, I have encoded the name both as a
               prosopographical datum (with the <gi>persName</gi> element and its attributes
                  <att>type</att> with value <val>attested</val>, <att>key</att> and, where
               applicable, <att>ref</att>, for linking the person to their political entity) and as
               an onomastic one (with the <gi>name</gi> element and its attributes <att>nymRef</att>
               and, where applicable, <att>type</att> with value <val>patronymic</val>,
                  <val>metronymic</val> or <val>andronym</val>).<note><p>Broadly following the
                     suggestions of the EpiDoc Guidelines v. 9.2, October 13, 2020, <ptr
                        target="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/idx-persnames.html"
               />.</p></note></p>
            <figure xml:id="example1">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <rs type="institution" subtype="official" role="eponym" key="damiorgos"
                     ref="#olous">ἐπὶ <w lemma="δαμιοργός">δαμιοργοῦ</w>
                     <persName type="attested" key="Leukos"><name nymRef="Λεῦκος"
                        >Λεύκου</name></persName></rs>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">The encoding of an institutional element (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#icret"><title level="m">I.Cret.</title> I 22 4 A, l. 31</ref>).</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Besides the institutional terms and the individuals holding an office, I also
               considered it useful to consistently mark up all the occurrences in the texts of
               toponyms and ethnic adjectives and of honored individuals, foreign rulers, and
               theonyms. The toponyms and ethnic adjectives I have marked up using the
                  <gi>placeName</gi> element with its attributes <att>ref</att> (for linking them to
               the relevant authority list) and, where applicable, <att>type</att> with the value
                  <val>ethnic</val>.<note><p>Again following the EpiDoc Guidelines v. 9.2, October
                     13, 2020: <ptr target="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/idx-geognames.html"
                     />.</p></note> The honored individuals, foreign rulers, and theonyms I have
               marked up similarly to the individual holding an office, by using the
                  <gi>persName</gi> element and, for honored individuals and foreign rulers, also a
               nested <tag type="start">name nymRef=&quot;&quot;</tag>. Broadly following a
               consolidated EpiDoc practice, I have added a <att>type</att> attribute to each
                  <gi>persName</gi>, with the values <val>honoured</val> for honored individuals,
                  <val>ruler</val> for the rulers, and <val>divine</val> for the
                     theonyms.<note><p>The values <val>attested</val> and <val>divine</val> are
                     recommended by the EpiDoc Guidelines v. 9.2, October 13, 2020, <ptr
                        target="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/idx-persnames.html"/>. The value
                        <val>ruler</val> (instead of the <val>emperor</val> suggested by the EpiDoc
                     Guidelines) has also been used by <title level="m">Inscriptions of Greek
                        Cyrenaica</title> (<ref type="bibl" target="#igcyr">Dobias-Lalou 2017</ref>)
                     and by <title level="m">IOSPE</title> (<ref type="bibl" target="#iospe"
                        >Ivantchik, Polinskaya, and Bodard 2011–</ref>): see, for example,
                     IGCyr033700, accessed September 15, 2021, <ptr
                        target="https://igcyr.unibo.it/igcyr/igcyr033700.xml"/> and IOSPE V 14,
                     accessed September 15, 2021, <ptr target="https://iospe.kcl.ac.uk/5.14.xml"
                     />.</p></note></p>
            <figure xml:id="example2">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <div type="edition" xml:lang="grc" xml:space="preserve">                <ab>                        <lb n="1"/><rs type="institution" subtype="practice" role="decreeing" key="dokeo" ref="#polyrrhenia"><w lemma="δοκέω"><supplied reason="lost">ἔ</supplied>δο<supplied reason="lost">ξ</supplied>ε</w></rs> <unclear>τ</unclear>οῖς <rs type="institution" subtype="board" role="decreer" key="kosmos" ref="#polyrrhenia"><w lemma="κόσμος">κόσμοις</w></rs>                        <lb n="2"/><supplied reason="lost">καὶ τ</supplied>ᾶι <rs type="institution" subtype="assembly" role="decreer" key="polis" ref="#polyrrhenia"><w lemma="πόλις"><unclear>π</unclear>όλ<unclear>ι</unclear></w></rs> <persName type="honoured" key="Onymarchos f. Habraios"><name nymRef="Ὀνύμαρχος">Ὀνύμαρ<lb break="no" n="3"/><supplied reason="lost">χ</supplied>ον</name> <name nymRef="Ἁβραῖος" type="patronymic">Ἁβ<unclear>ρ</unclear>αίω</name> <placeName ref="#gortyn" type="ethnic">Γορτύνι<lb break="no" n="4"/>ον</placeName></persName> <rs type="institution" subtype="social_status" role="granted_as_privilege" key="proxenos" ref="#polyrrhenia"><w lemma="πρόξενος">πρόξενον</w></rs> ἦμεν κα<supplied reason="lost">ὶ</supplied>                        <lb n="5"/><rs type="institution" subtype="social_status" role="granted_as_privilege" key="euergetes" ref="#polyrrhenia"><w lemma="εὐεργέτας"><supplied reason="lost">εὐερ</supplied><unclear>γέτ</unclear>αν</w></rs> αὐτὸν καὶ                        <lb n="6"/><w lemma="ἔκγονος"><supplied reason="lost">ἔκγο</supplied>να.</w>                </ab>            </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">The complete encoding of an inscription text (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#icret"><title level="m">I.Cret.</title> II 23 5</ref>).</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="figure1">
               <graphic url="img/formatted_inscription.png" width="270px" height="195px"/>
               <head type="legend">The formatted text of the inscription in <ptr target="#example2"
                     type="crossref"/> (<ref type="bibl" target="#icret"><title level="m"
                        >I.Cret.</title></ref> II 23 5).</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Given the markup described above, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R32" target="#EFES"
            /><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R32">EFES</rs> was able to generate detailed indexes
               having the appearance of rich tables, where each piece of information is displayed in
               a dedicated column and can easily be combined with the other ones at a glance.</p>
            <p>In the most complex case, that of the institutions, the index displays for each
               occurrence the base form of the term both in transliteration and in Greek (under the
               headings Istituzione and Termine attestato, obtained from <att>key</att> of
                  <gi>rs</gi> and <att>lemma</att> of <gi>w</gi>), the potentially relevant
               prosopographical element (under Individuo, obtained from <att>key</att> of
                  <gi>persName</gi>), its nature and role or sphere of competence (under Tipologia
               and Ambito/Ruolo, obtained from <att>subtype</att> and <att>role</att> of
               <gi>rs</gi>), its geographical and chronological context (under Località and Periodo,
               obtained from <att>ref</att> of <gi>rs</gi> and from <att>period</att> of
                  <gi>origDate</gi>, which is encoded among the other metadata in the
                  <gi>teiHeader</gi> of each inscription) and finally the epigraphic sources where
               it is attested (under Occorrenze).</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure2">
               <graphic url="img/institutional_index.png" width="1092px" height="656px"/>
               <head type="legend">An excerpt from the index of the institutional elements.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>The prosopographical index, similarly, displays for each individual a combination of
               additional data deriving from the EpiDoc markup: their onomastic formula (under Nome,
               obtained from <att>key</att> of <gi>persName</gi>), their geographical context (under
               Località, obtained from a <att>ref</att> linked to the authority list of
                     places),<note><p>If the individual has an ethnic adjective, marked up as <tag
                        type="start">placeName type="ethnic"</tag>, the <att>ref</att> is the one
                     corresponding to this <gi>placeName</gi>. Otherwise, if the individual is
                     associated with an institutional element, marked up with <tag type="start">rs
                        type="institution"</tag>, the <att>ref</att> is the one corresponding to
                     this <gi>rs</gi>. If the individual is not associated with a <gi>placeName</gi>
                     or an <gi>rs</gi>, a <att>ref</att> has been added directly to their
                        <gi>persName</gi>.</p></note> their general role (under Tipologia, obtained
               from <att>type</att> of <gi>persName</gi>), and the inscriptions where they are
               mentioned (under Occorrenze).</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure3">
               <graphic url="img/prosopographical_index.png" width="1098px" height="685px"/>
               <head type="legend">An excerpt from the prosopographical index.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>In addition to the more <soCalled>tabular</soCalled> institutional and
               prosopographical indexes, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R33" target="#EFES"/><rs
                  type="soft.name" ref="#R33">EFES</rs> facilitated the creation of other more
               traditional indexes, including the indexed terms and the references to the
               inscriptions that mention them. The encoding of the most significant words with <tag
                  type="start">w lemma=""</tag> led to the creation of a word index of relevant
               terms attested in the inscriptions. Similarly, an index of the attested toponyms and
               ethnic adjectives was generated from their encoding with <tag type="start">placeName
                  ref=""</tag>; an index of the attested divinities, nymphs, and heroes from their
               encoding with <tag type="start">persName type="divine" key=""</tag>; and an index of
               personal names—of individuals holding an office, honored individuals, and foreign
               rulers—from their encoding with <tag type="start">name nymRef=""</tag>.</p>
            <p>In total, the semantic markup has involved 8,162 lemmata (<gi>w</gi>), 4,353
               institutional elements (<gi>rs</gi>), 2,633 toponyms or ethnic adjectives
                  (<gi>placeName</gi>), 1,694 anthroponyms (<gi>name</gi>) and 1,651
               prosopographical elements (<gi>persName</gi>).</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="conclusions">
            <head>Conclusions</head>
            <p>In conclusion, I would like to emphasize how particularly efficient the combined use
               of EpiDoc and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R34" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name"
                  ref="#R34">EFES</rs> has proven to be for the creation of a thematic database
               like Cretan Institutional Inscriptions. By collecting in a searchable database all
               the inscriptions pertaining to the Cretan institutions, records that were hitherto
               accessible only in a scattered way, Cretan Institutional Inscriptions is a new
               resource that can facilitate the finding, consultation, and reuse of these very
               heterogeneous documents, many of which offer further points of reflection only when
               considered in light of the full documentation. The example of Cretan Institutional
               Inscriptions, moreover, could prove helpful—from the methodological point of view—to
               other epigraphists who are dealing with an analogous collection of inscriptions,
               either with a view to analyzing it or to publishing it in a digital format.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="babeu2011">
                  <author>Babeu, Alison</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title level="a"
                     >Epigraphy</title>, In <title level="m"><q>Rome Wasn’t Digitized in a Day</q>:
                     Building a Cyberinfrastructure for Digital Classicists</title>, by
                     <author>Alison Babeu</author>. <biblScope unit="page">96–117</biblScope>. CLIR
                  publication 150 (web only, PDF). <pubPlace>Washington</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>CLIR</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub150/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bodard_stoyanova2016">
                  <author>Bodard, Gabriel</author>, <author>Stoyanova, Simona</author>.
                     <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">Epigraphers and Encoders: Strategies for
                     Teaching and Learning Digital Epigraphy</title>. Chap. 3 in <title level="m"
                     >Digital Classics Outside the Echo-Chamber: Teaching, Knowledge Exchange &amp;
                     Public Engagement</title>, edited by <editor>Gabriel Bodard</editor> and
                     <editor>Matteo Romanello</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">51–68</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Ubiquity Press</publisher>. <idno
                     type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.5334/bat.d</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bodard_yordanova_2020">
                  <author>Bodard, Gabriel</author>, <author>Yordanova, Polina</author>.
                     <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">Publication, Testing and Visualization with
                        <ptr type="software" xml:id="EFES" target="#EFES"/><rs type="soft.name"
                        ref="#EFES">EFES</rs>: A Tool for All Stages of the EpiDoc XML Editing
                     Process</title>. <title level="j">Studia Universitatis Babeș-Bolyai
                     Digitalia</title>, no. <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>: <biblScope
                     unit="page">17–35</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.24193/subbdigitalia.2020.1.02</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="igcyr">
                  <author>Dobias-Lalou, Catherine</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="m"
                     >Inscriptions of Greek Cyrenaica</title>, in collaboration with <author>Alice
                     Bencivenni</author>, <author>Hugues Berthelot</author>, with help from
                     <author>Simona Antolini</author>, <author>Silvia Maria Marengo</author>, and
                     <author>Emilio Rosamilia</author>. <pubPlace>Bologna</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>CRR-MM, Alma Mater Studiorum Università di Bologna</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://igcyr.unibo.it/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="epidoc">
                  <author>Elliott, Tom</author>, <author>Bodard, Gabriel</author>, <author>Mylonas,
                     Elli</author>, <foreign>et al</foreign>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="m"
                     >EpiDoc Guidelines: Ancient Documents in TEI XML (Version 9.2)</title>. <ptr
                     target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="genevrois2017">
                  <author>Genevrois, Gerard</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="m">Le
                     vocabulaire institutionnel crétois d’après les inscriptions (VIIe-IIe s. av.
                     J.-C.). Étude philologique et dialectologique</title>. <pubPlace>Geneva,
                     Switzerland</pubPlace>: <publisher>Droz</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="icret">
                  <editor>Guarducci, Margherita</editor>, ed. <date>1935–1950</date>. <title
                     level="m">Inscriptiones Creticae: Opera et consilio Friderici Halbherr
                     collectae</title>. 4 vols. <pubPlace>Rome</pubPlace>: <publisher>La Libreria
                     dello Stato</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="iospe">
                  <author>Ivantchik, Askold</author>, <author>Polinskaya, Irene</author>,
                     <author>Bodard, Gabriel</author>, <foreign>et al</foreign>. <date>2011–</date>.
                     <title>IOSPE [Inscriptiones antiquae Orae Septentrionalis Ponti Euxini graecae
                     et latinae]: Ancient Inscriptions of the Northern Black Sea</title>. Accessed
                  July 16, 2021. <ptr target="https://iospe.kcl.ac.uk/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="aio">
                  <editor>Lambert, Stephen</editor>, <editor>Polly Low</editor>, <editor>Peter
                     Liddel</editor>, and <editor>Chris de Lisle</editor>, eds. <date>2012–</date>.
                     <title level="m">Attic Inscriptions Online</title>. Accessed July 16, 2021 <ptr
                     target="https://www.atticinscriptions.com/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="vagionakis2021"><author>Vagionakis, Irene</author>. <date>2021</date>.
                     <title level="m">Cretan Institutional Inscriptions</title>.
                     <publisher>VeDPH</publisher>, <publisher>ILC-CNR for CLARIN-IT</publisher>.
                  Accessed July 16, 2021. <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/20.500.11752/OPEN-550"
                     >http://hdl.handle.net/20.500.11752/OPEN-550</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
