<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Presentation Of Web Site On The Banking And Financial History Of Spain And Latin America</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Marichal</surname>
                        <forename>Carlos</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>El Colegio de Mexico, Mexico</affiliation>
                    <email>cmari@colmex.mx</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-04-27T19:25:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Name, Institution</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Street</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>City</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Country</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Name</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>history</term>
                    <term>Latinamerica</term>
                    <term>Spain</term>
                    <term>banks</term>
                    <term>webpages</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>databases &amp; dbms</term>
                    <term>historical studies</term>
                    <term>project design</term>
                    <term>organization</term>
                    <term>management</term>
                    <term>digitisation</term>
                    <term>resource creation</term>
                    <term>and discovery</term>
                    <term>spanish and spanish american studies</term>
                    <term>English</term>
                    <term>geography</term>
                    <term>public humanities and community engaged scholarship</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>The purpose of this ten-minute presentation is to present this thematic site which we have constructed in 2016 (and is bilingual) and is of use for professors, students, and general public. The object this academic web page (the first of its kind in this specific field) is to provide a large amount of documents (including links to over 200 working papers) historical statistics (over 600 Excel charts and graphs), bibliographies, guides to archival sources and short historical summaries of the banking histories of many countries in Latin America as well as Spain. Both El Colegio de México and the University of Cantabria (Spain) have collaborated in this project under the direction of Dr. Carlos Marichal. The site will soon be transferred to the electronic resources of the Libraries of both academic institutions. </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="color(212121)" xml:space="preserve">I argue that this thematic webpage corresponds to an increasing trend in contemporary academics to </hi>
                <hi rend="italic color(212121)">combine</hi>
                <hi rend="color(212121)" xml:space="preserve"> concrete and deep research results in </hi>
                <hi rend="italic color(212121)">subdisciplines</hi>
                <hi rend="color(212121)" xml:space="preserve"> with complementary resources of a varied nature, including historical statistical series, reference texts, images (photos and engravings), timelines, and resources for teaching. </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="color(212121)">Such resources are especially useful for consultation on line by professors and students in local universities, many of which – in Mexico and Latina America- do not have really rich library/digital resources In addition I might remark that there is a demand from schools and universities for advanced online courses in humanities and social sciences that can be especially useful for updating university professors, especially in the provinces, where there is urgent need for support to achieve a substantial improvement in teaching and research in humanities and social sciences in Mexico or other countries in the region. </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="color(212121)" xml:space="preserve">To accomplish this, a multidisciplinary working group of academics has been set up to gather pertinent information from the various humanities and social sciences in the field of banking and financial history of Latin America and Spain, which explains the international consortium engaged. The interest of the project lies in the pioneering projects in this field in the humanities and social sciences both in academia in Mexico and elsewhere. </hi>The site can be consulted at 
            </p>
            <p>
                <ref target="http://codexvirtual.com/hbancaria/">http://codexvirtual.com/hbancaria/</ref>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
