<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model 
   href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" 
   type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" 
   type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-cc-ra-barney-187-source.xml 1027 2021-04-20 09:26:08Z tiago.sousa-garcia $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"  rend="jTEI.internal">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">TEI, the Walt Whitman Archive, and the Test of Time </title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Brett</forename>
                  <surname>Barney</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>Brett Barney is a <roleName>research associate professor</roleName> at
                     <orgName>University of Nebraska–Lincoln’s Center for Digital Research in the
                     Humanities (CDRH)</orgName> and has been involved in the development of the
                  Walt Whitman Archive since 2000, first as a research assistant and more recently
                  as senior associate editor. He has also worked on a variety of other CDRH
                  projects, including the Willa Cather Archive and the Journals of the Lewis and
                  Clark Expedition Online. He served two terms (2010–2013) on the TEI Consortium’s
                  Technical Council and is especially interested in expanding TEI’s provisions for
                  documentary and genetic editing.</affiliation>
               <email>bbarney2@unl.edu</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>25/02/2021</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor role="guest">Susan Schreibman</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="13">Selected Papers from the 2018 TEI Conference</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for
               journals in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking
               to publish full-text articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>scholarly editing</term>
               <term>manuscripts</term>
               <term>genetic editions</term>
               <term>temporality</term>
               <term>diachronic markup</term>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2021-04-20">Tiago Sousa Garcia added author corrections to proof</change>
         <change when="2021-02-25">Pietro Liuzzo encoded the file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p><q>Diachronic Markup and Presentation Practices for Text Editions in Digital
               Environments</q>, a 2014–15 transatlantic collaboration funded jointly by DFG and NEH,
               provided an occasion to test TEI’s relatively new provisions for encoding
               temporality. My experiences in attempting to apply these provisions to Walt Whitman
               manuscripts led me to conclude that chapter 11 of the TEI Guidelines should be
               significantly revised and that the basic dichotomy it introduces between
                  <gi>sourceDoc</gi> and <gi>text</gi> deserves renewed scrutiny. Some of the
               problems in the chapter can be traced to the way the Guidelines have evolved over
               time through a series of choices motivated by expediency. The Whitman Archive has,
               since its first foray into TEI markup in 2000, been anxious to find a way to leverage
               its potential to encode the temporal characteristics and relationships among various
               manuscript and print instances. The customization we created, however, has shown
               itself inadequate to describe and make processable important genetic information.
               Unfortunately, TEI also continues to provide inadequate guidance in the area of
               encoding genetic relationships, both between documents and within them. My
               experiments during the Diachronic Markup project included using <gi>listChange</gi>
               to encode the sequence in which the text of a single document was inscribed and show
               that, although the Guidelines need to be developed with specific advice and examples,
               existing elements and attributes can be used to posit claims about the <soCalled>way the page
               was filled,</soCalled> thereby enabling useful processing and display.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="acknowledgements">
            <p>This essay has been substantially revised since I presented it at the 2018 TEI
               Conference in Tokyo. I am very grateful to Gerrit Brüning, who has offered wise and
               generous insights over the course of several years as we have discussed many of the
               specific issues I raise here. I have also attempted to benefit from the input of two
               anonymous reviewers, whose comments were at once kind, thoughtful, and incisive.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
        
            <p>The release of version 2.0 of the P5 Guidelines in late 2011 represented a
               culmination of sorts for the efforts, over the course of several years, of the
               Workgroup on Genetic Editions. The group’s stated goal was <quote source="#quoteref1">to develop an Application
               Profile for the encoding of genetic editions and, in general, genetic phenomena</quote>
               (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref1" target="#burnard">Burnard et al. n.d.</ref>). 
               In the words of the Council members who wrote the release
               notes, P5 v. 2 included <quote source="#quoteref2">several new elements <gap/> to facilitate a more
               <soCalled>document-focussed</soCalled> 
                  (as opposed to <soCalled>text-focussed</soCalled>) way of working.</quote> The most
               dramatic innovation was the introduction of the <gi>sourceDoc</gi> element, which as
               an analog to the <gi>text</gi> element can be used to group both <quote source="#quoteref2">images of a source
                  document</quote> and <quote source="#quoteref2">detailed <gap/> transcriptions of the source.</quote> To explain the ways in
               which one might undertake such a representation, chapter 11, <title level="a">Representation of
                  Primary Sources</title>, was <quote source="#quoteref2">exhaustively revised</quote> to include the new provisions, which
               were intended to <quote source="#quoteref2">improve <gap/> support <gap/> for documentary and genetic editing</quote>
               (<ref type="bibl" target="#TEI2011" xml:id="quoteref2">TEI Consortium 2011</ref>).</p>
         <p>Having used TEI in my work for the Walt Whitman Archive (<ptr
               target="whitmanarchive.org"/>) since 2000, I had been observing the progress of the
            Workgroup with great interest and had, in fact, been involved with them to an extent,
            first as one of many digital editors convened in 2009 to provide input and later as a
            member of the TEI Council when the Workgroup’s proposals were being debated and
            eventually implemented. I was therefore enthusiastic when the editors of the Whitman
            Archive were approached to contribute material to a two-year project with the
            no-nonsense title <q>Diachronic Markup and Presentation Practices for Text Editions
               in Digital Environments</q>, which was to be proposed to the National Endowment
            for the Humanities and the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft. Submitted by Anne
            Bohnenkamp-Renken and Malte Rehbein, the proposal states that the main purpose of the
            transatlantic project was <quote source="#quoteref3">to test, improve, and make usable for a broad audience the
            TEI Guidelines for diachronic markup</quote> 
            (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref3" target="#bohnenkamp2012">2012</ref>).<note>The term 
               <soCalled>diachronic</soCalled> came into the
               field of editing from linguistics and signifies the historical dimension of texts
               (i.e., their change across time). In this way it contrasts with the <soCalled>synchronic</soCalled>
               dimension, which is static and ahistorical, like a snapshot. Marina Buzzoni has
               discussed the relevance of the diachronic and synchronic in digital editing in terms
               of Gianfranco Cantini’s requirement that an edition <quote source="#quoteref4">aim at injecting history into
               the critically reconstructed text by taking into account the different synchronic
               states that make up its diachronic dimension</quote> 
               (<ref target="#buzzoni" type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref4">2016, 62</ref>).</note> Through a series of
            strange events I found myself and the Whitman Archive closer to the center of this
            project than I had anticipated, as I became the United States–based co-principal investigator when Rehbein
            relocated to Germany shortly before the project started.</p>
            <p>The work and outcomes of the Diachronic Markup project have been the subject of
               several previous presentations. Gerrit Brüning, Katrin Henzel, and Dietmar Pravida,
               who were engaged with Bohnenkamp-Renken in creating a digital edition of Johann
               Wolfgang von Goethe’s <title level="m">Faust</title>, have offered especially
               insightful reflections on their experiences in testing TEI’s then-new markup
               (<ref target="#bruning2013" type="bibl">2013</ref>).<note>Their 
                  edition is now available at <ptr target="https://faustedition.net"/>.</note> Joshua
               Schäuble and Hans Walter Gabler have also discussed the project and some of the
               interfaces that grew out of it (<ref type="bibl" target="#schauble2018">2018</ref>). 
               One sobering, though instructive, outcome of
               our collaboration was a clearer realization of the profound differences among our
               individual editorial projects, all of which deal with corpora of manuscripts by
               single authors of the modern era. Although each of the participants was committed to
               the collective goal of using TEI to encode the temporal dimensions of their author’s
               writings, the diversity of practices among those various authors meant that each
               corpus presented unique kinds and amounts of evidence for textual change across time.
               Furthermore, the editors’ diverse theoretical and methodological commitments inclined
               them toward heterogeneous emphases in presenting the materials to readers and,
               therefore, often toward different encoding approaches.</p>
            <p>It was my belief that the main value of our project lay not in producing an edition
               of Whitman’s or anyone else’s work but in its potential to advance the capacity of
               TEI markup for encoding genetic (and not simply <soCalled>diplomatic</soCalled>)<note>Although
                  <soCalled>genetic</soCalled>, <soCalled>documentary</soCalled>, and <soCalled>diplomatic</soCalled> 
                  are sometimes used, in the context of
                  digital editing, as loosely synonymous, even almost interchangeable, I wish to
                  exploit the ways that they are distinct. These distinctions are largely a matter
                  of emphasis (theoretical and/or methodological), which I would sketch as follows:
                     <term>Documentary</term> editing foregrounds the singularity of the
                  original upon which it is based (see <ref type="bibl" target="#pierazzo2014a">Pierazzo 2014a, 2</ref>, 
                  and <ref type="bibl" target="#klineND">Kline and Perdue
                  n.d.</ref>); <term>diplomatic</term> editing highlights the combination of a
                  high degree of fidelity to the physical disposition of writing with a low degree
                  of editorial interpretation (see <ref type="bibl" target="#bodard2020">Bodard 2020</ref>); and <term>genetic</term>
                  editing places emphasis on the process of writing as opposed to the text produced
                  by the process (see <ref target="#hay2017" type="bibl">Hay 2017, 531</ref>).</note> information. 
               And over the course of the
               grant period I did indeed formulate definite opinions about how P5 v. 2 could be
               revised so as to better serve the needs of those wishing to foreground the
               time-inflected aspects of the texts they are editing. I had occasion to carefully
               reread chapter 11 of the TEI Guidelines several times and to discuss it with
               colleagues on the <title level="m">Faust</title> project. Based on those readings and
               discussions, Brüning and I submitted a series of revision suggestions to the TEI
               Technical Council. Many of these revisions were what might be called, in TEI
               parlance, <soCalled>phrase-level</soCalled> tweaks and corrections that were implemented quickly and
               without need for much discussion. Others, however, involved at least chunk-level
               units. The most radical suggestion and the one that has generated the most discussion
               and debate is titled, in the TEI GitHub repository, <title level="a">Restructure chapter 11</title> (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1427">issue
               no. 1427</ref>).<note>See <ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1427"/>.</note> The process of
               reading the Guidelines, testing what they recommend, discussing results, and then
               proposing changes (which have sometimes been further discussed and negotiated) has
               resulted or will likely result in incremental improvements that, taken together,
               should make the Guidelines significantly more usable.<note>As I was revising this
                  essay for publication in August 2020, in fact, I was notified that the TEI Council
                  was planning to address issue no. 1427, our request that the chapter be
                  restructured, by issuing a new release of the Guidelines with some significant
                  changes to the prose of chapter 11. Among the revisions, the several new
                  introductory paragraphs are especially welcome, as they go some way toward making
                  explicit the basic difference in approach between transcriptions within
                     <gi>sourceDoc</gi>, which emphasize <quote source="#quoteref5">spatial features</quote>, and those within
                  <gi>text</gi>, which emphasize <quote  source="#quoteref5">logical textual structure</quote> (<ref
                        xml:id="quoteref5" type="bibl" target="#TEI2020">TEI Consortium
                  2020</ref>).</note> That same process, however, has also convinced me that for the TEI
               Guidelines to become truly adequate to the task of creating digital genetic editions
               of various kinds, the content models for <gi>sourceDoc</gi> and <gi>text</gi> should
               be thoughtfully rationalized, so as to disentangle (or at least acknowledge the
               entanglement of) markup most appropriate to the document (<gi>sourceDoc</gi>) and
               that most appropriate to the text (<gi>text</gi>).<note>The distinction that I am
                  referring to (and advocating) here is the one perhaps most succinctly articulated
                  by Peter Shillingsburg, who says that <quote source="#quoteref6"><mentioned>document</mentioned></quote> 
                  refers to <quote  source="#quoteref6">the physical vessel <gap/> that contains (or incarnates) the <mentioned>text</mentioned></quote>, whereas 
                  <quote  source="#quoteref6"><mentioned>text</mentioned></quote> refers to 
                  <quote  source="#quoteref6">the series
                  of words and pauses recorded in a document</quote> 
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#shillingsburg1996" xml:id="quoteref6">1996, 174</ref>).</note> Doing so would
               require that the TEI Council be willing at least to consider the full range of
               options, not excluding those that would break backward compatibility. I say this
               knowing only too well that radical change is a sort of third rail for TEI, where, at
               least in recent years, incremental evolution has become the <foreign xml:lang="la">modus
                  operandi</foreign>. In most cases I believe this institutional conservatism to be a
               positive aspect of TEI and, in fact, important to its continued use and adoption, but
               in this case a fresh, large-scale reconsideration rather than a localized tinkering
               is in order, as it could help to solidify TEI’s theoretical grounding, or at least
               better articulate it, for the benefit of both present and future practitioners.</p>
            <p>With regard to temporal encoding specifically, however, there is ample scope to
               <soCalled>build out</soCalled> the Guidelines’ facilities without attempting anything so fundamental and
               admittedly controversial as the redefinition of <gi>text</gi> and <gi>sourceDoc</gi>.
               In what follows, therefore, I will focus on chapter 11’s provisions for encoding a
               text’s diachronic dimensions, by which I mean its temporal characteristics both
               within a single document (that is, the posited sequence in which the textual content
               of a particular document was inscribed) and those between and among multiple
               documents (the time-sequenced relationships of text across the various components
               that an editor sees as constituting its genetic dossier).<note>I use the term
                  <term>genetic dossier</term> here as a synonym of <term>avant-texte</term> to refer to all of the
                  documents that contributed to a published work. In doing so, I follow the usage
                  of, for example, Dirk Van Hulle (<ref type="bibl" target="#vanhulle2016">2016, 46</ref>) 
                  and Elena Pierazzo (<ref type="bibl" target="#pierazzo2015">2015, 14</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="#pierazzo2016">2016,
                  49</ref>). Hans Walter Gabler notes, however, that the two terms are sometimes
                  contrasted, the former used to mean that which comprises <quote source="#quoteref7">transcription and image
                     in conjunction,</quote> thus offering <quote source="#quoteref7">the document perspective on what, from the text
                  perspective, is named <soCalled>avant-texte</soCalled></quote>
                  (<ref xml:id="quoteref7" type="bibl" target="#gabler2018">2018, 210</ref>). In fact,
                  although in the hands of later practitioners of the French school of genetic
                  criticism <soCalled>avant-texte</soCalled> has often been associated specifically with texts rather
                  than documents, as originally coined by Jean Bellemin-Noël it seems to have been
                  conceived as document-centric, referring to <quote source="#quoteref8">the totality of the material written
                  for any project that was first made public in a specific form</quote> 
                  (<ref xml:id="quoteref8" type="bibl" target="#bellemin2004">2004, 31</ref>).</note>
               During the Diachronic Markup project we sometimes talked about these two related but
               distinct types or levels of diachronic relationship as the <soCalled>micro</soCalled> and the <soCalled>macro</soCalled>,
                  respectively.<note>Note that I am using these terms to indicate temporal and
                  notional relationships different from those indicated by the <mentioned>microgenetic</mentioned> and
                  <mentioned>macrogenetic</mentioned> levels Van Hulle describes in his five-part scheme (the others
                  being <mentioned>exogenetic</mentioned>, <mentioned>endogenetic</mentioned>, 
                     and <mentioned>epigenetic</mentioned>), where the contrast is
                  essentially a matter of size or wholeness: the macrogenetic level involves <quote source="#quoteref9">the
                  genesis of the work in its entirety across multiple versions,</quote> and the
                     microgenetic <quote  source="#quoteref9">one specific textual instance across <gap/> versions</quote> 
                     (<ref xml:id="quoteref9" type="bibl" target="#vanhulle2016">2016,
                  50</ref>).</note>
            </p>
            <p>Much of the weakness of TEI’s provisions for conducting genetic editing generally,
               and for its inadequate address of the diachronic dimensions of texts specifically,
               can be traced to the peculiar historical circumstances in which chapter 11 has
               developed. I would suggest, then, that a consideration of the genesis of the
               Guidelines themselves is in order, so that ongoing discussions of their remediation
               can proceed with a shared understanding of their historical context.</p>
            <p>A second, closer look at the P5 v. 2 release notes reveals several significant
               details. First, it is worth noting that although the Workgroup carried out its remit
               under the banner of genetic editing, the innovations that resulted from that work
               were largely aimed at, and conceived in terms of, better equipping TEI for the
               purposes of producing narrowly documentary transcriptions, with only a brief nod to
               an overarching genetic purpose: the lead story in the release notes is that
               <quote source="#quoteref10"><supplied>s</supplied>everal new elements have been introduced to facilitate a more <soCalled>document-focussed</soCalled>
               (as opposed to <soCalled>text-focussed</soCalled>) way of working</quote> 
               (<ref type="bibl" target="#TEI2011" xml:id="quoteref10">TEI Consortium 2011</ref>). Of course,
               this characterization relies on the dichotomy between the semantic, intellectual
               signal (viz., the text) and the material, spatial properties of the carrier (viz.,
               the document). In the French tradition of genetic criticism, diplomatic
               transcriptions have been a central feature.<note>Pierazzo calls attention to some of
                  the problems of printed genetic editions, which have not only been <quote source="#quoteref11">criticized as
                  unreadable, unusable, time-consuming, and, in general deceptive</quote> 
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#pierazzo2009" xml:id="quoteref11">2009, 171</ref>) but
                  also as <quote source="#quoteref12">incapable of represent<supplied>ing</supplied> the time flow</quote> 
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#pierazzo2009" xml:id="quoteref12">2009, 171–73</ref>), even though,
                  as she notes, the editors of <title level="m">Genetic Criticism: Texts and
                     Avant-textes</title> state that genetic criticism <quote source="#quoteref13">aims to restore a temporal
                  dimension to the study of literature</quote> 
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#deppman" xml:id="quoteref13">Deppman, Ferrer, and Groden 2004, 2</ref>).</note>
               It is probably for this reason that the transcriptions enabled by the revisions
               introduced in P5 v. 2 are frequently termed <soCalled>genetic</soCalled>, even though they are for the
               most part concerned with the spatial layout of text without any necessary regard to
               genetic relationships. Also in this regard, I would point out that the release notes
               mistakenly (though tellingly) refer to the new container element as
                  <soCalled><gi>document</gi></soCalled>, making quite clear the connection between documentary editing
               and the sort of transcription provided for. The release notes’ explanation of the
               primary function of this new element is similarly telling: <quote source="#quoteref10">to organize digital
               images</quote> in the way previously allowed by <gi>facsimile</gi>, but now possible in
               tandem with a transcription.</p>
            <p>Another instructive oddity of the release notes is their surprising reference to
               chapter 11 as the <quote source="#quoteref10">chapter on <term>Physical Transcription</term></quote>, a slip
               that unwittingly evokes an earlier state of the Guidelines: The current chapter 11,
               <title level="a">Representation of Primary Sources</title>, began, in the P3 version of the TEI Guidelines,
               as chapter 18, <title level="a">Transcription of Primary Sources</title> (<ref type="bibl" target="#sperbergmcqueen1994">Sperberg-McQueen and Burnard
               1994</ref>), a title that it retained through the publication of P4 (<ref target="#TEI2002" type="bibl">TEI Consortium
                  2002</ref>).<note>Equally meaningful is the interpolation in the mis-title of the word
                  <mentioned>physical</mentioned>, which was not part of any actual version. The term <mentioned>physical
                  transcription</mentioned> does, however, pretty accurately reflect the foregrounding of
                  diplomatic transcription in the 2011 version of the chapter.</note> The change
               from <soCalled>transcription</soCalled> to <soCalled>representation</soCalled> was necessitated by the inclusion, in the
               2007 release of P5 v. 1, of the new elements <gi>facsimile</gi> (with its descendants
                  <gi>surface</gi> and <gi>zone</gi>) and <gi>msDesc</gi> (with its descendants
                  <gi>msPart</gi>, <gi>physDesc</gi>, etc.) (<ref type="bibl" target="#TEI2007">TEI Consortium 2007</ref>). Members of the
               TEI community had long lamented the Guidelines’ deficiencies for doing codicological
               work, a shortcoming that the P5 v. 1 release began to address by adding both an
               entirely new chapter, <title level="a">10 Manuscript Description</title>, and a relatively modest section at
               the beginning of what had been chapter 18, now retitled <title level="a">11 Representation of Primary
                  Sources</title> (<ref type="bibl" target="#TEI2007">TEI Consortium 2007</ref>). In its earlier incarnation this chapter was
               explicitly restricted in focus to <quote source="#quoteref14">the transcription of primary sources, particularly
                  manuscripts</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref14" type="bibl" target="#TEI2002">TEI Consortium 2002</ref>), 
               but it was now expanded to demonstrate the use of
                  <gi>facsimile</gi> as a way to provide a nontranscriptional representation of the
               object of interest either alone or as complement to a transcription.</p>
            <p>Having broadened the purview of the chapter to accommodate such a treatment, the
               Council no doubt viewed the subsequent request for a method to allow specific
               components of a transcription to be topographically located—a need of those wishing
               to create more faithful diplomatic transcriptions—as most easily accomplished by a
               further retooling of the existing <gi>facsimile</gi> and associated elements, along
               with the addition of several new elements, such as <gi>metamark</gi>,
                  <gi>transpose</gi>, and <gi>retrace</gi>. In this way, the chapter took on an
               emphasis on layout not so much through careful planning and <emph>building out</emph> of what
               was embryonically present to begin with, but by a sequence of choices characterized
               by expediency.</p>
            <p>I recount these aspects of the historical development of chapter 11 not simply to
               bemoan problems that this evolution has wrought. Rather, I suggest that not only is
               there a logical explanation for the continuing (though unfortunate) lack of solid
               guidance for those wishing to encode the temporal aspects of a text’s
               coming-into-being, but that the chapter’s developmental history has helped to obscure
               the lack. In short, although chapter 11 was chosen as the location of the revisions
               that grew out of the Workgroup on Genetic Editions, and although its contents are
               largely discussed in reference to genetic editing, the chapter brings with it a
               continuing slant toward physical layout, with provisions for encoding temporality
               still relatively poorly developed.</p>
            <p>Like most other TEI users, my interest in the development of TEI is profoundly
               conditioned by an investment in its use for a specific project. In the past two
               decades, much of my work has been devoted to using TEI, in its various iterations, to
               edit manuscripts for the Whitman Archive. Whitman was—and
               is—many things to many people: formal innovator of free verse, one of the first
               <soCalled>truly great</soCalled> American writers, pioneer of literary gay identity, poet of the working
               person, and master of self-promotion, among others. Certainly part of Whitman’s fame,
               in both his time and our own, can be attributed to the creation of an unusual public
               persona. Ed Folsom has claimed that <quote source="#quoteref15">no author’s life in the nineteenth century was
                  more continuously photographed than Whitman’s</quote> 
               (<ref xml:id="quoteref15" type="bibl" target="#folsom1986">1986, 2–3</ref>), and it was partly through
               the widespread distribution of the photographs he particularly liked that Whitman
               worked to construct what he believed to be his best public self. In a similar vein, I
               have come to believe that every presentation regarding the editing of Whitman’s works
               should make an opportunity to present the following image, which provides visual
               evidence that the poet was accurate in describing his living situation: <quote source="#quoteref16">The floor <gap/> is half cover’d by a deep litter of books, papers, magazines, thrown-down letters
               and circulars, rejected manuscripts, memoranda, bits of light or strong twine, a
               bundle to be <soCalled>express’d,</soCalled> and two or three venerable scrap books</quote> 
               (<ref xml:id="quoteref16" type="bibl" target="#whitman1892">Whitman 1892,
               517</ref>).</p>
         
            <figure xml:id="waltwithmannbedroom">
               <graphic url="images/Figure_01.jpg" 
                  width="620px" height="980px"/>
               <head type="legend">Walt Whitman in his bedroom, 1891, photographed by Dr.
                  William Reeder. Available at
                  <ptr target="https://whitmanarchive.org/multimedia/images/large/121.jpg"/>.</head>
            </figure>
         
            <p>At least some of what I like about this photograph is germane to the present topic.
               Most obviously, it presents an arresting visual emblem of both the volume and the
               disarray of the record that editors of Whitman have to confront. <ptr target="#spinesofsome" type="crossref"/> shows
               another favorite image, a graphic created for the Whitman Archive in its early days,
               before I began my association with it (and before the editors adopted TEI).</p>
            
               <figure xml:id="spinesofsome">
                  <graphic url="images/Figure_02.png"  
                     width="620px" height="980px"/>
                  <head type="legend">Spines of some of the various editions of <title level="m">Leaves of Grass</title>, as displayed on the Whitman Archive from 1995 to 2000.
                     Available at <ptr target="https://whitmanarchive.org/archive1/works/leaves/"/>.</head>
               </figure>
           
            <p>
              
            </p>
            <p>One of the ideas that this image vividly conveys is the multiplicity of Whitman’s
               poetry collection, <title level="m">Leaves of Grass</title>. In 1855 <title level="m">Leaves</title> was an oddly tall volume of about one hundred pages, containing twelve
               poems and a long preface in prose. The last incarnation, which Whitman prepared
               shortly before his death in 1892, was a book more conventional in appearance,
               containing nearly four hundred poems on over four hundred pages and a (different)
               long epilogue in prose. Throughout the three and a half decades between those first
               and last versions, Whitman’s masterwork was always a protean entity, moving through a
               series of transformations. Poems were revised; poems were added; poems were deleted;
               poems were retitled. The initial prose preface was turned into poetry. Poems were
               combined or shuffled into new groupings. Groupings were added, discarded, or
               retitled.</p>
            <p>One of the first conversations that I can recall from around the time that I joined
               the Whitman Archive in 2000 concerned the hope of leveraging the power of the
               computer to analyze these various and multiple ways in which <title level="m">Leaves
                  of Grass</title> and its constituent works transmuted over time, across various
               manuscript and printed instantiations. At least part of the appeal of using the Text
               Encoding Initiative’s scheme (embodied in P3, which I came to call <soCalled>the green books</soCalled>:
               see <ref type="bibl" target="#sperbergmcqueen1994">Sperberg-McQueen and Burnard 1994</ref>) 
               was its potential utility for such analysis.
               We found, however, that the markup they offered was inadequate to the task of
               indicating what seemed to us the most basic facts about the relationships among the
               various iterations of Whitman’s masterpiece: namely, that a certain poem in one
               edition developed from a certain poem in a previous edition or manuscript. Our desires
               to represent such relationships prompted a series of project-wide discussions that
               eventually led to the decision to add to our TEI DTD the custom elements
                  <gi>relations</gi> and <gi>work</gi>, with the goal of specifying such genetic
               relationships. These elements we included in our transcriptions of textual instances.
               Here, for example, is a relevant snippet, slightly simplified, from one of our
               TEI-encoded transcriptions of a manuscript draft:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
               <TEI>
                  <relations>
                     <work ref="xxx.00565" cert="high"/>
                  </relations>
                  <!-- ... -->
               </TEI>
            </egXML>
            <p>The key to this system, of course, is the <att>ref</att> attribute, which connects
               this instance to one of Whitman’s works—in this case, the poem <title level="a">After the
                  Argument</title>.<note>IDs are recorded, along with regularized titles, in separate
                  files, one per work (e.g., poem or essay). A third custom element,
                     <gi>workParent</gi>, is used in these files to indicate constituency
                  relationships (for example, to declare that a poem is one of several component
                  parts that constitute a series).</note>
            </p>
            <p>One might get the impression, from the photograph of the old man sitting amid chaotic
               mounds of papers, that Whitman saved absolutely everything—that the manuscript record
               of his literary production is complete, or nearly so. From another perspective, of
               course, the same picture provides clues as to why this is far from true, why the
               author’s <soCalled>system</soCalled> for saving things has resulted in a less-than-ideal record from
               which any would-be Whitman editor must work. Still, the genetic dossiers of 
               <emph>some</emph> of Whitman’s individual poems or essays—especially those
               that date from his last years—is relatively fully extant. Far fewer draft materials
               have survived from the 1850s than from the 1880s, and manuscripts that predate the
               first edition of <title level="m">Leaves of Grass</title> in 1855 are fewer still. It
               is, alas, these earliest manuscripts that are of greatest interest to most Whitman
               scholars, who would welcome evidence that might shed light on what has been one of
               the great <soCalled>mysteries</soCalled> of Whitman scholarship: what Whitman Archive editors Ed Folsom
               and Kenneth M. Price have described as <quote source="#quoteref17">his transformation from an unoriginal and
               conventional poet into one who abruptly abandoned conventional rhyme and meter and <gap/> exploited the odd loveliness of homely imagery, finding beauty in the commonplace
               but expressing it in an uncommon way</quote> (<ref  xml:id="quoteref17" type="bibl" target="#folsomNDb">n.d.</ref>). 
               As Ralph Waldo Emerson famously wrote,
               the remarkable poems of the 1855 edition <q>must have had a long foreground somewhere,
               for such a start</q>, but we have rather scant concrete evidence about the specific ways
               in which the text of that edition developed.<note>The quotation comes from a private
                  letter to Whitman, which he published widely (without Emerson’s permission), even
                  including it in some of the copies of the first edition of <title level="m">Leaves of Grass</title>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Although not many of Whitman’s early poems are attested extensively in the manuscript
               record, the manuscripts that do exist are often fascinating (sometimes in part
               because of the riddles that arise from their being partial). For the purposes of the
               Diachronic Markup project, I was fortunate that at least a passage from one of those
               first-edition poems exists in multiple manuscript forms. That passage, from the poem
               eventually titled <title level="a">The Sleepers</title>, has the added distinction of being of particular
               interest to Whitman scholars generally as evidence of Whitman’s treatment of racial
               issues. At least five different manuscripts related to this passage exist.<note>The
                  Whitman Archive has, in fact, recently completed work, funded by an NEH grant, to
                  publish a <soCalled>variorum</soCalled> edition of the 1855 <title level="m">Leaves of Grass</title>
                  that connects each poetic line in the first printed edition to known manuscripts
                     (<soCalled>avante-texte</soCalled>) as well as to significant textual and
                  spatial variations in different copies. In the course of that work, we identified
                  two additional related manuscripts. These do not affect the substance of my point
                  here, so I have not included them in the discussion. The <title level="m">Leaves
                     of Grass</title> (1855) Variorum is available at
                  <ptr target=" https://whitmanarchive.org/published/LG/1855/variorum/index.html"/>.</note> Four of
               these are individual leaves in the collection of the University of Virginia; the
               other is contained in a notebook at the Library of Congress that includes, besides
               the three consecutive pages of writing relevant to the passage from <title level="a">The Sleepers</title>,
               much writing that is unrelated.</p>
            <p>After a brief examination of images of these documents, nearly anyone would be able
               to surmise that they are related to one another. However, the exact <soCalled>nature</soCalled> of those relationships is far less apparent. The finding guide for
               the collection that houses the four manuscripts at University of Virginia (probably
               originally written by the famous descriptive bibliographer Fredson Bowers) describes
               their relationships thus: the first one shown below (<ptr target="#manuscriptsidentifiedp12" type="crossref"/>) 
               <quote source="#quoteref18">seems to have come
                  first or second</quote>; the next (<ptr target="#manuscriptsidentifiedp9" type="crossref"/>) 
               <quote  source="#quoteref18">was probably second</quote>, 
               the next (<ptr target="#manuscriptsidentifiedp11" type="crossref"/>) 
               <quote  source="#quoteref18">appears
                  to have come third</quote>; and the one in <ptr target="#manuscriptsidentifiedp10" type="crossref"/> 
               <quote source="#quoteref18">seems to have been the last</quote> 
               (<ref xml:id="quoteref18" type="bibl" target="#guidewwhitman">Special
               Collections, UVA Library 2011</ref>).</p>
            <figure xml:id="manuscriptsidentifiedp12">
               <graphic url="images/Figure_03.jpg"  width="620px" height="980px"/>
            
               <head type="legend">Manuscript identified as <q>Page 12. The sores on my
                  shoulders are from his</q> in the University of Virginia Library finding aid 
                  (<ref  type="bibl" target="#guidewwhitman">Special
                  Collections, UVA Library 2011</ref>) and as <q>uva.00260</q> in the Whitman Archive’s
                  <title level="u">Integrated Catalog of Walt Whitman’s Literary Manuscripts</title> 
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#folsomNDa">EAD Project Team, UNL
                  n.d.</ref>)</head></figure>
            
             <figure xml:id="manuscriptsidentifiedp9">  
                <graphic url="images/Figure_04.jpg"  width="620px" height="980px"/>
              <head type="legend">Manuscript identified as <q>Page 9. I am a curse</q> in the
                 University of Virginia Library finding aid (<ref  type="bibl" target="#guidewwhitman">Special Collections, UVA Library 2011</ref>)
                 and as <q>uva.00256</q> in the Whitman Archive’s <title level="u">Integrated Catalog of Walt Whitman’s Literary Manuscripts</title> 
                 (<ref type="bibl" target="#folsomNDa">EAD Project Team, UNL
                    n.d.</ref>).</head></figure>
            
           
               <figure xml:id="manuscriptsidentifiedp11">
                  <graphic url="images/Figure_05.jpg" width="620px" height="980px"/>
               <head type="legend">Manuscript identified as <q>Page 11. Topple down upon him</q> in
                  the University of Virginia Library finding aid (<ref  type="bibl" target="#guidewwhitman">Special Collections, UVA Library
                  2011</ref>) and as <q>uva.00258</q> in the Whitman Archive’s <title level="u">Integrated Catalog of Walt Whitman’s Literary Manuscripts</title> 
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#folsomNDa">EAD Project Team, UNL
                     n.d.</ref>).</head>
            </figure>
            
              <figure xml:id="manuscriptsidentifiedp10"> 
                 <graphic url="images/Figure_06.jpg"  width="620px" height="980px"/>
            <head type="legend">Manuscript identified as <q>Page 10. Black Lucifer was not
               dead</q> in the University of Virginia Library finding aid (<ref  type="bibl" target="#guidewwhitman">Special Collections, UVA
                  Library 2011</ref>) and as <q>uva.00257</q> in the Whitman Archive’s 
               <title level="u">Integrated Catalog of Walt Whitman’s Literary Manuscripts</title> 
               (<ref xml:id="quoteref20" type="bibl" target="#folsomNDa">EAD Project Team, UNL
                  n.d.</ref>).</head>
              </figure>
        
            <p>Only sketchy justifications are offered for these tentative conclusions, the key one
               being that since the published version in 1855 (see <ptr target="#detailp74" type="crossref"/>) contains neither a
               version of the line <q>I look off the river with my bloodshot eyes <gap/></q> nor any
               mention of a curse, the deletion of these words on leaf 11 suggests that it
               represents <quote source="#quoteref19">a reworking of the lines beginning <title>I am a Curse</title> in the . . . notebook</quote>
               (see <ptr target="#firsttwo" type="crossref"/>) combined with <quote  source="#quoteref19">verses added from Leaf 9</quote>
               (<ref  type="bibl" target="#guidewwhitman" xml:id="quoteref19">Special Collections,
               University of Virginia Library 2011</ref>)</p>
           
            <figure xml:id="detailp74"> 
               <graphic url="images/Figure_07.jpg" width="620px" height="980px"/>
               <head type="legend">Detail of page 74 in the first edition of <title level="m">Leaves of Grass</title>
                  (<ref type="bibl" target="#whitman1855">Whitman 1855</ref>).</head>
            </figure>
            
            <figure xml:id="firsttwo">
               <graphic url="images/Figure_08.jpg" width="620px" height="980px"/>
            
             <head type="legend"> First two pages of a three-page section of notebook in
                  which Whitman drafted lines for <title level="a">The Sleepers</title>, identified as
              <q>MSS45443, Box 8: Notebook LC #80</q> by the Library of Congress in the
                  Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman (<ref type="bibl" target="#mcelderry2013">McElderry 2013</ref>)
         and as <q>loc.00141</q> in
                the Whitman Archive’s <title level="u">Integrated Catalog of Walt Whitman’s Literary Manuscripts</title> 
                (<ref type="bibl" target="#folsomNDa">EAD Project Team, UNL
                   n.d.</ref>).</head></figure>
            
            <p>These details, plus the relatively close resemblances between leaf 10 and the
               published passage, make the scenario outlined in the finding guide seem quite
               plausible. Nevertheless, other scenarios are also imaginable. In fact, the University
               of Virginia finding guide itself offers one of them: On leaf 10 <quote source="#quoteref20">the word
               <mentioned>Sleepchaser’s</mentioned> appears in the upper right corner</quote>, and this word’s similarity to the
               title <title level="a">Sleep-Chasings</title> (first used in the 1860 edition) might indicate that, instead
               of inscribing leaf 10 just after leaf 11 and just before the printed version
               appeared, Whitman wrote leaf 10 <emph>after</emph> the first printing—that
               it <quote source="#quoteref21">is in fact a reworking of the section for the 1860 edition</quote>
               (<ref  type="bibl" target="#guidewwhitman" xml:id="quoteref21">Special Collections,
               UVA Library 2011</ref>). Ordering of the other four manuscripts similarly turns out to be
               not entirely straightforward (as one might infer from the speculation that leaf 9
               came either <quote source="#quoteref21">first or second</quote>). My point here, fortunately, is not to argue for a
               particular genetic sequence but to illustrate the fact that the <soCalled>dossier</soCalled> with which
               the genetic editor must work often offers ambiguous evidence regarding the order in
               which documents were inscribed and, hence, might oblige one to offer multiple genetic
               descriptions as possibilities.</p>
            <p>Our use of the home-grown elements <gi>relations</gi> and <gi>work</gi> to connect a
               particular documentary instance (manuscript or print) to a work has proven useful,
               most notably as the enabling presence behind our <title level="u"><ref target="https://whitmanarchive.org/manuscripts/finding_aids/integrated.html">Integrated Catalog of Walt Whitman’s Literary Manuscripts</ref></title> 
               (<ref type="bibl" target="#folsomNDa">EAD Project Team, UNL
                  n.d.</ref>), a union finding guide
               generated from individual EAD-encoded finding guides for several dozen separate
                  collections.<note>See
                     <ptr target="https://whitmanarchive.org/manuscripts/finding_aids/integrated.html"/>. It is worth
                  noting, however, that the finding guide draws on the connections between instance
                  and work as recorded in EAD records rather than in TEI-encoded
                  transcriptions.</note> While it has been useful, however, our system is in no way
               adequate to the task of representing the sort of genetic details that I’ve outlined
               for the <title level="a">Sleepers</title> manuscripts. Our encoding simply declares that the document
               currently under consideration (or some division of that document) is an instance of a
               specified work. That’s all it does. Of the many things it does <emph
                  >not</emph> do, perhaps the most fundamental is that it offers no
               machine-processable way of <emph>ordering</emph> the materials—of saying
               that a particular manuscript was the first draft, another was the second, etc.—let
               alone of indicating alternative possible orderings. I sometimes shake my head at our
               lack of foresight in neglecting to design such a provision, but then I remember that
               during the nineteen years we have been using this markup the TEI community has not
               developed <emph>any</emph> consensus facility for associating, in a
               documentary transcription, all of the various instances with a given work. If the
               Whitman Archive were coming to TEI for the first time today, in late 2020, we would
               search the Guidelines in vain for advice about encoding the genetic relationships
               among the various manuscript instances of <title level="a">The Sleepers</title>.</p>
            <p>For these macro, interdocument diachronies, two basic frameworks possibly worth
               consideration are RDF and <term>directed acyclic graphs</term>. The second of these was, in
               fact, suggested as a possibility in the draft recommendations of the TEI’s Workgroup
               on Genetic Editions (<ref type="bibl" target="#burnard">Burnard et al. n.d., sec. 4: <title>The Dossier Level</title></ref>). Either
               approach, however, would require further development to specify such things as types
               of relationships, degrees of certainty, and alternative theories. No already existing
               RDF vocabulary appropriate to describing genetic textual relationships seems to
               exist; likewise, to my knowledge, nothing like a universally applicable set of values
               for the components of a directed graph has been devised.</p>
            <p>What the TEI Guidelines do have to offer for the encoding of diachronic information
               pertains to the <soCalled>micro</soCalled> level, that is, those traces of the passage of time that
               exist within the bounds of a single document. In addition to the use of the
                  <att>seq</att> attribute to specify an order among the components of
                  <gi>choice</gi>, the P5 v. 2 Guidelines introduced a means of characterizing the
               temporal relationships among a broad range of textual alterations via
                  <gi>listChange</gi>, whose <gi>change</gi> children can be cross-referenced via
                  the <att>change</att> attributes of the various elements used to mark up
               blocks of text in the transcription proper. This method (though, importantly, not the
                  <gi>change</gi> element itself) was developed for the encoding of <soCalled>revision
               campaigns</soCalled> (i.e., the inferred rounds/sessions during which specific portions of a
               single document were inscribed), and the Guidelines discuss the markup of revision
               campaigns as the primary use of this set of elements and attributes. Of the four
               authors whose manuscripts formed the corpus under consideration in the Diachronic
               Markup project (Whitman, Goethe, Virginia Woolf, and James Joyce), Goethe’s writing
               processes most easily lend themselves to such an approach. Whitman’s individual
               manuscript documents rarely exhibit traces of having been inscribed in more than one
               writing session. That is, there are usually no changes of hand or medium to suggest
               that he made an initial inscription, paused, and then came back at a significantly
               later time or in a distinctly different <soCalled>fit</soCalled> to make changes. Unlike some other
               authors, he had no consistent habit of using, say, ink during an initial drafting
               phase and pencil during a proofreading one, nor did he employ scribes, as Goethe, for
               example, sometimes did. The lack of such typical kinds of evidence for <soCalled>revision
               campaigns</soCalled> <emph>per se,</emph> however, does not mean that the diachronic
               dimension is utterly imperceptible within Whitman’s manuscripts, only that the time
               frame is collapsed. The manuscripts are very frequently a tangle of writing and
               revision, and therefore pose significant challenges to understanding the processes by
               which they came into being. On occasion, I have spent hours examining a single
               manuscript image, slowly developing a theory of how the page was incrementally
                  inscribed.<note>Hans Walter Gabler has provocatively analyzed this process of
                  <quote source="#quoteref22">ascertaining the order in which the manuscript pages were filled</quote> as essentially
                     iterative, moving <quote  source="#quoteref22">loop by loop, from document to text in ever finer steps of
                  granularity</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref22" type="bibl" target="#gabler2007">2007, 201</ref>).</note> 
               Editors who want to record conclusions and/or
               posit conjectures about such processes might well wish to encode a sequential
               ordering of the parts of an inscription <emph>within</emph> a single
               <soCalled>revision campaign</soCalled>. Although it is <emph>possible</emph> to use
                  <gi>listChange</gi> and other elements to encode such time-dependent
               relationships, the Guidelines, as currently written, offer no clear direction for how
               this should be done.</p>
            <p>To illustrate some of the gaps that could be filled in future versions of the
               Guidelines, as well as some of the potential hermeneutical value of creating such
               encodings, I hereby offer my own modest experiment in employing <gi>listChange</gi>
               to encode hypotheses regarding <q>how the page was filled</q> for a single example
               manuscript, the one shown in <ptr target="#manuscriptsidentifiedp9" type="crossref"/>, above. 
               The following snippet shows part of the
                  <gi>listChange</gi> section of the <gi>teiHeader</gi>, which asserts the order in
               which I believe Whitman carried out the actions that produced what is now visible as
               the first line of the manuscript:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
               <listChange>
                  <change xml:id="ch01">
                     <desc>writes "I am blac"</desc>
                  </change>
                  <change xml:id="ch02">
                     <desc>overstrikes "blac"</desc>
                  </change>
                  <change xml:id="ch03">
                     <desc>writes "a curse:"</desc>
                  </change>
                  <!-- ... -->
                  <change xml:id="ch07">
                     <desc>writes "a black slave spoke me"</desc>
                  </change>
                  <!-- ... -->
                  <change xml:id="ch09">
                     <desc>overstrikes "black slave" and writes
                        "negro"</desc>
                  </change>
                  <change xml:id="ch10">
                     <desc>overstrikes "spoke" and writes "felt"</desc>
                  </change>
                  <change xml:id="ch11">
                     <desc>overstrikes "felt" and writes "thought"</desc>
                  </change>
                  <change xml:id="ch12">
                     <desc>overstrikes "thought" and writes "thinks"</desc>
                  </change>
               </listChange>
               
            </egXML>
            <p>To create this section, I populated <gi>listChange</gi> with the series of steps (one
               per <gi>change</gi>) that I believe Whitman took in inscribing the
                  manuscript.<note>It is important to acknowledge that, although populating
                     <gi>listChange</gi> might be <soCalled>simple</soCalled>, decisions about what constitutes a
                  discrete <soCalled>step</soCalled> are never simple. For example, in the case of a substitution,
                  should each deletion and each addition be a separate step or should the two be
                  grouped as a single <gi>change</gi>? For my purposes, I chose the latter approach.
                  It should also be noted that, in the encoding of the transcription, I chose to
                  forego <gi>subst</gi> altogether, since substitutions are already implied by the
                  corresponding <att>change</att> values on the <gi>del</gi> and <gi>add</gi>
                  elements.</note> For each <gi>change</gi> element I then added a <gi>desc</gi>
               containing human-readable prose, so that, taken together, these constitute a version
               of what John Bryant has called a <quote source="#quoteref23">revision narrative</quote> 
               (<ref xml:id="quoteref23" type="bibl" target="#bryant2002">2002, esp. 167–71</ref>).<!--<note>See
                  especially pp. 167–71.</note>--> Although I was not able to look to the TEI
               Guidelines for a model of how to create this narrative, I found it relatively easy,
               by extrapolation, to arrive at a workable and perhaps even adequate approach for this
               part of the encoding task. The following snippet from the body of the transcription
               shows my attempt to make this sequence machine-readable, via references in <att>change</att> to
               the <att>xml:id</att> of the relevant <gi>change</gi> in <gi> listChange</gi>:</p>
           <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <seg change="#ch01">I am
                 <del rend="overstrike" change="#ch02">black</del>
              </seg>
              <seg change="#ch03">a curse:</seg>
              <seg change="#ch07">a
                 <del rend="overstrike" change="#ch09">black slave</del>
                 <add rend="unmarked" place="above" change="#ch09">negro
                 </add>
                 <del rend="overstrike" change="#ch10"> spoke</del>
                 <del rend="overstrike" change="#ch11">
                    <add rend="unmarked" place="above" change="#ch10">felt
                    </add>
                 </del>
                 <del rend="overstrike" change="#ch12">
                    <add rend="unmarked" place="above" change="#ch11">
                       thought</add>
                 </del>
                 <add rend="unmarked" place="above" change="#ch12">
                    thinks</add>
                 me</seg>
              </egXML>
            <p>I felt (and feel) less satisfied with this part of the encoding. While it wasn’t
               difficult to describe a step-by-step order of inscription, the nesting of <gi>seg</gi>
               and <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi> elements in the transcription caused me anxiety. The
               change associated with <tag>xml:id="7"</tag>, which I describe as <q>writes <q>a black slave spoke
               me</q></q>, offers an example of my difficulty in translating the bits of my narrative
               description into unambiguous encoding. In the transcription excerpted above, the
               phrase is indicated as a <att>seg</att>, interrupted by elements embedded at various
               levels and conceived as the contents of the <att>seg</att> <emph>minus</emph>
               the child <gi>add</gi> elements. Child <gi>del</gi> elements, however, 
               <emph>are</emph> to be considered part of this change, <emph
                  >except</emph> when their contents are further marked as an addition. I am uncertain
               whether this logic is scalable to a larger set of Whitman documents, let alone to
               documents created by others.</p>
            <p>More immediately, however, I was uncertain whether the logic 
               actually <emph>was</emph> machine-readable, that is, whether it was both consistent
               and complete enough to allow some sort of algorithmic translation. Specifically, I
               hoped that two of my colleagues at the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities,
               Brian Pytlik Zillig and Jessica Dussault, could make use of the temporal information
               in my encoding to produce a meaningful display of the manuscript text. The grant
               period was very nearly at an end, so my expectations were modest, but in the few days
               that remained they did, in fact, create a JavaScript program that successfully uses
               the code to represent, albeit imperfectly, the temporal sequence of inscription via
               animation.</p>
         
              <figure xml:id="video">
                 <graphic url="images/Figure_09.gif" height="400px" width="651px"/>
                 <head type="legend">Brett Barney, Brian Pytlik Zillig, and Jessica Dussault. Temporal animation of Whitman’s manuscript changes (written in javascript). To view the animation select the original link below.</head>
              </figure>
            
            <p>Astute readers will quickly recognize that this animation doesn’t get everything
               right, and I remain uncertain how much of the work to perfect it might depend on
               changes to the encoding and how much on further development of the
                  script.<note>Dussault and I have only recently resumed conversations about this
                  and have begun exploring other, non-JavaScript alternatives for processing the
                  TEI. As we are both doing this work in our <soCalled>free time</soCalled>, however, progress is slow.
                  We would, of course, welcome suggestions or other constructive input.</note>
               However, when I consider it as purely a proof of concept, I find this to be a
               surprisingly powerful and satisfying rendering, one that suggests how an editor’s
               assertions about the time-dependent sequence of inscription within a document might
               be brought to life with an immediacy that no amount of <term>apparatus
                  criticus</term> prose could.<note>I was, in part, inspired by work done by Elena
                  Pierazzo and a group of collaborators to produce a prototype interactive rendering
                  of pages from one of Marcel Proust’s notebooks. By encoding <gi>zone</gi>s and
                     assigning to them a relative order, the project team was able to <quote source="#quoteref24">create an
                  interactive, accessible interface</quote> 
                     (<ref type="bibl" target="#pierazzo2014b" xml:id="quoteref24">2014b, 18</ref>). Unfortunately, their prototype
                  appears to be no longer available. Attempts to visualize the development of a text
                  across documents have been more common, though they face their own significant
                  challenges, of course. Such projects as <title level="m"
                     >Faustedition</title> (<ptr target="http://www.faustedition.net/"/>), the <title level="m">Samuel Beckett Digital
                        Manuscript Project</title> (<ptr target="https://www.beckettarchive.org/"/>), and <title level="m"
                     >Ulysses: A Digital Critical and Synoptic Edition</title>
                     (<ptr target="http://ulysses.online/index.html"/>) have produced various forms of visualization
                  (including, in the case of the Beckett Project, animation) that might serve as
                  inspiration for future work.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I believe that work remains to more fully implement the aspirations and
               recommendations of the Workgroup on Genetic Editions, especially with regard to
               diachronic markup, and I will continue to advocate for further development of the TEI
                  specification.<note>In making my case for further development I am mindful of
                  James Cummings’s sage discussion of common <quote source="#quoteref25">myths, misconceptions, and
                     misunderstandings</quote> about TEI, wherein he addresses <quote source="#quoteref25">the criticism often levelled
                        at the TEI</quote> of being <quote source="#quoteref25">too simple or too general.</quote> He rightly points out that such
                     complaints are often born of a <quote source="#quoteref25">superficial understanding of the scope of the TEI</quote>
                     or a lack of understanding of <quote source="#quoteref25">the way in which any individual element can be
                  further refined by using attributes or nested levels of encoding.</quote> Diachronic
                     markup, however, is not such a case but, rather, an example of a <quote source="#quoteref25">real instance<supplied></supplied></quote>
                     in which the TEI <quote source="#quoteref25">provides only a general level of markup for some phenomena</quote>
                     because <quote source="#quoteref25">the TEI community has not pushed the standard forward yet to greater
                  detail in this area</quote> (<ref target="#cummings" type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref25">2019, i58, i61–i62</ref>). What I am calling for, then, is a
                  harder collective push.</note> Future versions of the Guidelines should provide
               direction for representing macro-level temporal relationships among documents and
               allow for alternate orderings and indications of levels of certainty, perhaps by
               leveraging the possibilities of the <gi>standOff</gi> element, which was introduced
               in the February 2020 release of P5 v. 4.0.0. With regard to markup for micro-level
               diachronic information, I see an even easier—perhaps even
               non-controversial—opportunity for the Council to elaborate the Guidelines’ prose to
               show how this can be achieved within the existing scheme. By articulating
               recommendations and providing encoding examples, TEI could better fulfill an
               important part of its stated mission to <quote source="#quoteref26">facilitat<supplied>e</supplied> the loss-free interchange of
               data</quote> (<ref type="bibl" target="#TEI2020" xml:id="quoteref26">TEI Consortium 2020</ref>).</p>

      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bellemin2004"><author>Bellemin-Noël, Jean</author>. <date>2004</date>. <title level="a"
                     >Psychoanalytic Reading and the Avant-texte</title>. In <title level="m"
                     >Genetic Criticism: Texts and Avant-textes</title>, edited by <editor>Jed Deppman</editor>,
                  <editor>Daniel Ferrer</editor>, and <editor>Michael Groden</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">28–35</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bodard2020"><author>Bodard, Gabriel</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">Diplomatic
                  Transcriptions</title>. In <title level="m">EpiDoc Guidelines: Ancient
                     Documents in TEI XML</title>, edited by <editor>Tom Elliott</editor>, <editor>Gabriel Bodard</editor>, <editor>Elli Mylonas</editor>, <editor>Simona Stoyanova</editor>, <editor>Charlotte Tupman</editor>, <editor>Scott Vanderbilt</editor>, et al. <edition>Version 9.2</edition>.
                  Accessed February 19, 2021.
                  <ptr target="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/trans-diplomatic.html"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bohnenkamp2012">
                  <author>Bohnenkamp-Renken, Anne</author>, and <author>Malte Rehbein</author>. <date>2012</date>.
                     <title level="u">Diachronic Markup and Presentation Practices for Text
                        Editions in Digital Environments</title>. Unpublished grant proposal, September
                  26. PDF file.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bruning2013"><author>Brüning, Gerrit</author>, <author>Katrin Henzel</author>, and <author>Dietmar Pravida</author>. <date>2013</date>.
                     <title level="a">Multiple Encoding in Genetic Editions: The Case of
                     <title level="m">Faust</title></title>.
                  <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title> <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>.
                  <ptr target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/697"/>; doi:<idno type="doi">10.4000/jtei.697</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="bryant2002"><author>Bryant, John</author>. <date>2002</date>. <title level="m">The Fluid Text: A
                     Theory of Revision and Editing for Book and Screen</title>. <pubPlace>Ann Arbor</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>University of Michigan Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="burnard"><author>Burnard, Lou</author>, <author>Fotis Jannidis</author>, <author>Elena Pierazzo</author>, and <author>Malte
                  Rehbein</author>. <date>n.d.</date> <title level="a">An Encoding Model for Genetic Editions.</title>
                  Revised draft. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>: <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>. Workgroup on Genetic Editions (TEI MS SIG).
                  Accessed February 19, 2021. <ptr target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/TC/tcw19.html"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="buzzoni"><author>Buzzoni, Marina</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">A Protocol for
                     Scholarly Digital Editions? The Italian Point of View.</title> In <title
                     level="m">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and Practices</title>, edited
                  by <editor>Matthew James Driscoll</editor> and <editor>Elena Pierazzo</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">59–82</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Open Book Publishers</publisher>. doi:<idno type="doi">10.11647/OBP.0095</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="cummings"><author>Cummings, James</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title level="a">A World of
                     Difference: Myths and Misconceptions about the TEI.</title>
                  <title level="j">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> <biblScope unit="issue">34</biblScope> (supplement
                  1): <biblScope unit="page">i58–i79</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi">10.1093/llc/fqy071</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="deppman"><author>Deppman, Jed</author>, <author>Daniel Ferrer</author>, and <author>Michael Groden</author>. <date>2004</date>. <title
                     level="a">Introduction: A Genesis of French Genetic Criticism.</title> In
                     <title level="m">Genetic Criticism: Texts and Avante-Textes</title>, <biblScope unit="page">1–16</biblScope>.
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="folsom1986"><author>Folsom, Ed</author>. <date>1986</date>. <title level="a">Introduction: <q>This
                     Heart’s Geography’s Map</q>: The Photographs of Walt Whitman.</title> In <title
                     level="m">Whitman Photographs,</title> special double issue, <title
                     level="j">Walt Whitman Quarterly Review</title> <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope> (2–3, Fall): <biblScope unit="page">1–5</biblScope>.
                  doi:<idno type="doi">10.13008/2153-3695.1138</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="folsomNDa"><author>Folsom, Ed</author>, and <author>Kenneth M. Price</author>. <date>n.d.</date> <title level="u"
                     >Integrated Catalog of Walt Whitman’s Literary Manuscripts</title>. <orgName>Walt
                  Whitman Archive</orgName>, edited by <editor>Matt Cohen</editor>, <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>, and <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>. Accessed February 19,
                  2021. <ptr target="https://whitmanarchive.org/manuscripts/finding_aids/integrated.html"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="folsomNDb"><author>Folsom, Ed</author>, and <author>Kenneth M. Price</author>. <date>n.d.</date> <title level="u"
                     >Walt Whitman.</title> <orgName>Walt Whitman Archive</orgName>.
                  <ptr target="https://whitmanarchive.org/biography/walt_whitman/index.html"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="gabler2007"><author>Gabler, Hans Walter</author>. <date>2007</date>. <title level="a">The Primacy
                  of the Document in Editing</title>.
                  <title level="j">Ecdotica</title> <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">197–207</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="gabler2018"><author>Gabler, Hans Walter</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">The Draft
                     Manuscript as Material Foundation for Genetic Editing and Genetic
                     Criticism</title>. In <title level="m">Text Genetics in Literary Modernism
                     and Other Essays</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Open Book Publishers</publisher>, <biblScope unit="page">209–19</biblScope>.
                  doi:<idno type="doi">10.11647/OBP.0120</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="hay2017"><author>Hay, Louis</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">Genetic Criticism:
                     Another Approach to Writing?</title> <biblScope unit="chapter">Chap. 29</biblScope> in <title level="m">Research on
                     Writing: Multiple Perspectives</title>, edited by <editor>Sylvie Plane</editor>, <editor>Charles Bazerman</editor>, <editor>Fabienne Rondelli</editor>, <editor>Christiane Donahue</editor>, <editor>Arthur N. Applebee</editor>, <editor>Catherine Boré</editor>, <editor>Paula Carlino</editor>, <editor>Martine Marquilló Larruy</editor>, <editor>Paul Rogers</editor>, and <editor>David Russell</editor>,
                  <biblScope unit="page">531–47</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Fort Collins, CO</pubPlace>: <publisher>The WAC Clearinghouse</publisher>.
                  doi:<idno type="doi">10.37514/INT-B.2017.0919.2.29</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="klineND"><author>Kline, Mary-Jo</author>, and <author>Susan Holbrook Perdue</author>. <date>n.d.</date> <title
                     level="a">Introduction: What Is Documentary Editing? Where Did It Come
                     From?</title> In <title level="m">A Guide to Documentary Editing</title>. <edition>3rd
                  ed</edition>. Online edition. <pubPlace>Charlottesville</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Virginia Press</publisher>. Accessed
                 26 February 2021. <ptr target="https://gde.upress.virginia.edu/01A-gde.html"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="mcelderry2013"><author>McElderry, Michael</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="m">Thomas
                     Biggs Harned Collection of Walt Whitman Papers, 1842–1937. A Finding Aid to the
                     Collection in the Library of Congress.</title> Last updated February 2017.
                  Washington, D.C.: Manuscript Division, Library of Congress.
                  <ptr target="https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/eadmss.ms002007"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pierazzo2009"><author>Pierazzo, Elena</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">Digital Genetic
                     Editions: The Encoding of Time in Manuscript Transcription.</title> <biblScope unit="chapter">Chap. 11</biblScope> in
                     <title level="m">Text Editing, Print and the Digital World</title>, edited by
                  <editor>Marilyn Deegan</editor> and <editor>Kathryn Sutherland</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">169–86</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Farnham, England</pubPlace>: <publisher>Ashgate</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pierazzo2014a"><author>Pierazzo, Elena</author>. <date>2014</date>a. <title level="a">Digital
                     Documentary Editions and the Others.</title>
                  <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for
                     Documentary Editing</title> <biblScope unit="issue">35</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">1–23</biblScope>.
                  <ptr target="http://www.scholarlyediting.org/2014/essays/essay.pierazzo.html"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pierazzo2014b"><author>Pierazzo, Elena</author>. <date>2014</date>b. <title level="a">Of Time and
                     Space: Unpacking the Draft Page: A New Framework for Digital Editions of Draft
                     Manuscripts.</title>
                  <ptr target="https://hal.univ-grenoble-alpes.fr/hal-01182133"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pierazzo2015"><author>Pierazzo, Elena</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title level="m">Digital
                     Scholarly Editing: Theories, Models and Methods</title>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace> and <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>Routledge</publisher>. Preprint available at <ptr
                     target="https://hal.univ-grenoble-alpes.fr/hal-01182162"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="pierazzo2016"><author>Pierazzo, Elena</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">Modelling
                     Digital Scholarly Editing: From Plato to Heraclitus.</title> <biblScope unit="chapter">Chap. 2</biblScope> in <title
                     level="m">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and Practices</title>, edited
                  by <editor>Matthew James Driscoll</editor> and <editor>Elena Pierazzo</editor>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Open Book Publishers</publisher>,
                  <biblScope unit="page">41–58</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi">10.11647/OBP.0095</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="schauble2018"><author>Schäuble, Joshua</author>, with <author>Hans Walter Gabler</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title
                     level="a">Encodings and Visualisations of Text Processes across Document
                     Borders.</title> In <title level="m">Digital Scholarly Digital Editions as
                     Interfaces</title>, edited by <editor>Roman Bleier</editor>, <editor>Martina Bürgermeister</editor>, <editor>Helmut W. Klug</editor>, <editor>Frederike Neuber</editor>, and <editor>Gerlinde Schneider</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">165–91</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Norderstedt</pubPlace>: <publisher>BoD</publisher>.
                  <ptr target="https://kups.ub.uni-koeln.de/9116/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="shillingsburg1996">
                  <author>Shillingsburg, Peter L.</author> <date>1996</date>. <title level="m"
                     >Scholarly Editing in the Computer Age: Theory and Practice.</title> <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <pubPlace>Ann
                  Arbor</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Michigan Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="sperbergmcqueen1994"><author>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</author>, and <author>Lou Burnard</author>. <date>1994</date>.
                     <title level="m">TEI P3: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                     Interchange</title>. <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>; <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Text Encoding Initiative</publisher>. Available at
                  <ptr target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/GL/teip3doc.tar.gz"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="TEI2002"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2002</date>. <title level="m">TEI P4: Guidelines
                     for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange: XML-compatible Edition</title>,
                  edited by <editor>C. M. Sperberg-McQueen</editor> and <editor>Lou Burnard</editor>. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>: <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P4/doc/html/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="TEI2007"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2007</date>. TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text
                  Encoding and Interchange. <edition>Version 1.0.0</edition>. Last updated October 28.
                  <ptr target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/1.0.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="TEI2011"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2011</date>. <title level="u">P5 Version 2.0
                     Release Notes.</title> <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>: <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>.
                  <ptr target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/2.0.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/release/tei-p5-doc/share/doc/tei-p5-doc/readme-2.0.html"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="TEI2020"><author>TEI Consortium</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">Representation of
                     Primary Sources.</title> <biblScope unit="chapter">Chap. 11</biblScope> in <title level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text
                  Encoding and Interchange</title>. <edition>Version 4.1.0</edition>. Last updated August 19. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>: <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>.
                  <ptr target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/PH.html"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="guidewwhitman"><orgName>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library</orgName>.
                  <date>2011</date>. <title level="u">A Guide to the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1838–1987: A
                     Collection in the Clifton Waller Barrett Library, Special Collections, The
                     University of Virginia Library.</title> <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>: <publisher>Rector and Visitors of the
                  University of Virginia</publisher>. Accessed February 19,
                  2021. <ptr target="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=uva-sc/viu03978.xml"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="vanhulle2016"><author>Van Hulle, Dirk</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">Modelling a
                     Digital Scholarly Edition for Genetic Criticism: A Rapprochement.</title>
                  <title level="j">Variants</title> <biblScope unit="issue">12–13</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">34–56</biblScope>.
                  <ptr target="http://journals.openedition.org/variants/293"/>; doi:<idno type="doi">10.4000/variants.293</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="whitman1855"><author>Whitman, Walt</author>. <date>1855</date>. <title level="m">Leaves of
                     Grass.</title> <pubPlace>Brooklyn, NY</pubPlace>: <publisher>N.p.</publisher> Whitman Archive ID <idno>ppp.00271</idno>. Available at
                  <ptr target="https://whitmanarchive.org/published/LG/1855/whole.html"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="whitman1892"><author>Whitman, Walt</author>. <date>1892</date>. <title level="m">Complete Prose
                     Works.</title> <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>: <publisher>David McKay</publisher>. Whitman Archive ID <idno>ppp.00504</idno>.
                  Available at <ptr target="https://whitmanarchive.org/published/other/CompleteProse.html"/>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
