<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" <?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_software_annotation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">TEICORPO: A Conversion Tool for Spoken Language Transcription with a
          Pivot File in TEI</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Christophe</forename>
            <surname>Parisse</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>INSERM, Modyco-CNRS-Nanterre University, France</affiliation>
          <email>cparisse@parisnanterre.fr</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Carole</forename>
            <surname>Etienne</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>ICAR-CNRS, Lyon, France</affiliation>
          <email>carole.etienne@ens.lyon.fr</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Loïc</forename>
            <surname>Liégeois</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>University of Paris, France</affiliation>
          <email>loic.liegeois@univ.paris-diderot.fr</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>02/07/2021</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Susan Schreibman</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="13">Selected Papers from the 2018 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals
          in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish
          full-text articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>TEI</term>
          <term>transcription</term>
          <term>oral corpora</term>
          <term>conversion</term>
          <term>annotationBlock</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="Pietro Liuzzo" when="2021-05-07">Encoded from revised doc converted with
        Pandoc.</change>
      <change who="Pietro Liuzzo" when="2021-07-02">Re-encoded from revised doc converted with
        Pandoc (docx completed 28.6.2021).</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>CORLI is a consortium of Huma-Num, the French national infrastructure dedicated to the
          technical support and promotion of digital humanities. The goal of CORLI is to promote and
          provide tools and information for good and efficient research practices in corpus
          linguistics, especially on spoken language corpora. Because of the time required to
          collect and transcribe spoken language resources, their number is limited and thus corpora
          need to be interoperable and reusable in order to improve research on themes such as
          phonology, prosody, interaction, syntax, and textometry. To help researchers reach this
          goal, CORLI has designed a pair of tools: <ptr type="software" xml:id="R1" target="#teicorpo"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R1">TEICORPO</rs> to assist in the conversion and use of
          spoken language corpora, and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R2" target="#teimeta"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R2">TEIMETA</rs> for metadata purposes. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R3" target="#teicorpo"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R3">TEICORPO</rs> is based on the
          principle of an underlying common format, namely TEI XML as described in its specification
          for spoken language use (ISO 2016). This tool enables the conversion of transcriptions
          created with alignment software such as <ptr type="software" xml:id="R4" target="#clan"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R4">CLAN</rs>, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R5" target="#transcriber"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R5">Transcriber</rs>, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R6" target="#praat"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R6">Praat</rs>, or <ptr type="software"
            xml:id="R7" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R7">ELAN</rs> as well as
          common file formats (CSV, XLSX, TXT, or DOCX) and the TEI format, which plays the role of
          a lossless pivot format. Backward conversion is possible in many cases, with limitations
          inherent in the destination target format. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R8" target="#teicorpo"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R8">TEICORPO</rs> can run the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R9" target="treetager"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R9">Treetagger</rs> part-of-speech
          tagger and the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R10" target="stanfordcorenlp"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R10">Stanford CoreNLP</rs> tools on TEI files and can export the resulting files to
          textometric tools such as <ptr type="software" xml:id="R11" target="#txm"/><rs
            type="soft.name" ref="#R11">TXM</rs>, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R12" target="#letrameur"/><rs
              type="soft.name" ref="#R12">Le Trameur</rs>, or <ptr type="software" xml:id="R13" target="#iramuteq"/><rs
                type="soft.name" ref="#R13">Iramuteq</rs>, making it suitable for
          spoken language corpora editing as well as for various research purposes.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="corli">
        <head>The CORLI Consortium and Corpus Linguistic Research</head>
        <p>The CORLI consortium is a network of researchers and laboratories engaged in corpus
          linguistic research. CORLI (<ptr target="https://corli.huma-num.fr/en"/>) is one of the
          consortia of Huma-Num, a large French infrastructure dedicated to the digital humanities
            (<ptr target="https://www.huma-num.fr/"/>). CORLI aims to promote and assist research in
          corpus linguistics and is based on a network of researchers and engineers working in this
          field. The general policy of the consortium is to build on existing practices, research
          tools, and material from members of the consortium, and to improve them to match the needs
          of all the people and laboratories interested in corpus linguistics. The main activities
          of the consortium are helping corpus providers to produce open science and shareable data,
          providing continuous education for advanced students as well as senior researchers, and
          sharing good practices about data and tools. CORLI is now an official CLARIN K Centre
            (<ptr target="https://corli.huma-num.fr/en/kcentre"/>).</p>
        <div xml:id="datasharing">
          <head>The Importance of Data Sharing</head>
          <p>Data sharing is an absolute necessity for research and applications in spoken language,
            for two main reasons. First, creating spoken language corpora is very expensive. As a
            result, not only are existing data very frequently reused, but it is also often
            necessary to mix data coming from different origins when the goal is to produce very
            large datasets. Second, language production involves a very wide variety of speakers and
            contexts. Hence, in order to create interesting sociolinguistic data, it is very often
            efficient to mix corpora from different sources. Moreover, the development of open
            science, which is a key component of research today, cannot exist without data sharing,
            which allows the data sources behind scientific results to be checked.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="specificity">
          <head>Specificity of Spoken Language Data</head>
          <p>Spoken language corpora are different from corpora of written text. They consist of
            sound or video recordings that come with textual information—transcriptions and
            annotations. The spoken language is organized according to two dimensions, as described
            by Schmidt (<ref type="bibl" target="#schmidt2011">2011</ref>): the macrostructure,
            which refers to how transcriptions, annotations, and linking are organized (where they
            are in the file), and the microstructure, which refers to the details of how
            transcriptions and annotations are represented (how a transcription or an annotation is
            written down).</p>
          <p>Because linking the linguistic information (transcription and annotation) to audio or
            video data is not a straightforward process and because this information is crucial for
            studying spoken language, specific tools are used for creating and editing spoken
            language data. These tools provide the user with functionalities that are necessary for
            creating spoken language corpora and they also save data in controlled formats that can
            be used for data sharing. Unfortunately, although all these tools manage the
            macrostructure of spoken language corpora in a very strict fashion, this is not the case
            for the microstructure. Certain tools provide some microstructure information, but it is
            usually limited and not available for all corpora or for all types of research.</p>
          <p>There are two main reasons for these limitations. First, there is a wide variety of
            different microstructures that can be used, depending on the scientific goal and the
            research domain that call for corpus creation and use. The second is that controlling
            the microstructure when creating the data is extremely time-consuming, with the result
            that the microstructure is often restricted to the minimal requirements of the study.
            Moreover, the creation of user-friendly tools for controlling microstructures requires
            considerable programmer effort, which the creators of free tools for research into
            spoken language seldom have available. So the burden of controlling the quality of the
            microstructure most often falls on the shoulders of the corpus creator, and not on the
            tool used to create the corpus. Stability and uniformity in microstructure corpora is
            only found in repositories that follow clear and controlled instructions—for example,
            the TalkBank system (<ref type="bibl" target="#macwhinney2007">MacWhinney 2007</ref>,
              <ptr target="https://talkbank.org/"/>) and the Archiv für Gesprochenes Deutsch (<ptr
              target="http://agd.ids-mannheim.de"/>)—or in specific corpus projects, which have
            limited coverage, even if the corpora involved are very large.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="teicorpo">
          <head>The <ptr type="software" xml:id="R14" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R14">TEICORPO</rs> Approach</head>
          <p>The goal of the CORLI consortium is to make it easier to deposit, share, and reuse
            data. With this goal in mind, CORLI has always promoted the use of open public
            repositories and open formats. Our policy is to advocate for the use of a common single
            format which can support data sharing as well as long-term preservation. We encourage
            its use from the starting point of each new research project so as to ensure the
            development of open science. However, CORLI, as a consortium of linguists who share its
            practices, acknowledges that the most important thing for researchers remains the tools
            that they know and use. We know that few people will be working directly on the raw
            files, but rather using the tools that they have been trained with. So it is up to the
            tools to allow format and data sharing.</p>
          <p>For this reason, it was important for CORLI not only to stress the quality of a common
            data format, but also to make it possible to use this format with the tools that the
            researchers know and regularly use. These include editing tools, which make it possible
            to create and modify the corpus transcription, and exploration tools, which are
            necessary in many cases to produce scientific results. The exploration tools can be the
            same as the editing tools, but they can also include other types, such as textometric
            tools (<ref type="bibl" target="#lebart1998">Lebart, Salem, and Berry 1997</ref>; <ref
              type="bibl" target="#pincemin2011">Pincemin 2011</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
              target="#pincemin2020">Pincemin, Heiden; and Decorde 2020</ref>) and grammatical
            parsers.</p>
          <p>Finally, another constraint in the work of CORLI was to create tools that were suitable
            for the needs of linguists. This means that the goal of the project was not to create
            and promote new standards, but rather to emphasize the good practices of CORLI’s members
            and make data sharing with other researchers easier. The goal of the TEICORPO project
            can thus be summarized as:</p>
          <list>
            <item>creating a tool for conversion between the different pieces of software used for
              spoken language corpora creation and editing. The tool should be as lossless as
              possible;</item>
            <item>using TEI as a conversion pivot format, since it is already widely used,
              especially for written linguistic corpora, and is powerful enough for our
              purposes;</item>
            <item>creating complementary conversion tools that make it easier to explore and use the
              corpora for research.</item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="similarities">
          <head>Similarities with and Differences from Other Approaches</head>
          <p>Many software packages dedicated to editing spoken language transcription contain
            utilities that can convert many formats: for example, <ptr type="software"
              xml:id="15" target="#exmaralda"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R15"
                >EXMARaLDA</rs> (<rs type="Bib.Ref" target="#R15"><ref type="bibl" target="#schmidt2004">Schmidt 2004</ref>
                </rs>; see <rs type="URL" target="#R15"><ptr
                  target="https://exmaralda.org"/></rs>), <ptr type="software"
                    xml:id="16" target="#anvil"/> <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R16">Anvil</rs> (<rs type="Bib.Ref" target="#R16">
                      <ref type="bibl" target="#kipp2001">Kipp
                        2001</ref></rs>; see <rs type="URL" target="#R16"><ptr target="https://www.anvil-software.org"/></rs>), and <ptr
              type="software" xml:id="17" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#17"
                >ELAN</rs> (<rs type="bib.ref" target="#R17"><ref type="bibl" target="#wittenburg2006">Wittenburg et al. 2006</ref></rs>;
            see <rs type="URL" target="#R17"> <ptr target="https://archive.mpi.nl/tla/elan"/></rs>). However, in all cases, the
            conversions are limited to the features implemented in the tool itself—for example, with
            a limited set of metadata—and they cannot always be used to prepare data to be used by
            another tool.</ptr>
          <p>While our work is similar to that of Schmidt (<ref type="bibl" target="#schmidt2011"
              >2011</ref>), several differences make our approaches complementary. First, the two
            main common features are as follows:</p>
          <list>
            <item>the tool can automatically convert data coming from different linguistic
              tools;</item>
            <item>TEI is used as a destination format.</item>
          </list>
          <p>The list of tools that are considered in the two projects is nearly the same. The only
            tools missing in the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R18" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R18">TEICORPO</rs> approach are <ptr type="software" xml:id="19"
              target="#exmaralda"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R19">EXMARaLDA</rs> and 
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R19" target="#folker"/>FOLKER
                (<rs type="bib.ref" target="#R19"><ref type="bibl" target="#schmidts2010">Schmidt and 
                  Schütte 2010</ref></rs>; see <rs type="URL" target="#R19"><ptr
              target="https://exmaralda.org/en/folker-en/"/></rs>), but this was only because the
            conversion tools from and to <ptr type="software" xml:id="R20" target="#EXMARaLDA"
              /><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R20">EXMARaLDA</rs>, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R21" target="#folker"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R21">FOLKER</rs>, and TEI already exist.
            They are available as <ptr type="software" xml:id="R22" target="#XSLT"/><rs
              type="soft.name" ref="#R22">XSLT</rs> stylesheets in the open-source distribution of
              <ptr type="software" xml:id="R23" target="#exmaralda"/><rs type="soft.name"
              ref="#R23">EXMARaLDA</rs> (<rs type="url" ref="#R23"><ptr
                target="https://github.com/Exmaralda-Org/exmaralda"/></rs>). The other common point is the
            use of the TEI format, and especially the more recent ISO version of TEI for spoken
            language (ISO/TEI; see <ref type="bibl" target="#iso2016">ISO 2016</ref>). The TEI
            format produced by the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R24" target="#EXMARaLDA"/><rs
              type="soft.name" ref="#R24">EXMARaLDA</rs> and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R25" target="#folker"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R25">FOLKER</rs> software fit within the
            process chain of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R26" target="#teicorpo"/><rs type="soft.name" target="#R26">
              TEICORPO</rs>. This demonstrates the usefulness of a well-known and
            efficient format such as TEI.</ptr>
          <p>There are, however, differences between the two projects that make them nonredundant
            but complementary, each project having specificities that can be useful or damaging
            depending on the user’s needs. One minor difference is that the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R27" ref="teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" target="#R27">TEICORPO</rs> project is not
            a functionality of an editing tool, but is a standalone tool for converting data between
            one format and another. This had certain effects on the user interface and explains some
            of the choices made in the development of the two tools.</p>
            <p>There are two major differences between <ptr type="software" xml:id="R28" target="#teicorpo"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" target="#R28">TEICORPO</rs> and Schmidt’s approach, which affected
            both the design of the tools and how they can be used. The first difference is that in
            developing <ptr type="software" xml:id="R29" ref="teicorpo"/><rs type="soft.name" target="#R29">TEICORPO</rs>,
              it was decided that the conversion between the original formats and
            TEI had to be lossless (or as lossless as possible) because we wanted to offer a means
            to store the research data for long-term conservation and dissemination in a standard
            XML format instead of in proprietary formats such as those used by <ptr type="software" xml:id="R30" target="#clan"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R30">CLAN</rs> (<rs type="bib.soft" ref="#R30"><ref
              type="bibl" target="#macwhinney200">MacWhinney 2000</ref></rst>; see <rs type="url" ref="#R30"><ptr
                target="http://dali.talkbank.org/clan/"/></rs>), <ptr type="software" xml:id="R31"
                  target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R31">ELAN</rs>, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R32" target="#praat"/>
                <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R32">Praat</rs> (<rs type="bib.soft" ref="#R32"><ref type="bibl"
                  target="#boersma2001">Boersma and van Heuven 2001</ref></rs>; see <rs type="url" ref="#R32"><ptr
                    target="http://www.fon.hum.uva.nl/praat/"/></rs>), and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R33" target="#transcriber"/>
                <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R33">Transcriber</rs> (<rs type="bib.soft" ref="#R33"><ref type="bibl"
                  target="#barras2000">Barras et al. 2000</ref></rs>; see <rs type="url" ref="#R33"><ptr
                    target="http://trans.sourceforge.net/en/presentation.php"/></rs> and <rs type="url" ref="#R33"><ptr
              target="http://perso.ens-lyon.fr/matthieu.quignard/Transcriber/"/></rs>). These proprietary
            formats are in XML or Unicode formats so that they can be conserved for the long term.
            However, they are not all well described or constrained, at least not in the same way as
            TEI—which, moreover, offers a semantically relevant structure as well as an official
            format for long-term conservation in France. Moreover, as the durability of these four
            pieces of software cannot be guaranteed in the long term, it does not seem safe to keep
            corpora in a format available only for a given tool that may disappear or fall into
            disuse.</ptr>
          <p>The second major difference is that the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R34" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R34">TEICORPO</rs> initiative does not target only spoken
            language, but all types of annotation, including media of any type. This covers all
            spoken languages, vocal as well as sign languages, and also gesture and any type of
            multimodal coding. The goal of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R35" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R35">TEICORPO</rs> was not to advocate a linguistic mode of coding
            spoken data as a transcription convention does, but rather to propose a research model
            for storing and sharing data about language and other modalities. Consequently, the
            focus of the work was not on how the spoken data were coded (i.e., the microstructure),
            nor on the standard that should be used for transcribing in orthographic format.
            Instead, the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R36" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R36">TEICORPO</rs> approach focused on how to integrate multiple pieces of
            information into the TEI semantics (the macrostructure), as this is possible with tools
            such as <ptr type="software" xml:id="R37" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name"
              ref="#R37">ELAN</rs> or <ptr type="software" xml:id="R38" target="#praat"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R38">PRAAT</rs>. The goal was to be able to convert a file produced by
            these tools so that it can be saved in TEI format for long-term conservation.</p>
                <p>Data in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R39" target="#praat"/>
                  <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R39">PRAAT</rs> and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R40" target="#elan"/><rs
              type="soft.name" ref="#R40">ELAN</rs> formats can contain information that is
            different from what is usually present in an ISO/TEI description, but that nonetheless
            remains within the structures authorized in the ISO/TEI. For example, the information is
            stored as described below in <gi>spanGrp</gi>, an element available in the ISO/TEI
            description. This means that whenever information is organized according to the
              <soCalled>classical</soCalled> approach to spoken language (by
              <soCalled>classical</soCalled>, we mean approaches based on an orthographic
            transcription represented as a list, as in the script of a play), it will be available
            for further processing by using the export features of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R41" target="#teicorpo"/>
                  <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R41">TEICORPO</rs> (see <ptr
              target="#exporting" type="crossref"/> and further below for export functionalities)
                  but other types of information are also available. Compared to <ptr type="software" xml:id="R42" target="#praat"/>
                  <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R42">PRAAT</rs> and <ptr
              type="software" xml:id="R43" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R43"
                >ELAN</rs>, the integration of tools such as <ptr type="software" xml:id="R44" target="#clan"/>
                  <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R44">CLAN</rs> or <ptr type="software" xml:id="R45" target="#transcriber"/>
                  <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R45">Transcriber</rs> was much more
            straightforward, as the organization of the files is less varied and more
              <soCalled>classical</soCalled>.</p>
          <div xml:id="microstructures">
            <head>Choice of the Microstructure Representation</head>
            <p>Processing of the microstructure, with the exception of information already available
              in the tools themselves (for example silence in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R46" target="#transcriber"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R46">Transcriber</rs>), is not done during the
              conversion to TEI. The division into words or other elements such as morphemes or
              phonemes is not systematically done in any of the tools used by researchers in CORLI.
              When it exists, it is not included in the main transcription line but most often in
              dependent lines, as it represents an annotation with its own rules and guidelines.
              Division into words or other elements is part of the linguistic analysis rather than a
              simple storage operation.</p>
            <p><ptr type="software" xml:id="R47" target="#teicorpo"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R47">TEICORPO</rs> therefore preserves as long-term storage data both the original information
              that was created in the original software—the full unprocessed transcription—and the
              other linguistically processed transcriptions and annotations. For <ptr type="software" xml:id="R48" target="#teicorpo"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R48">TEICORPO</rs>,
              microstructure processing, such as division into words, or text standardization when
              necessary, belongs to the linguistic analysis of the corpora. Hence, the TEI data file
              can be used both for data exploration and for scientific purposes. For example, when a
              researcher needs to parse the data, or to explore the data with textometric tools,
              then it is necessary to decide which type of preprocessing is necessary. As this
              decision often depends on the initial project as well as on linguistic choices, it is
              difficult to standardize this task.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="teicorpoproject">
        <head>The <ptr type="software" xml:id="R49" target="#teicorpo"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R49">TEICORPO</rs> Project</head>
        <p>The <ptr type="software" xml:id="R50" target="#teicorpo"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R50">TEICORPO</rs> project contains two different sets of tools. One set focuses on conversion
          between various software packages used for spoken language coding and TEI. The other set
          focuses on using the TEI format for linguistic analyses (textometric or grammatical
          analyses).</p>

        <div xml:id="alignmenttools">
          <head>Alignment Tools</head>
          <p>Several alignment tools are used by researchers working with spoken language corpora to
            align the recording, whether an audio or a video file, with its textual transcription
            and other specific annotations. The choice of tools is usually related to the choice of
            annotations, or to the common practices in a given research field, or simply to the
            researcher’s preferences, knowledge, and requirements.</p>
          <p>Some common practices have been identified in our community but other uses of the same
            software are of course possible:</p>
          <list>
            <item><ptr type="software" xml:id="R51" target="#transcriber"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R51">Transcriber</rs> is widely used in sociolinguistics;</item>
            <item><ptr type="software" xml:id="R52" target="#clan"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R52">CLAN</rs> is widely used in language acquisition and especially in the Talkbank
              project;</item>
          </list>
          <list>
            <item>Praat is more specialized for phonetic or phonological annotations;</item>
            <item><ptr type="software" xml:id="R53" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name"
                ref="#R53">ELAN</rs> is recommended for annotating video and particularly
              multimodality (for example, components such as gazes, gestures, and movements), and is
              often used for rare languages to describe the organization of the segments.</item>
          </list>
          <p>It should be pointed out here that whereas Transcriber and CLAN files nearly always
            contain <soCalled>classical</soCalled> orthographic transcriptions, this is not the case
            for Praat and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R54" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name"
              ref="#R54">ELAN</rs> files. As our goal is to provide a generic solution for
            long-term conservation and use for any type of project, conversion of all types of files
            produced by the four tools cited above will be possible. It is up to the user to
            determine which part of a corpus can be used with a classical approach, which parts
            should not, and how they should be processed.</p>
          <p>The list of tools reflects the uses and practices in the CORLI network, and is very
            similar to the list suggested by Schmidt (<ref target="#schmidt2011" type="bibl"
              >2011</ref>) with the exception of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R55"
                target="#exmaralda"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R55">EXMARaLDA</rs> and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R56" target="#folker"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R56">FOLKER</rs>.
            These two tools already have built-in conversion features, so adding them to the
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R57" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R57">TEICORPO</rs> project would be easy at a later date.</p>
          <p>Alignment applications deal with two main types of data presentation and organization.
            The presentation of the data has direct consequences for how the data are exploited, and
            therefore on the design of the tools that are used.</p>
          <list>
            <item>In list or text format (as in the script of a play), the speakers’ productions are
              displayed in vertical order, from the beginning to the end of the recording, in the
              order that they are produced, speaker by speaker, with the speaker’s name on the left
              followed by their production. The timeline is vertical, going from top to bottom. In
              the result file, the speaker’s productions appear between two time points in the
              chronological order of the timelines, the start and the end of the production. The
              list format can be extended as a hierarchical format, as is the case in TEI, for
              example;</item>
            <item>In partition format (as in a musical score), each speaker has their own tier, a
              horizontal line representing the information pertaining to the speaker (like each
              instrument in a musical score). Sometimes several tiers are associated with the same
              speaker, for example gestures and gazes, aligned with the verbal production. The
              timeline is horizontal, going from left to right. The result file is not organized
              chronologically but is sorted by the names of the tiers (or any other order), with all
              the production within the same tier sorted by timeline.</item>
          </list>
          <p>No tool offers both types of presentation. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R58"
              target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R58">ELAN</rs> offers some alternatives to
            editing or displaying data with the partition format, but none of the existing tools
            offer full-fledged list format editing. It is possible to represent the two structures
            within a similar model, as demonstrated by Bird and Liberman (<ref type="bibl"
              target="#bird2001">2001</ref>). However, this is not the case for the four tools
            listed above: each of them represents the data in a unique underlying data structure.
            Transcriber and CLAN are organized in list format; Praat and <ptr type="software"
              xml:id="R59" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R59">ELAN</rs> have a
            partition format.</p>
          <p>Each presentation format has its own pros and cons. Because of the possibilities
            offered by the presentation formats, and because the same software, even within the same
            presentation models, rarely provides a solution for all the needs of all users,
            researchers often have to use two or more pieces of software.</p>
          <p>The use of multiple tools is quite common. For example, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R60" target="#praat"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R60">Praat</rs> and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R61" target="#transcriber"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R61">Transcriber</rs> cannot be
            used when working on video recordings because these programs are limited to audio
            formats. But if researchers need to conduct spectral analysis for some purpose, they
            will have to use the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R62" target="#praat"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R62">Praat</rs> software and convert not only the transcription, but also the
            media. In the field of language acquisition, where the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R63" target="#clan"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R63">CLAN</rs> software is generally used
            to describe both the child productions and the adult productions, when researchers are
            interested in gestures, they use the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R64" target="#elan"
              /><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R64">ELAN</rs> software, importing the CLAN file to add
            gesture tiers, as <ptr type="software" xml:id="R65" target="#elan"
            /><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R65">ELAN</rs> is more suitable for the fine-grained analysis
            of visual data. Another common practice consists in first doing a rapid transcription
            using only orthographic annotations in Transcriber and then in a second stage annotating
            some more interesting excerpts in greater detail including new information. In this case
            researchers will import the first transcription file into other tools such as Praat or
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R66" target="#elan"
            /><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R66">ELAN</rs> and annotate them partially. It is therefore necessary to import or export
            files in different formats if researchers need to use different tools for different
            parts of their work.</p>
          <p>Another need concerns the pooling of corpora coming from other resources or other
            projects. Conversions are necessary, and can be problematic because going from one piece
            of software to another often leads to a loss of information, as each tool handles corpus
            information differently, beyond the differences between list and partition formats.
            Researchers need a convenient tool to convert each file from one format to another
            without losing information. If such a tool is not provided by the software itself, it is
            necessary to create one. Such a custom tool is generally developed in each laboratory,
            operates only on a given platform (Windows, MacOS, Linux, etc.), is often not
            maintained, and does not include the latest releases of each software package or the
            requirements of the conversion process options. For these reasons, we decided in the
            CORLI consortium and in collaboration with the ORTOLANG infrastructure to design a
            common tool that could be used by the whole linguistic community. The goal was to make
            open-source software with proper maintenance freely available on <ptr type="software" xml:id="R67" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="url" ref="#R67"><ptr
              target="http://ct3.ortolang.fr/teicorpo/"/></rs>.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="conversion">
          <head>Conversion to and from TEI</head>
          <p>As explained above (see <ptr target="#similarities" type="crossref"/>), the conversion
            tools do not focus on the microstructure of the linguistic encoding, as it was not the
            goal of CORLI to push for a unique way to encode linguistic data. Nor did we split the
            transcription into words, as that is a research-dependent process and would not preserve
            the content of the original files. Processing the microstructure and splitting
            utterances into words is part of the second stage of our work (see <ptr
              target="#exporting" type="crossref"/>), which concerns the exploitation of the
            corpora. The goal of the conversion tool is to convert all the information in the
            metadata and all the macrostructure information into the TEI format.</p>
          <div xml:id="basicstruct">
            <head>Basic Structures</head>
            <p>Converting the metadata is straightforward, as the four tools (<ptr type="software" xml:id="R68" target="#clan"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R68">CLAN</rs>, <ptr
                type="software" xml:id="R69" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R69"
                  >ELAN</rs>, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R70" target="#praat"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R70">Praat</rs>, and 
              <ptr type="software" xml:id="R71" target="#transcriber"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R71">Transcriber</rs>) do not enable a large amount of metadata to be
              edited. Most of the metadata available concerns the content of the sequence; some user
              metadata is also available, especially in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R72" target="#clan"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R72">CLAN</rs>
              . The insertion of metadata follows the
              indications of the ISO/TEI 24624:2016 standard (<ref type="bibl" target="#iso2016">ISO
                2016</ref>).</p>
            <p>Moreover, some tools, such as Transcriber, include information about silences,
              pauses, and events in their XML format. This information is also processed within
              <ptr type="software" xml:id="R73" target="#teicorpo"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R73">TEICORPO</rs>, once again following the recommendations of the ISO/TEI standard.</p>
            <p>Conversion of the main data, the transcription and the annotations, cannot always be
              done solely on the basis of the description provided in the ISO/TEI guidelines. These
              guidelines do, however, suffice to fully describe the content of the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R74" target="#clan"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R74">CLAN</rs> and
              <ptr type="software" xml:id="R75" target="#transcriber"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R75">Transcriber</rs> software. We took advantage of the new <gi>annotationBlock</gi> element,
              which codes several annotation levels, a function that is commonly required in
              spoken-language annotations.</p>
            <p>The <gi>annotationBlock</gi> contains two major elements: the <gi>u</gi> element,
              which contains the transcription in orthographic form, and the <gi>spanGrp</gi>
              elements, which contain tier elements that annotate the utterance described in the
                <gi>u</gi> element. A <gi>spanGrp</gi> element contains as many <gi>span</gi>
              elements as required. All <gi>span</gi> elements have the same type of content, as
              indicated in the parent <gi>spanGrp</gi> element. <ptr target="#example_code_1"
                type="crossref"/> and <ptr target="#example_code_2" type="crossref"/> provide an
              example of conversion from a <ptr type="software" xml:id="R76" target="#clan"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R76">CLAN</rs> file to illustrate how a production annotated on
              different levels (orthography, morphosyntax, dependencies) is represented in TEI with
              a first main utterance element <gi>u</gi> to which two <gi>spanGrp</gi>s are linked,
              one for each annotation level, in our case one <gi>spanGrp</gi> for morphosyntax and
              one <gi>spanGrp</gi> for dependencies (see <ptr target="#fig2" type="crossref"/>). A
                <gi>timeline</gi> element gives the start (<val>T1</val>) and end (<val>T2</val>)
              timecodes and an <gi>annotationBlock</gi> element specifies the speaker with the
                <att>who</att> attribute and the <att>start</att> and <att>end</att> attributes with
              the timecode anchors <val>#T1</val> and <val>#T2</val>. The <gi>annotationBlock</gi>
              element includes both the utterance element and the two annotations. No semantic
              constraint is imposed on the inner content of the span elements. The content of the
                <att>type</att> attribute in the <gi>spanGrp</gi> element represents and documents
              the choice of the researchers who produced the original corpus. The content generated
              is preserved as it was in the original file, making backward conversion possible. In
                <ptr target="#example_code_1" type="crossref"/>, the <val>mor</val> and
                <val>gra</val> attribute values represent grammatical knowledge. Using the content
              of these elements to produce advanced grammatical representation in more elaborate TEI
              and XML formats is of course possible, but would be a tailored task which is beyond
              the scope of the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R77" target="#teicorpo"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R77">TEICORPO</rs> project.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example_code_1">
              <eg xml:space="preserve">*MOT: look at the tree ! 2263675_2265197
%mor: v|look prep|at det|the n|tree !
%gra: 1|0|ROOT 2|1|JCT 3|4|DET 4|2|POBJ 5|1|PUNCT</eg>
              <head type="legend">CLAN representation of data (first three lines)</head>
            </figure>

            <figure xml:id="example_code_2">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <timeline unit="s">
                  <when absolute="0" xml:id="T0"/>
                  <when interval="2263.675" since="#T0" xml:id="T1086"/>
                  <when interval="2265.197" since="#T0" xml:id="T1087"/>
                </timeline>
                <annotationBlock end="#T1087" start="#T1086" who="MOT" xml:id="au551">
                  <u>
                    <seg>look at the tree ! </seg>
                  </u>
                  <spanGrp type="mor">
                    <span>v|look prep|at det|the n|tree ! </span>
                  </spanGrp>
                  <spanGrp type="gra">
                    <span>1|0|ROOT 2|1|JCT 3|4|DET 4|2|POBJ 5|1|PUNCT</span>
                  </spanGrp>
                </annotationBlock>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">Representation in TEI corresponding to <ptr
                  target="#example_code_1" type="crossref"/>.</head>
            </figure>

          </div>
          <div xml:id="advancedstructures">
            <head>Advanced Structures</head>
            <p>Although the presentation described above can represent the data of many corpora and
              tools, a single-level annotation structure within the <gi>spanGrp</gi> elements is
              insufficient to represent the complex organization that can be constructed with the
                <ptr type="software" xml:id="R78" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R78"
                  >ELAN</rs> and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R78" target="#praat"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R79">Praat</rs> tools. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R80" target="#elan"/><rs
                type="soft.name" ref="#R80">ELAN</rs> is a tool used by many researchers to
              describe data of greater complexity than the data presented in the ISO/TEI guidelines.
              As the goal of the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R81" target="#teicorpo"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R81">TEICORPO</rs> project was to convert all types of structure used in the
              spoken language community, including <ptr type="software" xml:id="R82" target="#elan"
              /><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R82">ELAN</rs> and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R83" target="#praat"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R83">Praat</rs>, it was necessary to extend
              the description method presented in <ptr target="#basicstruct" type="crossref"/>.</p>
            <p>In <ptr type="software" xml:id="R84" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name"
              ref="#R84">ELAN</rs> and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R85" target="#praat"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R85">Praat</rs>, the multitiered annotations can be organized in a
              structured manner. These tools take advantage of the partition presentation of the
              data, so that the relationship between a parent tier and a child tier can be precisely
              organized. There are two main types of organization: symbolic and temporal.</p>
            <p>In symbolic division, the elements of a child tier, C<hi rend="sub">1</hi> to C<hi
                rend="sub">n</hi>, can be related to an element of a parent tier P. For example, a
              word is divided into morphemes. In <ptr target="#fig1" type="crossref"/>, the main
              tier has two representations, <term>BEJ_MV_NARR_11_coffee_18</term> and <term>gahwat
                mu:nai end //</term>. The tier of the second level contains individual words,
                <term>gahwat</term>, <term>mu:na</term>, and so on. On the third tier, the words are
              broken down into morphemes: <term>gahw</term>, <term>-t</term>, and so on. There are
              three other levels of organization, which follow either the organization of the
              morphemes or that of the main tier. In all these cases, the relationships between
              tiers are symbolic, and could be represented by symbolic links instead of temporal
              links.</p>
            <figure xml:id="fig1">
              <graphic url="media/image1.PNG" width="620px" height="980px"/>
              <head type="legend"><ptr type="software" xml:id="R86" target="#elan"/><rs
                  type="soft.name" ref="#R86">ELAN</rs> annotation with symbolic structures</head>
            </figure>

            <p>In temporal division, the association between the main tier and the dependent tiers
              is described by temporal information rather than by symbolic information. An element
              is included in the parent if the starting and end points are within the time limits of
              the starting and end points of the parent tier. <ptr target="#fig2" type="crossref"/>
              provides an example of such an organization created using Praat. In this example, the
              tier at the top of the representation contains phonemes that are included in the
              second tier, which contains syllables (for example, <term>S</term> and <term>a</term>
              are included in <term>Sa</term>). Then the syllables are included in turn in the
              word-level tier (bottom tier). In this example, as well as for the previous example,
              there are other tiers which will not be described here, but which show how complex the
              representation of the data can be.</p>
            <figure xml:id="fig2">
              <graphic url="media/image2.PNG" width="620px" height="980px"/>
              <head type="legend">Praat representation of a temporal structure</head>
            </figure>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="representation">
            <head>Representation of Advanced Structures</head>
            <p>The two types of data organization presented above—multiple levels where the relation
              between the parent and the child tier is either symbolic or temporal (and the two
              types of relation can appear in the same file at different levels)—correspond to uses
              in corpus linguistics that are more advanced than the usage presented in the ISO/TEI
              guidelines. This type of corpus can in some cases contain a large amount of data, or
              it can correspond to smaller corpora with very fine-grained coding. It can also encode
              unusual data, or new types of corpora, such as gesture and sign language studies, for
              instance. In these cases, the actual data coding can be far removed from that of a
              usual spoken language corpus (such as those described in Schmidt 2011). However, as
              this type of data is produced by members of the CORLI consortium, it needs to be
              preserved. Encoding the data in TEI using a standard tool makes the process
              reproducible, which is one of the goals of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R87" target="#teicorpo"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R87">TEICORPO</rs>.</p>
            <p>Although this type of data is not described in the ISO/TEI guidelines, it is in fact
              possible to store it in TEI format using current TEI features. TEI provides a general
              mechanism for storing hierarchically structured data by using the <gi>spanGrp</gi> and
                <gi>span</gi> mechanism. Moreover, the <gi>span</gi> and <gi>spanGrp</gi> tags have
              attributes that can point to other elements or to timelines. Using this coding schema,
              it is therefore possible to store any type of structure, symbolic and/or temporal,
              that can be generated with <ptr type="software" xml:id="R88" target="#elan"/><rs
                type="soft.name" ref="#R88">ELAN</rs> or 
              <ptr type="software" xml:id="R89" target="#praat"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R89">PRAAT</rs>, as described above.</p>
            <p>To do this, each element which is in a symbolic or temporal relation is represented
              by a <gi>spanGrp</gi> element of the TEI. The <gi>spanGrp</gi> element contains as
              many <gi>span</gi> elements as necessary to store all the elements present in the <ptr
                type="software" xml:id="R90" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R90"
                  >ELAN</rs> or  <ptr type="software" xml:id="R91" target="#praat"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R91">PRAAT</rs> representation. The parent element of a <gi>spanGrp</gi> is the
              main <gi>annotationBlock</gi> element when the division in <ptr type="software"
                xml:id="R92" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R92">ELAN</rs> or PRAAT is
              the first division of a main element. The parent element is another <gi>span</gi>
              element when the division in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R93" target="#elan"/><rs
                type="soft.name" ref="#R93">ELAN</rs> or <ptr type="software" xml:id="R94" target="#praat"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R94">PRAAT</rs> is a subdivision of another element
              which is not a main element. This XML structure is complemented by explicit
              information as allowed in TEI. The <gi>span</gi> elements are linked to the element
              they depend on, either with a symbolic link using the <att>target</att> attribute of
              the <gi>span</gi> element, or with temporal links using the <att>from</att> and
                <att>to</att> attributes of the <gi>span</gi> element.</p>
            <p>Two examples of how this is displayed in a TEI file are given below. The first
              example (see <ptr target="#fig3" type="crossref"/> and <ptr target="#example_code_3"
                type="crossref"/>) corresponds to the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R95"
                  target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R95">ELAN</rs> example above (see <ptr
                target="#advancedstructures" type="crossref"/>, <ptr target="#fig1" type="crossref"
              />). The TEI encoding represents the words of the sentence from left to right (from
                <term>gahwat</term> to <term>endi</term> in our example). The detail of the
              transcription is represented recursively, with <gi>span</gi> containing
                <gi>spanGrp</gi>, and <gi>spanGrp</gi> containing other <gi>span</gi> elements,
              until all the data are represented. This can be pursued down to any depth. In <ptr
                target="#fig3" type="crossref"/> and <ptr target="#example_code_3" type="crossref"
              />, this is the case with <term>gahw -t</term> which is divided into <term>BOR</term>
              and <term>-DET</term>.</p>
            <figure xml:id="fig3">
              <graphic url="media/image1.PNG" width="620px" height="980px"/>
              <head type="legend"><ptr type="software" xml:id="R96" target="#elan"/><rs
                  type="soft.name" ref="#R96">ELAN</rs> example of a symbolic division</head>
            </figure>

            <figure xml:id="example_code_3">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <annotationBlock end="#T24" start="#T23" who="ref@SP" xml:id="ann296">
                  <u>
                    <seg>BEJ_MV_NARR_11_coffee_18</seg>
                  </u>
                  <spanGrp type="tx@SP">
                    <span target="#ann296" xml:id="ann304"> gahwat muːna end // <spanGrp
                        type="mot@SP">
                        <span target="#ann304" xml:id="a69"> gahwat <spanGrp type="mb@SP">
                            <span target="#a69" xml:id="a186"> gahwa <spanGrp type="ge@SP">
                                <span target="#a186" xml:id="a318">coffee</span>
                              </spanGrp>
                              <spanGrp type="rx@SP">
                                <span target="#a186" xml:id="a450">BORR</span>
                              </spanGrp>
                            </span>
                            <span target="#a69" xml:id="a187"> -t <spanGrp type="ge@SP">
                                <span target="#a187" xml:id="a319">-INDF.F</span>
                              </spanGrp>
                              <spanGrp type="rx@SP">
                                <span target="#a187" xml:id="a451">-DET</span>
                              </spanGrp>
                            </span>
                          </spanGrp>
                        </span>
                      </spanGrp>
                    </span>
                  </spanGrp>
                </annotationBlock>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">TEI encoding corresponding to <ptr target="#fig3" type="crossref"
                />.</head>
            </figure>


            <p>The second example is structured using time references. This example (see <ptr
                target="#fig4" type="crossref"/> and <ptr target="#example_code_4" type="crossref"
                />) corresponds to the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R97" target="#praat"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R97">Praat</rs> example above (see <ptr target="#advancedstructures"
                type="crossref"/>, <ptr target="#fig2" type="crossref"/>). In this case, each part
              of the transcription is represented according to the timeline, but there is also a
              hierarchy which is represented by the <gi>spanGrp</gi> and <gi>span</gi> tags. Each
                <gi>span</gi> is part of the parent <gi>spanGrp</gi> with starting and ending points
              (which correspond to the <att>from</att> and <att>to</att> attributes in the example
              below). The use of <att>from</att>
              <att>to</att> versus <att>target</att> is the only difference between the two
              organizations. In the example below, the syllable <term>Sa</term> is divided into two
              phonemes, <term>S</term> and <term>a</term> (see <att>xml:id</att> s s34, s36, and
              s37).</p>
            <figure xml:id="fig4">
              <graphic url="media/image2.PNG" width="620px" height="980px"/>
              <head type="legend"><ptr type="software" xml:id="R98" target="#elan"/><rs
                type="soft.name" ref="#98">ELAN</rs> example of a temporal division</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="example_code_4">
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <span from="#T2" to="#T4" xml:id="s4"> $L1 <spanGrp type="syllabe">
                    <span from="#T2" to="#T4" xml:id="s5"> e <spanGrp type="prom">
                        <span xml:id="s6">W</span>
                      </spanGrp>
                      <spanGrp type="phone">
                        <span from="#T2" to="#T4" xml:id="s7">e</span>
                      </spanGrp>
                    </span>
                    <span from="#T4" to="#T6" xml:id="s10"> Sa <spanGrp type="prom">
                        <span xml:id="s11">S</span>
                      </spanGrp>
                      <spanGrp type="phone">
                        <span from="#T4" to="#T7" xml:id="s12">S</span>
                        <span from="#T7" to="#T6" xml:id="s13">a</span>
                      </spanGrp>
                    </span>
                  </spanGrp>
                </span>
              </egXML>
              <head type="legend">TEI encoding corresponding to <ptr target="#fig4" type="crossref"
                />.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>The <gi>spanGrp</gi> and <gi>span</gi> offer a generic representation of data coming
              from relatively unconstrained representations produced by partition software. The
              names of the tiers used in the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R99" target="#elan"/><rs
                type="soft.name" ref="#R99">ELAN</rs> and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R100" target="#praat"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R100">Praat</rs> tools are given in the content of
              the <att>type</att> attribute. These names are not used to provide structural
              information, the structure being represented only by the <gi>spanGrp</gi> and
                <gi>span</gi> hierarchy. However, the organization into <gi>spanGrp</gi> and
                <gi>span</gi> is not always sufficient to represent all the details of the tier
              organization of each software feature. This is the case for some of the <ptr
                type="software" xml:id="R101" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R101"
                >ELAN</rs> structures, which can specify the nature of <gi>span</gi> elements
              further than in the TEI feature. For example, the <term>timediv</term>
              <ptr type="software" xml:id="R102" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R102"
                >ELAN</rs> property specifies that only contiguous temporal division is allowed,
              whereas the <term>incl</term> property allows non-contiguous elements. It was
              therefore necessary to include the type of organization in the header of the TEI file,
              using the <term>note</term> structure. The <gi>note</gi> element here points to a case
              where dedicated tags do not currently exist in TEI, so we used the <gi>note</gi>
              element as the best way not to lose the information. Dedicated tags could be added to
              future versions of TEI.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="exporting">
          <head>Exporting to Research Tools</head>
          <p>In the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R103" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R103">TEICORPO</rs> approach, no modification is made to the original format and conversion
            remains as lossless as possible. This allows for all types of corpora to be stored for
            long-term preservation purposes. It also allows the corpora to be used with other
            editing tools, some of which are suited to specific processing: for example, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R104" target="#praat"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R104">Praat</rs> for
            phonetics/phonology; <ptr type="software" xml:id="#R105" target="#transcriber"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R105">Transcriber</rs>/<ptr type="software" xml:id="R106" target="#clan"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R106">CLAN</rs> for raw transcription; and <ptr type="software"
              xml:id="R107" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R107">ELAN</rs> for gesture
            and visual coding.</p>
          <p>However, a large proportion of scientific research and applications done using corpora
            requires further processing of the data. For example, although querying or using raw
            language forms is possible, many research investigations and tools use words, parts of
            speech (POS), or other grammatical or semantic information. This requires further
            processing starting with the original raw corpus form. In the case of spoken language
            corpora, the nature of the information inserted in the transcription has to be taken
            into account. This corresponds to what Schmidt (2011) calls <term>micro
            structure</term>. This microstructure is integrated in Schmidt’s approach, in which the
            TEI file can contain standardized information about words, specific spoken language
            information, and sometimes even POS information.</p>
          <p>This approach was not adopted in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R108" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R108">TEICORPO</rs> for several reasons. First, we had to deal
            with a large variety of coding approaches, which makes it difficult to conduct work
            similar to that done in CHILDES (<ref type="bibl" target="#macwhinney200">MacWhinney
              2000</ref>; see <ptr target="https://childes.talkbank.org/"/>). Second, there was no
            consensus about the way tokenization should be performed, as many researchers consider
            tokenization as a choice with multiple possibilities, each with different consequences
            for the resulting data and grammatical analyses. In other words, tokenization is part of
            the linguistic analysis, so it should not be frozen at the level of data
            conservation.</p>
          <p>For these reasons we decided, first, to make it possible to include in a corpus both
            the original raw language material and the modified tokenized and analyzed forms. This
            is easy to do in TEI, as any analyzed material can be inserted in <gi>spanGrp</gi>/
              <gi>span</gi> elements without modifying the original <gi>u</gi> element information.
            Second, we decided to design another category of tools for processing or making it
            possible to process the spoken language corpus, and to use powerful tools in corpus
            analysis. This part of the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R109" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R109">TEICORPO</rs> library is described in the next section.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="applications">
        <head>Applications</head>
        <p>Two types of applications have been designed: applications that are implemented as web
          services and applications that require command-line processing. The choice between web
          service and command-line processing was most often determined by user needs. The web
          service interface was developed based on user requests, and further development will be
          done if new needs appear in the future. The web service covers only the most frequently
          used and basic features, such as conversion between data formats. It also contains some
          specific features such as conversion from and to text, spreadsheet, and word processing
          formats, which were required by non-advanced users.</p>
        <p>The command-line interface contains features required by more advanced users. It can
          handle conversion between basic formats and the TEI, and is more efficient than the web
          service to handle a large number of primary files. The command-line interface contains
          other features such as syntactic analysis, metadata processing, and complex export
          features. Implementation of the command-line parameters is less costly than the
          implementation of these options in a web page, so they are easier to develop first, before
          they have to be made available in a more sophisticated user interface.</p>
        <div xml:id="basicimport">
          <head>Basic Import and Export Functions</head>
          <p>The command-line interface (see <ptr target="http://ct3.ortolang.fr/teicorpo/"/>) can
            perform conversions between TEI and the formats used by the following programs: 
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R110" target="#clan"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R110">CLAN</rs>,
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R111" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R111"
              >ELAN</rs>, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R112" target="#praat"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R112">Praat</rs>, and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R113" target="#transcriber"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R113">Transcriber</rs>. The conversions can be performed on single files
            or on whole directories or on a file tree. The command-line interface is suited to
            automatic processing in offline environments. The online interface (see <ptr type="software" xml:id="R114" target="#teiconvert"/>
            <rs type="url" ref="#R114"><ptr
              target="http://ct3.ortolang.fr/teiconvert/"/></rs>) can convert one or several files
            selected by the user, but not whole directories. Results appear in the user’s download
            folder.</p>
          <p>In addition to the conversion to and from the alignment software, the online version of
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R115" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R115">TEICORPO</rs> offers import and export in common spreadsheet formats (.xlsx and .csv) and
            word processing formats (.docx and .txt). Importing data is useful to create new data,
            and exporting is used to make reports or examples for a publication and for end users
            not familiar with transcription tasks or computer software (see <ptr
              target="#example_code_1" type="crossref"/> and <ptr target="#table1" type="crossref"
            />).</p>
          <table xml:id="table1">
            <head>Visual representation of data from Example 1 after being processed through
              TEI</head>
            <row role="label">
              <cell><p>6</p></cell>
              <cell><p>7.674</p></cell>
              <cell><p>CHI</p></cell>
              <cell><p>look</p></cell>
              <cell><p>at</p></cell>
              <cell><p>the</p></cell>
              <cell><p>tree</p></cell>
              <cell><p>.</p></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell/>
              <cell><p>mor</p></cell>
              <cell><p>v look</p></cell>
              <cell><p>prep at</p></cell>
              <cell><p>det:art the</p></cell>
              <cell><p>tree n</p></cell>
              <cell><p>.</p></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell/>
              <cell><p>gra</p></cell>
              <cell><p>1|0|ROOT</p></cell>
              <cell><p>2|1|JCT</p></cell>
              <cell><p>3|4|DET</p></cell>
              <cell><p>4|2|POBJ</p></cell>
              <cell><p>5|1|PUNCT</p></cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <p>In each case, some options are available to specify how to produce the:</p>
          <list>
            <item>timeline: <list>
                <item>at the beginning</item>
                <item>before or after the speaker’s production</item>
                <item>timeline precision</item>
              </list></item>
            <item>line number</item>
            <item>spoken language annotations: the user can choose to export without any specific
              annotation, which is useful for automatic tools that only need an orthographic lexical
              transcription.</item>
          </list>
          <p>Other features are available in both types of interface (command line and web service).
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R116" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R116">TEICORPO</rs> allows the user to exclude some tiers, for example adult tiers in acquisition
            research where the user wants to study child production only, or comment tiers which are
            not necessary for some studies.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="exportspec">
          <head>Export to Specialized Software</head>
          <p>Another kind of export concerns textometric software. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R117" target="#teiconvert"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R117">TEICONVERT</rs> makes spoken language
            data available for <ptr type="software" xml:id="R118" target="#txm"/><rs type="soft.name"
              ref="#R118">TXM</rs> (<rs type="bib.ref"
                ref="#R118"><ref type="bibl" target="#heiden2010">Heiden 2010</ref></rs>; see <rs type="url"
                  ref="#R118"><ptr
                    target="http://textometrie.ens-lyon.fr"/></rs>), <ptr type="software" xml:id="R119" target="#letrameur"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R119">Le Trameur</rs> (<rs type="bib.ref" ref="#R119"><ref type="bibl"
              target="#fleury2014">Fleury and Zimina 2014</ref></rs>; see <rs type="url" ref="#R119"><ptr
                target="http://www.tal.univ-paris3.fr/trameur/"/></rs>), and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R120" target="#iramuteq"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R120">Iramuteq</rs> (see <rs type="url" ref="#R120"><ptr
              target="http://iramuteq.org/"/></rs> and <rs type="bib.ref" ref="#R120"><ref type="bibl" target="#souza2018">de Souza et
              al. 2018</ref></rs>), providing a dedicated TEI export for these tools. For example, for
            the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R121" target="#txm"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R121"
              >TXM</rs> software, the export includes a text element made of utterance elements
            including age and speaker attributes. <ptr target="#example_code_5" type="crossref"/>
            presents an example for the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R122" target="#txm"/><rs
              type="soft.name" ref="#R122">TXM</rs> software.</p>
          <figure xml:id="example_code_5">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <TEI file="lily-4-00-02.tei_corpo.xml">
                <teiHeader/>
                <text>
                  <u age="28.0" end="2875.100" start="2873.395" who="MOT">
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">you</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">have</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">to</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">rest</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">now</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">.</w>
                  </u>
                  <u age="4.0" end="2875.970" start="2875.100" who="CHI">
                    <w age="4.0" loc="CHI">yes</w>
                    <w age="4.0" loc="CHI">.</w>
                  </u>
                  <u age="28.0" end="2877.893" start="2875.970" who="MOT">
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">from</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">your</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">big</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">singing</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">extravaganza</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">.</w>
                  </u>

                </text>
              </TEI>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Example of XML for the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R123"
                target="#txm"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R123">TXM</rs> software</head>
          </figure>

          <p>An export has been developed for Lexico and Le Trameur textometric software with a
            simple SGML file without timelines (see <ptr target="#example_code_6" type="crossref"
            />).</p>

          <figure xml:id="example_code_6">
            <eg>&lt;file=/corpusformat/exemple/japan/lily-4-00-02-extract.tei_corpo.xml&gt;
              &lt;loc=MOT&gt;you have to rest now ? &lt;loc=CHI&gt;yes . &lt;loc=MOT&gt;from your
              big singing extravaganza ? &lt;loc=CHI&gt;yes that was a party . &lt;loc=MOT&gt;woof </eg>
            <head type="legend">Example of export for the Lexico or Le Trameur software</head>
          </figure>

          <p>Likewise, another export is available for the textometric tool <ptr type="software" xml:id="R124" target="#iramuteq"
          /><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R124">Iramuteq</rs> without
            timelines (see <ptr target="#example_code_7" type="crossref"/>).</p>
          <figure xml:id="example_code_7">
            <eg>**** -*MOT you have to rest now ? -*CHI yes . -*MOT from your big singing
              extravaganza ? -*CHI yes that was a party . -*MOT woof . -*MOT that was a party that
              sure was some party . </eg>
            <head type="legend">Example of export for the IRAMUTEQ software</head>
          </figure>
          <p>In all these cases, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R125" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R125">TEICORPO</rs> is able to provide an export file and to remove
            unnecessary information from the TEI pivot format. This is useful, for example, with
            textometric software, which works only with orthographic tiers without a timeline or
            dependent information.</p>

        </div>
        <div xml:id="using">
          <head>Using an Automatic Grammatical Analyzer</head>
          <p>Many researchers in linguistics wish to use automatic grammatical analyzers on corpora
            in order to improve the querying and analysis of a text, or to implement other types of
            linguistic research. A present difficulty with these grammatical analyzers is that most
            often they run only on raw orthographic material, excluding other information. Moreover,
            their results are not always in a format that can be used with traditional spoken
            language software such as <ptr type="software" xml:id="R126" target="#clan"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R126">CLAN</rs>
            , <ptr type="software" xml:id="R127" target="#elan"/><rs
              type="soft.name" ref="#R127">ELAN</rs>, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R128" target="#praat"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="R128">Praat</rs>, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R129" target="#transcriber"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R129">Transcriber</rs>, nor of course in TEI
            format.</p>
          <p><ptr type="software" xml:id="R130" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R130">TEICORPO</rs> provides a way to solve this problem by running analyzers and putting the
            results from the analysis back into TEI format. Once the TEI format has been enriched
            with grammatical information, it is possible to use the results and convert them back to
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R131" target="#elan"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R131"
              >ELAN</rs> or <ptr type="software" xml:id="R132" target="#praat"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R132">Praat</rs> and use the grammatical information in these spoken language
            software packages. It is also possible to export to <ptr type="software" xml:id="R133"
              target="#txm"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R133">TXM</rs> and to use the grammatical
            information in the textometric software. Two grammatical analyzers have been implemented
            in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R134" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R134">TEICORPO</rs>: <ptr type="software" xml:id="R135" target="#treetagger"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R135">TreeTagger</rs> and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R136" target="#corenlp"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R136">CoreNLP</rs>.</p>
          <div xml:id="treetagger">
            <head><ptr type="software" xml:id="R138" target="#treetagger"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R138">TreeTagger</rs></head>
            <p><ptr type="software" xml:id="R139" target="#treetagger"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R139">TreeTagger</rs><note>
                <p>Accessed March 11, 2021, <rs type="url" ref="#R139"><ptr
                  target="https://www.cis.uni-muenchen.de/~schmid/tools/TreeTagger/"/></rs>.</p>
              </note> (<rs type="bib.ref" ref="#R139"><ref type="bibl" target="#schimd1994">Schmid 1994</ref></rs>; <rs type="bib.ref" ref="#R139"><ref type="bibl"
                target="#schmid1995">1995</ref></rs>) is a tool for annotating text with part-of-speech
              and lemma information. The software is freely available for research, education, and
              evaluation. It is available in twenty-five languages, provides high-quality results,
              and can be easily improved by enriching the training set, as was done for instance by
              Benzitoun, Fort, and Sagot (<ref type="bibl" target="#benzitoun2012">2012</ref>) in
              the PERCEO project. They defined a syntactic model suitable for spoken language
              corpora, using the training feature of TreeTagger and an iterative process including
              manual corrections to improve the results of the automatic tool.</p>
            <p>The command-line version of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R140" target="#teicorpo"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R140">TEICORPO</rs> should be used to generate an annotated file
              with lemma and POS information based on <ptr type="software" xml:id="R141" target="#treetagger"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#141">TreeTagger</rs>. <ptr type="software" xml:id="142" target="#treetagger"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#142">TreeTagger</rs> should be installed
              separately. The implementation of <ptr type="software" xml:id="143" target="#treetagger"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#143">TreeTagger</rs> in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R144" target="#teicorpo"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R144">TEICORPO</rs> includes the ability to use
              any syntactic model. For French data, we used the PERCEO model (<ref type="bibl"
                target="#benzitoun2012">Benzitoun, Fort, and Sagot 2012</ref>).</p>
            <p>The command line to be used is: <code>java -cp TEICORPO.jar
                fr.ortolang.TEICORPO.TeiTreeTagger filenames...</code> with additional
              parameters:</p>
            <table xml:id="table2">
              <row role="label">
                <cell><p><code>-syntaxformat</code>
                    <gi>param</gi></p></cell>
                <cell><p><gi>param</gi> can take the values w or ref or conll (see examples
                    below).</p></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><p><code>-model</code>
                    <gi>filename</gi></p></cell>
                <cell><p><gi>filename</gi> is the full name of the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R145" target="#treetagger"/>
                  <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R145">TreeTagger</rs> syntactic model. In
                    our case, we use the PERCEO model.</p></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><p><code>-program</code>
                    <gi>filename</gi></p></cell>
                <cell><p><gi>filename</gi> is the full location of the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R146" target="#treetagger"/>
                  <rs type="soft.name" ref="#146">TreeTagger</rs> program, according
                    to the system used (Windows, MacOS, or Linux).</p></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell><p><code>-normalize</code>
                    <gi>format</gi></p></cell>
                <cell><p><gi>format</gi> specifies the origin of the corpus. This can be useful when
                    cleaning up source files.</p></cell>
              </row>
            </table>
            <p>The environment variable TREE_TAGGER can be used to locate the model and the program.
              If no <code>-program</code> option is used, the default name for the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R147" target="#treetagger"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#147">TreeTagger</rs>
              program is used.</p>
            <p>The <code>-model</code> parameter is mandatory.</p>
            <p>The resulting filename ends with <code>.tei_corpo_ttg.tei_corpo.xml</code> or a
              specific name provided by the user (option <code>-o</code>).</p>
            <p>Three <code>syntaxformat</code> parameters are available:</p>
            <list>
              <item><code>-w</code> (word) format where the utterance element <gi>u</gi> is divided
                into word elements <gi>w</gi> with an <att>ana</att> attribute for POS and a
                  <att>lemma</att> attribute (see <ptr target="#example_code_8" type="crossref"/>).
                This is the basic format in the TEI specification. This format can be used to
                produce data that include POS information which follows the standard recommendation
                of the TEI. <figure xml:id="example_code_8">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                    <annotationBlock end="#T7" start="#T6" who="CHI" xml:id="au4">
                      <u>
                        <w lemma="thank" pos="VV">thank</w>
                        <w lemma="you" pos="PP">you</w>
                        <w lemma="it" pos="PP">it</w>
                        <w lemma="be" pos="VBD">was</w>
                        <w lemma="a" pos="DT">a</w>
                        <w lemma="singing" pos="NN">singing</w>
                        <w lemma="party" pos="NN">party</w>
                        <w lemma="." pos="SENT">.</w>
                      </u>
                      <spanGrp type="xpho">
                        <span>ˈθæku ɪwəzəˈsɪŋɪŋpɑrdi</span>
                      </spanGrp>
                    </annotationBlock>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Tagging results in <gi>w</gi> format</head>
                </figure>
              </item>
              <item><code>-ref</code> format with a <gi>ref</gi> element in a
                  <gi>spanGrp</gi>/<gi>span</gi>. It is made of word elements <gi>w</gi>, so that
                the original utterance format is preserved (see <ptr target="#example_code_9"
                  type="crossref"/>). This format is easier to process automatically than the CONLL
                format (see below) but contains only the word information described in the standard
                TEI specification (as for the <gi>w</gi> format). <figure xml:id="example_code_9">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                    <annotationBlock end="#T7" start="#T6" who="CHI" xml:id="au4">
                      <u>
                        <seg>thank you , it was a singing party . </seg>
                      </u>
                      <spanGrp type="xpho">
                        <span>ˈθæku ɪwəzəˈsɪŋɪŋpɑrdi</span>
                      </spanGrp>
                      <spanGrp inst="treetagger" type="ref">
                        <span>
                          <ref>
                            <w lemma="thank" pos="VV">thank</w>
                            <w lemma="you" pos="PP">you</w>
                            <w lemma="it" pos="PP">it</w>
                            <w lemma="be" pos="VBD">was</w>
                            <w lemma="a" pos="DT">a</w>
                            <w lemma="singing" pos="NN">singing</w>
                            <w lemma="party" pos="NN">party</w>
                            <w lemma="." pos="SENT">.</w>
                          </ref>
                        </span>
                      </spanGrp>
                    </annotationBlock>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Tagging results in <gi>ref</gi> format</head>
                </figure>
              </item>
              <item><code>-conll</code><note>
                  <p>CoNLL-U Format, <ptr target="https://universaldependencies.org/format.html"/>,
                    accessed May 5.</p>
                </note> format with a <gi>spanGrp</gi> with a <att>type</att> attribute value of
                  <code>connl</code> describing each token as a table (see <ptr
                  target="#example_code_10" type="crossref"/>). This format takes advantage of the
                possibilities offered by the TEI <gi>spanGrp</gi> and <gi>span</gi> elements. It is
                very powerful as it enables the user to insert as many description levels as
                necessary (ten levels exist in the current version of CONLL). The implementation of
                CoreNLP (see below) takes full advantage of these possibilities. <figure
                  xml:id="example_code_10">
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                    <annotationBlock end="#T7" start="#T6" who="CHI" xml:id="au4">
                      <u>
                        <seg>thank you , it was a singing party . </seg>
                      </u>
                      <spanGrp type="xpho">
                        <span>ˈθæku ɪwəzəˈsɪŋɪŋpɑrdi</span>
                      </spanGrp>
                      <spanGrp inst="treetagger" type="conll">
                        <span> 1 <spanGrp type="word">
                            <span>thank</span>
                          </spanGrp>
                          <spanGrp type="pos">
                            <span>VV</span>
                          </spanGrp>
                          <spanGrp type="lemma">
                            <span>thank</span>
                          </spanGrp>
                        </span>
                        <span> 2 <spanGrp type="word">
                            <span>you</span>
                          </spanGrp>
                          <spanGrp type="pos">
                            <span>PP</span>
                          </spanGrp>
                          <spanGrp type="lemma">
                            <span>you</span>
                          </spanGrp>
                        </span>
                      </spanGrp>
                    </annotationBlock>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">Tagging results in <gi>conll</gi> format</head>
                </figure>
              </item>
            </list>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="stanford">
            <head><ptr type="software" xml:id="R148" target="#stanfordcorenlp"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#148">Stanford CoreNLP</rs></head>
            <p><ptr type="software" xml:id="R149" target="#stanfordcorenlp"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#149">The Stanford Core Natural Language Processing</rs><note>
                <p>Accessed March 11, 2021, <rs type="url" ref="#149"><ptr target="https://nlp.stanford.edu/software/"/></rs>.</p>
              </note> (<ptr type="software" xml:id="R150" target="#stanfordcorenlp"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R150">CoreNLP</rs>) package is a suite of tools (<rs type="bib.ref" ref="#R150"><ref type="bibl" target="#manning2014"
                >Manning et al. 2014</ref></rs>) that can be used under a GNU General Public License. The
              suite provides several tools such as a tokenizer, a POS tagger, a parser, a named
              entity recognizer, temporal tagging, and coreference resolution. All the tools are
              available for English, but only some of them are available for all languages. All
              software libraries are integrated into <ptr type="software" xml:id="R151"
                target="#Java"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R151">Java</rs> JAR files, so all that is
              required is to download JAR files from the CoreNLP website<note>
                <p>Accessed May 5, 2021, <ptr
                    target="https://stanfordnlp.github.io/CoreNLP/index.html#download"/>.</p>
              </note> to use them with <ptr type="software" xml:id="R152" target="#teicorpo"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R152">TEICORPO</rs>. Using the analyzer is similar to using <ptr type="software" xml:id="R153" target="#treetagger"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R153">TreeTagger</rs>
              .
              The -model and -syntaxformat parameters can be used in a similar way to specify the
              grammatical model to be used and the output format. A command line example is:</p>
            <p><code>java -cp &quot;teicorpo.jar:directory_for_SNLP/*&quot;
                fr.ortolang.teicorpo.TeiSNLP -syntaxformat svalue -model
                filename.tei_corpo.xml</code></p>
            <p>The <term>directory_for_SNLP</term> is the name of the location on a computer where
              all the CoreNLP JAR files can be found. Note that using the CoreNLP software makes
              heavy demands on the computer’s memory resources and it is necessary to instruct the
              <ptr type="software" xml:id="R154" target="#Java"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R154"
                >Java</rs> software to use a large amount of memory (for example to insert parameter
              -mx5g before parameter <code>-cp</code> to indicate that 5 GB of memory will be used
              for a full English analysis).</p>
            <p>The <code>-model</code> parameter can take three values: english (use the full
              English grammar), french (use the full French grammar), or the name of a CoreNLP
              parameter file which specifies any type of analysis that is available in CoreNLP.</p>
            <p>The <code>-syntaxformat</code> parameter can take four values: <val>conll</val> (a
              full analysis with all possible tools: ten levels are produced in this case),
                <val>dep</val> (a syntactic analysis using a dependency grammar), and <val>ref</val>
              or <val>w</val> (only POS tagging and lemma).</p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="exportinggrammatical">
          <head>Exporting the Grammatical Analysis</head>
          <p>The results from the grammatical analysis can be used in transcription files such as
            those used by <ptr type="software" xml:id="R155" target="#praat"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R155">Praat</rs> and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R156" target="#elan"/><rs
              type="soft.name" ref="#R156">ELAN</rs>. A partition-like visual presentation of data
            is very handy to represent a part of speech or a CONLL result. The orthographic line
            will appear at the top with divisions into words, divisions into parts of speech, and
            other syntactic information below. As the result of the analysis can contain a large
            number of tiers (each speaker will have as many tiers as there are elements in the
            grammatical analysis: for example, word, POS, and lemma for TreeTagger; ten tiers for
            CoreNLP full analysis), it is helpful to limit the number of visible tiers, either using
            the <code>-a</code> option of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R157" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R157">TEICORPO</rs>, or limiting the display with the annotation
            tool.</p>
          <p>An example is presented below in the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R158" target="#elan"
          /><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R158">ELAN</rs> tool (see <ptr target="#fig5"
              type="crossref"/>). The original utterance was <term>si c’est comme ça je m’en
              vais</term> (if that’s how it is, I’m leaving). It is displayed in the first line,
            highlighted in pink. The analysis into words (second line, consisting of numbers),
            lemmas (third line), parts of speech (fourth line), and orthographic words (final line)
            is displayed below. So, for example, word 3 has the lemma <term>être</term> (to be) and
            the POS VER:pres (verb in the present tense), and it is the word <term>est</term>
            (is).</p>
          <figure xml:id="fig5">
            <graphic url="media/image3.png" width="620px" height="980px"/>
            <head type="legend">Example of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R159" target="#treetagger"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R159">TreeTagger</rs>
              analysis representation in a partition
              software program</head>
          </figure>

          <p>Export can be done from TEI into a format used by textometric software (see <ptr
              target="#example_code_11" type="crossref"/>). This is the case for <ptr
                type="software" xml:id="R160" target="#txm"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R160">TXM</rs>,<note>
                  <p>See the Textométrie website, last updated June 29, 2020, <rs type="ulr" ref="#R160"><ptr
                  target="http://textometrie.ens-lyon.fr/?lang=en"/></rs>.</p>
            </note> a textometric software application. In this case, instead of using a partition
            representation, the information from the grammatical analysis is inserted at the word
            level in an XML structure. For example, in the case below, the <ptr type="software"
              xml:id="R161" target="#txm"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R161">TXM</rs> export includes
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R162" target="#treetagger"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R162">TreeTagger</rs> annotations in POS, adding <att>lemma</att> and <att>pos</att> attributes to
            the word element <gi>w</gi>.</p>
          <figure xml:id="example_code_11">
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <TEI file="lily-4-00-02.tei_corpo_ttg_conll.xml">
                <teiHeader/>
                <text>
                  <u age="28.0" end="2875.1000000000" start="2873.3950000000" who="MOT">
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">you</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">have</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">to</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">rest</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">now</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">.</w>
                  </u>
                  <u age="4.0" end="2875.9700000000" start="2875.1000000000" who="CHI">
                    <w age="4.0" loc="CHI">yes</w>
                    <w age="4.0" loc="CHI">.</w>
                  </u>
                  <u age="28.0" end="2877.8930000000" start="2875.9700000000" who="MOT">
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">from</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">your</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">big</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">singing</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">extravaganza</w>
                    <w age="28.0" loc="MOT">.</w>
                  </u>

                </text>

              </TEI>
            </egXML>
            <head type="legend">Example of 
              <ptr type="software" xml:id="R163" target="#treetagger"/>
              <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R163">TreeTagger</rs> analysis representation that can be imported
              into <ptr type="software" xml:id="R164" target="#txm"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R164"
                >TXM</rs></head>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="comparison">
          <head>Comparison with Other Software Suites</head>
          <p>The additional functionalities available in the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R165" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R165">TEICORPO</rs> suite are close to those
            available in the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R166" target="#weblicht"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R166">Weblicht</rs> web services ( <rs type="bib.ref" ref="#R166"><ref type="bibl" target="#hinrichs2010"
              >Hinrichs, Hinrichs, and Zastrow 2010</ref></rs>). To a certain extent, the two suites of
            tools (
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R167" target="#weblicht"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R167">Weblicht</rs> and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R168" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R168">TEICORPO</rs>) have the same purpose and functionalities. They can import
            data from various formats, run similar processes on the data, and export the data for
            scientific uses. In some cases, the services could complement each other or <ptr type="software" xml:id="R169" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R169">TEICORPO</rs>
            could be integrated in the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R170" target="#weblicht"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R170">Weblicht</rs> services. This is the case, for example, for
            handling the CHILDES format, which at the time of writing is more functional in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R171" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R171">TEICORPO</rs>
            than in 
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R172" target="#weblicht"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R172">Weblicht</rs>.</p>
          <p>A major difference between the two suites is in the way they can be used and in the
            type of data they target. <ptr type="software" xml:id="R173" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R173">TEICORPO</rs> is intended to be used not as an independent tool,
            but as a utility tool that helps researchers to go from one type of data to another. For
            example, the syntactic analysis is intended to be used as a first step before being used
            in tools such as <ptr type="software" xml:id="R174" target="#praat"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R174">Praat</rs>, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R175" target="#elan"/><rs
              type="soft.name" ref="#R175">ELAN</rs>, or <ptr type="software" xml:id="R176"
                target="#txm"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R176">TXM</rs>. Our more recent developments
            (see <ref type="bibl" target="#badin2021">Badin et al. 2021</ref>) made it possible to
            insert metadata stored in CSV files (including participant metadata) into the TEI files.
            This makes it possible to achieve more powerful corpus analysis using a tool such as
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R177" target="txm"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R177"
              >TXM</rs>.</p>
          <p>Our approach is somewhat similar to what is suggested in the conclusion of Schmidt,
            Hedeland, and Jettka (<ref type="bibl" target="#schmidt2017">2017</ref>), who describe a
            mechanism that makes it possible to use the power of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R178" target="#weblicht"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R178">Weblicht</rs> to process their files
            that are in the ISO/TEI format. A similar mechanism could be used within <ptr type="software" xml:id="R179" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R179">TEICORPO</rs> to
            take advantage of the tools that are implemented in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R180" target="#weblicht"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R180">Weblicht</rs>. However, Schmidt,
            Hedeland, and Jettka (<ref type="bibl" target="#schmidt2017">2017</ref>) suggest in
            their conclusion that it would be more interesting to work directly on ISO/TEI files
            because they contain a richer format. This is exactly what we did in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R181" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R181">TEICORPO</rs>. Our
            suggestion would be to use the tools created by Schmidt, Hedeland, and Jettka (<ref
              type="bibl" target="#schmidt2017">2017</ref>) directly with the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R182" target="#teicorpo"/>
            <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R182">TEICORPO</rs> files, so
            that their work would complement ours. Moreover, in this way, the two projects would be
            compatible and provide either new functionalities when the projects have clearly
            different goals, or data variants when the goals are closer.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="conclusion">
        <head>Conclusion</head>
        <p><ptr type="software" xml:id="R183" target="#teicorpo"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="R183">TEICORPO</rs> is a functional tool, created by the CORLI network and ORTOLANG, that converts
          files created by software specializing in editing spoken-language data into TEI format.
          The result is fully compatible with the most recent developments in TEI, especially those
          that concern spoken-language material.</p>
        <p>The TEI files can also be converted back to the original formats or to other formats used
          in spoken-language editing to take advantage of their functionalities. This makes TEI a
          useful pivot format. Moreover, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R184" target="#teicorpo"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R184">TEICORPO</rs> allows conversion to formats used by tools
          dedicated to corpus exploration and browsing.</p>
        <p><ptr type="software" xml:id="R185" target="#teicorpo"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R185">TEICORPO</rs> exists as a command-line interface as well as a web service. It can thus be used
          by novice as well as advanced users, or by developers of linguistic software. The tool is
          free and open source so it can be further used and developed in other projects.</p>
        <p><ptr type="software" xml:id="R186" target="#teicorpo"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R186">TEICORPO</rs> is intended to be part of a large set of tools using TEI for linguistic corpus
          research. It can be used in parallel with or as a complement to other tools such as
          Weblicht or the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R187" target="#exmaralda"/><rs
            type="soft.name" ref="#R187">EXMARaLDA</rs> tools (see <ref type="bibl"
            target="#schmidt2017">Schmidt, Hedeland, and Jettka 2017</ref>). A specificity of
          <ptr type="software" xml:id="R188" target="#teicorpo"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R188">TEICORPO</rs> is that it is more suitable for processing extended forms of TEI data (especially
          forms which are not inside the main <gi>u</gi> element in the TEI code). <ptr type="software" xml:id="R189" target="#teicorpo"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R189">TEICORPO</rs> is also
          linked to <ptr type="software" xml:id="R190" target="#teimeta"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R190">TEIMETA</rs>, a flexible tool for describing spoken language corpora in a web
          interface generated from an ODD file (<ref type="bibl" target="#etienne">Etienne, Liégois,
            and Parisse, accepted</ref>). As TEI enables metadata and data to be stored in the same
          file, sharing this format will promote metadata sharing and will keep metadata linked to
          their data during the life cycle of the data.</p>
        <p>Potential further developments could provide wider coverage of different formats such as
          CMDI or linked data for editing or data exploration purposes; allow <ptr type="software" xml:id="R191" target="#teicorpo"/>
          <rs type="soft.name" ref="#R191">TEICORPO</rs> to work with
          other external tools such as grammatical analyzers; or enable the visualization of
          multilevel annotations.</p>
        <p/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="badin2021"><author>Badin, Flora</author>,<author>Loïc Liégeois</author>,
              <author>Gabriel Thiberge</author>, and <author>Christophe Parisse</author>.
            Forthcoming <date>2021</date>. <title level="a">Vers un outillage informatique optimisé
              pour corpus langagiers oraux en vue d’une exploitation textométrique: le cas des
              interrogatives partielles dans ESLO.</title>
            <title level="j">Corpus</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">22</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="DOI"
            >10.4000/corpus.5752</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="barras2000"><author>Barras, Claude</author>, <author>Edouard
              Geoffrois</author>, <author>Zhibiao Wu</author>, and <author>Mark Liberman</author>.
              <date>2000</date>. <title level="a">Transcriber: Development and Use of a Tool for
              Assisting Speech Corpora Production.</title> In <title level="m">Speech Annotation and
              Corpus Tools</title>, edited by <editor>Steven Bird</editor> and <editor>Jonathan
              Harrington</editor>, special issue, <title level="j">Speech Communication</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">33 (1–2)</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">5–22</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0167-6393(00)00067-4</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="benzitoun2012"><author>Benzitoun, Christophe</author>, <author>Karën
              Fort</author>, and <author>Benoît Sagot</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a"
              >TCOF-POS: un corpus libre de français parlé annoté en morphosyntaxe.</title> In Actes
            de la conférence conjointe JEP-TALN-RECITAL 2012, volume 2: TALN (JEP-TALN 2012 -
            Journées d’Études sur la Parole et conférence annuelle du Traitement Automatique des
            Langues Naturelles), <biblScope unit="page">99–112</biblScope>. Authors’ version
            available at <ptr target="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00709187"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="bird2001"><author>Bird, Steven</author>, and <author>Mark Liberman</author>.
              <date>2001</date>. <title level="a">A Formal Framework for Linguistic
              Annotation.</title> In <title level="m">Speech Annotation and Corpus Tools</title>,
            edited by <editor>Steven Bird</editor> and <editor>Jonathan Harrington</editor>, special
            issue, <title level="j">Speech Communication</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">33 (1–2)</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">23–60</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0167-6393(00)00068-6</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="boersma2001"><author>Boersma, Paul</author>. <date>2001</date>. <title
              level="a">Praat, A System for Doing Phonetics by Computer</title>. <title level="j"
              >Glot International</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">5 (9/10)</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">341–45</biblScope>.
              <ptr target="https://www.fon.hum.uva.nl/paul/papers/speakUnspeakPraat_glot2001.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="etienne"><author>Etienne, Carole</author>, <author>Loïc Liégeois</author>,
            and <author>Christophe Parisse</author>. Accepted. <title level="a">TEIMETA: An
              Evolutive Solution to Describe Spoken Language Corpora in a Web Interface Generated
              from an ODD File.</title></bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fleury2014"><author>Fleury, Serge</author>, and <author>Maria
              Zimina</author>. <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">Trameur: A Framework for
              Annotated Text Corpora Exploration.</title> In Proceedings of COLING 2014, the 25th
            International Conference on Computational Linguistics: System Demonstrations, edited by
              <editor>Lamia Tounsi</editor> and <editor>Rafal Rak</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >57–61</biblScope>. N.p.: Dublin City University and Association for Computational
            Linguistics. <ptr target="https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/C14-2013"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="heiden2010"><author>Heiden, Serge</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title
              level="a">The <ptr type="software" xml:id="TXM" target="#TXM"/><rs type="soft.name"
                ref="#TXM">TXM</rs> Platform: Building Open-Source Textual Analysis Software
              Compatible with the TEI Encoding Scheme.</title> In Proceedings of the 24th Pacific
            Asia Conference on Language, Information and Computation (PACLIC24), edited by
              <editor>Ryo Otoguro</editor>, <editor>Kiyoshi Ishikawa</editor>, <editor>Hiroshi
              Umemoto</editor>, <editor>Kei Yoshimoto</editor>, and <editor>Yasunari
            Harada</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">389–98</biblScope>. Sendai, Japan: Institute for
            Digital Enhancement of Cognitive Development, Waseda University. <ptr
              target="https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/Y10-1044/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="hinrichs2010"><author>Hinrichs, Erhard</author>, <author>Marie
              Hinrichs</author>, and <author>Thomas Zastrow</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title
              level="a">WebLicht: Web-Based LRT Services for German.</title> In Proceedings of the
            ACL 2010 System Demonstrations, <biblScope unit="page">25–29</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="http://www.aclweb.org/anthology/P10-4005"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="iso2016">ISO (International Organization for Standardization).
              <date>2016</date>. Language Resource Management — Transcription of Spoken Language.
            ISO 24624:2016. <ptr target="http://www.iso.org/iso/catalogue_detail.htm?csnumber=37338"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kipp2001"><author>Kipp, Michael</author>. <date>2001</date>. <title
              level="a">Anvil: A Generic Annotation Tool for Multimodal Dialogue.</title> In
            Proceedings of the 7th European Conference on Speech Communication and Technology
            (Eurospeech 2001 Scandinavia), vol. 2, edited by <editor>Paul Dalsgaard</editor>,
              <editor>Børge Lindberg</editor>, and <editor>Henrik Benner</editor>, <biblScope
              unit="page">1367–70</biblScope>. Bonn, Germany: ISCA-Secretariat. <ptr
              target="https://www.isca-speech.org/archive/eurospeech_2001/e01_1367.html"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lebart1998"><author>Lebart, Ludovic</author>, <author>André Salem</author>,
            and <author>Lisette Berry</author>. <date>1998</date>. <title level="m">Exploring
              Textual Data. Text, Speech and Language Technology (TLTB) 4</title>. Dordrecht:
            Springer Science+Business Media.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="macwhinney200"><author>MacWhinney, Brian</author>. <date>2000</date>. <title
              level="m">The CHILDES Project: Tools for Analyzing Talk</title>. Vol. 1, Transcription
            Format and Programs. 3rd ed. Mahwah, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates Publishers.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="macwhinney2007"><author>MacWhinney, Brian</author>. <date>2007</date>.
              <title level="a">The TalkBank Project</title>. In <title level="m">Creating and
              Digitizing Language Corpora</title>. Vol. 1, Synchronic Databases, edited
              by<editor>Joan C. Beal</editor>, <editor>Karen P. Corrigan</editor>, and
              <editor>Hermann L. Moisl</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">163–80</biblScope>.
            Houndmills, Basingstoke, Hampshire: Palgrave-Macmillan.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="manning2014"><author>Manning, Christopher D.</author>, <author>Mihai
              Surdeanu</author>,<author>John Bauer</author>, <author>Jenny Finkel</author>,
              <author>Steven J. Bethard</author>, and <author>David McClosky</author>.
              <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">The Stanford CoreNLP Natural Language Processing
              Toolkit.</title> In Proceedings of the 52nd Annual Meeting of the Association for
            Computational Linguistics: System Demonstrations, edited by <editor>Kalina
              Bontcheva</editor> and <editor>Jingbo Zhu</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >55–60</biblScope>. Stroudsburg, PA: Association for Computational Linguistics. <ptr
              target="https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/P14-5010/"/>; doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.3115/v1/P14-5010</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pincemin2011"><author>Pincemin, Bénédicte</author>. <date>2011</date>.
              <title level="a">Sémantique interprétative et textométrie – Version abrégée.</title>
            <title level="j">Corpus</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">259–69</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="DOI">10.4000/corpus.2121</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pincemin2020"><author>Pincemin, Bénédicte</author>, <author>Serge
              Heiden</author>, and <author>Matthieu Decorde</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title
              level="a">Textometry on Audiovisual Corpora</title>. Paper intended for the 15th
            International Conference on Statistical Analysis of Textual Data, JADT 2020. Toulouse,
            France, June 16–19, postponed. <ptr
              target="https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-02779055"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="schimd1994"><author>Schmid, Helmut</author>. <date>1994</date>. <title
              level="a">Probabilistic Part-of-Speech Tagging Using Decision Trees</title>. In
            Proceedings of International Conference on New Methods in Language Processing, edited by
              <editor>Daniel Jones</editor>. Manchester, UK: Centre for Computational Linguistics.
            Author’s version available at <ptr
              target="https://www.cis.uni-muenchen.de/~schmid/tools/TreeTagger/data/tree-tagger1.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="schmid1995"><author>Schmid, Helmut</author>. <date>1995</date>. <title
              level="a">Improvements in Part-of-Speech Tagging with an Application to
            German</title>. In From Text to Tags: Issues in Multilingual Analysis. Proceedings of
            the ACL SIGDAT Workshop. Author’s version available at <ptr
              target="https://www.cis.uni-muenchen.de/~schmid/tools/TreeTagger/data/tree-tagger2.pdf"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="schmidt2004"><author>Schmidt, Thomas</author>
            <date>2004</date>. <title level="a">Transcribing and Annotating Spoken Language with
                <ptr type="software" xml:id="EXMARaLDA" target="#EXMARaLDA"/><rs type="soft.name"
                ref="#EXMARaLDA">EXMARaLDA</rs></title>. In Proceedings of the LREC-Workshop on
            XML-based Richly Annotated Corpora. Paris: ELRA. Author’s version available at <ptr
              target="https://ids-pub.bsz-bw.de/frontdoor/index/index/docId/2317"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="schmidt2011"><author>Schmidt, Thomas</author>. <date>2011</date>. <title
              level="a">A TEI-based Approach to Standardising Spoken Language Transcription</title>.
              <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/142"/>; doi:<idno type="DOI"
              >10.4000/jtei.142</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="schmidt2017"><author>Schmidt, Thomas</author>, <author>Hanna
              Hedeland</author>, and <author>Daniel Jettka</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title
              level="a">Conversion and Annotation Web Services for Spoken Language Data in
              CLARIN.</title> In Selected Papers from the CLARIN Annual Conference 2016, edited by
              <editor>Lars Borin</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">113–30</biblScope>. Linköping
            Electronic Conference Proceedings 136. Linköping, Sweden: LiU Electronic Press. <ptr
              target="https://ep.liu.se/ecp/article.asp?issue=136&amp;article=009&amp;volume=0"/>; <ptr
              target="https://ep.liu.se/ecp/136/009/ecp17136009.pdf"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="schmidts2010"><author>Schmidt, Thomas</author>, and <author>Wilfried
              Schütte</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title level="a">FOLKER: An Annotation Tool for
              Efficient Transcription of Natural, Multi-party Interaction.</title> In Proceedings of
            the Seventh Conference on International Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC’10),
              <biblScope unit="page">2091–96</biblScope>. N.p.: European Language Resources
            Association (ELRA). <ptr target="http://lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2010/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="souza2018"><author>Souza, Marli Aparecida Rocha de</author>,
              <author>Marilene Loewen Wall</author>, <author>Andrea Cristina de Morais Chaves
              Thuler</author>, <author>Ingrid Margareth Voth Lowen</author>, and <author>Aida Maris
              Peres</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">The Use of IRAMUTEQ Software for
              Data Analysis in Qualitative Research</title>. <title level="j">Revista da Escola de
              Enfermagem da USP 52</title>, <biblScope unit="issue">e03353</biblScope>. doi:<idno
              type="DOI">10.1590/S1980-220X2017015003353</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="wittenburg2006"><author>Wittenburg, Peter</author>, <author>Hennie
              Brugman</author>, <author>Albert Russel</author>, <author>Alex Klassmann</author>, and
              <author>Han Sloetjes</author>. <date>2006</date>. <title level="a"><ptr
                type="software" xml:id="ELAN" target="#ELAN"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#ELAN"
                >ELAN</rs>: A Professional Framework for Multimodality Research.</title> In
            Proceedings of LREC 2006, Fifth International Conference on Language Resources and
            Evaluation, <biblScope unit="page">1556–59</biblScope>. N.p.: European Language
            Resources Association (ELRA). <ptr
              target="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2006/"/>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
