<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-cc-ra-winslow-186-source.xml 1061 2021-09-24 17:27:24Z tiago.sousa-garcia $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Authenticating Features in the TEI</title>
            <!-- author information in separate <author> elements per author -->
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Sean M.</forename>
                  <surname>Winslow</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation><roleName>Postdoc</roleName> on the FWF (Austrian Science Fund) project
                  Retain Domain Specific Functionalities in a Generic Repository with Humanities
                  Data (ORD84), <orgName>Karl-Franzens-Universität Graz</orgName></affiliation>
               <email>sean.winslow@uni-graz.at</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>2021-09-23</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor role="guest">Susan Schreibman</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="13">Selected Papers from the 2018 TEI Conference</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for
               journals in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking
               to publish full-text articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>authentication</term>
               <term>seal</term>
               <term>stamp</term>
               <term>authenticity</term>
               <term>diplomatics</term>
               <term>charters</term>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2021-09-23" who="TSG">First encoding</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p>Textual and paratextual elements that serve to establish the authenticity of
               documents abound and carry meaning that is important—often central—to the meaning of
               the document as received, but are currently only lightly modeled in TEI. This paper
               will discuss issues in the modeling of authenticating features across time periods
               and regional boundaries, from the existing <gi scheme="TEI">seal</gi> element to
               medieval European chirographs to Japanese <foreign xml:lang="ja">jitsu-in</foreign>.
               Here, I will make the case for the applicability of authenticating elements,
               introduce a preliminary working vocabulary of methods of authenticating elements, and
               demonstrate how they can be modeled in TEI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <!-- text divisions, each with an @xml:id and <head> -->
         <div xml:id="introduction">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Textual and paratextual elements that serve to establish the authenticity of
               documents abound and carry authority that is important—often central—to the meaning
               of the document as received. An authentic document from a legitimate sender issuing
               an order, for example, is completely different in interpretation from an inauthentic
               copy of an order, although the reception may change based upon whether it was
               perceived by the recipients as authentic. Issues related to authentication are
               currently only lightly modeled in TEI. This paper will discuss issues in the modeling
               of authenticating features across time periods and regional boundaries, from the
               existing <gi scheme="TEI">seal</gi> element to medieval European chirographs to
               Japanese <foreign xml:lang="ja">jitsu-in.</foreign> Here, I will make the case for
               the applicability of authenticating elements, introduce a preliminary working
               vocabulary of methods of authenticating elements, and demonstrate how they can be
               modeled in TEI.</p>
            <p>The present use case arises out of the ongoing work of mapping of medieval documents
               marked up by the <ref target="http://www.cei.lmu.de/">Charters Encoding
                  Initiative</ref> (CEI),<note><ref type="bibl" target="#vogeleretal2018">CEI
                     website</ref>, accessed June 25, 2021, <ptr target="http://www.cei.lmu.de/"
                  />.</note> a charters-data-specific fork of TEI P4 with its own elements and
               structures and separate development history, to TEI P5. Georg Vogeler, who began the
               CEI, wondered what a model that encompassed both seals and digital hashes might look
               like and initiated the current discussion of authentication and the current ODD
                  (<q>One Document Does it all</q>) extension. This discussion and the ODD extension
               are part of the Austrian Science Fund (FWF) Open Research Data (ORD) Project 84,
               Retain Domain Specific Functionalities in a Generic Repository with Humanities Data,
               for which I worked as a postdoctoral research associate. Vogeler’s observation, and
               the model of the CEI, were the genesis of the current discussion of authentication
               and the current extension, and the present author would like to acknowledge Georg
               Vogeler’s advice and feedback throughout the process.<note>I am also grateful for the
                  advice and feedback of the anonymous reviewers of this paper.</note> In the
               process of modeling medieval documents for the update of CEI to TEI P5, it was
               necessary to address such issues as they occur in the context of medieval documents,
               with elements like chirographs, monograms, and lists of witnesses. The practices
               modeled in the CEI, however, are similar across time periods and regions, with little
               clear demarcation in the exact differences in form and function of seals, stamps,
               monograms, <foreign xml:lang="ja">jitsu-in</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >rotas</foreign>: all of these practices exist within a larger spectrum of
               practice that spans time and culture, from ancient Mesopotamia to medieval England to
               modern Japan. Accordingly, this paper considers not just medieval charters and
               documents currently being encoded for the CEI, but also potential needs for the
               modeling of related materials and of items like text-bearing museum objects that have
               authentication features, such as banknotes and passports. Born-digital objects such
               as email likely need further, specialized attention in the future, and are beyond the
               scope of the present study. The paper introduces a dedicated element for
               authentication, based upon (and expanding) current practice in the CEI.</p>
            <p>This paper attempts to generalize the markup of authenticating elements encountered
               through diplomatic study of and markup of medieval documents, moving beyond the
               original disciplinary context of the originating project. The approach here is very
               different from that taken by SigiDoc (<ref xml:id="ref1" type="bibl"
                  target="#sopracasaetal2020">Sopracasa 2020</ref>), a recent offshoot of EpiDoc,
               which takes a rather numismatic approach, focusing on seals as individual objects,
               independent of any accompanying materials, a decision derived from the conditions of
               Byzantine sigillography, where scarcely any documents survive. It also differs from
               other projects that contain elements describing authentication (e.g.,
                     Nomisma<note><title level="a">Nomisma Ontology</title>, accessed July 1, 2021,
                     <ptr target="http://nomisma.org/ontology"/>.</note>) which are
               discipline-specific (i.e., numismatic) in approach, in aiming for generalizable
               universality.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="priorart">
            <head>Prior Art: Manuscript Catalogues and Diplomatics</head>
            <p>Diplomatics, the science of the interpretation of charters and other documentary
               materials, has since its inception been concerned with the authenticity of documents.
               Foundational episodes in the history of the discipline center on this concern:
               Lorenzo Valla’s debunking of the Donation of Constantine set the model that
               diplomatists have generally followed, that of the expert making decisions based upon
               the totality of the evidence about the content and context of a historical document
               to determine whether it is authentic or a forgery (<ref xml:id="ref2" type="bibl"
                  target="#valla1440">Valla 1440</ref>). When Jean Mabillon laid the groundwork for
               the modern discipline in his <title level="m">De re diplomatica libri VI</title>, he
               did so in response to competing claims about the authenticity of documents held in
               the abbey of Saint-Denis (<ref xml:id="ref3" type="bibl" target="#mabillon1681"
                  >Mabillon 1681</ref>). His six-year-long program to establish the authentic nature
               of those documents led to the foundation of the disciplines of paleography and
               diplomatics and also set the model for the learned diplomatist who approaches
               historical documents in a holistic way to deliver expert and authoritative judgments
               on the authenticity of historical documents.</p>
            <p>Diplomatics as a discipline is one of the auxiliary sciences of history (<foreign
                  xml:lang="de">Historische Hilfswissenschaften</foreign>), and exists as both a
               general tool for historians and a specialist field of inquiry on its own. In its
               modern form, it sees significant use in archival cataloging of documents. While the
               TEI manuscript description (<ident>msdescription</ident>) module provides many
               elements for representing traditional catalog elements in TEI (<ref xml:id="ref4"
                  type="bibl" target="#cummings2017">Cummings 2017</ref>), these cataloging elements
               are highly focused on books, not documents. Not only do documents have their own
               forms, but they also have the specific trait of being anchored in a legal context: a
               document which is treated entirely as text without reference to its authentic status
               can be misleading to the modern historian, as treating an inauthentic document as if
               it were authentic (i.e, with the force of law behind it) leads the modern scholar
               down a false historical path.<note>I leave aside here the question of forged
                  authentication, which is outside the limited scope of this paper, and, in any
                  event, could be dealt with appropriately using existing markup.</note>
               Traditionally, authentication has been a matter for an expert, who makes a decision
               based upon the totality of the form and content of the document, processes it through
               personal expertise in the relevant historical and legal contexts, and makes a
               pronouncement on whether it is authentic or inauthentic.<note>The concept of
                  authentication as witness to something both being true and being legal is
                  discussed by <ref xml:id="ref14" type="bibl" target="#chango2012">Chango
                     (2012)</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Ideally, TEI would make room for the inclusion of specialist expert knowledge and
               judgment, but at the same time, as content-based markup, de-link that judgment from
               the real, present elements which are evidence for authentication. This separates the
               text, as an object that can be freely transcribed, edited, and forwarded, from the
               images, which can be reproduced through photographs; from the authenticating value of
               those textual or image elements; and also from the document itself, the authenticity
               of which can only be determined by the kind of connoisseurship which comes from long
               experience and exposure to documents. In this way, a combination of authentic and
               inauthentic, authenticating and nonauthenticating elements can be separated from the
               overall document (which, in the case that it contains a mix of authentic and
               inauthentic authentication elements, is likely itself inauthentic). That
               authenticating elements bear significance beyond their text or image and convey
               information that is on par with the text itself is well established (<ref
                  xml:id="ref5" type="bibl" target="#ruck1996">Rück 1996</ref>). This paper suggests
               a way to regularly mark up such elements using an extension of TEI, with a suggested
               preliminary controlled vocabulary useful as a target for subtype pointers.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="authenticatingfeatures">
            <head>Authenticating Features</head>
            <p>Seals, whether affixed (applied directly to the document) or pendant (hanging from
               the document from a cord or parchment/paper tag), served to express that the document
               had been legitimately and authentically issued by the owner of the seal.<note>A
                  useful (though UK-centric) introduction to sealing practices is by <ref
                     xml:id="ref6" type="bibl" target="#new2010">New (2010)</ref>.</note> Seal
               matrices were physical devices with complex carvings on them, presenting both a
               material and an artistic/technological barrier to forgery, and therefore serving as
               an attestation of the authentic nature of the document to which they were attached.
               But seals are not specific to the format enshrined in the TEI Guidelines, the
               medieval wax seal: its predecessors, circular seals meant for rolling in clay, are
               much attested from the ancient Middle East, and using signet rings for personal
               attestation was a common practice from the Ancient Middle East<note>From about 3400
                  BCE. <ref xml:id="ref15" type="bibl" target="#collon1987">Collon
                  1987</ref>.</note> through the Middle Ages, with variances in fashion, until going
               out of general use in the nineteenth century.</p>
            <p>Though wax seals have a physical and artistic character that can be described with
               the relevant TEI elements, their intended purpose points to their value as
               paratextual elements, as their authenticating value is independent of their value as
               art or as text. Accordingly, it makes sense that the authenticating value needs
               highlighting, and the <gi scheme="TEI">sealDesc</gi> and <gi scheme="TEI">seal</gi>
               elements largely handle these concerns, bundling the various aspects of seals—their
               artistic description, physical character, prosopographical attributes, and other
               paratextual qualities—in one place, representing the plural modes of communication
               that seals are involved in. But do seals in themselves represent the full range of
               features that similarly combine textual, artistic, and paratextual elements for the
               purpose of authenticating documents?</p>
            <p>TEI P5 provides the elements <gi scheme="TEI">seal</gi> and <gi scheme="TEI"
                  >sealDesc</gi> as part of the msdescription module. A closely related feature of
               manuscripts which is also modeled is <gi scheme="TEI">stamp</gi>. Stamps, while
               differing in material form, often have similar (if not identical) visual arrangement,
               incorporating elements of text and heraldry in round or pointed oval seals, directly
               borrowing their visual forms from such seals; in fact, there is little to distinguish
               a single-matrix affixed seal (one matrix, pressed into hot wax applied to the page)
               from the impression of an ink stamp (one stamp, pressed into ink applied to the
               page). Historically, they have been largely interchangeable, with stamps taking over
               as authenticating features and still widely used by government and corporate offices,
               as well as for indicating ownership (as in the Bodleian stamp, <ptr type="crossref"
                  target="#stamp_wiki"/>). Stamps outside of Europe have a long history of use in
               ways that are directly analogous to the use of seals in Europe, with widespread use
               in the Middle East and East Asia; when discussing the latter, the term
                  <term>seal</term> refers to inked stamps (<foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >jitsu-in</foreign> in Japan and colloquially <soCalled>chops</soCalled> in China)
               used to sign and authenticate documents.</p>
            <p>Despite the similar ways that (wax) seals and (inked) seals/stamps operate, at
               present TEI treats them quite differently. Inked seals/stamps are treated as
               text-level elements, placed where they appear in the running text, unlike <gi
                  scheme="TEI">seal</gi>s, which are considered to be part of the physical
               description of the document, within <ident>msDesc/physDesc/sealDesc/seal</ident>,
               although seals often contain text themselves (since <gi scheme="TEI">msDesc</gi> is
               catalog-level information, text in seals is currently treated as a description of the
               seal, not as text, making text in seals problematic to properly capture). <ref
                  type="crossref" target="#example1">Examples 1</ref> and <ref type="crossref"
                  target="#example2">2</ref> show how they are currently described.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example1">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <rubric>
                     <lb/>Apologyticu TTVLLIANI AC IGNORATIA IN XPO IHV <lb/>SI NON LICET <lb/>NOBIS
                     RO <lb/>manii imperii <stamp>Bodleian stamp</stamp>
                     <lb/>
                  </rubric>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Stamps: The example in the TEI P5 documentation for stamp (<title
                     level="a">Watermarks and Stamps</title>, <ref xml:id="figref1" type="bibl"
                     target="#tei2019">TEI Consortium 2019, sec. 10.3.3</ref>, <ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.6.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html#mswat"
                  /></head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="example2">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <seal n="2" type="pendant" subtype="cauda_duplex">
                     <p>The seal of <name>Jens Olufsen</name> in black wax: <bibl>
                           <ref>DAS 1061</ref>
                        </bibl>. Legend: <quote>S IOHANNES OLAVI</quote>. Parchment tag on which is
                        written: <quote>Woldorp Iohanne G</quote>.</p>
                  </seal>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Seals. The example in the TEI P5 documentation for seal (<title
                     level="a">Seals</title>, <ref xml:id="figref2" type="bibl" target="#tei2019"
                     >TEI Consortium 2019, sec. 10.7.3.2</ref>, <ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.6.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html#msphse"
                  />)</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="stamp_wiki">
               <graphic url="img/Bibliotheksstempel_Bodleiana.jpg" width="218px" height="223px"/>
               <head type="legend">An example Bodleian stamp.</head>
               <head type="license">Image from Wikimedia.<ptr
                     target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Bibliotheksstempel_Bodleiana.jpg"
                  /></head>
            </figure>
            <p>Note that despite being part of the running text of the document, the content of the
               stamp element in <ptr type="crossref" target="#example1"/> is not text. Presumably,
               in this case, it should read <q>BIBLIOTHECA BODLEIANA</q> as seen in <ptr
                  type="crossref" target="#stamp_wiki"/> (and, if the writing in the Coat of Arms of
               the University of Oxford is included, also <q>DOMINUS ILLUMINATIO MEA</q>), but
               instead the example is a text reference to the identity of the stamp (although, since
               there have presumably been multiple Bodleian stamps over the years, a rather
               insufficient one). In this sense, the content of the <gi scheme="TEI">stamp</gi>
               element is rather parallel to the content of the <gi scheme="TEI">seal</gi> element,
               despite the actual content models being quite different (<gi scheme="TEI">seal</gi>,
               which may contain <ident>model.pLike</ident> and <gi scheme="TEI">decoNote</gi>, only
               serves as a direct container for three different elements; <gi scheme="TEI"
                  >stamp</gi>, which may contain <ident>macro.phraseSeq</ident>, serves as a
               container for over 100, but none of the same three that <gi scheme="TEI">seal</gi>
               contains: <gi scheme="TEI">decoNote</gi>, <gi scheme="TEI">p</gi>, and <gi
                  scheme="TEI">ab</gi>).<note><gi scheme="TEI">p</gi>, in turn, has a larger number
                  of descendants, but the point is that these essentially equivalent features are
                  modeled in such a way that they have no direct overlap in child elements.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="authenticatingfeaturesnotcovered">
            <head>Authenticating Features Not Covered by the TEI: Medieval Examples</head>
            <p>As explained above, despite the differences in modeling in TEI P5, seals and stamps
               often—though not always—perform the same or similar functions, while having the same
               or similar layouts and very similar physical forms. But these are far from the only
               authenticating forms, as medieval documents also used split media (chirograph, poll,
               indenture, or tally), witnessing, various forms of signing (crosses, <foreign
                  xml:lang="la">rota</foreign>s, and monograms), reproduction/publication (<foreign
                  xml:lang="la">vidimus</foreign>, etc.), and less easily catalogued features, like
               specific chancellery styles of documents and handwriting (most notably, the ornate
               papal chancellery style). All of these elements served to establish that a document
               was what it claimed to be, and that the contents of the document had the force of law
               behind them. A legal document marked up without attention to these features is just a
               text (generally a very formulaic one, written from a model), and missing a crucial
               and inseparable aspect of its value to its producers and recipients: its status as a
               legal object. Compare, for example, the XML representation of document
                  <idno>570411a</idno> from the <ref xml:id="ref7" type="bibl"
                  target="#monumenta2019">Monumenta Germaniae Historica</ref> (<ptr
                  target="http://telota.bbaw.de/constitutiones/data/texts/570411a.xml"/>)<note>
                  <bibl>
                     <title level="m">Monumenta Germaniae Historica: Constitutiones et acta publica
                        imperatorum et regum 1357–1378</title>, <publisher>Berlin-Brandenburgische
                        Akademie der Wissenschaften</publisher>, accessed <date>July 22,
                     2019</date>, <ptr target="http://telota.bbaw.de/constitutiones/index.html"
                     />.</bibl></note> with its image (<ptr
                  target="http://telota.bbaw.de/constitutiones/resources/images/Urkunde.gif"/>.
               Though the document does mention a <q>Monogramm</q>, it is not marked up with any
               specialized element, and both the monogram and the half of the seal that remains—both
               bearing text and crucial for establishing that the accompanying text is authentic—are
               not treated as text or with the care with which text would be treated.</p>
            <figure xml:id="rotapope">
               <graphic url="img/rotapope.png" width="956px" height="892px"/>
               <head type="legend">Rota of Pope Innocent II in a charter, second graphic of
                        <bibl><title level="m">Chartularium Sangallense</title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">03</biblScope> (<idno>1004–1277</idno>) <biblScope
                        unit="part">Nr. 898, S. 21–22</biblScope>, accessed <date>July 2,
                        2021</date>, <ptr
                        target="https://www.monasterium.net/mom/CSGIII/Nr_898_S_21-22/charter"
                     /></bibl></head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="leadenbull">
               <graphic url="img/leadenbull.png" width="804px" height="1212px"/>
               <head type="legend">Leaden bull attached to a charter, second graphic of <bibl><title
                        level="m">Chartularium Sangallense</title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">03</biblScope> (<idno>1004–1277</idno>) <biblScope
                        unit="part">Nr. 898, S. 21–22</biblScope>, accessed <date>July 2,
                        2021</date>, <ptr
                        target="https://www.monasterium.net/mom/CSGIII/Nr_898_S_21-22/charter"
                     /></bibl>.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="benevalete">
               <graphic url="img/benevalete.png" width="846px" height="1058px"/>
               <head type="legend">Bene Valete in a charter, second graphic of <bibl><title
                        level="m">Chartularium Sangallense</title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">03</biblScope> (<idno>1004–1277</idno>) <biblScope
                        unit="part">Nr. 898, S. 21–22</biblScope>, accessed <date>July 2,
                        2021</date>, <ptr
                        target="https://www.monasterium.net/mom/CSGIII/Nr_898_S_21-22/charter"
                     /></bibl></head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="subscription">
               <graphic url="img/subscription.png" width="2312px" height="392px"/>
               <head type="legend">Subscription of Pope Innocent II in a charter, second graphic of
                        <bibl><title level="m">Chartularium Sangallense</title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">03</biblScope> (<idno>1004–1277</idno>) <biblScope
                        unit="part">Nr. 898, S. 21–22</biblScope>, accessed <date>July 2,
                        2021</date>, <ptr
                        target="https://www.monasterium.net/mom/CSGIII/Nr_898_S_21-22/charter"
                     /></bibl></head>
            </figure>
            <p>A feature that is currently not specifically modeled at all in TEI, but which serves
               a similar purpose to both stamp and seal, and even appears similar to both, is a
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">rota</foreign> or monogram. Both are handwritten or
               hand-drawn devices involving the names or initials of the issuer of the document,
               formalized enough to be recognizable as separate from other forms of signing. A
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">rota</foreign> is a specific, papal form of the monogram,
               which is characteristic enough to be described using its own term and structured
               similarly to a stamp (see <ptr type="crossref" target="#rotapope"/>). Similarly to
               the stamp and seal above, the <foreign xml:lang="la">rota</foreign> contains both
               textual and figural elements, arranged in a formalized and consistent way, serving to
               establish the authenticity of the sender of the document. The round format of the
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">rota</foreign> and the consistent styling of the materials
               within directly invoke the style of seals or stamps, and contain notable similarities
               with the specific papal version of the seal, the leaden <term>bull</term> (<ptr
                  type="crossref" target="#leadenbull"/>).</p>
            <p>Extending the idea of a drawn device that represents the person and authority of the
               drafter, the notarial signet is a related conventional symbol in the form of a
               drawing (often with writing) that stands in for the person preparing or acting in a
               notarial authority for the document. A similar element, unique to the papal
               chancellery, is the <term>Bene Valete</term> (<ptr type="crossref"
                  target="#benevalete"/>), which is structured like a monogram and accompanies the
               other elements of papal authentication, like the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >rota</foreign> and signature as well as the bull (papal seal, <ptr
                  type="crossref" target="#leadenbull"/>).</p>
            <p>All of these features are supplemented (or, in many modern European and American
               cases, replaced) by the autograph signature (as pictured in <ptr type="crossref"
                  target="#subscription"/>), but that is far from the only version of signing used
               historically, and the cross, and in some cases fingerprints, used for signing work
               equivalently to indicate consent to the terms of a document. Indeed, seals, stamps,
               signatures, and crosses all have overlapping uses for asserting assent. Crosses were
               commonly used by witnesses to documents when the witnesses did not attach their own
               seals. Crosses overlap with signatures for the illiterate, and did so into the recent
               past. Stamps used for signing are still current in East Asia and coexist with
               signatures on documents throughout the world, often asserting that the person signing
               has the authority to sign on behalf of an organization or institution, represented by
               the stamp. An interesting case of the coexistence of stamps and crosses and
               signatures was documented by <ref xml:id="ref8" type="bibl" target="#ramble2018"
                  >Ramble (2018)</ref>, who additionally finds inked fingerprints thrown into the
               mix. He tracks changes in the documentary practice of the Mustang region of Nepal
               from inked stamps (associated with Tibetan practices) to fingerprints (associated
               with Indian, perhaps British Raj, practice), these practices corresponding to a
               movement from Tibetan to Nepali legal terms. Fingerprints (and handprints, in some
               examples) can be clearly seen to replace stamps on a one-for-one basis, demonstrating
               their analogous authentication value.<note>Going beyond medieval examples, a
                  technology which also uses fingerprints, biometric identity management, once the
                  purview of science fiction, has become increasingly common in personal computing
                  devices: iOS and Android devices, among others, support fingerprint or facial
                  recognition technology, supplementing traditional passwords (<ref xml:id="ref9"
                     type="bibl" target="#mac2018"><title level="a">Use Touch ID on your Mac</title>
                     n.d.</ref>; <ref xml:id="ref10" type="bibl" target="#biometrics2018"><title
                        level="a">Biometrics</title> n.d.</ref>). Future technology may include
                  retina or iris scans (already in use at airport gates), fingerprints (associated
                  with biometric passports), and other biometric data associated with a record in
                  order to establish its identity.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As the above examples show, there are a range of technologies and practices which
               bleed together both in their place on a visual spectrum and in their practical use,
               and can thus be productively classified together, serving a similar function to
               seals, often with similar forms, but not yet described by the TEI. Other less
               obviously similar practices also serve a similar function, which we can easily infer
               through their co-use in service to proving the authenticity of documents, though they
               may not immediately be visually similar. An interesting medieval example is what I
               will call <soCalled>split medium</soCalled> authentication, and includes a number of
               related practices: chirographs, polls, indentures, and tally sticks.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="beyondseals">
            <head>Beyond Seals and Stamps: Medium as Authentication</head>
            <figure xml:id="chirograph">
               <graphic url="img/chirograph.jpg" width="735px" height="600px"/>
               <head type="legend">Chirograph from 1177, Departmental Archives of Val-d’Oise, part
                  of the virtual exhibition <title level="m">Ciro graphum, un charte exceptionnelle
                     de 1177</title> (<ptr
                     target="http://archives.valdoise.fr/expositions/exposition-ciro-graphum-une-charte-exceptionnelle-de-3/n:213"
                  />). Paris, Archives nationales, <idno>AE/II/181</idno> digitally reunited with
                  Pontoise, Archives départementales du Val-d’Oise, <idno>9 H 81</idno>.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Chirographs are a medieval practice of authenticating documents, named from the
               practice of writing the word <foreign xml:lang="la">chirographum</foreign> (with
               inconsistent orthography), which means <q>handwritten</q>, between two identical
               copies of the same document and then cutting the two halves apart through the word,
               so that the parts can be recombined to show that the word lines up exactly. Actual
               practices vary, and need not include the word <foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >chirographum</foreign>, but rely instead on images (see <ptr type="crossref"
                  target="#chirograph"/>) or the shape of the cut: wavy cuts are called polls,
               jagged (<soCalled>teeth-like</soCalled>) cuts are called indentures, and some
               chirographs might have three parts. A similar split-medium practice exists for
               account sticks, called tally sticks, which would be broken as a receipt, such that
               the splinters would uniquely match the account and prove that it had been paid. The
               medium is itself authenticating in a way that is simply not the case in ordinary
               documents. In <ptr type="crossref" target="#chirograph"/>, an example with both seals
               and chirograph attests to their shared use, as the authority of either half does not
               rest entirely upon the seals, but rather upon the status of each half lining up with
               its mate. In practice, chirographs, polls, and indentures circulated widely without
               seals, the split itself being sufficient authentication.</p>
            <p>Another authenticating medium is so-called <soCalled>banknote paper</soCalled>, a
               special blend of different materials and fibers that is distinctive and can only be
               manufactured by specialized producers. An additional physical aspect of the medium,
               the watermark traditionally laid into paper, serves to identify the maker, and in the
               case of banknotes and other secure media serves to identify the paper as being made
               of the proper material (and presumably under the proper authority). Offices and
               individuals have long used basic authentication through physical media by writing or
               typing letters on institutional or individualized letterhead, controlling access to
               the stationery in order to protect its authority.</p>
            <p>Going beyond the medium, there is a category of practices which combine physical
               characteristics and printing (spanning practices that are almost all the former to
               practices that are all the latter) in the service of authentication: security
               printing. This can include micrography (extremely small type that is hard to
               duplicate because cutting such fine dies is expensive) and unique typefaces with
               distinctive, purposeful irregularities that, owing to their very imperfections, are
               harder to duplicate than perfectly regular typefaces. It includes guilloche patterns,
               intricate and regular patterns that are hard to duplicate when cutting dies for
                  printing.<note>After all, printed type and printed banknotes are produced through
                  functionally the same process as stamping a document, and the use of dies differs
                  little from pressing a matrix into wax to seal it.</note> Other forms of security
               printing include the use of special inks, including inks designed to fluoresce in
               various wavelengths of light. Such inks are used in Canadian passports, where under
               UV light, Parliament Hill is surrounded by colorful fireworks, as it is on Canada
               Day.</p>
            <p>Following this chain of physical interventions in the service of authentication, one
               of the best ways to be assured that material is authentic is to receive it directly
               from a trusted source in a controlled manner. For a medieval document, a continuous
               chain of transmission through known and documented sources may suffice, as would
               continuous presence in a trusted and secure archival context. Ethiopian charters were
               often copied into the margins of <soCalled>golden gospels</soCalled> or other locally
               important manuscripts that would be well guarded by the local church and community.
               Presence in the margins of these sacred works ensured preservation and guarded
               against independently circulating forgeries. An example, from a copy of the <foreign
                  xml:lang="eth">Mäṣḥafä gizeyat</foreign>(a lectionary with extracts from the
                  <foreign xml:lang="eth">Wəddase Maryam</foreign>, <title level="a">Praise of
                  Mary</title>) of Zala ʾƎnda ʾAmanuʾel Church in Tigray, has been discussed
               elsewhere, in terms of its clear documentary characteristics, despite not sharing
               much in material format with the typical single-page European charter (<ref
                  xml:id="ref11" type="bibl" target="#wion2018">Wion 2018</ref>; <ref xml:id="ref12"
                  type="bibl" target="#vogeler2018">Vogeler 2018</ref>). Similarly to storage in a
               locked safe, packaging or enclosure (where tamper-resistant) assures the recipient
               that the item has been delivered in an unaltered condition. Security bags, security
               tape, tamper seals (on pharmaceuticals, for example), and lamination of documents all
               serve to establish the unaltered character of the material so enclosed, and therefore
               its unforged authenticity.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="genericelement">
            <head>5 A Generic Element: <gi scheme="TEI">authen</gi></head>
            <p>In order to clearly model all of these related practices, and in the interest of not
               favoring one period or type of document over another, a generic element seems both
               desirable and advisable. The proposed element, as implemented in the TEI_CEI
                  ODD,<note>See the <ref xml:id="ref13" type="bibl" target="#winslowetal2019"
                     >CEI2TEI GitHub repository, accessed June 25, 2021</ref>, <ptr
                     target="https://github.com/GVogeler/CEI2TEI/blob/master/tei_cei.odd"/>.</note>
               is simple (<ident>attList</ident> items suppressed for brevity: they follow the
               top-level distinctions in the sample controlled vocabulary visualized in <ptr
                  type="crossref" target="#example4"/>):</p>
            <figure xml:id="example4">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <elementSpec ident="authen" mode="add ">    <desc>Description of an element that
                        is used to authenticate a document. Specifically, elements that would be
                        intended, from a juridical perspective, to be authenticating. May contain a
                        forged element, in which case the forgery should be noted and certainty
                        marked.</desc>   <classes>      <memberOf key="att.dateable"/> 
                               <memberOf key="att.global"/>      <memberOf key="att.typed"/> 
                               <memberOf key="model.inter"/>    </classes>    <content> 
                               <alternate minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded">      <classRef
                              key="model.pLike"/>         <classRef key="model.limitedPhrase"/> 
                                      <elementRef key="decoNote"/>          <elementRef
                              key="condition"/>         </alternate>        </content> 
                              <attList>        ...    </attList>  </elementSpec>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend"><gi scheme="TEI">elementSpec</gi> with content model for element
                     <gi scheme="TEI">authen</gi>.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>This feature genericizes the combination of physical/textual and paratextual elements
               in a seal to cover a whole range of authenticating features, serving not only the
               specific needs of charters encoding in the TEI, but also allowing for a fuller and
               more intercultural understanding of the nature of authenticating features that may be
               analogous to sealing in various contexts. By choosing to encode using <gi
                  scheme="TEI">authen</gi>, a richer, fuller, and more accurate view of the material
               can be encoded, as the intended context of these features (and with it the fullness
               of their import) is not discarded. It has a broader content model than <gi
                  scheme="TEI">seal</gi>, specifically <ident>model.LimitedPhrase</ident>, which is
               needed to cover all of the use cases of the CEI but also importantly captures
                  <ident>model.pPart.msdesc</ident>, with a number of elements that are useful for
               describing seals themselves, as well as other types of authentication. Currently,
               this element is implemented in the TEI_CEI ODD for encoding charters, but the
               principles outlined here suggest that it should be available for broader use in the
               TEI. Alongside these changes, for the purposes of the TEI_CEI ODD, <gi scheme="TEI"
                  >sealDesc</gi> has been renamed to <gi scheme="TEI">authDesc</gi>, to make the
               semantics consistent and understandable to the user.</p>
            <p>In order to control the wide range of different variants of this practice, here is a
               proposed vocabulary, provided in SKOS (Simple Knowledge Organization System) format
               (as part of the project’s <ref
                  target="https://github.com/GVogeler/CEI2TEI/blob/master/Authentication/authen.skos.ttl"
                  > GitHub repository</ref>,<note>Accessed July 13, 2021, <ptr
                     target="https://github.com/GVogeler/CEI2TEI/blob/master/Authentication/authen.skos.ttl"
                  />.</note> at <ptr
                  target="https://github.com/GVogeler/CEI2TEI/blob/master/Authentication/authen.skos.ttl"
               />, which allows the identification of individual items of authentication from a
               large list. It is the product of a preliminary categorization of the various types of
               authentication that might appear in text-bearing objects encoded in the TEI P5. A
               visualization of this scheme, which was used in the preparation of the SKOS
               vocabulary, is reproduced in the appendix of this article. With the combination of
               this basic element and the wide range of potential subtype pointers (or equivalent
               modification of the ODD to enforce a project-specific <ident>attList</ident>), it
               should be possible to model a wide range of text-bearing documents, from ancient
               seals to modern banknotes and passports, as well as to enrich content-based markup of
               important paratextual authenticating elements.</p>
            <p>It is my hope that this element, if picked up, will go some way toward allowing for
               more meaningful markup of a broad swath of transregional paratextual practices,
               helping TEI transcend some of its narrowly constructed limitations in the approach to
               such subjects from one specific regional/disciplinary perspective.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <!-- the bibliography for the article, organized as a series of <bibl> elements inside <listBibl> -->
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="biometrics2018"><title level="a">Biometrics.</title>
                  <author>Android Open Source Project</author>. <date>Accessed December 4,
                     2018</date>. <ref target="https://source.android.com/security/biometric"
                     >https://source.android.com/security/biometric</ref>.</bibl>
               <!--<bibl xml:id="boyle1992"><author>Boyle, Leonard E.</author>
                  <date>1992</date>. <title level="a">Diplomatics.</title> In <title level="m"
                     >Medieval Studies: An Introduction</title>, edited by <editor>James M.
                     Powell</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">82–113</biblScope>. <edition>2nd
                     ed.</edition>
                  <pubPlace>Syracuse, NY</pubPlace>: <publisher>Syracuse University
                     Press</publisher>.</bibl>-->
               <bibl xml:id="chango2012"><author>Chango, Mawaki</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title
                     level="u">Becoming Artifacts: Medieval Seals, Passports and the Future of
                     Digital Identity.</title> PhD diss., <publisher>Syracuse
                  University</publisher>. <ref target="https://surface.syr.edu/it_etd/74"
                     >https://surface.syr.edu/it_etd/74</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="clemensetal2007"><author>Clemens, Raymond</author>, and <author>Timothy
                     Graham</author>. <date>2007</date>. <title level="m">Introduction to Manuscript
                     Studies.</title><pubPlace>Ithaca, NY</pubPlace>: <publisher>Cornell University
                     Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <!--              orphan reference: this entry is referenced in two other entries, even though it’s not cited directly in the text. This is acceptable in Chicago style. .-->
               <bibl xml:id="collon1987"><author>Collon, Dominique</author>. <date>1987</date>.
                     <title level="m">First impressions: cylinder seals in the Ancient Near
                     East.</title><pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>British
                  Museum</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="cubelicetal2018"><editor>Cubelic, Simon</editor>, <editor>Axel
                     Michaels</editor>, and <editor>Astrid Zotter</editor>, eds. <date>2018</date>.
                     <title level="m">Studies in Historical Documents from Nepal and
                     India.</title><series>Documenta Nepalica</series>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Heidelberg</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Heidelberg University Publishing</publisher>.
                  doi:10.17885/heiup.331.454.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="cummings2017"><author>Cummings, James</author>. <date>2017</date>.
                     <title level="a">Manuscript Description.</title> Chap. 3 in <title level="m"
                     >Digital Editing of Medieval Texts: A Textbook</title>,edited by
                     <editor>Marjorie Burghart</editor>. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>N.p</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://www.digitalmanuscripts.eu//wp-content/uploads/2017/09/03-ms-desc-JC.pdf"
                  />; <ptr target="https://www.digitalmanuscripts.eu/?page_id=648"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="mabillon1681"><author>Mabillon, Jean</author>. <date>1681</date>.
                     <title level="m">De re diplomatica libri
                  VI.</title><pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>.</bibl>
               <!--      <bibl xml:id="macneilletal2005"><author>MacNeil, Heather</author>, <author>Chen
                     Wei</author>, <author>Luciana Duranti</author>, <author>Anne
                     Gilland-Swetland</author>, <author>Maria Guercio</author>, <author>Yvette
                     Hackett</author>, <author>Babak Hamidzadeh</author>, et al. <date>2005</date>.
                     <title level="a">Authenticity Task Force Report.</title> Chap. 1 in <title
                     level="m">The Long-term Preservation of Authentic Electronic Records: the
                     findings of the InterPARES Project,</title>edited by <editor>Luciana
                     Duranti</editor>. <pubPlace>Italia</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>Archilab</publisher>.</bibl>-->
               <!--  <bibl xml:id="charlemagne2015"><author>The Making of Charlemagne’s Europe
                     (768–814)</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title level="m">User Guide for Data
                     Entry.</title>Version 18. The Making of Charlemagne’s Europe (768–814).
                     <date>Last revised January 20</date>. <ref
                     target="http://www.charlemagneseurope.ac.uk/media/uploads/charlemagne_project_user_guide_v18.pdf"
                     >http://www.charlemagneseurope.ac.uk/media/uploads/charlemagne_project_user_guide_v18.pdf</ref>.</bibl>-->
               <bibl xml:id="monumenta2019"><title level="a">Monumenta Germaniae Historica:
                     Constitutiones et acta publica imperatorum et regum 1357–1378.</title>
                  <date>2019</date>. <publisher>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der
                     Wissenschaften</publisher>. Accessed <date>July 22</date>. <ref
                     target="http://telota.bbaw.de/constitutiones/index.html"
                     >http://telota.bbaw.de/constitutiones/index.html</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="new2010"><author>New, Elizabeth A</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title
                     level="m">Seals and Sealing Practices</title>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>British Records Association</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ramble2018"><author>Ramble, Charles</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title
                     level="a">Producing <q>South Asian</q> Tibetan Documents in Highland Nepal,
                     19th to 20th Centuries: The Emergence and Disappearance of a Local Diplomatic
                     Tradition.</title> In <editor>Cubelic</editor>, <editor>Michaels</editor>, and
                     <editor>Zotter</editor>
                  <ref type="bibl" target="#cubelicetal2018"><date>2018</date></ref>, <biblScope
                     unit="page">111–33</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ruck1996"><editor>Rück, Peter</editor>, ed. <date>1996</date>. <title
                     level="m">Graphische Symbole in mittelalterlichen Urkunden: Beiträge zur
                     diplomatischen Semiotik</title>. <series>Historische
                     Hilfswissenschaften</series>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Sigmaringen</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Jan Thorbecke</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="sopracasaetal2020"><author>Sopracasa, Alessio</author>, and
                     <author>Martina Filosa</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">Encoding
                     Byzantine Seals: SigiDoc</title>, in <title level="m">Atti del IX Convegno
                     Annuale AIUCD. La svolta inevitabile: sfide e prospettive per l`Informatica
                     Umanistica</title>, <biblScope unit="page">240–45</biblScope>.
                     <pubPlace>Milano</pubPlace>: <publisher>Università Cattolica del Sacro
                     Cuore</publisher>. <ref
                     target="http://aiucd2020.unicatt.it/aiucd-Sopracasa_Filosa.pdf"
                     >http://aiucd2020.unicatt.it/aiucd-Sopracasa_Filosa.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tei2019"><author>TEI Consortium</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title
                     level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                     Interchange</title>. Version 3.6.0. Last updated <date>July 19</date>.
                     <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>: <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>. <ref
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.6.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"
                     >https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.6.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="mac2018"><title level="a">Use Touch ID on your Mac</title>.<title
                     level="m">MacOS User Guide</title>. <publisher>Apple Inc</publisher>. Accessed
                     <date>December 4, 2018</date>. <ref
                     target="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT207054"
                     >https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT207054</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="valla1440"><author>Valla, Lorenzo</author>. <date>1440</date>. <title
                     level="m">De falso credita et ementita Constantini Donatione
                  declamatio</title>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="vogeler2018"><author>Vogeler, Georg</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title
                     level="a">Digital Diplomatics: The Evolution of a European Tradition or a
                     Generic Concept?</title> In <editor>Cubelic</editor>,
                  <editor>Michaels</editor>, and <editor>Zotter</editor>
                  <ref type="bibl" target="#cubelicetal2018"><date>2018</date></ref>, <biblScope
                     unit="page">85–109</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="vogeleretal2018"><author>Vogeler, Georg</author>, et al.
                     <date>2018</date>. <title level="m">CEI – Charters Encoding Initiative</title>.
                  Accessed <date>December 4</date>. <ref target="https://www.cei.lmu.de"
                     >https://www.cei.lmu.de</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="winslowetal2019"><author>Winslow, Sean M</author>., and <author>Georg
                     Vogeler</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title level="m">CEI2TEI.</title>Github.
                  Last revised <date>June 21</date>. <ref
                     target="https://github.com/GVogeler/CEI2TEI"
                     >https://github.com/GVogeler/CEI2TEI</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="wion2018"><author>Wion, Anaïs</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title
                     level="a">The TEI-XML Architecture of <title level="m">Ethiopian Manuscript
                        Archives</title>: Respecting the Integrity of Primary Sources and Asserting
                     Editorial Choices</title>. <title level="m">Comparative Oriental Manuscript
                     Studies Bulletin</title><biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">(1)</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">33–38</biblScope>.
                     <ptr target="https://www.aai.uni-hamburg.de/en/comst/pdf/bulletin4-1/33-38.pdf"
                  />.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>Addendum: Preliminary Work on Classification of Authenticating Features</head>
            <figure xml:id="figure7">
               <graphic url="img/visualrep.jpg" width="1407px" height="1827px"/>
               <head type="legend">Visual representation of the organization behind the vocabulary
                  of authenticating elements.</head>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
