<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- $Id: jtei-cc-ra-mcallister-185-source.xml 1043 2021-06-01 09:40:20Z tiago.sousa-garcia $ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI.internal">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Quotes, Paraphrases, and Allusions: Text Reuse in Sanskrit
               Commentaries and How to Encode It</title>
            <!-- author information in separate <author> elements per author -->
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Patrick</forename>
                  <surname>McAllister</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation><!-- a prose description of this author's affiliation, containing <roleName> and <orgName>-->Patrick
                  McAllister is currently a <roleName>researcher</roleName> at the <orgName>Austrian
                     Academy of Sciences’ Institute for the Cultural and Intellectual History of
                     Asia</orgName>. His main research interest is the development of Buddhist
                  epistemological theories during the ninth to eleventh centuries (primarily in the
                  works of Prajñākaragupta, Jñānaśrīmitra, and Ratnakīrti).</affiliation>
               <email>patrick.mcallister@​oeaw.ac.at</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>10/04/2021</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <editor role="guest">Susan Schreibman</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
            <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
            <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="13">Selected Papers from the 2018 TEI Conference</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for
               journals in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking
               to publish full-text articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <!-- a list of keywords, each in its own <term> -->
               <term>scholarly Sanskrit</term>
               <term>commentaries</term>
               <term>quotations</term>
               <term>linked texts</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="TSG" when="2021-03-15">Final corrections</change>
         <change who="TSG" when="2021-03-12">Added encoding for sigla, corrected xml:lang, created
            appendix, other small corrections</change>
         <change who="TSG" when="2021-03-10">Finished encoding the article</change>
         <change who="TSG" when="2021-03-09">Started encoding of the article</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p> The Sanskrit literary genre of commentaries has several characteristics that are a
               challenge to the structural encoding of its texts. One particular tricky feature is
               the skillful and sophisticated reuse of text in such commentaries. This article
               examines practical examples of encoding these types of passages, drawing on the
               documents of <ref target="https://sarit.indology.info/">SARIT</ref><note><ptr
                     target="https://sarit.indology.info/"/></note> (Search and Retrieval of Indic
               Texts) and the author’s own encoding projects.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <!-- text divisions, each with an @xml:id and <head> -->
         <div xml:id="div1">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>This article explores possibilities for encoding the reuse of text in the works of
               the logico-epistemological school of Buddhism in South Asia (the texts of the <title
                  level="m" xml:lang="sa">pramāṇavādin</title>s). This school starts in about the
               fifth century CE in South Asia with Dignāga (ca 480 – ca 540 CE) and continues to
               produce texts up to around the thirteenth century. This corpus of Sanskrit literature
               consists of roughly 150 works, which were written by at least, but not many more
               than, forty authors. In terms of volume, again roughly speaking, the relevant section
               of the Tibetan canon, which includes translations of a significant number of these
               Sanskrit texts, is around 25 MB in size (encoded in ASCII). For comparison, a simple
                  <soCalled>text-only</soCalled> measurement of the Folger Shakespeare edition
               results in approximately 8 MB of such raw text.<note>The Shakespeare estimate is
                  based on measuring the result of <code lang="XPath">//text()</code> on the XML
                  files in <ptr
                     target="http://www.folgerdigitaltexts.org/download/xml/FolgerDigitalTexts_XML_Complete.zip"
                  />, downloaded 2018-09-11. So this includes any notes or additional material. The
                     <foreign xml:lang="sa">bstan ’gyur</foreign> section of the Tibetan canon as
                  downloaded from <ptr
                     target="https://asianclassics.org/data/TENGYUR%20(Roman%20%20%20Letters).zip"
                  />(md5sum: 4c6cb125c9eb8c6cfffa08e3da232010, downloaded 2019-05-07) has a zipped
                  size of 76 MB, and of 244 MB unzipped. It contains hardly any additional content
                  like editorial comments or markup. The subdirectory <ident>TENGYUR (Roman
                     Letters)/11_TSAD_MA</ident>, which contains many of the texts that belong to
                  the group being discussed here in their Tibetan translation, is 25 MB in size.
                  Other common measures of the size of collections do not easily transfer to the
                  texts under consideration here: in the absence of a reliable tokenizer for
                  Sanskrit combined with the characteristic lack of space between words, the number
                  of distinct tokens in our collection remains a guess (see Hellwig [<ref
                     type="bibl" xml:id="refHel" target="#Hellwig2015">2015</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                     xml:id="refHel2" target="#Hellwig2016">2016</ref>] for the state of the art and
                  limitations to Sanskrit tokenizing and splitting). In a recent printed edition,
                  the Tibetan section of <foreign xml:lang="sa">pramāṇa</foreign> texts (<foreign
                     xml:lang="sa">tshad ma</foreign>) including minimal notes runs to approximately
                  18,000 pages in twelve volumes (see <ref type="bibl" xml:id="refKrung"
                     target="#krung19942009" xml:lang="sa">krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug lte gnas
                     kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang 1994–2009, vols. 97–108</ref>).</note> These
               texts of the logico-epistemological school of Buddhism range in extent from a few
               hundred words to multivolume works. Not all texts survive in their original language,
               Sanskrit. Some are accessible only in translations, usually Tibetan ones, and others
               are known only through fragments surviving in other texts. Many of those texts that
               do survive in their original have not been critically edited.</p>
            <p>Recent years have witnessed increased efforts to understand the various literary and
               social conventions that are characteristic of premodern South Asian literature, which
               this group of works belongs to. <ref type="bibl" xml:id="FresRef" target="#Freschi2015">Freschi (2015)</ref>, introducing a two-volume collection of
               specialist papers on text reuse in South Asian literature, provides a succinct
               overview of the expectations, difficulties, and hermeneutic considerations attached
               to the editing of these texts. Freschi (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="FresRef2"
                  target="#Freschi2015">2015, 86–87</ref>) distinguishes three reasons for studying
               the reuse of text: first, it aids textual criticism, allowing the reconstitution of
               texts and increasing the certainty of editorial decisions; second, it facilitates a
               clearer understanding of the relations between works (and their authors); third, it
               provides an opportunity for reflecting on <quote source="#quote1">historically
                  conditioned notions of <term>text</term>, <term>author</term>,
                     <term>originality</term>, <term>copyright</term> and so on</quote> (<ref
                  type="bibl" xml:id="quote1" target="#Freschi2015">Freschi 2015,
                  87</ref>).<note>Freschi and Maas (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="quote2"
                     target="#Freschietal2017b">2017b, 13–21</ref>) develop the notion of <quote
                     source="#quote2">adaptive reuse</quote>, where a significant and inseparable
                  element of text reuse is the intention that is attached to it.</note> Most of
               these questions are outside the focus of this article, however. It aims one level
               below them: how to provide scholars and editors with the basis for making such
               judgments or decisions.</p>
            <p>The term <term>text reuse</term>, furthermore, is broad. Even in the literature that
               deals with the texts under consideration, it subsumes such varied notions as
                  <term>citation</term>, <term>quote</term>, <term>quasi-quotation</term>,
                  <term>report</term>, <term>passages that have been silently used</term>, or
               <term>secondary usage</term>.<note>See <ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref1" target="#Steinkellner2017">Steinkellner (2017, xii–xiii)</ref> for the various
                  phenomena considered, as well as <ref type="bibl" xml:id="quote3" target="#Preisendanz2008">Preisendanz (2008, 611)</ref> for the <quote source="#quote3"
                     >quasi-quotations</quote>.</note>
               <term>Quotation</term> is too narrow a category to subsume even the most basic cases
               of intratextual relations that are encountered in these texts.</p>
            <p>To understand the phenomena that the term <term>reuse</term> is supposed to cover
               here, it is first necessary to delimit and characterize this group of texts. These
               texts fall mainly within two categories: some of them belong to the literary genre
               called <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhāṣya</foreign> (commentary). The others are
               independent treatises that are mostly dedicated to a particular topic, either
               refuting opposing views or establishing tenets of this Buddhist group as the author
               saw them. The works of both groups are composed in what is often referred to as a
                  <quote source="#quote5">nominal style</quote> (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="quote5"
                  target="#Jacobi1903">Jacobi 1903</ref>), a style that avoids the complex verb
               forms that Sanskrit can boast of and favors formally simpler noun formations. This
               leads to a high degree of abstraction and compression.</p>
            <p>More significantly for our purposes, however, these texts share a certain set of ways
               to make use of other texts.<note>An accessible overview to the <term xml:lang="sa"
                     >bhāṣya</term> style is given by Tubb and Boose (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref3"
                     target="#Tubbetal2007">2007</ref>). Apart from the observations on the general
                  purpose and techniques of commentaries in Sanskrit traditions, they discuss the
                  most common ways in which a commentary can quote or paraphrase the base text for
                  the purpose of explaining it.</note> This method, or technique, consists of
               several acceptable conventions that can, at first glance, all be classified as
               quotes, either explicit or not, and that can show strongly diverging degrees of literal
               accuracy.</p>
            <p>A formal system of analysis for these occurrences was developed by Ernst Steinkellner
               for printed critical editions. This system is the most differentiated that has been
               advanced for the classification of intertextual relations in the field of Buddhist
               studies. Its purpose is as follows:</p>
            <cit><quote source="#quote4">It is with a view to providing a fairly general system of
                  categories for differentiating between the various materials available as witness
                  for original Sanskrit texts in their degree of testimonial validity that I would
                  like to present below a more detailed list of kinds of text.</quote> <ref
                  type="bibl" xml:id="quote4" target="#Steinkellner1988">Steinkellner 1988,
                  112</ref></cit>
            <p>The system defines a set of sigla that are to be used for the characterization of
               reused text. The most important ones are these:<note>This reference system was
                  formalized by Steinkellner (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="refStein" target="#Steinkellner1988">1988, 116–18</ref>), and revised in later publications,
                  e.g., <ref type="bibl" xml:id="refSteinetal" target="#Steinkellneretal2005">Steinkellner, Krasser, and Lasic (2005, 1:lii–liv)</ref>. The latest version is
                  described and argued for by Steinkellner (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="refStein2017" target="#Steinkellner2017">2017, xx–xxv</ref>). Here, only the more
                  common cases will be discussed.</note>
            </p>
            <list type="gloss">
               <label><mentioned>T</mentioned>:</label>
               <item><foreign xml:lang="la">textus</foreign>, the text being edited;</item>
               <label><mentioned>Ce</mentioned>:</label>
               <item><foreign xml:lang="la">citatum ex alio</foreign>, a quotation from another text
                  in <mentioned>T</mentioned>;</item>
               <label><mentioned>Ce'</mentioned>:</label>
               <item><mentioned>Ce</mentioned>
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">usus secundarii</foreign> in <mentioned>T</mentioned>:
                  like <mentioned>Ce</mentioned>, but not explicitly acknowledged as a quote;</item>
               <label><mentioned>e</mentioned>:</label>
               <item>added to <mentioned>Ce</mentioned> or <mentioned>Ce'</mentioned>: signifying
                     <foreign xml:lang="la">modus edendi</foreign>, that the reused text was
                  modified by the person quoting it;</item>
               <label><mentioned>Ci</mentioned>:</label>
               <item>
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">citatum in alio</foreign>, quotation of
                     <mentioned>T</mentioned> in another text, again with the possible addition of
                  an apostrophe (<mentioned>'</mentioned>) or an <mentioned>e</mentioned>, yielding
                     <mentioned>Ci'</mentioned>, <mentioned>Cie</mentioned>, and
                     <mentioned>Ci'e</mentioned>;</item>
               <label><mentioned>R</mentioned>:</label>
               <item><foreign xml:lang="la">citatum in alio modo referendi</foreign>, a span of text
                  in <mentioned>T</mentioned> that is referred to in a later work.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Each combination of sigla is usually followed by either a bibliographic reference to
               an edition of the related text, or, if the text has not been edited, the name of the
               related text.</p>
            <p>The individual letters used in this system of characterization have separate and
               rather diverse functions. The initial capital, <mentioned>T</mentioned>,
                  <mentioned>C</mentioned>, or <mentioned>R</mentioned>, qualifies a span of text
               either, in the case of <mentioned>T</mentioned>, as the aim of the editorial
               endeavor, or, in the other cases, as a passage that has been found to be reused.</p>
            <p>The second character, <mentioned>i</mentioned> or <mentioned>e</mentioned>, indicates
               the direction of reuse, either in another text or from another text.<note>The
                  qualifier <mentioned>i</mentioned> is of somewhat limited use in the present investigation: if a passage
                  in a given text is marked like this, it is mainly a helpful reminder to the reader
                  that the passage in question is quoted somewhere else, and that this occurrence
                  has been considered in editing the present text. It does not actually mark the
                  passage as a quotation in the context of the text being edited.</note> In a recent
               explanation of the symbol <mentioned>e</mentioned>, Steinkellner (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#Steinkellner2017" xml:id="refSte">2017, xii, n. 4</ref>) has made it
               explicit that it should not be understood to imply direct quotation: if the reuse of
               text A in text B is marked by an editor of text B with the appropriate symbols
                  (<mentioned>Ce</mentioned>, <mentioned>Ce'</mentioned>, etc.), we should not
               conclude that the editor is asserting that the author of text B had direct access to
               text A.<note>This distinction becomes relevant when a passage is reused more than
                  once by subsequent authors, or when it is contained in a passage that is itself a
                  case of text reuse. See the discussion of <ref type="crossref"
                     target="#example_8">example 8</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This second character is, furthermore, defined from the perspective of the edited
               text. Any passage in text B that is marked as a case of reuse of text A
                  (<mentioned>Ce</mentioned> etc.) commits the editor to acknowledging a
               corresponding <mentioned>Ci</mentioned> in the (perhaps hypothetical) edition of text
               A. This <mentioned>Ci</mentioned> in text A is also fully dependent on the
                  <mentioned>Ce</mentioned> in text B: obviously, nothing about a passage marked as
                  <mentioned>Ci</mentioned> indicates that it is reused in another text, and it is
               only by finding it reused in that other text that we can classify it in this way.</p>
            <p>The decision whether this span of text is to be characterized as <term>secondary
                  usage</term>, signalled by adding an apostrophe as the third character, is usually
               derived from the context in which the passage appears, the para-text surrounding the
               reused span of text. Any certainty in this regard is usually due to the author
               explicitly saying that the current passage was said, thought, or held by someone. The
               addition of this apostrophe is a binary sign: either a passage is reused secondarily,
               or it is not. It allows no further differentiation.</p>
            <p>The presence of the final letter, <mentioned>e</mentioned> (for <foreign
                  xml:lang="la">modus edendi</foreign>), is supposed to reflect the editor’s
               estimate of the difference between the reused text as it appears in a source and as
               it appears in the context of its reuse, insofar as one might reasonably assume that
               differences are due to an intentional change by the author of the text that
               incorporates the passage from another. Several editors (including this writer) have
               found it hard to give good reasons for this kind of decision in their editions, and
               have avoided the use of this category altogether.<note>Steinkellner (<ref type="bibl"
                     xml:id="quote6" target="#Steinkellner2017">2017, xxv</ref>) has recently
                  maintained: <quote source="#quote6">When comparing two texts, it is not always
                     possible to determine the nature and origin of specific noticeable differences,
                     yet the difference between changes due to a text being adapted to a new context
                     and those due to scribal and/or editorial work is usually recognizable.</quote>
                  There is, as yet, no consensus on this point.</note> In any case, this siglum
               never was intended to characterize differences that could be due to simple mistakes
               in copying manuscripts, but to mark intentional changes on the part of the author
               reusing the text. This siglum is again a binary operator, and as such allows only for
               a basic distinction without further characterization.</p>
            <p>Even though this system of characterizations has been criticized in recent years
               because of a basic impossibility of being certain about which copy of a text an
               author quoting another text might have had,<note>Steinkellner (<ref type="bibl"
                     xml:id="ref4" target="#Steinkellner2017">2017, xxi–xxv</ref>) summarizes and
                  responds to the main concerns that have been raised against his suggestions. Since
                  the debate is, by and large, about the certainty that can be had about what these
                  symbols posit about a span of text, the issues raised should be further discussed
                  in publications pertinent to the corresponding field of research.</note> it cannot
               be disputed that the distinctions in the conceptual space opened up by this analysis
               are significant and useful ones for any research concerned with these kinds of texts:
               <mentioned>C</mentioned> and <mentioned>R</mentioned> mark reused material as either literally accurate or only paraphrased or
               alluded to; <mentioned>e</mentioned>, together with a source description, makes it clear where the quote is
               from; the apostrophe (<mentioned>'</mentioned>) reflects a basic observation about
               the passage’s context in the text being edited (whether it occurs as an explicit
               quote or not). And the final, optional <mentioned>e</mentioned> represents the editor’s estimate of the
               quoted material’s accuracy as a representation of the source.</p>
            <p>In the rest of this article, these categories will be applied to some sample passages
               using the conceptual framework of the TEI Guidelines. The purpose is to illustrate
               light-weight markup rules for some general cases of textual reuse in the works of
               this genre that allow for easy querying of the resulting structured information.
               Before doing that, however, it will be useful to briefly consider the current
               infrastructure that the version 4.1 of the Guidelines (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref6"
                  target="#TEI2020">TEI Consortium 2020</ref>) offers as to its general
               applicability to these phenomena.</p>
            <div xml:id="div1.1">
               <head>Markup of quotations in the TEI P5 Guidelines version 4.1</head>
               <p>The part of the TEI P5 Guidelines version 4.1 most relevant to our inquiry is
                  section <ref
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#COHQQ"
                     >3.3.3: Quotation</ref> (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref5" target="#TEI2020">TEI
                     Consortium 2020</ref>). It occurs within a longer section that <quote
                     source="#quote7"><gap/> deals with a variety of textual features, all of which
                     have in common that they are frequently realized in conventional printing
                     practice by the use of such features as underlining, italic fonts, or quotation
                     marks, collectively referred to here as <emph>highlighting</emph></quote> (<ref
                     type="bibl" xml:id="quote7" target="#TEI2020">TEI Consortium 2020, 3.3: <ptr
                        target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#COHQ"
                     />Highlighting and Quotation</ref>). Many of the texts under discussion here
                  show features that are particular to South Asian manuscript culture. So, the
                  categories of <quote source="#quote7">conventional printing practice</quote>
                  (primarily European and American practice, that is) cannot be naively applied to
                  the encoding of these texts: the devices employed in the manuscripts, and also the
                  texts, for emphasizing, distancing oneself from, or quoting words or longer
                  phrases are often quite different from those encountered in printed
                     editions.<note>The modern editions of these texts generally do use the
                     categories of modern printing. Insofar as texts are digitized not from
                     manuscripts but from printed editions (as are many of the texts in the SARIT
                     library, accessed October 10, 2020, <ptr
                        target="https://github.com/sarit/SARIT-corpus"/>), the categories are a
                     better, though not perfect, fit. For further observations on the history of
                     book printing in relation to South Asian manuscript culture, see <ref
                        type="bibl" xml:id="refPol" target="#Pollock2007">Pollock
                     (2007)</ref>.</note> Before looking at some of these conventions, it will be
                  useful to summarize the main points in section 3.3.3. of the TEI Guidelines. The
                  elements presented there are as follows, grouped by their nearest model class (all
                  quotes in the following list are from <ref type="bibl" xml:id="quote8"
                     target="#TEI2020">TEI Consortium 2020, 3.3.3</ref>):<note>See also <ref
                        type="crossref" target="#table_1">table 1</ref> for an overview together
                     with the attributes most useful for linking the segment of text to either a
                     source or a parallel instance.</note>
               </p>
               <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>
                     <p>in the class of <ident>model.hiLike</ident> (and <ident>model.common</ident>)</p>
                     <list rend="bulleted">
                        <item>
                           <gi scheme="TEI">q</gi>: the most generic marker for quotations;</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>in the class of <ident>model.attributable</ident>
                     </p>
                     <list rend="bulleted">
                        <item>
                           <p>
                              <gi scheme="TEI">said</gi>: for quotations of what someone says or
                              thinks;</p>
                           <list rend="bulleted">
                              <item>with the boolean attributes <att>direct</att> and/or
                                    <att>aloud</att>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>in the sub-class <ident>model.quoteLike</ident>
                           </p>
                           <list rend="bulleted">
                              <item>
                                 <p>
                                    <gi scheme="TEI">quote</gi>: for any passage that is
                                       <q>attributed by the narrator or author to some agency
                                       external to the text</q>;</p>
                                 <list rend="bulleted">
                                    <item>allows the attribute <att>source</att>, which points at a
                                       source;</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <gi scheme="TEI">cit</gi>, <q>cited quotation</q>, a container for
                                    <gi scheme="TEI">quote</gi> in which it is associated with an
                                 explicit (in the text) reference to a source;<note>The element <gi
                                       scheme="TEI">cit</gi> is used also in dictionaries, but this
                                    is not the issue here.</note>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>in the class of <ident>model.emphLike</ident>
                     </p>
                     <list rend="bulleted">
                        <item>
                           <gi scheme="TEI">mentioned</gi>: <quote source="#quote8">marks words or
                              phrases mentioned, not used</quote><note>The <title
                                 level="m">Chicago Manual of Style</title> (<ref type="bibl"
                                 xml:id="quote9" target="#Chicago2010">University of Chicago Press
                                 2010, 7.58</ref>) describes the situation like this: <quote
                                 source="#quote9">When a word or term is not used functionally but
                                 is referred to as the word or term itself, it is either italicized
                                 or enclosed in quotation marks.</quote> It is for this kind of
                              phenomenon that the <gi scheme="TEI">mentioned</gi> tag is
                              intended.</note> in a given context;</item>
                        <item>
                           <gi scheme="TEI">soCalled</gi>: for <quote source="#quote8">cases in
                              which quotation marks are used to distance the quoted text from the
                              narrator or speaker.</quote></item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>That the TEI Guidelines define elements and attributes largely through their
                  inclusion in such classes means that these classes are relevant not only for the
                  correct (as intended) employment of the elements in marking up documents, but also
                  for the development of reliable software that queries the documents. For even
                  though section 3.3.3 discusses the varying use cases for all the above-mentioned
                  elements as candidates for analyzing material surrounded by quotation marks,
                  querying for them efficiently presupposes the correct expectations of their
                  various properties. And these are mostly a function of the classes that the
                  elements belong to. For example, an XPath<note>Unless indicated otherwise, all
                     XPath and XQuery expressions shown in this paper operate in the default
                     namespace, <ident>http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0</ident>.</note> that collects all
                  elements likely to be used for quotation marks would be <code lang="XPath"
                     >//(q|said|quote|cit|mentioned|soCalled)</code> (with duplication).<note>A more
                     elegant solution would be to derive the elements’ names from the corresponding
                     documentation (or ODD file). See <ref type="crossref" target="#example_1"
                        >example 1</ref> for a slightly less naive approach that returns the local
                     names of the elements in <ident>model.attributable</ident> and its immediate
                     subclasses. Even this simple example shows that <q>a
                        search for all quotations</q> in a TEI document needs to take a schema
                     as its basis, for it includes <gi scheme="TEI">floatingText</gi> in its
                     results, which is, however, differentiated from quotes in an important respect:
                        <quote source="#quote11"><gap/>the semantics of <gi scheme="TEI">quote</gi>
                        suggest that its content derives from a source external to the current text,
                           <gi scheme="TEI">floatingText</gi> carries no such implication
                        <gap/></quote> (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="quote11" target="#TEI2020">TEI
                        Consortium 2020, section 4.3.2</ref>)</note>
               </p>
               <figure xml:id="example_1">
                  <eg>
                     <code lang="XQuery">declare default element namespace "http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0";
                        doc("https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/xml/tei/odd/p5subset.xml")
                        //elementSpec[
                           classes/memberOf[
                              @key=(
                                 "model.attributable",
                                 //classSpec[
                                    classes/memberOf[@key="model.attributable"]]
                                 /@ident/string())]]
                        /@ident/string()</code></eg>
                  <head type="legend">XQuery for the local names of elements in
                        <ident>model.attributable</ident> class (according to <ref type="bibl" xml:id="refTEI" target="#TEI2020">TEI Consortium 2020</ref>).
                     The result is the list (<gi scheme="TEI">said</gi>, <gi scheme="TEI"
                     >quote</gi>, <gi scheme="TEI">cit</gi>, <gi scheme="TEI"
                     >floatingText</gi>).</head>
               </figure>
               <table xml:id="table_1">
                  <head>TEI elements for marking material in quotation marks, with selected
                     attributes for linking to a source or other occurrence of the material</head>
                  <row role="label" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1"> Element </cell>
                     <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1"> Nearest Model </cell>
                     <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1"> Attributes linking to other occurrences
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <gi scheme="TEI">q</gi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <ident>model.hiLike</ident>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <att>who</att>; <att>source</att>; <att>corresp</att>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <gi scheme="TEI">said</gi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <ident>model.attributable</ident>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <att>who</att>; <att>source</att>; <att>corresp</att>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <gi scheme="TEI">quote</gi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <ident>model.quoteLike</ident>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <att>source</att>; <att>corresp</att>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <gi scheme="TEI">cit</gi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <ident>model.quoteLike</ident>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <att>source</att>; <att>corresp</att>; source usually encoded in a child
                        element</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <gi scheme="TEI">mentioned</gi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <ident>model.emphLike</ident>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <att>source</att>; <att>corresp</att>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <gi scheme="TEI">soCalled</gi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <ident>model.emphLike</ident>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                        <att>source</att>; <att>corresp</att>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>It is noteworthy that the elements suggested for marking quotation in section
                  3.3.3 of the TEI Guidelines do not share one class: some belong to
                     <ident>model.attributable</ident>, others to <ident>model.emphLike</ident>, and
                  the most general marker—<gi scheme="TEI">q</gi>—belongs to
                     <ident>model.hiLike.</ident> This is a result of the presentation in section
                  3.3.3, which focuses on the use of quotation marks. Since modern printing does
                  not, on the analysis proposed there, employ them to mark only related features,
                  there need not be any expectation of a common superclass for the elements
                  discussed here.</p>
               <p>The quotation elements as described in the TEI Guidelines all share the
                     <att>source</att> and <att>corresp</att> attributes. These two properties are
                  expressive enough to provide the required intertextual links—that is, a link to a
                  work, either in the abstract or as found in a certain edition, and to a passage in
                  that edition. <note>At least if a well-construed system is used. A noteworthy
                     example is the definition of the Uniform Resource Name (URN) defined for the
                        <title level="a">Canonical Text Services</title> (CTS) in the Homer
                     Multitext Project (<ptr
                        target="http://www.homermultitext.org/hmt-doc/cite/texts/ctsoverview.html"/>
                     see <ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref7" target="#Blackwelletal2013">Blackwell and
                        Smith 2013</ref>). <ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref8" target="#Bertietal2015"
                        >Berti, Almas, et al. (2015)</ref> show that this reference format has
                     proven useful even for organizing fragments, i.e., text passages that have been
                     taken from works that did not survive as a whole. Applying this observation,
                        <ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref9" target="#Bertietal2016">Berti, Blackwell, et
                        al. (2016)</ref> provide a detailed discussion and case-study of
                     constructing valid URNs that are expressive enough to encode text reused in
                     several ways, together with its referential aspects. Especially interesting
                     here are their proposed solutions for encoding text that is either reused in a
                     direct quotation, alluded to, or repeated for further explanation. They propose
                     a very general system of aligning texts, mainly through the judicious use of
                     three locators: one for the passage as found in a canonical edition, one for
                     the passage as found in the work reusing it, and one for the new edition of the
                     work as constituted by the collection of the reused passages.</note> For this
                  reason, they need not be discussed further here. What is not so easily solved,
                  however, is how these various elements map onto the conceptual distinctions
                  underlying Steinkellner’s model. Should one just use <gi scheme="TEI">q</gi>, the
                  most general form, and be done with it? Or can something be gained from
                  differentiating among the elements for different cases? The next section will
                  consider some examples to answer these questions.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div2">
            <head>Simple Quotations (and Their Context)</head>
            <p>Example 2 shows a quotation in the fullest sense of the word.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example_2">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                  <div>
                     <div xml:lang="sa">
                        <p>
                           <seg>etena yad uktam <persName>udyotakareṇa</persName>
                              <quote source="NBhV.xml#p312l21">avācakatve śabdānāṃ pratijñāhetvor
                                 vyāghāta</quote> iti tad api pratyuktaṃ bhavati.</seg>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <p>
                           <seg>Through this also what <persName>Uddyotakara</persName> said,
                                 <quote>If words do not denote anything, both the proposition and
                                 the reason [in your inference] are inconsistent.</quote> has been
                              rejected.</seg>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Simple quote with attribution (the target of
                     <code lang="XPath">tei:quote/@source</code> is not shown).</head>
            </figure>
            <p><ref type="crossref" target="#example_2">Example 2</ref> is from the ca.
               eighth-century <title level="a" xml:lang="sa">Tattvasaṅgrahapañjikā</title> (see <ref
                  type="bibl" xml:id="ref16" target="#Krishnamacharya1926">Krishnamacharya
                  1926</ref>), the commentary by Kamalaśīla on Śāntarakṣita’s panorama, in verse, of
               contemporary philosophy, the <title level="a" xml:lang="sa">Tattvasaṅgraha</title>
               (see <ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref17" target="#Krishnamacharya1926">Krishnamacharya
                  1926</ref>).</p>
            <p>There are three voices that must be distinguished in this passage:</p>
            <list rend="ordered">
               <item>The passage as a whole is spoken by Kamalaśīla, the commentator.</item>
               <item>He is connecting a passage in the base text, the text he is
                  commenting upon, to an objection by a non-Buddhist opponent. The base text is here
                  not quoted but only pointed at, by saying <mentioned>Through this</mentioned>,
                  that is, through what is said in the base text.</item>
               <item>The opponent’s text is quoted verbatim, as a subphrase in a statement
                  that rejects it. In this case, we can verify that it is a faithful quote, since
                  the sentence is found in Uddyotakara’s work (<title level="a" xml:lang="sa"
                     >Nyāyabhāṣyavārttika</title> 312.21–22, in <ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref18"
                     target="#Thakur1997">Thakur 1997</ref>).</item>
            </list>
            <p>The commentary here performs various functions:</p>
            <list rend="ordered">
               <item>The construction <mentioned><q>Through this <gap/> has been rejected.</q></mentioned>
                     (<mentioned><q xml:lang="sa">etena <gap/> pratyuktaṃ bhavati</q></mentioned>): connection of
                  the text commented upon and the provided quote</item>
               <item>
                  <mentioned>What was said</mentioned> (<foreign xml:lang="sa">yad uktam</foreign>):
                  introduction of the quote</item>
               <item>Uddyotakara (<foreign xml:lang="sa">udyotakareṇa</foreign>): attribution
                  of the quote (the spelling with a double <mentioned>d</mentioned> is
                  preferable)</item>
               <item>
                  <gi scheme="TEI">quote</gi>: repetition of what Uddyotakara said</item>
            </list>
	    <p>Since it is generally useful to capture the context of a quote, it is embedded
            in a <gi scheme="TEI">seg</gi> element, which carries little semantic baggage. One
            could also consider the employment of a <gi scheme="TEI">cit</gi> element instead
            of it in this case. But in the absence of a <quote source="#quote17">bibliographic
            reference to <supplied>the</supplied> source</quote> (<ref type="bibl"
            xml:id="quote17" target="#TEI2020">TEI Consortium 2020, 3.3.3</ref>) of the
            quotation, this would not be an appropriate use case for <gi scheme="TEI"
            >cit</gi>.</p>
            <p>All of these functions can be tied to parts or segments of the sentences under
               consideration. Ideally, all these functions that the commentary performs should be
               easy to find by general queries run on the group of texts. A simple search for <code
                  lang="XPath">//quote</code> will catch this type of quote, and its context can be
               discovered by checking the parent (<code lang="XPath">//quote/parent::*</code>).
               Possible refinements that could be made by employing <att>type</att> and/or
                  <att>ana</att> attributes, and which are not reflected in the structure of the
               markup, will not be discussed here.</p>
            <p>In Steinkellner’s analysis, Uddyotakara’s words in this passage would be categorized
               as <mentioned>Ce</mentioned>, an explicit quotation that is exactly the same as in a source available to us
               today.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div3">
            <head>Quotes as References</head>
            <p>Later in the same text, Kamalaśīla introduces verse 1061 of the text he is commenting
               on as shown in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_3">example 3</ref>.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example_3">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                  <div n="1061">
                     <div xml:lang="sa">
                        <div type="base-text">
                           <lg xml:id="ts__1061">
                              <l>agobhinnaṃ ca yad vastu tad akṣair vyavasīyate /</l>
                              <l>...</l>
                           </lg>
                        </div>
                        <div type="commentary">
                           <p>yac coktam <hi rend="bold">indriyair</hi> ityādi, tad asiddham iti
                              darśayann āha—<hi rend="bold">agobhinnaṃ ce</hi>tyādi.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <div type="base-text">
                           <lg xml:id="ts__1061__trl">
                              <l>Also a real thing excluded from what is not a cow is ascertained
                                 through the sense faculties.</l>
                              <l>...</l>
                           </lg>
                        </div>
                        <div type="commentary">
                           <p>Further, what was [previously] stated starting with [the word] <hi
                                 rend="bold" xml:lang="sa">indriyaiḥ</hi>, that is unestablished. In
                              order to show this, [Śāntarakṣita, the author of the base text,] spoke
                              [the verse] that begins with [the words] <hi rend="bold">Also [a real
                                 thing] excluded from what is not a cow</hi>.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Quotes as references, markup following typography .</head>
            </figure>
            <p>The passage in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_3">example 3</ref> shows a type
               of quote significantly different from the one we saw before. The commentator’s
               introduction of the passage from the base text, the text the commentary is written
               on, contains at least two elements (here still marked graphically by <gi scheme="TEI"
                  >hi</gi>) <note>This example is taken from a file produced by the project <title
                     level="m">
                     <ref
                        target="https://github.com/sarit/SARIT-corpus/blob/a355567b5bc61032e1d7fa39392f5e06d679be5c/tattvasangrahapanjika.xml"
                        >Search and Retrieval of Indic Texts (SARIT)</ref></title>. This project
                  digitized Sanskrit texts from printed publications, and the first-level markup (as
                  shown in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_3">example 3</ref>) consisted in
                  marking the typographical features of the text encoded: in this case, <gi
                     scheme="TEI">hi</gi> elements with <att>rend</att> set to
                  <val>bold</val>.</note> that should be categorized as <gi scheme="TEI">quote</gi>
               elements of some sort:</p>
            <list rend="ordered">
               <item>The first is <foreign xml:lang="sa">indriyair</foreign>
                  <foreign xml:lang="sa">ityādi</foreign>. This refers to an earlier verse,
                  Tattvasaṅgraha 939 (see <ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref10"
                     target="#Krishnamacharya1926">Krishnamacharya 1926</ref>), which itself is a
                  quote, in the base text, of a passage by an opponent.</item>
               <item>The second is <foreign xml:lang="sa">agobhinnaṃ ca</foreign>
                  <foreign xml:lang="sa">ityādi</foreign>, which points to the beginning of the
                  verse in the base text, Tattvasaṅgraha 1061, in which the author of the base text
                  answers the opponent’s claim that was reproduced in Tattvasaṅgraha 939.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Both of these phrases have as their main function the indication of the passage that
               the commentator is going to speak about, and they indicate it by repeating a few
               words from the beginning of the passage.<note>Since these kinds of reuse are intended
                  to point at the beginning of a passage, they should usually not be translated, or
                  the translation should just indicate which words are at the
                  beginning of the translated passage. When the translation happens to
                  follow the order of words in Sanskrit, this issue remains hidden. The
                  translation in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_3">example 3</ref> shows two
                  of these solutions.</note> It is characteristic about this type of quotation that
               its content is usually irrelevant: it is a reference to a particular string of
               characters, or sequence of sounds, much like a lemma in a note of a critical edition
               indicates the place to which the note applies. <ref type="bibl" xml:id="quote12"
                  target="#Steinkellner1988">Steinkellner (1988, 117)</ref> remarks that these cases
               should be categorized as <quote source="#quote12">quotations from another
                  text</quote> (<mentioned>Ce</mentioned>), though in his own editions he usually marked these kinds of
               quotes by graphical means (bold face), probably so as not to make the apparatus
                  overflow.<note>See, for example, <ref type="bibl" xml:id="quote13"
                     target="#Steinkellneretal2005">Steinkellner, Krasser, and Lasic (2005,
                     1:lvi)</ref>: <quote source="#quote13">Words from the text commented upon—as
                        <term>pratīka</term>, in grammatical or lexicographical explanations, or as
                     used in an explanatory context—are in bold face.</quote> (The term
                     <term>pratīka</term> is here used to describe the quotations that are mainly
                  pointers to the base text.)</note>
            </p>
            <figure xml:id="example_4">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                  <div n="1061">
                     <div type="base-text">
                        <lg xml:id="ts__1061">
                           <l>agobhinnaṃ ca yad vastu tad akṣair vyavasīyate /</l>
                           <l>...</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                     <div type="commentary">
                        <p>
                           <seg>yac coktam <quote type="lemma" source="#ts__939">indriyair</quote>
                              ityādi, tad asiddham iti darśayann āha—<quote type="lemma"
                                 source="#ts__1061">agobhinnaṃ ce</quote>tyādi.</seg>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Quotes as references, first attempt (translated in example 3; the
                  element with the <att>xml:id</att> of <val>ts__939</val> is not shown).</head>
            </figure>
            <p>A first solution, shown in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_4">example 4</ref>,
               is to use the <gi scheme="TEI">quote</gi> tag for these repetitions, with
                  <att>type</att> set to <val>lemma</val> (in the sense used in textual criticism,
               not to be confused with the linguistic value as in the <att>lemma</att> attribute).
               With this markup we can separate these <gi scheme="TEI">quote</gi> elements from
               other types quite easily. The reference to the base text is encoded in a
                  <att>source</att> attribute. A possible drawback in this encoding is that the
               referring function of the passage in which the quotation appears does not become
               evident. Ultimately, one would have to establish (in the <gi scheme="TEI"
                  >encodingDesc</gi>) that the value <val>lemma</val> in the <att>type</att> of a
                  <gi scheme="TEI">quote</gi> element means that this element has some features of a
                  reference.<note>One might consider encoding this information in a
                     <att>corresp</att> attribute. But this could lead to misunderstandings, as the
                  TEI Guidelines (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="quote14" target="#TEI2020">16.5.1:
                     Correspondence</ref>) state: <quote source="#quote14">the correspondence
                     relationship is not <emph>from</emph> one to the other, but
                        <emph>between</emph> the two objects. It is thus different from the
                        <att>target</att> attribute</quote>
                  <ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SA.html#SACS1"
                  />. In the current case, we would want to encode precisely such a
                     <soCalled>from</soCalled> relationship: from the commentary to the base text,
                  but not the other way around.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The next suggested solution, in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_5">example
                  5</ref>, tries to make this feature explicit by using <gi scheme="TEI">ref</gi>
               elements. However, this creates problems. Semantically, it is problematic because it
               is not the content of the quote that <gi scheme="TEI">ref</gi> refers to:
               the commentary uses the phrase <q>that starting with xyz</q> to refer to
               the base text but only <q>xyz</q> is an actual quote. It also has the significant
               drawback that any query intended to catch all quote-like elements will now have to
               include certain <gi scheme="TEI">ref</gi> elements. This would increase the
               complexity of queries significantly.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example_5">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                  <div n="1061">
                     <div type="base-text">
                        <lg xml:id="ts__1061">
                           <l>agobhinnaṃ ca yad vastu tad akṣair vyavasīyate /</l>
                           <l>...</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                     <div type="commentary">
                        <p>
                           <seg>yac coktam <ref target="#ts__939" type="lemma">indriyair</ref>
                              ityādi, tad asiddham iti darśayann āha—<ref target="#ts__1061"
                                 type="lemma">agobhinnaṃ ce</ref>tyādi.</seg>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Quotes as references, second attempt (translated in <ref
                     type="crossref" target="#example_3">example 3</ref>; the element with the
                     <att>xml:id</att> of <val>ts__939</val> is not shown).</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="example_6">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                  <div n="1061">
                     <div type="base-text">
                        <lg xml:id="ts__1061">
                           <l>agobhinnaṃ ca yad vastu tad akṣair vyavasīyate /</l>
                           <l>...</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                     <div type="commentary">
                        <p>
                           <seg>yac coktam <ref target="#ts__939"><quote type="lemma"
                                    >indriyair</quote> ityādi</ref>, tad asiddham iti darśayann
                                 āha—<ref target="#ts__1061"><quote type="lemma">agobhinnaṃ
                                    ce</quote>tyādi</ref>.</seg>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Quotes as references, proposed solution (translated in <ref
                     type="crossref" target="#example_3">example 3</ref>; the element with the
                     <att>xml:id</att> of <val>ts__939</val> is not shown).</head>
            </figure>
            <p>It thus seems best to combine these solutions, and treat the quote together with its
               embedding phrase as a reference as shown in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_6"
                  >example 6</ref>. This expresses most of the features that we can see in
               these quotations: we can pick out these <gi scheme="TEI">quote</gi> elements along with
               all the other types, and still easily differentiate them by examining whether they are
               embedded in a <gi scheme="TEI">ref</gi> to the base text.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div4">
            <head>Quotes of Individual Words/Phrases for Elucidation</head>
            <p>In a second passage that follows later in the commentary on the same verse,
               Kamalaśīla takes up the Sanskrit word <foreign xml:lang="sa">ca</foreign> (usually
                  <mentioned>and</mentioned> or <mentioned>furthermore</mentioned>), and explains
               how it is to be understood in the verse: its function there is the inclusion of
               objects that are not explicitly mentioned in the verse, rather than the simple
               conjunction of this sentence with the previous one. This is not the same kind of
               referring quotation that we considered above in <ref type="crossref"
                  target="#example_4">examples 4–6</ref>, because its main purpose is to comment on
               the significance or meaning of the term, not to indicate a particular point in the
               base text. A proposal for its markup with <gi scheme="TEI">mentioned</gi> and <gi
                  scheme="TEI">gloss</gi> is shown in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_7"
                  >example 7</ref>.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example_7">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                  <div n="1061">
                     <div xml:lang="sa">
                        <div type="base-text">
                           <lg xml:id="ts__1061">
                              <l><seg xml:id="ts__1061__a">agobhinnaṃ</seg> <seg xml:id="ts__1061__b"
                                    >ca</seg> yad vastu tad akṣair vyavasīyate /</l>
                              <l>...</l>
                           </lg>
                        </div>
                        <div type="commentary">
                           <p>
                              <seg><mentioned source="#ts__1061__b">ca</mentioned>kāro <gloss
                                    target="#ts__1061__b">'nuktārthasamuccaye</gloss>.</seg>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                        <div type="base-text">
                           <lg xml:id="ts__1061__trl">
                              <l><seg xml:id="ts__1061__b__trl">Also</seg> a real thing <seg
                                    xml:id="ts__1061__a__trl">excluded from what is not a cow</seg>
                                 is ascertained through the sense faculties.</l>
                              <l>...</l>
                           </lg>
                        </div>
                        <div type="commentary">
                           <p>
                              <seg>The particle <mentioned source="#ts__1061__b__trl">ca</mentioned>
                                 [is used] <gloss target="#ts__1061__b__trl">in the sense of
                                    indicating objects not mentioned [in the verse]</gloss>.</seg>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Quotes for explanation.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>In terms of query complexity, this has similar problems to the simple <gi
                  scheme="TEI">ref</gi> solution just discussed: any query for quotes in general
               will have to take the variation introduced by <gi scheme="TEI">mentioned</gi> into
               account, and will therefore become more complicated. However, section 3.3.3 of the
               TEI Guidelines does suggest <gi scheme="TEI">mentioned</gi> as the element to use for
               the phenomenon described here. The element <gi scheme="TEI">mentioned</gi> therefore
               must be considered in well-constructed queries for reused text.</p>
            <p>The primary function of repeating the word that is to be explained, <foreign
                  xml:lang="sa">ca</foreign>, is not to refer to the text, but to say something
               about the meaning or content of that term. This explanation can be encoded as a <gi
                  scheme="TEI">gloss</gi> element. Both elements, <gi scheme="TEI">mentioned</gi>
               and <gi scheme="TEI">gloss</gi>, are loosely tied to the base text, and not to each
               other, because there are variant forms of this phenomenon where either there is no
               clearly identifiable <gi scheme="TEI">gloss</gi>, or the term which could be <gi
                  scheme="TEI">mentioned</gi> is not repeated in the text. As before, the context
               useful to understanding this occurrence is wrapped in an anonymous <gi scheme="TEI"
                  >seg</gi> element.</p>
            <p>Steinkellner marks text segments of this kind with <mentioned>T'</mentioned>
                  (<foreign xml:lang="la">textus usus secundarii</foreign>), though he notes that
                  <quote source="#quote15"><supplied>f</supplied>ormally this kind of text would
                  correspond to the group of
                  <soCalled><mentioned>Ce'</mentioned>-texts</soCalled><gap/> But in order to
                  distinguish the group of quotation-texts in their hierarchical position more
                  clearly I prefer the reference to the <foreign xml:lang="la">textus</foreign> in
                  the present definition</quote> (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="quote15"
                  target="#Steinkellner1988">1988, 116–17</ref>). This hierarchical position amounts
               to an expression of the value that an editor assigns to a text as a witness for some
               other text. In the present case, it declares the editor’s conviction that the direct
               commentary is a privileged witness that is second in reliability only to direct
               witnesses (usually manuscripts) for the text that is being commented upon. The markup
               solution proposed here (with <gi scheme="TEI">mentioned</gi>) does not explicitly
               express this facet, since it captures only the typed structural correspondence between text
               passages. However, this facet can be defined by the editor in a systematic fashion through
               the annotation of the target of the <att>source</att> attribute: the determination of
               the <quote source="#quote15">hierarchical position</quote> is something that the
               editor will usually make explicit in their organization and interpretation of the
               sources. The encoding proposed here thus has the benefit of keeping two unrelated
               things separate: the similarity (or, in some cases, identity) of sequences of
               characters in different texts, and the editor’s estimate of their value as witnesses
               for certain editorial decisions. For example, an explicit quote from the base text in
               a commentary (corresponding to <mentioned>Ce</mentioned> in Steinkellner’s schema) would receive the same
               markup as an explicit quote in any other text (<gi scheme="TEI">quote</gi> with
                  <att>source</att>). If the editor decided that the commentary had greater
               reliability than the other text, this could be made explicit in any of the many ways
               that the TEI Guidelines provide for: for example, since a document encoded on the basis
               of witnesses will probably have a <gi scheme="TEI">listWit</gi> element,
               one could at least add an <att>ana</att> attribute to the <gi scheme="TEI"
                  >witness</gi> elements contained therein, and derive the desired hierarchical
               position from a query of that attribute.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div5">
            <head>Silent Quotes and Allusions</head>
            <p>The last case of text reuse to be discussed is that of <soCalled>silent
                  reuse</soCalled>. In this variant, phrases, sentences, or even longer passages are
               reused without explicitly marking them as being due to another agency. This
               phenomenon is characterized as <foreign xml:lang="la">usus secundarii</foreign> by
               Steinkellner. These passages can, in this process, also change to varying degrees,
               and it is a difficult philological problem to judge the differences between the
                  <soCalled>reused</soCalled> and <soCalled>original</soCalled> texts.<note>Silent
                     reuse is very common across the genre of scholastic Sanskrit. See <ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref11" target="#Gnoli1960">Gnoli (1960a, xix n. 2)</ref> for an
                  example from Maṇḍana (<title level="a" xml:lang="sa">Sphoṭasiddhi</title>,
                  99.1–100.15, in <ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref12" target="#Bhattetal1958">Bhatt and
                     Ramanujam 1958</ref>): the reused passage is not especially differentiated from
                  the surrounding text, which is closed simply by the phrase <foreign xml:lang="sa"
                     >kevalam eṣa manorathaḥ</foreign> (<title xml:lang="sa">Sphoṭasiddhi</title>,
                  100.15–16, my translation: <q>This is only wishful thinking.</q>).</note> The
               markup outlined for passages in this category also applies to cases where a
               passage is only paraphrased or alluded to.</p>
            <p>In practice, all three possible modes of reuse are encountered: a text might
               reproduce a passage from another by embellishing or otherwise extending it, it might
               summarize or condense the original passage, or it might reproduce it very faithfully.
               Often, one will find all three modes mixed together in the same text.<note>Well-known
                  examples are Ravigupta’s reworking of Prajñākaragupta’s <title level="a"
                     xml:lang="sa">Pramāṇavārttikālaṅkārabhāṣya</title> (see <ref type="bibl"
                     xml:id="refSan" target="#Sānkntyāyana1953" xml:lang="sa">Sāṅkṛtyāyana
                     1953</ref>), or Ratnakīrti’s writings, discussed below.</note> In many cases it
               is also not possible to determine through how many intermediary steps a passage has
               been received, especially when the work it is supposedly taken from has not
               survived as a whole.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example_8">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                  <div>
                     <!-- source text -->
                     <div type="text1">
                        <p>...<anchor xml:id="j-1-s"/>tatraikas tāvad bāhyo ... dṛṣṭāv iva
                              iti<anchor xml:id="j-1-e"/></p>
                        <p>... atrāpy uktam ... <anchor xml:id="j-2-e"/>...</p>
                     </div>
                     <!-- First reuse: Ratnakīrti’s Apohasiddhi -->
                     <div type="text2">
                        <p>...<anchor xml:id="r-1-s"/>tatra bāhyo ’rtho ... dṛṣṭāv iva iti<anchor
                              xml:id="r-1-e"/></p>
                        <p>...atrāpy uktam ...<anchor xml:id="r-2-e"/>...</p>
                     </div>
                     <!-- Second reuse: Mokṣākaragupta’s Tarkabhāṣā -->
                     <div type="text3">
                        <p>...<anchor xml:id="m-1-s"/>bāhyārtho ... dṛṣṭāv iva iti<anchor
                              xml:id="m-1-e"/></p>
                     </div>
                     <linkGrp type="silentreuse">
                        <link target="#j-1-s #j-2-e #r-1-s #r-2-e"/>
                        <link target="#j-1-s #j-1-e #r-1-s #r-1-e #m-1-s #m-1-e"/>
                     </linkGrp>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Encoding parallels, suggested solution with stand-off markup (<gi
                     scheme="TEI">anchor</gi> only). The three <gi scheme="TEI">div</gi> elements
                  could be in different documents. For the text content, see examples <ref
                     type="crossref" target="#example_11">11</ref>, <ref type="crossref"
                     target="#example_13">13</ref>, and <ref type="crossref" target="#example_15"
                     >15</ref>. The internal markup of the text passages linked in this way is not
                  relevant to this solution.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>The source text referred to in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_8">example
                  8</ref> is from a work by Jñānaśrīmitra, a Buddhist monk and scholar active at the
               beginning of the eleventh century CE in Bengal. The section of text is from his
                  <title level="a" xml:lang="sa">Apohaprakaraṇa</title> (see <ref type="crossref"
                  target="#example_11">example 11</ref> for the full text). This section was reused
               twice, with various degrees of abridgements.</p>
            <p>Its first reuse (encoded in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_13">example
                  13</ref>) is taken from the <title level="a" xml:lang="sa">Apohasiddhi</title>
               (see <ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref13" target="#Mcallister2020">McAllister 2020</ref>)
               of Ratnakīrti, who lived in the first half of the eleventh century: he calls his
               texts <q>abridgements</q> or <q>summaries</q> (<foreign xml:lang="sa"
                  >saṃkṣepa</foreign>) of the much more extensive works of his teacher,
               Jñānaśrīmitra. The same passage is again reused a few centuries later by
               Mokṣākaragupta in his <title level="a" xml:lang="sa">Tarkabhāṣā</title> (see <ref
                  type="bibl" xml:id="ref14" target="#Iyengar1952">Iyengar 1952</ref>; encoded in <ref
                  type="crossref" target="#example_15">example 15</ref>). This
               third manifestation of the passage is heavily abridged. This case illustrates how
               text passages were reused by several authors. It also contains a
               quote-within-a-quote, an explicit quotation of a partial verse from a foundational
               text for the logico-epistemological school of Buddhism, the <title level="a"
                  xml:lang="sa">Pramāṇaviniścaya</title> (see <ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref15"
                  target="#Steinkellner2007">Steinkellner 2007</ref>) (in the examples below, a
               modern partial edition of it is referred to by <val>#pvin1</val>; the
                  <att>target</att>
               <val>PVin.xml#v15</val> refers to a TEI XML edition containing the quote). One might
               hesitate about how to categorize this quote from the <title level="a" xml:lang="sa"
                  >Pramāṇaviniścaya</title>: it is, on the surface, an explicit quote, but it is
               unlikely that any of the two authors reusing the passage in which it occurs should be
               said to have quoted this contained item itself. It is more likely that the verse was
               transmitted by them in the form found in the passage surrounding it, which was being
               reused as a whole. This question has to be answered when one wishes to judge the
               value of the preserved version of the verse for an edition of the <title level="a"
                  xml:lang="sa">Pramāṇaviniścaya</title>. The proposed markup should enable a
               researcher to easily collect information that allows them to answer that
               question.</p>
            <p>Two solutions will be proposed here. The first employs only lightweight stand-off
               markup and might be suitable for cases where the markup of the source documents
               cannot easily be changed. The second solution has the benefit of simpler querying,
               but at the cost of deeper interventions in the source documents.</p>
            <p>The first solution is to use encoding such as that shown in <ref type="crossref"
                  target="#example_8">example 8</ref>. This proposal marks up parallel text passages
               in a way that is minimally invasive on the source documents. It adheres closely to
               the <gi scheme="TEI">linkGrp</gi> solution proposed in section 16.5.2 of the TEI
               Guidelines, <ref
                  target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SA.html#SACSAL"
                  >Alignment of Parallel Texts</ref>.<note><ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SA.html#SACSAL"
                  /></note> This solution has at least two advantages: often, the interpretation of
               textual parallels is a rather subjective matter. The separation of this
               interpretative layer from the main text requires only <gi scheme="TEI">anchor</gi>
               elements in the document, so that the impact on existing applications should be
               minimal. The <gi scheme="TEI">linkGrp</gi> elements can be easily shared, stored in
               separate files, and one can have several of them, so that they can accommodate
               conflicting interpretations by different researchers. A second benefit is that they
               also work when the quoted material does not align nicely with block-level elements,
               as is the case in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_8">example 8</ref>, where the
               reused material crosses over a paragraph border in the first case of its reuse.</p>
            <p>A drawback of this solution is that the search for quotes will become more
               complicated. But I feel that in this situation this disadvantage is justified to a
               certain extent: all members of <ident>model.attributable</ident> are defined, after
               all, as having been explicitly marked as quotes in the source text. These
                  <soCalled>silent quotes</soCalled> are not marked in such a way.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example_9">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                  <div>
                     <linkGrp type="silentreuse">
                        <link target="#j1 #r1 #m1"/>
                        <link target="#j2 #r2"/>
                     </linkGrp>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Encoding parallels, solution with linked elements (the documents
                  presupposed are shown in examples <ref type="crossref" target="#example_11"
                     >11</ref>, <ref type="crossref" target="#example_13">13</ref>, and <ref
                     type="crossref" target="#example_15">15</ref>).</head>
            </figure>
            <p>The second proposed solution is as shown in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_9"
                  >example 9</ref>. This solution is superficially similar to the one shown in <ref
                  type="crossref" target="#example_8">example 8</ref>, but it links whole elements
               to each other, not the start and end points of spans of text. It thus requires the
               identification of spans of texts (at least as <gi scheme="TEI">seg</gi>) that are to
               be linked, even in the case of the original text that is being reused. It might be
               preferable, however, since it facilitates easier querying of the document. It employs
               the mechanisms provided in <gi scheme="TEI">att.global.linking</gi> , that is, the
                  <att>next</att> and <att>prev</att> attributes as described in section 16.7 of the
               TEI Guidelines, <ref
                  target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SA.html#SAAG"
                  >Aggregation</ref>.<note><ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SA.html#SAAG"
                  /></note> This allows elements to be constructed around the hierarchical
               constraints of the XML tree. In this variant, the employment of <gi scheme="TEI"
                  >seg</gi> (for a quote’s context) and <gi scheme="TEI">quote</gi> (for the quoted
               material) would cohere closely to the suggestions offered above for the cases of
               explicit quotations. But to the extent that the employment of
                  <ident>model.attributable</ident> elements is questionable, this solution might be
               inadequate. The main practical benefit is certainly that a simple <soCalled>search
                  for all quotes</soCalled>, for example, <code lang="Xpath">//quote</code>, would
               return these results as well as any quotes explicitly marked as such in the sources.
               In <ref type="crossref" target="#example_13">examples 13</ref> and <ref
                  type="crossref" target="#example_15">15</ref>, I have differentiated the <gi
                  scheme="TEI">quote</gi> elements by setting <att>type</att> to
               <val>silent</val>.</p>
            <p>Both solutions could be simplified by using CTS URNs as suggested and discussed by
               <ref type="bibl" xml:id="refBertietAl" target="#Bertietal2015">Berti, Almas, et al. (2015)</ref> and <ref type="bibl" xml:id="refBertietAl16" target="#Bertietal2016">Berti, Blackwell, et al. (2016)</ref>. Such references
               would replace the simple internal references (like <val>#j1</val> in the examples).
               For the first solution, we would then not even have to introduce <gi scheme="TEI"
                  >anchor</gi> elements, since we could link directly into the text. For the second
               solution, it would at least save us the necessary markup in the document containing
               the reused text.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div6">
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>All cases of text reuse analyzed so far can be quite clearly expressed within the
               framework of the TEI Guidelines. So in this sense, no particular changes are
               necessary to accommodate this facet of Sanskrit literature. The markup proposed here
               is expressive enough to allow for all of the distinctions that were developed
               expressly for the study and edition of these texts (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="refStein2" target="#Steinkellner1988">Steinkellner 1988</ref>). However, it
               also allows for a cleaner separation of the raw textual evidence and the editor’s
               judgement, by encoding only the textual correspondences. The TEI Guidelines
               provide a rich set of mechanisms for attaching interpretations to the basic set of
               structural elements discussed here. A simple way would be the addition of
                  <att>ana</att> and/or <att>type</att> attributes to the appropriate <gi
                  scheme="TEI">seg</gi> or <gi scheme="TEI">quote</gi> elements. An alignment of a
               source text and a derived text, even through multiple derivations, is possible and
               could be opened for further automatic processing after adequate normalization of the
                  <gi scheme="TEI">linkGrp</gi> elements.</p>
            <figure xml:id="example_10">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                  <div xml:id="cases-of-silent-reuse">
                     <p>...<anchor xml:id="j-1-s"/>tatraikas tāvad bāhyo ... dṛṣṭāv iva iti<anchor
                           xml:id="j-1-e"/>
                     </p>
                     <p>... atrāpy uktam ... <anchor xml:id="j-2-e"/>...</p>
                     <p>...<anchor xml:id="r-1-s"/>tatra bāhyo ’rtho ... dṛṣṭāv iva iti<anchor
                           xml:id="r-1-e"/>
                     </p>
                     <p>...atrāpy uktam ...<anchor xml:id="r-2-e"/>...</p>
                     <p>...<anchor xml:id="m-1-s"/>bāhyārtho ... dṛṣṭāv iva iti<anchor
                           xml:id="m-1-e"/>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">List of passages connected through <gi scheme="TEI">link</gi> elements (for
                  documents as in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_8">example 8</ref>).</head>
            </figure>
            <p>To summarize, the following (simplified) XPath expressions might be used to select
               and find the different categories of reuse discussed in the introduction:</p>
            <list rend="bulleted">
               <item>
                  <p><mentioned>Ce</mentioned> <foreign xml:lang="la">citatum ex alio</foreign>, the quotation from another
                     text in the text being encoded (<mentioned>T</mentioned>):</p>
                  <list rend="bulleted">
                     <item>A simple <code lang="XPath">//quote</code> is sufficient (see also <ref
                           type="crossref" target="#example_1">example 1</ref>)</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p><mentioned>Ce'</mentioned>
                     <foreign xml:lang="la">citatum ex alio usus secundarii</foreign>, a silent
                     quote in <mentioned>T</mentioned>:</p>
                  <list rend="bulleted">
                     <item>
                        <p>On the first solution (see <ref type="crossref" target="#example_8">example 8</ref>), an XPath is not as straightforward as in the cases
                           of explicit quotes. Given the <gi scheme="TEI">link</gi> elements used in <ref
                              type="crossref" target="#example_8">example 8</ref>, one could list
                           the corresponding passages as follows:</p>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true">
                           <div xml:id="cases-of-silent-reuse">{
                              //anchor[contains(string-join(//link/@target, " "), concat("#",
                              @xml:id))]/parent::* }</div>
                        </egXML>
                        <p>The result is shown in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_10">example
                              10</ref>. This XQuery expression is not a general solution because the
                           analysis of the links is very naive (matching on a partial string) and
                           there is no loop over the elements of the <gi scheme="TEI">linkGrp</gi>
                           or grouping of results.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>On the second solution proposed above (see <ref type="crossref" target="#example_9">example 9</ref>), the results of <code lang="XPath"
                           >//quote</code> would include these cases; one could filter on attribute
                        values (not discussed here).</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p><mentioned>e</mentioned> added to <mentioned>Ce</mentioned> or
                        <mentioned>Ce'</mentioned>, signifying that the editor believes that the
                     text was changed by the author of <mentioned>T</mentioned> (<foreign xml:lang="la">modus
                        edendi</foreign>)</p>
                  <list rend="bulleted">
                     <item>This is judged from the comparison of two passages; the editor’s
                        decision can be recorded in an <att>ana</att> attribute to all of the
                        proposed elements, but should not be expressed in the structure of the
                        markup.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p><mentioned>Ci(')</mentioned>
                     <foreign xml:lang="la">citatum in alio (usus secundarii)</foreign>, (silent)
                     quotation of <mentioned>T</mentioned> in another text</p>
                  <list rend="bulleted">
                     <item>This is a simple reversion of previous relations (i.e., a <code
                           lang="XPath">//quote</code> or similar search on the target text).</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p><mentioned>R</mentioned> <foreign xml:lang="la">citatum in alio modo referendi</foreign>, a text of <mentioned>T</mentioned>
                  referred to or paraphrased</p>
                  <list rend="bulleted">
                     <item>This case belongs to the ones discussed in <ref type="crossref"
                           target="#div5">section 5</ref>. An editor might express peculiarities of
                        the reference or paraphrase with an <att>ana</att> attribute that can be
                        added to any of the given relations. In most cases, the
                           <soCalled>quotation</soCalled> expressed through a <gi scheme="TEI"
                           >link</gi> element will be the obvious place for such a specifier. In the
                        solution that encodes silent quotes as <gi scheme="TEI">quote</gi>, an
                        example was given that would match <code lang="XPath"
                           >//quote[@type="silent"]</code>.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <!-- the bibliography for the article, organized as a series of <bibl> elements inside <listBibl> -->
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Bertietal2015"><author>Berti, Monica</author>, <author>Bridget
                     Almas</author>, <author>David Dubin</author>, <author>Greta Franzini</author>,
                     <author>Simona Stoyanova</author>, and <author>Gregory R. Crane</author>.
                     <date>2015</date>. <title level="a">The Linked Fragment: TEI and the Encoding
                     of Text Reuses of Lost Authors.</title>
                  <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>. <ptr
                     target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1218"/>; <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.4000/jtei.1218</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Bertietal2016"><author>Berti, Monica</author>, <author>Christopher
                     Blackwell</author>, <author>Mary Daniels</author>, <author>Samantha
                     Strickland</author>, and <author>Kimbell Vincent-Dobbins</author>.
                     <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">Documenting Homeric Text-Reuse in the
                     Deipnosophistae of Athenaeus of Naucratis.</title>
                  <title level="j">Bulletin of the Institute of Classical Studies</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">(2)</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                  >121–39</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                  >doi:10.1111/j.2041-5370.2016.12042.x</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Bhattetal1958"><author>Bhatt, N. R.</author>, and <author>T.
                     Ramanujam</author>, eds. <date>1958</date>. <title level="m" xml:lang="sa"
                     >Sphoṭa Siddhi. La démonstration du Sphoṭa par Maṇḍana Miśra.</title>
                  Translated by <editor role="translator">Madeleine Biardeau</editor>.
                     <series>Publications de l’Institut français d’indologie</series>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Pondichéry</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Institut français d’indologie</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Blackwelletal2013"><author>Blackwell, Christopher</author>, and
                     <author>Neel Smith</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title level="m">Homer
                     Multitext Project: Documentation</title>. Accessed <date>May 23, 2019</date>.
                     <ptr target="http://www.homermultitext.org/hmt-doc/index.html"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="krung19942009"><author>krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug lte gnas kyi
                     bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang</author> ed. <date>1994–2009</date>. <title level="m"
                     xml:lang="sa">bstan ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma)</title>. <pubPlace>Beijing</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>krung-go’i bod kyi shes rig dpe skrun khang / China Tibetology
                     Publishing House</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Freschi2015"><author>Freschi, Elisa</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title
                     level="a">The Reuse of Texts in Indian Philosophy: Introduction.</title>
                  <title level="j">Journal of Indian Philosophy</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope><biblScope unit="issue">(2–3)</biblScope>:
                     <biblScope unit="page">85–108</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                     >doi:10.1007/s10781-014-9232-9</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Freschietal2017a"><author>Freschi, Elisa</author>, and <author>Philipp
                     A. Maas</author>, eds. <date>2017a</date>. <title level="j">Adaptive Reuse:
                     Aspects of Creativity in South Asian Cultural History.</title>
                  <series>Abhandlungen für die Kunde des Morgenlandes</series>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">101</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Harrassowitz Verlag</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Freschietal2017b"><author>Freschi, Elisa</author>, and <author>Philipp
                     A. Maas</author>. <date>2017b</date>. <title level="a">Introduction: Conceptual
                     Reflections on Adaptive Reuse.</title> In <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#Freschietal2017a">Freschi and Maas 2017a, 11–25</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Gnoli1960"><author>Gnoli, Raniero</author>. <date>1960</date>. <title
                     level="a">Introduction.</title> In <title level="m" xml:lang="sa">The
                     Pramāṇavārttikam of Dharmakīrti. The First Chapter with the Autocommentary;
                     Text and Critical Notes</title>, <biblScope unit="page">xv–xl</biblScope>.
                     <series>Serie Orientale Roma</series>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Rome</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Istituto Italiano per il Medio ed Estremo
                  Oriente</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Hellwig2015"><author>Hellwig, Oliver</author>. <date>2015</date>.
                     <title level="a">Using Recurrent Neural Networks for Joint Compound Splitting
                     and Sandhi Resolution in Sanskrit.</title><title level="j">Human Language
                     Technologies as a Challenge for Computer Science and Linguistics. 7th Language
                     &amp; Technology Conference: Proceedings</title>, edited by <editor>Zygmunt
                     Vetulani</editor> and <editor>Joseph Mariani</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >289–93</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Poznań, Poland</pubPlace>: <publisher>Fundacja
                     Uniwersytetu im. Adama Mickiewicza w Poznaniu</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="http://ltc.amu.edu.pl/a2015/book/papers/LRL-1.pdf"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Hellwig2016"><author>Hellwig, Oliver</author>. <date>2016</date>.
                     <title level="a">Detecting Sentence Boundaries in Sanskrit Texts.</title><title
                     level="j">Proceedings of COLING 2016, the 26th International Conference on
                     Computational Linguistics: Technical Papers</title>, edited by <editor>Yuji
                     Matsumoto</editor> and <editor>Rashmi Prasad</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >288–97</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Osaka, Japan</pubPlace>: <publisher>The COLING
                     2016 Organizing Committee</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/C16-1028/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Iyengar1952"><author>Iyengar, H. R. Rangaswami</author>.
                     <date>1952</date>. <title level="m" xml:lang="sa">Tarkabhāṣa and Vādasthāna of
                     Mokṣākaragupta and Jitāripāda.</title>
                  <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <pubPlace>Mysore</pubPlace>: <publisher>Hindusthan
                     Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Jacobi1903"><author>Jacobi, Hermann</author>. <date>1903</date>. <title
                     level="a" xml:lang="de">Über den nominalen Stil des wissenschaftlichen
                     Sanskrits.</title>
                  <title level="j" xml:lang="de">Indogermanische Forschungen</title>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                  >236–51</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Krishnamacharya1926"><author>Krishnamacharya, Embar</author>, ed.
                     <date>1926</date>. <title level="m" xml:lang="sa">Tattvasaṅgraha of
                     Śāntarakṣita: With the Commentary of Kamalaśīla.</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">2 vols</biblScope>. <series>Gaekwad’s Oriental
                     Series</series>
                  <biblScope unit="page">30–31</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Baroda</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Central Library</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Mcallister2020"><author>McAllister, Patrick</author>.
                  <date>2020</date>. <title level="m">Ratnakīrti’s Proof of Exclusion.</title>
                  <series>Beiträge zur Kultur- und Geistesgeschichte Asiens</series>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Austrian Academy of Sciences</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="McCrea2010"><author>McCrea, Lawrence J</author>., and <author>Parimal
                     G. Patil</author>. <date>2010</date>. <title level="m">Buddhist Philosophy of
                     Language in India: Jñānaśrīmitra on Exclusion.</title>
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Columbia University
                  Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Pollock2007"><author>Pollock, Sheldon</author>. <date>2007</date>.
                     <title level="a">Literary Culture and Manuscript Culture in Precolonial
                     India.</title> In <title level="m">Literary Cultures and the Material
                     Book</title>, edited by <editor>Simon Elliot</editor>, <editor>Andrew
                     Nash</editor>, and <editor>Ian Willison</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
                     >77–94</biblScope>. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>The British
                     Library</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Preisendanz2008"><author>Preisendanz, Karin</author>.
                  <date>2008</date>. <title level="a">Text, Commentary, Annotation. Some Reflections
                     on the Philosophical Genre.</title>
                  <title level="j">Journal of Indian Philosophy</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="issue">(5–6)</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                     >599–618</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI"
                  >doi:10.1007/s10781-008-9036-x</idno>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Sānkntyāyana1953"><author>Sāṅkṛtyāyana, Rāhula</author>.
                     <date>1953</date>. <title level="m" xml:lang="sa">Pramāṇavārtikabhāshyam or
                     Vārtikālaṅkāraḥ of Prajñākaragupta (Being a Commentary on Dharmakīrti’s
                     Pramāṇavārtikam)</title>. <series>Tibetan Sanskrit Works Series</series>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Patna</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Kashi Prasad Jayaswal Research Institute</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Steinkellner1988"><author>Steinkellner, Ernst</author>.
                     <date>1988</date>. <title level="a">Methodological Remarks on the Constitution
                     of Sanskrit Texts from the Buddhist pramāṇa-Tradition.</title>
                  <title level="j" xml:lang="de">Wiener Zeitschrift für die Kunde Südasiens und
                     Archiv für indische Philosophie</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
                  >103–29</biblScope>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Steinkellner2007"><author>Steinkellner, Ernst</author>, ed.
                     <date>2007</date>. <title level="m" xml:lang="sa">Dharmakīrti’s
                     Pramāṇaviniścaya: Chapters 1 and 2.</title>
                  <series>Sanskrit Texts from the Tibetan Autonomous Region</series>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Beijing</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>China Tibetology Research Center</publisher>;
                     <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>: <publisher>Austrian Academy of
                     Sciences</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Steinkellner2017"><author>Steinkellner, Ernst</author>.
                     <date>2017</date>. <title level="m">Early Indian Epistemology and Logic:
                     Fragments from Jinendrabuddhi’s Pramāṇasamuccayaṭīkā 1 and 2.</title>
                  <series>Studia Philologica Buddhica Monograph Series</series>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>International Institute for Buddhist Studies of the International
                     College for Postgraduate Buddhist Studies</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Steinkellneretal2005"><author>Steinkellner, Ernst</author>,
                     <author>Helmut Krasser</author>, and <author>Horst Lasic</author>, eds.
                     <date>2005</date>. <title level="m" xml:lang="sa">Jinendrabuddhi’s
                     Viśālāmalavatī Pramāṇasamuccayaṭīkā. Chapter 1</title>. <biblScope
                     unit="volume">2 vols</biblScope>. <series>Sanskrit Texts from the Tibetan
                     Autonomous Region</series>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Austrian Academy of Sciences</publisher>, in cooperation with
                     <publisher>China Tibetology Publishing House</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="TEI2020"><author>TEI Consortium</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title
                     level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                     Interchange</title>. <edition>Version 4.1.0</edition>. Last updated
                     <date>August 19</date>. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>: <publisher>TEI
                     Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
                     target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.1.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Thakur1987"><author>Thakur, Anantalal</author>, ed. <date>1987</date>.
                     <title level="m" xml:lang="sa">Jñānaśrīmitranibandhāvali: Buddhist
                     Philosophical Works of Jñānaśrīmitra</title>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>.
                     <series>Tibetan Sanskrit Works Series</series>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Patna</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Kashi Prasad Jayaswal Research Institute</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Thakur1997"><author>Thakur, Anantalal</author>. <date>1997</date>.
                     <title level="m" xml:lang="sa">Nyāyabhāṣyavārttika of Bhāradvāja
                     Uddyotakara</title>. <series xml:lang="sa">Nyāyacaturgranthikā</series>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>. <pubPlace>New Delhi</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Indian Council of Philosophical Research</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Tubbetal2007"><author>Tubb, Gary A.</author>, and <author>Emery R.
                     Boose</author>. <date>2007</date>. <title level="m">Scholastic Sanskrit: A
                     Handbook for Students</title>. <series>Treasury of the Indic Sciences</series>.
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>The American Institute of Buddhist
                     Studies at Columbia University</publisher> and <publisher>Columbia University
                     Press</publisher>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Chicago2010"><author>University of Chicago Press</author>.
                     <date>2010</date>. <title level="m">The Chicago Manual of Style</title>.
                     <edition>16th ed</edition>. <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>: <publisher>University
                     of Chicago Press</publisher>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <figure xml:id="example_11">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <div xml:id="jna">
                     <p> ... <seg xml:id="j1">tatraikas tāvad bāhyo ’dhyavasāyād eva vācyo
                           vyavasthāpyate, na svalakṣaṇaparisphūrttyā katham iti cet? anubhavād eva.
                           yathā hi pratyakṣacetasi deśakālāvasthāniyatāni parisphuṭarūpāṇi
                           svalakṣaṇāni pratibhānty anubhūyante, tathā na vikalpakāle. vikalpakāle
                           hi vijātivyāvṛttameva parasparākārākīrṇam ivāsphuṭam iva
                           pratyakṣāparicitaṃ kiñcid rūpam ābhāsamānam anubhavaviṣayaḥ. <seg>yac
                                 <bibl corresp="#pvin1">chāstram</bibl>
                              <quote source="PVin.xml#v15">
                                 <lg>
                                    <l>śabdenāvyāpṛtākṣasya buddhāv apratibhāsanāt /</l>
                                    <l>arthasya dṛṣṭāv iva</l>
                                 </lg>
                              </quote> iti. </seg>
                        </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p><seg xml:id="j2">upāyabhedād ekasyaiva pratibhāsabhedaḥ. ekatra hi buddhāv
                           indriyam āśrayo 'nyatra śabdādīti cet? atrāpy uktam ...</seg> ... </p>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Source text from Jñānaśrīmitra’s <title level="a" xml:lang="sa"
                     >Apohaprakaraṇa</title> (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref19" target="#Thakur1987"
                     >p. 208, in Thakur 1987</ref>; for a translation, see <ref type="crossref"
                     target="#example_12">example 12</ref>). Markup as presupposed in <ref
                     type="crossref" target="#example_9">example 9</ref>.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="example_12">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <div>
                     <p>... Now of these, the first, the external, is conditionally adopted as what
                        is expressed only on the basis of determination, and not through the
                        appearance of a particular. If you say, “How is this so?” We say, “Purely on
                        the basis of experience.” For the way in which particulars are experienced
                        when they appear in perceptual awareness—fixed with respect to place, time,
                        and condition, and having a clearly manifest form—is not the way they are
                        experienced when we have a conceptual awareness of them. For when we have a
                        conceptual awareness of them, the object of our experience appears having a
                        certain form (1) which is not familiar from perceptual awareness, (2) which
                        is really excluded from what belongs to a different class, (3) which seems
                        as if it were mixed up with each and every individual form, and (4) which
                        seems as if it were unclear. <seg>As it is said <bibl corresp="#pvin1">in
                              the authoritative text, <author>Dharmakīrti’s</author>
                              <title>Pramānaviniścaya</title></bibl>, <quote source="PVin.xml#v15">
                              <lg>
                                 <l>... because through language, an object does not appear in the
                                    awareness of someone whose eye is inactive</l>
                                 <l>as it would in visual awareness.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </quote>
                        </seg></p>
                     <p>If you say, <quote>Because of a difference in method of awareness, there is
                           a difference in the appearance of one and the same thing. For the basis
                           of one awareness is the sense faculty and that of the other is language,
                           and the like.</quote> In response to this, Dharmakīrti has said, ....</p>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Translation by McCrea and Patil (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="refMcC"
                     target="#McCrea2010">2010, 60–61</ref>) of the text in <ref type="crossref"
                     target="#example_11">example 11</ref>, with relevant markup added and some
                  formatting removed.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="example_13">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <div xml:id="ratna">
                     <p>... <seg xml:id="r-context1" next="#r-context2">vidhiśabdena ca
                           yathādhyavasāyam atadrūpaparāvṛtto bāhyo ’rtho ’bhimataḥ,
                           yathāpratibhāsaṃ buddhyākāraś ca. <quote xml:id="r1" next="#r2"
                              type="silent">tatra bāhyo ’rtho ’dhyavasāyād eva śabdavācyo
                              vyavasthāpyate, na svalakṣaṇaparisphūrtyā, pratyakṣavad
                              deśakālāvasthāniyata pravyaktasvalakṣaṇāsphuraṇāt. <seg>yac <bibl
                                    corresp="#pvin1">chāstram</bibl>
                                 <quote source="PVin.xml#v15">
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>śabdenāvyāpṛtākṣasya buddhāv apratibhāsanāt /</l>
                                       <l>arthasya dṛṣṭāv iva </l>
                                    </lg>
                                 </quote> iti.</seg></quote></seg></p>
                     <p>
                        <seg xml:id="r-context2" prev="#r-context1"><quote xml:id="r2" prev="#r1"
                              type="silent">indriyaśabdasvabhāvopāyabhedād ekasyaivārthasya
                              pratibhāsa bheda iti cet. atrāpy uktam ... </quote> ...</seg>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">First instance of silently reused text in Ratnakīrti’s <title
                     level="a" xml:lang="sa">Apohasiddhi</title> (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="ref20"
                     target="#Mcallister2020">pp. 53–54, in McAllister 2020</ref>; see the
                  translation in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_14">example 14</ref>). Markup
                  as presupposed in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_9">example 9</ref>.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="example_14">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <div>
                     <p>... <seg xml:id="r-context1" next="#r-context2">And by the word “positive
                           element” an external object that is distinguished from that of another
                           nature is meant according to determination, and according to appearance a
                           form of awareness [is meant]. <quote xml:id="r1" next="#r2" type="silent"
                              >Amongst these, the external object is defined as that to be expressed
                              by a word only because of determination, not because of a particular’s
                              appearance, since there is no appearance of a manifest particular that
                              is limited to a [certain] place, time and condition as [there is in
                              the case of] perception. <seg>[This is] what <bibl corresp="#pvin1"
                                    >the treatise</bibl> [says, too]: <quote source="PVin.xml#v15">
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>Because an object does not appear due to a word in the
                                          awareness of [someone having] an inactive sense organ</l>
                                       <l>in the same way as [it does] in perception [, .... ]</l>
                                    </lg>
                                 </quote></seg></quote></seg></p>
                     <p>
                        <seg xml:id="r-context2" prev="#r-context1"><quote xml:id="r2" prev="#r1"
                              type="silent">[Opponent:] There is a difference in the appearance of
                              [what is in fact] a single object, because the ways [of apprehending
                              an object, according] to the nature of a sense faculty [or] a word,
                              are different. [Proponent:] Also with regard to this it was said:
                              ...</quote> ...</seg>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Translation as in <ref type="bibl" xml:id="refMcA" target="#Mcallister2020">McAllister (2020, 96–97)</ref> of the text in <ref
                     type="crossref" target="#example_13">example 13</ref>, with markup
                  added.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="example_15">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <div xml:id="moksa">
                     <p>... <seg>tasmāt sthitam etat, <quote xml:id="m1" type="silent">bāhyārtho
                              'dhyavasāyād eva śabdavācye vyavasthāpyate; na tu
                              svalakṣaṇaparisphūrtyā; pratyakṣavad
                              deśakālākārāvasthānaniyatapravyaktasvalakṣaṇāsphuraṇāt. <seg>yad āha
                                    <persName corresp="#dharmakīrti">nyāyaparameśvaraḥ</persName>—
                                    <quote source="PVin.xml#v15">
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>sabdenāvyāpṛtākṣasya buddhāv apratibhāsanāt |</l>
                                       <l>arthasya dṛṣṭāv iva</l>
                                    </lg> iti </quote></seg></quote></seg></p>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Second instance of silently reused text in Mokṣākaragupta’s
                     <title level="a" xml:lang="sa">Tarkabhāṣā</title> (<ref type="bibl"
                     xml:id="ref21" target="#Iyengar1952">pp. 53–54, in Iyengar 1952</ref>; see the
                  translation in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_16">example 16</ref>). Markup
                  as presupposed in <ref type="crossref" target="#example_9">example 9</ref>.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="example_16">
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <div>
                     <p>... <seg>Therefore, this is established: <quote xml:id="m1" type="silent">An
                              external object is defined to be what a word denotes only on account
                              of determination; but not on account of an appearance with its
                              individual characteristic, because this object does not appear with
                              its individual characteristic that is fixed as to its location, time,
                              and state. <seg>Which <persName corresp="#dharmakīrti">the lord of
                                    logic</persName> said— <quote source="PVin.xml#v15">
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>Because an object does not appear due to a word in the
                                          awareness of [someone having] an inactive sense organ</l>
                                       <l>in the same way as [it does] in perception [, .... ]</l>
                                    </lg>
                                 </quote></seg></quote></seg></p>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <head type="legend">Translation of the text in <ref type="crossref"
                     target="#example_15">example 15</ref>, with corresponding markup.</head>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
