<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://github.com/DH-RSE/software-citation/raw/main/schema/tei_jtei_annotated.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Medieval Glosses as a Test Subject for the Building of Tools for Digital
          Critical Editions</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <forename>Emmanuelle</forename>
            <surname>Kuhry</surname>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Emmanuelle Kuhry is a <roleName>postdoctoral researcher</roleName> in digital
            humanities applied to medieval manuscript studies at <orgName>Institut de Recherche et
              d’Histoire des Textes</orgName>, CNRS (Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique). </affiliation>
          <email>emmanuelle.kuhry@irht.cnrs.fr</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>22/08/2021</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license has
              been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Susan Schreibman</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Tanja Wissik</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Joel Kalvesmaki</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Pietro Maria Liuzzo</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Tiago Sousa Garcia</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="13">Selected Papers from the 2018 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals
          in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish
          full-text articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>critical editions</term>
          <term>tools</term>
          <term>medieval manuscripts</term>
          <term>Oxford gloss</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2020-08-26">Ron Van den Branden applied author’s proofing corrections.</change>
      <change when="2021-08-22">Ron Van den Branden encoded the file.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
        <p>The thirteenth-century Latin corpus of the Oxford gloss has challenging features. A
          digital scholarly edition of this corpus necessitates innovative solutions that on the one
          hand account for the complex structure and content of the text and its manuscript
          transmission, and on the other hand convey these data comprehensibly to the reader. There
          are still few user-friendly tools which allow scholars to encode a digital critical
          edition easily, particularly its critical apparatus, in TEI XML. In this article, I
          document my approach to editing a digital corpus of philosophical glosses, and explain the
          tools I am using and customizing to make available to a larger public of digital scholarly
          editors, especially in the field of medieval studies.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="oxfordgloss">
        <head>The Oxford Gloss</head>
        <p>The Oxford gloss, or <foreign xml:lang="la">glossa anglicana</foreign>,<note>To read more
            about the Oxford gloss, see Burnett (<ref type="bibl" target="#burnett96">1996</ref>);
            R. K. French (<ref type="bibl" target="#burnett97">1997</ref>).</note> is a chain of
          annotations copied in thirteenth-century manuscripts around the Latin translations of
          Aristotle’s treatises on nature.<note>The corpus gathers the <soCalled>older</soCalled>
            Latin translations of Aristotle’s treatises on nature, which is why it is named <foreign
              xml:lang="la">corpus vetustius</foreign>. These translations were completed between
            the middle of the twelfth century and the middle of the thirteenth century, before
            William of Moerbeke’s translations in the 1260s and 1270s (the latter are called
                <soCalled><foreign xml:lang="la">corpus recentius</foreign></soCalled>). The former
            are: <title level="m">Physica</title>, <title level="m">De celo et mundo</title> (On the
            Heavens), <title level="m">De generatione et corruptione</title> (On Generation and
            Corruption), <title level="m">Meteora</title> (Meteorology), <title level="m">De
              plantis</title> (On Plants, apocryphal), <title level="m">De anima</title> (On the
            Soul), <title level="m">De memoria et reminiscentia</title> (On Memory), <title
              level="m">De sensu et sensato</title> (On Sense and the Sensible), <title level="m">De
              somno et vigilia</title> (On Sleep), <title level="m">De morte et vita</title> (On
            Youth and Old Age, Life and Death, and Respiration), <title level="m">De differentiis
              spiritus et anime</title> (On the Differences between the Spirit and the Soul,
            apocryphal), <title level="m">Liber de causis</title> (Book of Causes,
            apocryphal).</note></p>
        <figure xml:id="figure1">
          <graphic url="images/figure1.jpg" width="3093px" height="1376px"/>
          <head type="legend">First folio of <title level="m">Physica</title> in manuscripts
            Firenze, Biblioteca Medicea Laurenziana Plut.13 sin.5, f. 1; London, British Library
            Royal 12 G II, f. 2; and London, British Library Harley 3487, f. 4.</head>
        </figure>
        <p>The Aristotelian text was written in the middle of the page, in a large module. Most of
          the gloss was copied in the margins, which were designed to accommodate several columns of
          those notes, but a significant portion was placed between the lines. Each manuscript
          therefore has both marginal and interlinear annotations, which are referred to universally
          as glosses, no matter the length or content. Different techniques were used, even on the
          same page, to link a marginal gloss to its lemma, the word or phrase in the central text.
          Either an attachment sign was copied above the lemma and reproduced beside the gloss, or
          the lemma was repeated at the beginning of the gloss.</p>
        <div xml:id="glossorscholion">
          <head>Gloss or Scholion?</head>
          <p>The term <term>gloss</term> is sometimes distinguished from the term
              <term>scholion</term> or <term>scholium</term>. Both designate marginal or interlinear
            notes. For most scholars, a gloss explains a particular word through synonyms or a brief
            definition, whereas a <term>scholium</term> treats a larger part of the text and
            provides part of a general commentary (<ref type="bibl" target="#tov20">Tov 2020,
              41–42</ref>). E. Tov lists even other types of additions, like interlinear and
            marginal corrections, exegetical elements, variant readings, or scribal remarks, but in
            the end he admits that it is difficult to distinguish between them. Other scholars treat
            a <term>scholium</term> as a specific kind of gloss that is longer than average, and has
            an interpretative or explanatory nature. Glosses can be assembled in a separate
            commentary, and one can distinguish them according to a typology: prosodic, lexical,
            morphological, etc. (<ref type="bibl" target="#wieland98">Wieland 1998, 59–60</ref>). In
            glossed Bibles, <term>scholia</term> would be notes added in the margins for teaching
            purposes, but not pertaining to the <term>Glossa ordinaria</term>, the corpus of glosses
            on the Biblical text standardized in the twelfth century (<ref type="bibl"
              target="#morard17b">Morard 2017b</ref>). In the Oxford gloss, it is difficult to
            differentiate between glosses and <term>scholia</term> along the lines proposed by
            scholars for other corpora, such as position or length. Some interlinear glosses in one
            manuscript are marginal in another, and one version of a gloss might be short in one
            manuscript but in another it might be lengthy. It is nevertheless possible to
            distinguish types of glosses: lexical, translation-related, paraphrasing, variant
            readings, or commentary (some of which are lengthy, and quote from one or more other
            authors). Besides, as E. Tov (<ref type="bibl" target="#tov20">2020, 41</ref>) states,
            the term <term>glossa</term> or <term>gloss</term> is not used in the same way in Greek
            studies, because the Greek term <foreign xml:lang="gr">γλῶσσα</foreign> designates a
            word in a foreign language or dialect which needs an explanation. It seems that the
            meaning of explanation of an individual word, which was attached to the term
              <term>glossa</term> in the High Middle Ages as a continuation of the meaning inherited
            from the Greek, gradually dissolved into the larger meaning of <soCalled>marginal and
              interlinear commentary</soCalled> in the Late Middle Ages, as can be witnessed in the
            case of the <term>Glossa ordinaria</term> or of the <term>Oxford gloss</term>, which
            both designate a corpus of notes, both marginal and interlinear, attached to a central
            text, and for which the term <term>scholium</term> is seldom found in the literature. As
            a matter of fact, and with the meaning of marginal commentary in medieval manuscripts,
              <term>scholium</term> is a modern term, not used in this way in medieval lexicon and
            bibliotheconomy; <term>scholia</term> were then designated by the terms
              <term>notulae</term>, <term>glossae</term>, or sometimes <term>distinctiones</term>
              (<ref type="bibl" target="#morard17b">Morard 2017b</ref>).</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="materiality">
          <head>Materiality of the Oxford Gloss</head>
          <p>Around twenty-six manuscripts have been found to contain part of the Oxford gloss. A
            complete textbook usually has two hundred to three hundred folios.<note>On average the
              dimensions of the textbooks are 300 x 200 cm. See the entries for <term>Corpus
                vetustius</term> in the <title level="m">Aristoteles Latinus Codices</title> (see
                <ptr type="crossref" target="#note16"/>).</note> In the manuscripts, not every
            treatise was glossed to the same extent. Some treatises are very sparsely glossed, and
            others receive glosses of another origin (for instance, Thomas Aquinas’s commentaries)
            that, obviously, do not belong to the corpus of the Oxford gloss.</p>
          <p>Masters of Arts created the gloss at the University of Oxford so that students could
            understand Aristotelian philosophy. The gloss is believed to originate from the middle
            of the thirteenth century, but recent studies suggest that it was in use much earlier,
            maybe as early as the twelve twenties (<ref type="bibl" target="#kuhry19">Kuhry
              2019</ref>).<note>See also <ptr type="crossref" target="#note8"/>.</note> It reflects
            a lively learning environment in Oxford. Students copied glosses either during or after
            lectures—thus implying oral transmission—or they copied them from a manuscript
            model.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="structures">
        <head>Challenging Structures</head>
        <p>From the researcher’s point of view, this material is remarkably complex. Unlike the
          Biblical gloss,<note>About the Biblical gloss, see the Glossae Scripturae
            Sacrae-electronicae (Gloss-e) program: the blog <bibl><title level="m">Sacra
                Pagina</title>, accessed June 3, 2021, <ptr target="https://big.hypotheses.org/"
              /></bibl>, and the digital edition <bibl><title level="a">Gloses et commentaires de la
                Bible latine au Moyen Âge</title>, accessed June 3, 2021, <ptr
                target="https://gloss-e.irht.cnrs.fr"/></bibl>.</note> which achieved a high level
          of standardization, the Oxford gloss is quite variable across the manuscripts, which show
          different levels of transmission between text and gloss as well as changes in the
          marker-lemma which appears at the head of the gloss.<note>For a typology of the concept of
            lemma in medieval glosses, see Morard (<ref type="bibl" target="#morard17a"
            >2017a</ref>).</note> There are thus at least three different possible levels of
          transmissions of the glossed text: at the levels of the central text, the lemma, and the
          gloss’s content.<note>See <ptr target="#features" type="crossref"/> below.</note></p>
        <p>The high level of variation among the manuscripts points to another factor of complexity:
          that the gloss is usually considered to result from oral transmission. This means that one
          cannot understand the text solely in terms of witnesses copied from a textual model. On
          the other hand, there is evidence for some transmission through copying: common errors
          between two witnesses, or a similar presentation of some groups of glosses in two or more
          manuscripts, which cannot be explained by the layout features of the manuscript or the
          position of the lemmas. Such features must have been arranged that way in imitation of a
          manuscript model.</p>
        <p>The Oxford gloss gives us an insight, albeit indirect, to a reality which is still hard
          to apprehend concretely: the acts of teaching and of learning in thirteenth-century
          universities. Unfortunately, the location of the glosses (between the lines, in the
          margins), as well as their small size, make them difficult to read. Few editions have been
          published. The consequence is that the corpus is seldom used in academic research.</p>
        <p>Beside the structural features, intertextual features need to be highlighted, such as the
          relationship between the Oxford gloss and its sources, like Averroes’s commentaries, and
          between the gloss and thirteenth-century literature that quoted it. As a matter of fact,
          careful identification shows that some later authors incorporated some of the glosses in
          their texts without ever distinguishing them, as if they were part of the cited
          Aristotelian text.<note xml:id="note8">At least two authors use quotations of the Oxford
            gloss in the second third of the thirteenth century: Bartholomeus Anglicus in his
            best-selling encyclopedia <title level="m">De proprietatibus rerum</title>, and the
            anonymous author of the Aristotelian compilation <title level="m">Compendium
              philosophie</title> or <title level="m">Compilatio de libris naturalibus
              Aristotelis</title> (<ref target="#venture07" type="bibl">Ventura 2007</ref>; <ref
              target="#kuhry19" type="bibl">Kuhry 2019</ref>).</note></p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="digiglosses">
        <head>The <soCalled>Digigloses</soCalled> Project</head>
        <div xml:id="editorialproblems">
          <head>Editorial Problems</head>
          <p>The fluid and variant character of the glosses and of their links to the text make them
            difficult to edit. The few paper editions are partial (<ref target="#burnett97"
              type="bibl">Burnett and Mendelsohn 1997</ref>; <ref target="#french97" type="bibl">R.
              K. French 1997</ref>; <ref target="#french98" type="bibl">E. J. French 1998</ref>;
              <ref target="#galle08" type="bibl">Galle 2008</ref>). Representing the links between
            the glosses and the text and the variant character of the glosses and the lemmata proves
            to be a problem in all of them. The most accurate edition is not very easy to read (<ref
              target="#galle08" type="bibl">Galle 2008</ref>). The corpus is huge, as the twenty-six
            or so manuscripts span a dozen different treatises. There is no electronic edition yet.
            My current project aims to make an electronic edition of the gloss on <title level="m"
              >De plantis</title>. The edition will provide a critical text, but also let the reader
            follow text and gloss as easily as a medieval reader could do, that is, text and gloss
            being immediately connected to one another.</p>
          <p>Reproducing the medieval layout seems a difficult goal to reach, whether in print or
            digitally. The medieval annotators arranged the material to fit the space left on the
            page. To spare writing space they could abbreviate some places, or tighten the script.
            They could adapt the writing and disposition of the glosses according to the situation
            and context, because they could see and reflect on the text as readers. Tailoring an
            algorithm to resolve contextual and potentially subjective issues seems rather
            cumbersome, and to promise uncertain results. New solutions must be found to represent
            glossed corpora, other than the paper or digital editions tried so far.<note>I give a
              survey of such solutions in my contribution (<ref target="#kuhry20" type="bibl">Kuhry
                2020</ref>).</note></p>
          <p>The high degree of variation between witnesses, both in content and in presentation of
            the glosses, as well as the uncertainty about the transmission of the text (oral,
            written, or both) both make the idea of a stemmatic or reconstructed edition irrelevant,
            if not wrong-headed. Furthermore, the very instability and mutability of the manuscript
            tradition best helps us understand medieval teaching; differences are windows into the
            lively and social context which generated them. This is perhaps one of the main values
            of an edition based on the manuscript tradition, unlike the sole publication of a
            reconstructed text, as the content of the gloss is mainly a compilation of commentaries,
            and can probably not be retraced to an archetypal authorial version.<note>About the lack
              of <soCalled>authorial</soCalled> character, see <ptr type="crossref" target="#note17"
              />. Siemens et al. (<ref target="#siemens16" type="bibl">2016</ref>) reach a similar
              conclusion about the importance of accounting for the social context of the
              text.</note> On the contrary, the Oxford gloss is the result of gradual, collaborative
            work by Masters of Arts of the University of Oxford throughout the second third of the
            thirteenth century (<ref target="#kuhry19" type="bibl">Kuhry 2019</ref>).<note
              xml:id="note11">Identification of the sources of the Oxford gloss and of the texts of
              Adam of Buckfield, an early commentator of the Aristotelian treatises on nature at
              Oxford, shows that Buckfield, while being a major source for the gloss, probably
              himself used a primitive state of the gloss (<ref target="#kuhry19" type="bibl">Kuhry
                2019</ref>).</note> The ideal edition should thus represent the peculiarities of
            each of several manuscripts that carry a given treatise, to help readers identify those
              layers.<note>See Pierazzo (<ref target="#pierazzo16b" type="bibl">2016b</ref>), who
              argues for an opposition between a Neoplatonic view of texts, which perpetuates the
              notion of an ideal text to be reconstructed, and a Heraclitean view, which accepts and
              accounts for the mutability of texts.</note></p>
          <p>On the other hand, an edition which provides merely facsimiles or document-centered
            editions of each manuscript would not be a satisfactory scholarly edition.<note
              xml:id="note13">P. Robinson (<ref target="#robinson13" type="bibl">2013</ref>) exposes
              the debate between advocates of document-centered and text-centered editions,
              concluding that facsimile editions are not suited to creating a dialogue between the
              reader, the edition, and the editor, and that a digital scholarly edition should not
              concentrate on the document alone, but should provide the reader with means to explore
              the text. F. Fischer (<ref target="#fischer17" type="bibl">2017</ref>) stresses the
              need for digital editions to supply critical value, corresponding to critical
              annotation. He also calls for ways to search corpora of digital critical editions from
              a single gateway in addition to the possibilities offered on each distinct digital
              critical edition website. F. Duval (<ref target="#duval17" type="bibl">2017</ref>)
              argues for editions both critical and documentary, and highlights the importance of
              enlightening the reader about the complexity of the transmission of texts, which
              necessitates some form of critical apparatus to accompany an edition (<ref
                target="#duval17" type="bibl">Duval 2017</ref>).</note> Born-digital critical
            editions are also different from print critical editions that have been
              digitized.<note>Digital scholarly editions cannot be printed without loss of content
              and functionality, and depend on a digital paradigm in their conception: see Sahle
                (<ref target="#sahle16" type="bibl">2016</ref>).</note> They must offer features not
            found in a traditional critical edition, including means of reading, exploring, and
            analyzing the text.<note>See the state of the art about functionalities, including the
              distinction between the concepts of <soCalled>scriptons</soCalled> (strings as they
              appear to the readers) and <soCalled>textons</soCalled> (strings as they exist in the
              text), described by Pierazzo (<ref target="#pierazzo16a" type="bibl">2016a,
                34–36</ref>).</note> Document-centered editions and digitized critical editions are
            thus two models from which any digital critical edition should be distinguished.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="features">
          <head>Features of the Corpus</head>
          <p>In the edition I am preparing of <title level="m">De plantis</title>, I have determined
            that the corpus has the following main features: <list rend="ordered">
              <item>From one glossed manuscript to another, the central text can be variant, with
                missing, variant, or additional lemmata, which means that the central text should
                display textual variance. The glosses being fluid, it is not possible to restrict
                the encoding to the lemmata: the entire Aristotelian text must also be encoded. On
                the other hand, the purpose is not to redo the <title level="m">Aristoteles
                  latinus</title>.<note xml:id="note16">Initiated in 1930 under the auspices of the
                  International Union of Academies, the <title level="m">Aristoteles latinus</title>
                  project envisions publishing critical editions of all the Latin translations of
                  Aristotle’s texts, and of the works falsely attributed to him, that circulated in
                  the Middle Ages. To this end, a catalogue of all manuscripts containing Latin
                  translations of Aristotle was established: as a result, the three volumes of the
                    <title level="m">Aristoteles Latinus Codices</title> were published from 1939 to
                  1961 by a commission directed by G. Lacombe, followed by L. Minio-Paluello (<ref
                    target="#lacombe39" type="bibl">Lacombe et al. 1939</ref>, <ref
                    target="#lacombe55" type="bibl">1955</ref>; <ref target="#minio61" type="bibl"
                    >Minio-Paluello 1961</ref>), now available at <ptr
                    target="https://hiw.kuleuven.be/dwmc/al/DALE"/>. So far, thirty volumes of
                  editions of Latin translations have been published. To this enterprise can be
                  added the parallel project of Aristoteles Semitico-Latinus, which aims to publish
                  the Syriac, Arabic, and Hebrew translations of Aristotle’s works, of their Latin
                  translations, and of their medieval commentaries.</note> Only the glossed
                manuscripts are transcribed and encoded.</item>
              <item>At a given passage from <title level="m">De plantis</title>, a gloss might be in
                one manuscript but not another, or may come in different versions. Because I wish to
                show such variation, the glosses’ variants must be encoded too.</item>
              <item>A given gloss can be linked to different lemmata from one manuscript to another,
                or to a lemma not existing in the manuscript, which means that the design of the
                encoding should take into account the fluidity of the glosses, to reflect accurately
                the state of the manuscript tradition.</item>
              <item>One gloss in one manuscript can be two or three in another.</item>
              <item>One gloss can be interlinear in one manuscript but marginal in another.</item>
              <item>Glosses in the same manuscript might be written by several hands.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>These last two characteristics imply that any encoded gloss must allow additional
            levels of description, beside the text and its variants.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="editorialprinciples">
          <head>Editorial Principles</head>
          <p>For this corpus, which is far less standardized than the Biblical <term>Glossa
              ordinaria</term>, stemmatical reconstruction of the text is irrelevant, even if it
            were possible, as I have already said.<note xml:id="note17">A. Andrée draws the same
              conclusion about the <term>Glossa ordinaria</term> and the lack of
                <soCalled>authorial</soCalled> character in this type of text (<ref
                target="#andree16" type="bibl">2016, 9–10</ref>).</note> Before the digital edition
            can be published, several steps must be completed, according to a specific
              methodology.<note>I have described the methodology (<ref target="#kuhry20" type="bibl"
                >Kuhry 2020</ref>).</note> The manuscript witnesses must be classified according to
            the glosses’ typology. In the absence of precise dating for the copying of the glosses,
            a typology can be achieved only after significant samples have been collated for each
            one. Collected samples should help to identify layers of composition in the glosses’
            content, and thus to define stages in the development of the glossed corpus in the
            thirteenth century.<note>An example of an interesting research question that might be
              answerable: can we identify glosses dating from a pre-Buckfield era? (See <ptr
                type="crossref" target="#note11"/>.)</note> Then, a base manuscript containing an
            extended version of the glosses is chosen and the variants of the most significant
            manuscripts of each type are collated against its text. This comparative activity will
            enable the creation of a thesaurus of the glosses, each gloss archetype—a gloss in an
            abstract sense, instantiated in different versions—receiving a unique identifier.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="tools">
          <head>Creating Versatile Tools for Digital Scholarly Editions</head>
          <p>In her paper presented at the 2015 TEI Conference, M. Burghart (<ref
              target="#burghart16" type="bibl">2016</ref>) describes three areas in which the
            digital scholarly editor of medieval texts could need help: detection of human errors in
            the apparatus, ability to display different versions of the work-in-progress edition
            (corresponding to the text of different manuscripts), and handling of editions encoded
            with <gi>rdg</gi> or <gi>lem</gi> elements in the apparatus. Those needs are met by the
            <ptr type="software" xml:id="R6"
              target="#teicat"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R6">TEI Critical Apparatus Toolbox</rs>, which she created.<rs type="soft.agent soft.url" ref="#R6"><note><bibl><author>Marjorie
                Burkhart</author> et al.</bibl>, <title level="u">TEI Critical Apparatus Toolbox</title>,
                accessed June 3, 2021, <ptr target="http://teicat.huma-num.fr/"/>.</note></rs> I
            would add another prior and very basic need: finding help to encode the edition. Indeed,
            the task of encoding is described as the main difficulty confronted by TEI users, partly
            because of the lack of user-friendly tools (<ref target="#burghart12" type="bibl"
              >Burghart and Rehbein 2012</ref>). One can find tools to annotate images and
            transcribe sources,<note>Such tools include <ptr type="software" xml:id="R7"
              target="#transkribus"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R7">Transkribus</rs> (from <rs type="soft.agent" ref="#R7">READ-COOP SCE</rs>, accessed
              June 3, 2021, <rs type="soft.url" ref="#R7"><ptr target="https://transkribus.eu/Transkribus/"/></rs>) and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R8"
                target="#archetype"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R8">Archetype</rs>
              (previously called the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R9"
                target="#digipal"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R9">DigiPal framework</rs>, now supported by <rs type="soft.agent" ref="#R8">King’s Digital Laboratory,
              King’s College London</rs>, accessed June 3, 2021, <rs type="soft.url" ref="#R9"><ptr target="http://archetype.ink/"
              /></rs>).</note> but these tools do not enable the scholar to encode variants and the
            critical apparatus as specified in the TEI Guidelines. They are therefore purely
            document-centered tools, and we have seen above (see <ptr type="crossref"
              target="#note13"/>) that there is a general demand for text-oriented digital scholarly
            editions designed to be critical. Collation of several manuscripts can also produce an
            automatically encoded critical apparatus using the TEI parallel segmentation method, by
            means of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R10"
              target="#collatex"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R10">CollateX</rs> or <ptr type="software" xml:id="R11"
                target="#juxta"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R11">Juxta</rs> software, provided one already has the separate
            transcriptions at one’s disposal.<note><rs type="soft.agent" ref="#R10">Interedition Development Group, CollateX –
              Software for Collating Textual Sources</rs>, accessed June 4, 2021, <rs type="soft.url" ref="#R10"><ptr
                target="https://collatex.net/"/></rs>. For a history of collation tools and especially of
              the developments leading to <ptr type="software" xml:id="R12"
                target="#collatex"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R12">CollateX</rs>, see Nury and Spadini (<ref target="#nury20"
                type="bibl">2020</ref>). <ptr type="software" xml:id="R13"
                  target="#juxta"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R13">Juxta</rs> is no longer maintained; it has been replaced by two
              programs both developed by <rs type="soft.agent" ref="#R14 #R15">Performant Software Solutions</rs>: <ptr type="software" xml:id="R14"
                target="#faircopy"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R14">Faircopy</rs> (accessed June 4,
              2021, <rs type="soft.url" ref="#R14"><ptr target="https://faircopyeditor.com/"/></rs>), a transcription interface
              producing TEI encoding, and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R15"
                target="#textlab"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R15">TextLab</rs> (accessed June 4, 2021, <rs type="soft.url" ref="#R15"><ptr
                  target="https://www.textlab.org/"/></rs>), which seems to be more focused on genetic
              editing. However, a legacy version of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R16"
                target="#juxta"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R16">Juxta</rs>, accessed June 4, 2021, can be found at
                <rs type="soft.url" ref="#R15"><ptr target="https://www.juxtasoftware.org/download/"/></rs>. Roeder (<ref
                target="#roeder20" type="bibl">2020</ref>) provides a survey of three web-based
              tools offering automated collation.</note> As such, the result is not a proper
            critical edition, as no selection of variants has been made to produce a critical text
            with an apparatus. Critical editors therefore still need a user-friendly tool which
            allows them to establish the edited text, select variants, and introduce all the
            necessary critical annotation.</p>
          <p>As a matter of fact, many scholars are invited by the TEI to encode their research data
            but they have neither the time nor the opportunity to get proper training in TEI XML
            encoding. So the second part of the project consists in creating a panel of tools for
            the encoding of ancient textual sources in TEI XML. These tools will enhance existing
            software, and not create it from scratch.</p>
          <p>The tools include <ptr type="software" xml:id="R1" target="#xslt"/><rs
              type="soft.name" ref="#R1">XSLT</rs> stylesheets that convert styled Word or
            LibreOffice documents to TEI XML.<note>Sample transformations can already be made using
              <ptr type="software" xml:id="R17"
                target="#oxgarage"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R17">OxGarage</rs> (accessed June 4, 2021, <rs type="soft.url" ref="#R17"><ptr target="https://oxgarage.tei-c.org/"/></rs>), and
                <ptr type="software" xml:id="R2" target="#teistylesheets"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R2"
                >XSLT stylesheets</rs> can be found in the <rs type="soft.agent" ref="#R2">TEI Consortium</rs>’s <ptr type="software" xml:id="R18"
                  target="#github"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R18">GitHub</rs> repository,
              accessed June 4, 2021,<rs type="soft.url" ref="#R2"><ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets"/></rs>.</note>
            Pre-encoding a text in a word processor can be useful, but frequently a deeper level of
            encoding is needed, which is difficult to reach working only on the text document. So a
            second category of tools is a series of frameworks or encoding environments made through
            customization of two widely used XML editors: <list rend="bulleted">
              <item><ref target="https://www.xmlmind.com/index.html"><ptr type="software" xml:id="R19"
                target="#xmlmind"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R19">XMLmind XML Editor</rs></ref>
                  (XXE),<note>Accessed June 4, 2021, <rs type="soft.url" ref="#R19"><ptr
                    target="https://www.xmlmind.com/index.html"/></rs>. Customization of this editor is a
                  central part of the work of the Document numérique team of Maison de la Recherche
                  en Sciences Humaines (MRSH) de Caen (see the Métopes workflow, accessed August 14,
                  2021, <ptr target="http://www.metopes.fr/index.html"/>). <ptr type="software" xml:id="R20"
                    target="#xmlmind"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R20">XMLmind XML Editor</rs> was
                  used in the team’s collaboration with the Biblissima Equipex (Equipment of
                  Excellence project funded by the French National Research Agency – ANR), for which
                  an encoding environment for ancient library catalogues was issued: Digital
                  environment for scientific editing in XML-TEI of lists of books from ancient
                  libraries, accessed June 4, 2021, <ptr
                    target="https://outils.biblissima.fr/fr/outils-edition-xml/"/>.</note> which I
                used to build a critical edition encoding environment. The encoding environment
                allows one to display the document in different views thanks to the use of CSS
                stylesheets, and to automate and speed up the encoding tasks with custom
                commands.</item>
              <item><ref target="https://www.oxygenxml.com/"><ptr type="software" xml:id="R22"
                target="#oxygen"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R22">Oxygen XML Editor</rs></ref>,<note>Accessed
                  June 4, 2021, <rs type="soft.url" ref="#R22"><ptr target="https://www.oxygenxml.com/"/></rs>.</note> which supports
                right-to-left scripts, unlike the current version of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R23"
                  target="#xmlmind"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R23">XXE</rs> (however, recent steps have
                    been made in this direction by the developers of <ptr type="software" xml:id="R24"
                      target="#xmlmind"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R24">XXE</rs>). A framework similar to <ptr type="software" xml:id="R25"
                        target="#xmlmind"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R25">XXE</rs>’s
                was developed for <ptr type="software" xml:id="R26"
                  target="#oxygen"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R26">Oxygen</rs>’s Author mode, to be used by projects focusing on Hebrew or
                Arabic sources.<note>Since version 15.1, <ptr type="software" xml:id="R27"
                  target="#oxygen"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R27">Oxygen</rs> has handled RTL scripts quite
                  effectively in author mode (but not text mode). See discussions about this issue
                  on the Epidoc and TEI listservs: <bibl><author>Hugh Cayless</author>, <title
                      level="u">RTL texts</title>, MARKUP mailing list archives, February 13,
                      <date>2020</date>, <ptr
                      target="https://lsv.uky.edu/scripts/wa.exe?A2=MARKUP;a8d5593f.2002"/></bibl>,
                  and <bibl><author>David J. Birnbaum</author>, <title level="u">Editing Arabic
                      TEI</title>, TEI-L mailing list archives, February 2, <date>2017</date>, <ptr
                      target="https://listserv.brown.edu/cgi-bin/wa?A2=TEI-L;8f4291f.1702"/>.</bibl>
                  Information about directionality is not documented in TEI except in
                    <att>style</att> and <att>xml:lang</att>, and should be left to CSS:
                      <bibl><author>Martin Holmes</author>, <title level="u">Calling all Arabic and
                      Hebrew experts</title>, TEI-L mailing list archives, October 29,
                      <date>2013</date>, <ptr
                      target="https://listserv.brown.edu/cgi-bin/wa?A2=TEI-L;1bf8073.1310"/>.</bibl>
                  The CSS module <title level="m">Writing Modes Level 3</title> describes how to
                  handle RTL scripts (W3C Recommendation, edited by Elika J. Etemad and Koji Ishii,
                  December 10, 2019, <ptr
                    target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2019/REC-css-writing-modes-3-20191210/"
                />).</note></item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Customized frameworks in existing XML editors presents multiple advantages: <list
              rend="bulleted">
              <item>The use of CSS stylesheets makes the appearance of the document being encoded
                significantly more user-friendly, which helps scholars unfamiliar with TEI encoding
                  .<note>Some projects have been funded to produce an online TEI-encoded edition,
                  but the encoding is done by contractors who are usually experts in the scientific
                  field but are unfamiliar with TEI and XML.</note> Moreover, in both applications,
                views corresponding to different CSS configurations allow one to highlight groups of
                elements and attributes in different ways depending upon the work’s progress, thus
                facilitating the encoding tasks.</item>
              <item>In both applications, using custom commands and CSS stylesheets calling the
                commands or combined with CSS extensions enabling advanced encoding features allows
                the automatization of a great number of tasks, many of which are tiresome and
                error-prone when done by hand, like stand-off annotation, linking, or
                indexing.</item>
              <item>A framework can be adapted very easily to any other scholarly editing project.
                Each framework can be customized to the structure specified by the project, which is
                helpful for scholars with limited previous knowledge of XML and TEI, who could be
                confused by the myriad possibilities of the TEI All schema. Nevertheless, the raw
                encoding can be verified at any moment by switching to the text mode in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R28"
                  target="#oxygen"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R28">Oxygen</rs> or to
                the tree view in <ptr type="software" xml:id="R29"
                  target="#xmlmind"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R29">XXE</rs>.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>A framework can be configured to offer guidance for the use of elements and attributes,
            thanks to the use of custom commands and of features of CSS stylesheets like drop-down
            menus, checkboxes, and pop-ups.</p>
          <p>For instance, the attribute values of a number of elements can be listed and explained
            in the <gi>teiHeader</gi> by means of several <gi>valItem</gi> elements grouped in a
              <gi>valList</gi>. These values are informed by the editor at the beginning of the work
            and can be completed (but preferably not changed) at a later stage. <figure
              xml:id="figure2">
              <graphic url="images/figure2.png" height="765px" width="1268px"/>
              <head type="legend">In the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> element of the <gi>teiHeader</gi>,
                defining a list of values for the <att>place</att> attribute of the <gi>note</gi>
                element (<ptr type="software" xml:id="R30"
                  target="#oxygen"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R30">Oxygen</rs> framework).</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>In the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R31"
            target="#oxygen"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R31">Oxygen</rs> framework, inside the <gi>text</gi> element, the insertion of tags for
            which the typology of attribute values has been described in the <gi>teiHeader</gi> (and
            registered as available in drop-down menus) generates a drop-down menu listing these
            values, thanks to the use of XPath. <figure xml:id="figure3">
              <graphic url="images/figure3.png" height="189px" width="657px"/>
              <head type="legend">In the corpus, choosing one of the defined values for the
                <att>place</att> attribute of the <gi>note</gi> element (<ptr type="software" xml:id="R32"
                  target="#oxygen"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R32">Oxygen</rs> framework).</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>The same principle is used for references to witnesses in the critical apparatus, by
            means of the description of witnesses in the <gi>sourceDesc</gi>, and for references to
            particular hands described in <gi>handNote</gi>, inside a <gi>handDesc</gi>, which is a
            component of the <gi>msDesc</gi>.</p>
          <p>That way, the editor can customize the semantic part of the encoding (namely, the
            attribute values), in a <soCalled>go with the flow</soCalled> mode, that is, after the
            formalization of the structure. This <soCalled>open</soCalled> characteristic is
            essential when it comes to adapting the framework to different projects. On the other
            hand, the frameworks do not prevent the user from inserting unexpected tags or from
            coming up with different attributes than the ones suggested. Ultimately, a restriction
            of the schema is desirable, notably for validation purposes (<ref target="#burnard19"
              type="bibl">Burnard 2019</ref>).</p>
          <p>The challenge in developing encoding frameworks is not so much technical, as they use
            features available in each application. Frameworks consist of command configuration and
            CSS files, sometimes <ptr type="software" xml:id="R3" target="#xslt"/><rs
              type="soft.name" ref="#R3">XSLT</rs> files. They provide an economic, versatile way
            to provide scholars with customized tools for digital scholarly editing.<note>The
              <ptr type="software" xml:id="R33"
                target="#ediarum"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R33">Ediarum</rs> framework for Oxygen has been developed at the <rs type="soft.agent" ref="#R33">Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of
                  Sciences and Humanities</rs> to help scholars create digital editions of historical
              documents in TEI XML. However, this framework does not enable one to encode variant
              readings and is therefore not designed for critical editing of medieval sources. See
              <rs type="soft.bib.ref" ref="#R33">Mertgens (<ref target="#mertgens19" type="bibl">2019</ref>)</rs> and the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R34"
                target="#Ediarum"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R34">Ediarum</rs> website:
                <rs type="soft.url" ref="#R34"><ptr
                  target="https://www.bbaw.de/en/bbaw-digital/telota/research-and-software/ediarum"/></rs>.
              The Caen team Pôle Document numérique has since published a <ptr type="software" xml:id="R36"
                target="#unicaenapparat"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R36">framework for critical
              editing in TEI Parallel Segmentation</rs> based on <ptr type="software" xml:id="R35"
                target="#xmlmind"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R35">XMLmind XML Editor</rs> software: see <title
                level="u">Éditer des sources avec apparat critique</title>, accessed June 4, 2021,
                <rs type="soft.url" ref="#R36"><ptr target="http://www.unicaen.fr/recherche/mrsh/document_numerique/outils/apparat"
                /></rs>.</note> The challenge is rather about ontology and modeling.<note>I am taking part
              in a collective effort between scholarly editors and scientific publishing services
              (in collaboration with IRHT’s publication team, the Caen team, and Ecole nationale des
              Chartes) to collect and analyze editorial and encoding practices when it comes to
              ancient sources, in order to model a common core of editorial features and to make
              encoding and publishing tools more interoperable and complementary.</note></p>
          <p>Among the difficulties or constraints are thus: <list rend="ordered">
              <item>
                <p>the need to offer tools specialized enough to fill the particular needs of each
                  scholarly edition project, especially in the medieval field, but also generic and
                  customizable enough to be used by other projects.<note>About tools, E. Pierazzo
                    expresses the need for sustainability and ability to meet the needs of other
                    projects, which implies the modeling of the working methods and concepts of a
                    potentially large community of textual scholars (<ref target="#pierazzo16a"
                      type="bibl">2016a, 111</ref>).</note> A solution is to identify a core of
                  basic needs likely common to many projects, and create a library of specialized
                  commands for each scholar to apply as they like to their own project.<note>This
                    solution could be compared to T. Andrews’s and E. Pierazzo’s different
                    conceptions of a <soCalled>third way</soCalled> besides
                      <soCalled>traditional</soCalled> or <soCalled>manual</soCalled> philology and
                    use of the computer to satisfy precise needs without involvement from the
                    scholar (which E. Pierazzo calls <soCalled>computer-assisted
                      philology</soCalled>). T. Andrews’s idea of a third way involves complete
                    digital philology actively invested by the scholar in every step of the
                    editorial task, from transcription to analysis, which eventually produces
                    unexpected results, thanks to innovative tools and methods crafted by
                    philologists themselves, and finally to electronic publication (<ref
                      target="#andrews13" type="bibl">Andrews 2013</ref>; <ref target="#pierazzo16a"
                      type="bibl">Pierazzo 2016a, 109–16</ref>). E. Pierazzo doubts that
                    philologists can acquire such a highly technical profile in the near future,
                    with exceptions. She advocates instead for a <soCalled>bricks
                      approach</soCalled>: the definition of microtasks common to most text editing
                    projects and for which individual tools could be built, customized, and combined
                    in different ways according to the needs of each project (<ref
                      target="#pierazzo16a" type="bibl">2016a, 109–17</ref>). The approach described
                    in the present paper is closer to Pierazzo’s view.</note> The publication phase,
                  whether in print or in digital form, can be supported by existing tools which the
                  scholar can configure.<note>See, for example, the <soCalled>Print an
                      edition</soCalled> tool in the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R37"
                        target="#teicat"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R37">TEI Critical Apparatus Toolbox</rs> by M. Burghart,
                    in which the sample <ptr type="software" xml:id="R4" target="#xslt"/><rs
                      type="soft.name" ref="#R4">XSLT</rs> stylesheet to transform TEI XML into
                    LaTeX, to produce a printable PDF with a traditional critical apparatus, can be
                    downloaded and modified: <ptr target="http://teicat.huma-num.fr/print.php"/>.
                    Burghart (<ref target="#burghart16" type="bibl">2016</ref>) provides a survey of
                    transformation and display tools for scholarly editions encoded with TEI. TEI
                    Publisher (<ptr target="https://teipublisher.com/index.html"/>) and the Max
                    display engine (<ptr
                      target="http://www.unicaen.fr/recherche/mrsh/document_numerique/outils/max"/>)
                    are good candidates for online publication but the average scholarly editor
                    probably needs help using and customizing these tools, especially when creating
                    critical editions.</note></p>
                <p>The tools described in this paper are meant primarily for my colleagues in
                  medieval studies. Collaboration over several months has allowed me to collect
                  information about the precise needs of several digital scholarly edition
                    projects.<note>Namely, a project aiming to create an electronic critical edition
                    of a Hebrew dictionary of the thirteenth century and of its translation into
                    Latin (IRHT-CNRS, <ptr target="https://shorashim.hypotheses.org/"/>); an edition
                    project about the notebooks of a nineteenth-century blind medievalist (Orléans
                    University and IRHT-CNRS, <ptr target="https://archat.hypotheses.org/"/>); and a
                    project dealing with the electronic editing of medieval Latin encyclopedias
                    (IRHT-CNRS, <ptr target="http://sourcencyme.irht.cnrs.fr/"/>).</note> The
                  functionality and user-friendliness of the tools can be improved by enhancing the
                  underlying code in accordance with the needs expressed during this test phase.
                  Having been tested through use by scholars with little previous knowledge of
                  digital editing, the tools can be reused by any other project.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <p>the need to tailor the tools to the practice of scholars with little or no
                  previous training in encoding and to anticipate potential issues they might
                  confront while encoding.</p>
                <p>Regarding this point, collaboration with my colleagues leading projects has also
                  allowed me to draw a more precise sketch of their needs and of their behavior when
                  switching from the creation of a traditional critical edition to that of a digital
                  one.</p>
                <p>The tools will be available online as soon as they are tested and stable.
                  Currently two different frameworks are in testing phases in several projects. One
                  of these frameworks is for critical editions and one for genetic editions, the
                  latter being more document-centered. The user base includes all digital scholarly
                  editors, especially in medieval studies.</p>
              </item>
            </list>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="problemssolutions">
          <head>Problems and Solutions</head>
          <p>I was able to address the constraints imposed by the nature of the glossed corpus
            thanks to TEI encoding and to the support of frameworks. To test the selected solutions,
            I have encoded a small part of the text, the prologue of <title level="m">De
              plantis</title>, as follows: <list rend="bulleted">
              <item>The <soCalled>parallel segmentation</soCalled><note><ref target="#tei21"
                    type="bibl">TEI Consortium 2021, 12.2.3</ref>, <ptr
                    target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.2.2/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPPS"
                  />.</note> method has been used to encode the variant readings of the central text
                and of the glosses.<note>Parallel segmentation is not devoid of issues, mainly the
                  lack of support for overlapping structures and of transpositions, and for the
                  expression of critical data, like editorial comments, beside the variant itself:
                  see Buzzoni (<ref target="#buzzoni17" type="bibl">2017</ref>).</note></item>
              <item>Text and glosses have been separated into two files. Both are linked to one
                another via stand-off encoding, where the <att>target</att> attribute on the central
                text’s lemmata (i.e., the words to which the glosses refer, which are encoded in a
                  <gi>term</gi> element) points to the <att>xml:id</att> attribute of the gloss (see
                  <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure4"/>). A complete stand-off approach would be
                more difficult because the central text is not fixed: it receives more variant
                readings as new manuscripts of the Oxford gloss are collated.<note>By
                    <soCalled>complete</soCalled> stand-off, I mean a working scheme in which all
                  the encoding would be stored outside of the document. One of the goals of
                  stand-off encoding can be to preserve the text from interpretative marking (see
                    <ref target="#spadini19" type="bibl">Spadini and Turska 2019</ref>). In this
                  case I use stand-off encoding only to prevent overlapping structures when applying
                  several layers of encoding that correspond to different categories of analysis and
                  interpretation.</note> Under such an approach, tokenization is more complicated,
                since the target text is constantly moving, and therefore the tokens would be as
                well. Besides, encoding the glosses in the same file allows one to compare the
                different versions of a particular gloss while encoding, thanks to the parallel
                segmentation, and thus to facilitate part of the philological analysis. This
                arrangement accommodates the fluid nature of the glosses, which cannot be encoded in
                a fixed point in the text. To anchor a gloss to the text while expressing its
                fluidity from one manuscript to another, the <gi>term</gi> element is set inside an
                apparatus entry: in a <gi>rdg</gi> element contained in an <gi>app</gi> element.
              </item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>The consequence of encoding the lemma in a <gi>term</gi> is that the same lesson in two
            given manuscripts can result in two readings depending whether there is a lemma in one
            of them or not. This is indeed a problem because it overloads the critical apparatus,
            because the shifting of the lemma to another word from one manuscript to another is very
            common, and does not represent a variant reading in a strict sense. When encoding the
            lemma in a <gi>term</gi> element, which is itself hosted in a <gi>rdg</gi>, actual
            variant readings are mixed with lemmata, the latter being very numerous.<note>On the
              prologue of the <title level="m">De plantis</title> collated from seven manuscripts,
              in which this piece of text barely exceeds one folio, one finds 131 variant locations
                (<gi>app</gi> elements) holding lemmata, whereas only 50 variant locations do not
              have lemmata but have actual variant readings.</note> The problem might be solved by
            moving the lemma information somewhere else, possibly into another type of the
              <gi>witDetail</gi> element mentioned below, which should be located in the text after
            the word bearing the lemma quality, as if it were a note. The <gi>witDetail</gi> can
            have <att>wit</att> and <att>target</att> attributes, which point respectively to the
            witness in which the word is a lemma, and to the related gloss in the glosses’
            thesaurus.</p>
          <p>The framework is particularly helpful when encoding two files that must interlink.
              <figure xml:id="figure4">
              <graphic url="images/figure4.png" height="892px" width="1679px"/>
              <head type="legend">The working interface of the <ptr type="software" xml:id="R38"
                target="#xmlmind"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R38">XMLmind</rs> framework. The central pane
                shows the CSS-customized view of the file containing the central text. The left pane
                shows the—almost—raw code of the same file. The <ident>+</ident> command designed in
                the CSS to be available on the lemma (element <tag>term type="lemme"</tag>) opens a
                transformed version of the glosses’ thesaurus and allows one to choose the
                appropriate gloss archetype toward which the <att>target</att> attribute must point
                (<ptr type="software" xml:id="R39"
                  target="#xmlmind"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R39">XMLmind</rs> framework).</head>
            </figure>
            <list rend="bulleted">
              <item>In the file containing the glosses (the glosses’ library or thesaurus), each
                gloss archetype is encoded in an <ident>item</ident> element, inside a first-level
                apparatus entry containing two readings: the first listing the witnesses not
                containing the gloss and having a <att>type</att> attribute with value
                  <val>omission</val> (see <ptr type="crossref" target="#figure5"/>). This feature
                allows one to see easily, in the framework, a list of the witnesses transmitting the
                gloss or not. After the second <ident>rdg</ident> element, which contains the
                gloss’s text with internal variant readings, a <ident>witDetail</ident> element
                describes the location of the gloss in each witness (marginal or interlinear), by
                means of <att>n</att>, and to specify, if needed, the hand which copied the gloss,
                thanks to <att>corresp</att>. The <att>target</att> attribute identifies the
                  <gi>rdg</gi> at issue, and <att>wit</att> points to the precise
                witness(es).</item>
            </list>
            <figure xml:id="figure5">
              <graphic url="images/figure5.png" height="750px" width="1860px"/>
              <head type="legend">Display of the glosses’ thesaurus (<ptr type="software" xml:id="R40"
                target="#xmlmind"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R40">XMLmind</rs> framework).</head>
            </figure>
            <list rend="bulleted">
              <item><gi>lem</gi> elements are not used because there is no putative original text.
                Nevertheless, offering a single base text for a gloss archetype is a future
                possibility. A single reconstructed text seems to be necessary in a paper edition
                because of layout limitations. But it is also needed in a digital critical edition,
                which should provide a <quote source="#quoteref1">representative text version with a
                  canonical work structure</quote> (<ref xml:id="quoteref1" target="#fischer17"
                  type="bibl">Fischer 2017, S281</ref>), allowing citation and reuse both inside and
                outside the project. Translations, semantic analysis, inclusion in larger corpora,
                and so forth all need a canonical version.</item>
              <item>A future encoding layer will deal with the identification of the sources,
                probably with stand-off markup pointing to <gi>milestone</gi> elements framing the
                identified segment and referred to by the <att>target</att> of a <gi>note</gi>. Each
                  <gi>note</gi> will contain the references to the source of the passage, possibly
                through <att>source</att> on <gi>author</gi> and <gi>ref</gi>, within a
                  <gi>bibl</gi>.<note>This encoding scheme has been used on the SourcEncyMe corpus
                  of medieval Latin encyclopedias: <ptr target="http://sourcencyme.irht.cnrs.fr/"
                  />.</note></item>
            </list>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="display">
          <head>Display Possibilities</head>
          <p>A publication prototype has been created using <ptr type="software" xml:id="R5"
              target="#xslt"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R5">XSLT</rs> stylesheets and <ptr type="software" xml:id="R41"
                target="#javascript"/><rs type="soft.name" ref="#R41">Javascript</rs>
            to produce interactive HTML pages. The current version allows one to <list
              rend="bulleted">
              <item>read the reconstructed text of each manuscript;</item>
              <item>open each gloss in a pop-up with a click on the lemma (each pop-up can be moved
                where one likes);</item>
              <item>show interactive and optional layers of information, like textual variance (by
                means of a form of critical apparatus), distinction between glossing hands (by means
                of color), and critical notes.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>The transition from print to digital form represents a real opportunity for critical
            editions, with the possibility of offering more, if not all, available data.<note>E.
              Pierazzo writes about the <soCalled>page paradigm</soCalled> that continues to
              constrain digital scholarly editions (<ref target="#pierazzo16a" type="bibl">2016a,
                156</ref>).</note> But the danger of overwhelming the reader with a mass of data is
            real, as well as of losing the critical criterion which is a feature of scientific
            editions. A balance must be found between usability / readability and completeness. A
            selection of configurable (through display options) reading paths such as the ones
            provided by the digital editions published with the support of the <soCalled>Pôle
              Document numérique</soCalled> of MRSH Caen may be a solution.<note>See the list of
              projects at <ptr
                target="http://www.unicaen.fr/recherche/mrsh/document_numerique/projets"
            />.</note></p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="conclusion">
        <head>Conclusion</head>
        <p>Texts with complex structures allow one to test the limits of the technical possibilities
          available for historians not trained in computer science. In this paper, I have used the
          example of a corpus of medieval philosophical glosses to illustrate how TEI XML encoding
          can provide solutions to issues unsolved by print editions, among which are multiple
          layers of manuscript transmission, textual variance, and links between the central text
          and the glosses.</p>
        <p>I have tried to show that it is possible to build flexible tools for digital scholarly
          editing, namely building frameworks within existing XML editors. Quick-tech solutions like
          these are critical to a future that seems to promise ever-decreasing funding in the
          humanities.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl xml:id="andree16"><author>Andrée, Alexander</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title
              level="a">Editing the Gloss (Later <foreign xml:lang="la">Glossa Ordinaria</foreign>)
              on the Gospel of John: A Structural Approach.</title> In <title level="m">The Arts of
              Editing Medieval Greek and Latin: A Casebook</title>, edited by <editor>Elisabet
              Göransson</editor>, <editor>Gunilla Iversen</editor>, <editor>Barbara
              Crostini</editor>, <editor>Brian M. Jensen</editor>, <editor>Erika Kihlman</editor>,
              <editor>Eva Odelman</editor>, and <editor>Denis Searby</editor>, <biblScope
              unit="page">2–21</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>: <publisher>Pontifical
              Institute of Mediaeval Studies</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="andrews13"><author>Andrews, Tara L.</author>
            <date>2013</date>. <title level="a">The Third Way: Philology and Critical Edition in the
              Digital Age.</title>
            <title level="j">Variants</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">61–76</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.7892/boris.43071</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burghart16"><author>Burghart, Marjorie</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title
              level="a">The TEI Critical Apparatus Toolbox: Empowering Textual Scholars through
              Display, Control, and Comparison Features.</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1520"/>; doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.4000/jtei.1520</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burghart12"><author>Burghart, Marjorie</author>, and <author>Malte
              Rehbein</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title level="a">The Present and Future of the
              TEI Community for Manuscript Encoding.</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/372"/>; doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.4000/jtei.372</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burnard19"><author>Burnard, Lou</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title
              level="a">What Is TEI Conformance, and Why Should You Care?</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1777"/>; doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.4000/jtei.1777</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burnett96"><author>Burnett, Charles</author>. <date>1996</date>. <title
              level="a">The Introduction of Aristotle’s Natural Philosophy in Great Britain: A
              Preliminary Survey of the Manuscript Evidence.</title> In <title level="m">Aristotle
              in Britain during the Middle Ages</title>, edited by <editor>John Marenbon</editor>,
              <biblScope unit="page">21–50</biblScope>. <series>Rencontres de philosophie
              médiévale</series>
            <biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Turnhout, Belgium</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Brepols</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="burnett97"><author>Burnett, Charles</author>, and <author>Andrew
              Mendelsohn</author>. <date>1997</date>. <title level="a">Aristotle and Averroes on
              Method in the Middle Ages and Renaissance: The <soCalled>Oxford Gloss</soCalled> to
              the <title level="m">Physics</title> and Pietro d’Afeltro’s <title level="m">Expositio
                Proemii Averroys</title>.</title> In <title level="m">Method and Order in
              Renaissance Philosophy of Nature: The Aristotle Commentary Tradition</title>, edited
            by <editor>Daniel A. Di Liscia</editor>, <editor>Eckhard Kessler</editor>, and
              <editor>Charlotte Methuen</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">53–111</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Aldershot</pubPlace>: <publisher>Ashgate</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="buzzoni17"><author>Buzzoni, Marina</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title
              level="a">A Protocol for Scholarly Digital Editions? The Italian Point of
              View.</title> In <title level="m">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and
              Practices</title>, edited by <editor>Matthew James Driscoll</editor> and <editor>Elena
              Pierazzo</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">59–82</biblScope>. <series>Digital
              Humanities Series</series>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Open Book
              Publishers</publisher>. <ptr target="http://books.openedition.org/obp/3400"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="duval17"><author>Duval, Frédéric</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title
              level="a">Pour des éditions numériques critiques. L’exemple des textes
              français.</title>
            <title level="j">Médiévales</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">73</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">13–29</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.4000/medievales.8165</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="fischer17"><author>Fischer, Franz</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title
              level="a">Digital Corpora and Scholarly Editions of Latin Texts: Features and
              Requirements of Textual Criticism.</title>
            <title level="j">Speculum</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">92 (S1)</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">S265–87</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.1086/693823</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="french98"><author>French, Edmund J.</author>
            <date>1998</date>. <title level="u">Adam of Buckfield and the Early
              Universities.</title> PhD diss., University of London.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="french97"><author>French, Roger K.</author>
            <date>1997</date>. <title level="a">Teaching Aristotle in the Medieval English
              Universities: <title level="m">De Plantis</title> and the Physical <title level="m"
                >Glossa Ordinaria</title>.</title>
            <title level="j">Physis: Rivista Internazionale Di Storia Della Scienza</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">34</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
            >225–96</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="galle08"><editor>Galle, Griet</editor>, ed. <date>2008</date>. <title
              level="a">Edition and Discussion of the Oxford Gloss on <title level="m">De
                Sensu</title> I.</title>
            <title level="j">Archives d’ Histoire Doctrinale et Littéraire du Moyen Âge</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">75</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page"
            >197–281</biblScope>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kuhry19"><author>Kuhry, Emmanuelle</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title
              level="a">The <title level="m">Compilatio de Libris Naturalibus Aristotelis</title>
                (<title level="m">Compendium Philosophie</title>): Evidence for the Early Reception
              of the <title level="m">Glossa Anglicana</title> and of Adam of Buckfield’s
              Commentaries.</title>
            <title level="j">Recherches de Théologie et Philosophie Médiévales</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">283–313</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.2143/RTPM.86.2.3287114</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="kuhry20"><author>Kuhry, Emmanuelle</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title
              level="a">Vers une édition électronique de la glose d’Oxford</title> [Towards an
            Electronic Edition of the Oxford Gloss]. <title level="j">Humanités numériques</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>. <idno type="doi"
              >doi.org/10.4000/revuehn.450</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lacombe39"><author>Lacombe, Georges</author>, <author>Aleksander
              Birkenmajer</author>, <author>Marthe Dulong</author>, and <author>Etzio
              Franceschini</author>. <date>1939</date>. <title level="m">Aristoteles latinus:
              Codices.</title> Pars prior [vol. 1]. Union académique internationale. Corpus
            philosophorum Medii Aevi. <pubPlace>Rome</pubPlace>: <publisher>Libreria dello
              stato</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="lacombe55"><author>Lacombe, Georges</author>, <author>Aleksander
              Birkenmajer</author>, <author>Marthe Dulong</author>, <author>Etzio
              Franceschini</author>, and <author>Lorenzo Minio-Paluello</author>. <date>1955</date>.
              <title level="m">Aristoteles latinus: Codices.</title> Pars posterior [vol. 2]. Union
            académique internationale. Corpus philosophorum Medii Aevi.
              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Cambridge University
            Press</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="mertgens19"><author>Mertgens, Andreas</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title
              level="a">Ediarum: A Toolbox for Editors and Developers.</title>
            <title level="j">RIDE: A Review Journal for Digital Editions and Resources</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-11/ediarum/"/>; doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.18716/ride.a.11.4</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="minio61"><editor>Minio-Paluello, Lorenzo</editor>, ed. <date>1961</date>.
              <title level="m">Aristoteles latinus: Codices.</title> Supplementa altera. Union
            académique internationale. Corpus philosophorum Medii Aevi. <pubPlace>Bruges</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Desclée de Brouwer</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="morard17a"><author>Morard, Martin</author>. <date>2017</date>a. <title
              level="a">Le texte biblique des livres glosés.</title>
            <title level="m">Sacra Pagina: Gloses et commentaires de la Bible latine au Moyen Âge
              (blog)</title>. October 1. <ptr target="https://big.hypotheses.org/624"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="morard17b"><author>Morard, Martin</author>. <date>2017</date>b. <title
              level="a">Quelques définitions.</title>
            <title level="m">Sacra Pagina: Gloses et commentaires de la Bible latine au Moyen Âge
              (blog)</title>. November 3. <ptr target="https://big.hypotheses.org/865"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="nury20"><author>Nury, Elisa</author>, and <author>Elena Spadini</author>.
              <date>2020</date>. <title level="a">From Giant Despair to a New Heaven: The Early
              Years of Automatic Collation.</title>
            <title level="j">it – Information Technology</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">61–73</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1515/itit-2019-0047</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pierazzo16a"><author>Pierazzo, Elena</author>. <date>2016</date>a. <title
              level="m">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories, Models and Methods</title>.
              <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Routledge</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="pierazzo16b"><author>Pierazzo, Elena</author>. <date>2016</date>b. <title
              level="a">Modelling Digital Scholarly Editing: From Plato to Heraclitus.</title> In
              <title level="m">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and Practices</title>, edited by
              <editor>Matthew James Driscoll</editor> and <editor>Elena Pierazzo</editor>,
              <biblScope unit="page">41–58</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Open Book Publishers</publisher>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.11647/OBP.0095.03</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="robinson13"><author>Robinson, Peter</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
              level="a">Towards a Theory of Digital Editions</title>. <title level="j">Variants: The
              Journal of the European Society for Textual Scholarship</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">105–31</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.1163/9789401209021_009</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="roeder20"><author>Roeder, Torsten</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title
              level="a">Juxta Web Service, LERA, and Variance Viewer. Web Based Collation Tools for
              TEI.</title>
            <title level="j">RIDE: A Review Journal for Digital Editions and Resources</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>. <ptr
              target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-11/web-based-collation-tools/"/>; doi:<idno
              type="doi">10.18716/ride.a.11.5</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="sahle16"><author>Sahle, Patrick</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title
              level="a">What Is a Scholarly Digital Edition?</title> In <title level="m">Digital
              Scholarly Editing: Theories and Practices</title>, edited by <editor>Matthew James
              Driscoll</editor> and <editor>Elena Pierazzo</editor>, <biblScope unit="page"
              >19–39</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Open Book
              Publishers</publisher>. doi:<idno type="doi">10.11647/OBP.0095.02</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="siemens16"><author>Siemens, Ray</author>, <author>Constance
              Crompton</author>, <author>Daniel Powell</author>, and <author>Alyssa
              Arbuckle</author>, with <author>Maggie Shirley</author> and the <author>Devonshire
              Manuscript Editorial Group</author>. <date>2016</date>. <title level="a">Building
                <title level="m">A Social Edition of the Devonshire Manuscript</title></title>. In
              <title level="m">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and Practices</title>, edited by
              <editor>Matthew James Driscoll</editor> and <editor>Elena Pierazzo</editor>,
              <biblScope unit="page">137–60</biblScope>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Open Book Publishers</publisher>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.11647/OBP.0095.08</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="spadini19"><author>Spadini, Elena</author>, and <author>Magdalena
              Turska</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title level="a">XML-TEI Stand-off Markup: One
              Step Beyond.</title>
            <title level="j">Digital Philology: A Journal of Medieval Cultures</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope> (<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>):
              <biblScope unit="page">225–39</biblScope>. doi:<idno type="doi"
              >10.1353/dph.2019.0025</idno>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tei21"><orgName>TEI Consortium</orgName>. <date>2021</date>. <title
              level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>.
              <edition>Version 4.2.2</edition>. Last updated April 9. <pubPlace>N.p.</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>. <ptr
              target="https://tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.2.2/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"/>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="tov20"><author>Tov, Emanuel</author>. <date>2020</date>. <title level="a"
              >Glosses, Interpolations, and Other Types of Scribal Additions in the Text of the
              Hebrew Bible.</title> In <title level="m">Language, Theology, and the Bible: Essays in
              Honour of James Barr</title>, edited by <editor>Samuel E. Balentine</editor> and
              <editor>John Barton</editor>, <biblScope unit="page">40–66</biblScope>.
              <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Clarendon</publisher>. Accessed April 1. <ptr
              target="https://www.academia.edu/38345587/94._Glosses_Interpolations_and_Other_Types_of_Scribal_Additions_in_the_Text_of_the_Hebrew_Bible_in_Language_Theology_and_the_Bible_Essays_in_Honour_of_James_Barr_ed._S._E._Balentine_and_John_Barton_Oxford_Clarendon_1994_40_66"
            />.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="venture07"><editor>Ventura, Iolanda</editor>, ed. <date>2007</date>. <title
              level="m">De Proprietatibus Rerum, Volume VI: Liber XVII</title>. By Bartholomeus
            Anglicus. De Diversis Artibus 79. <pubPlace>Turnhout, Belgium</pubPlace>:
              <publisher>Brepols</publisher>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="wieland98"><author>Wieland, Gernot R.</author>
            <date>1998</date>. <title level="a">Interpreting the Interpretation: The Polysemy of the
              Latin Gloss.</title>
            <title level="j">The Journal of Medieval Latin</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>: <biblScope unit="page">59–71</biblScope>.
              doi:<idno type="doi">10.1484/J.JML.2.304089</idno>.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
